Now I'd like to share with you my testimony.
How I used my experiences in life during the session.
You know, I came to have the renewal experience in 1982.
But I by nature am a very shy and timid person.
So I never went to the prayer group for 10 years.
After 10 years I started going to my prayer meetings.
I would leave the prayer meeting soon after the meeting was over.
I would not stay back for any fellowship.
And that was the time in 1993.
The Lord spoke to me.
The Lord said, I want, I am appointing you to renew, to revive the capital city of India.
I tada je Bog rekao, imenujem tebe i određujem te, da ideš i obnoviš glavni grad Indije.
Because I used to be working for the Parliament of India.
I used to live in New Delhi.
I was surprised when the Lord said, I want you to renew, revive the capital city.
And I was nowhere in the spiritual leadership.
But I came back to my city.
And I came back to my city.
So after three weeks, the parish priest told me, be on the call team of the prayer group.
And after one year, I was made the leader of the prayer group.
And after one year, I was made the coordinator for the archdioces and renewables.
And after one year, the Lord put me on a leadership role.
I was not experienced at all.
I was not equipped at all.
Now when I became the chairman of the archdioces and renewables.
I was very new.
But I began to start doing something.
And that is the time that the priest in charge of renewing.
The priest in charge of renewing.