[SPEAKER_00] Halleluja
[SPEAKER_00] So this is going to be my last teaching
[SPEAKER_01] So this time we are just going to look at the Catholic charismatic renewal
[SPEAKER_00] And we as leaders
[SPEAKER_00] You know one of the greatest news for us is
[SPEAKER_00] That our Pope, the Holy Father, Pope Francis
[SPEAKER_01] Is the greatest supporter of the Catholic charismatic renewal
[SPEAKER_00] As we were preparing for the golden jubilee of the Catholic charismatic renewal
[SPEAKER_01] The Holy Father invited all charismatics to Rome
[SPEAKER_01] Saying join me in celebrating our jubilee
[SPEAKER_00] So today we are privileged to have a Pope who not only encourages us, not only supports us
[SPEAKER_00] But also promotes the Catholic charismatic renewal
[SPEAKER_00] So shall we give a clap to the Holy Spirit who has given us such a Holy Father
[SPEAKER_01] Zdravljujem da se da dupi svetom koji nam je poslao takvim svetom svetom godinicom.
[SPEAKER_01] To je bilo u srpnju 2015.
[SPEAKER_00] Papa je ovo rekao:
[SPEAKER_02] "Tražim od svakoga od vas"
[SPEAKER_00] Dakle, on se obrađa biskupima i svečenicima.
[SPEAKER_00] Tražim od svakoga od vas
[SPEAKER_00] da organizirate seminare u dupi svetom
[SPEAKER_01] u vašim žijupama,
[SPEAKER_01] seminarištima,
[SPEAKER_01] školama
[SPEAKER_01] i vašim susijestima.
[SPEAKER_00] in order to share the baptism in the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_01] Even in catechesis.
[SPEAKER_02] So that the Holy Spirit
[SPEAKER_00] could bring about that personal encounter with Jesus Christ.
[SPEAKER_01] Which changes our lives.
[SPEAKER_00] Now,
[SPEAKER_00] the Holy Father has been repeatedly asking us charismatics
[SPEAKER_01] to organize life in the spirit seminar in all the places.
[SPEAKER_01] u svim drugim mjestima, života u Dugu svetom.
[SPEAKER_00] And to share the grace of the baptism in the Holy Spirit with everyone.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, here, he is also asking the priest and the bishops to do it.
[SPEAKER_00] So, how many of us have taken this message of the Holy Father seriously?
[SPEAKER_00] Personally, I was very delighted and encouraged to receive this message.
[SPEAKER_01] And in India, we decided that we are going to promote the Life in the Spirit seminar in all apparitions.
[SPEAKER_00] And in India.
[SPEAKER_01] So, we have set a two-year period.
[SPEAKER_00] we have set a two-year period.
[SPEAKER_00] We have set a two-year period.
[SPEAKER_00] We have set a three-year period.
[SPEAKER_00] And we have set a three-year period.
[SPEAKER_01] And we have set a three-year period.
[SPEAKER_01] And we are doing it because the Holy Father has given us this mandate.
[SPEAKER_00] This year, I had the opportunity to address the bishops.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I asked all the bishops to cooperate with the Catholic and Hispanic Renewal.
[SPEAKER_00] Because I said this is what the Holy Father wants.
[SPEAKER_00] And now we are addressing the bishops even at the regional conferences.
[SPEAKER_01] And we are giving trainings to people everywhere.
[SPEAKER_00] So that they could go around and preach the Life in the Spirit seminar.
[SPEAKER_01] So we are moving in a big way.
[SPEAKER_01] So that we comply with what the Holy Father has been asking us.
[SPEAKER_01] One of the things that we have set as a target is.
[SPEAKER_01] One of the things.
[SPEAKER_00] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[SPEAKER_01] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[UNKNOWN] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[SPEAKER_00] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[SPEAKER_01] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know if anywhere in Croatia or in any of your countries.
[SPEAKER_00] The charismatic renewal is fully merged with the church.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know if anywhere in Croatia or any of your countries.
[SPEAKER_01] The charismatic renewal is fully merged with the church.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know if there is a target for us.
[SPEAKER_01] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[SPEAKER_00] One of the things that we have set as a target for us.
[SPEAKER_00] The charismatic renewal is not only to be confined to this small room.
[SPEAKER_01] The charismatic renewal should move from here to the shrine.
[SPEAKER_01] The recitation of the rosary and the holy mass should become charismatic.
[SPEAKER_01] I know that there is a parish in the United States.
[SPEAKER_01] Where they begin the mass with praise and worship.
[SPEAKER_01] It is in the parish.
[SPEAKER_00] It is open for the public.
[SPEAKER_00] But they know that the parish is charismatic parish.
[SPEAKER_01] The parish is charismatic.
[SPEAKER_01] So the mass begins with praise and worship.
[SPEAKER_01] And that should happen in every parish.
[SPEAKER_01] That is what the Holy Father is asking us.
[SPEAKER_00] Many of the time, at least in our country, I hear people coming and saying,
[SPEAKER_00] You know, our parish parish parish does not support us.
[SPEAKER_01] I am telling you there is the Holy Father who is supporting us.
[SPEAKER_00] And one of our leaders went to a parish parish priest asking him permission to organize the life in the spirit seminar.
[SPEAKER_00] And as usual, the parish parish parish said no.
[SPEAKER_01] I on je uzeo citat koji je rekao sam Sveti Otac i dao je taj citat žuklimu i rekao je, rečasni, ja od vas to ne tražim.
[SPEAKER_01] Sveti Otac to tražio vas.
[SPEAKER_00] I onda je Žuklim rekao, ređu, može. Prista je.
[SPEAKER_01] I dakle, pitanje je, jesmo li mi ozibihni glede onoga što je Papa Franjo zadražio od nas?
[SPEAKER_00] I am reminding everywhere, wherever I go, that, you know, the Holy Father wants the charismatic renewal to be completely merged with the church.
[SPEAKER_00] And we as charismatic should take that initiative.
[SPEAKER_01] I ja sam, mene pocijećaju da bilo gdje gdje se nalazi, dakle, karizmatski pokrej treba biti sjedinjen s crkvom i mi karizmatici trebamo preuzeti tu inicijativu.
[SPEAKER_01] Ali većinu vremena se dogodi da mi kao voditelji smo nekako kaskamo zadine.
[SPEAKER_00] Jedna od stvari koje je Papa Franjo rekao je
[SPEAKER_00] mlakost u crkvi.
[SPEAKER_00] Mislim kako sam vam ovome pričao prvog dana.
[SPEAKER_01] U knjizi od Trierija treće poglavlje
[SPEAKER_00] jasno kaže
[SPEAKER_00] da mi smo
[SPEAKER_01] želim vam to pročitati.
[SPEAKER_00] Redak petnaestih poglade trećih knjiga odgrivenja.
[SPEAKER_01] Znam tvoja dijela, nisi ni studen ni vrunč.
[SPEAKER_01] Oda si studen ili vrunč.
[SPEAKER_01] Ali jer si mlak, ni vruč, ni studen, povratit ću te iz usta.
[SPEAKER_02] Znam tvoja dijela, nisi ni studen ni vrunč.
[SPEAKER_02] Oda si studen ili vrunč.
[SPEAKER_02] Ali jer si mlak, ni vruč, ni studen,
[SPEAKER_01] povratit ću te iz usta.
[SPEAKER_01] i treće poglade redak prvi kaže
[SPEAKER_01] I anđelu crkve u sardu napiši
[SPEAKER_01] Ovo govori onaj koji ima sedam duhova Božih i sedam zvijezda.
[SPEAKER_01] Znam tvoja dijela, imaš ime da živiš, a mrtav si.
[SPEAKER_00] Gospodji duh koji govori kaže
[SPEAKER_01] Jedan od najvećih problema s kojima se mi u crkvi sustećemo je blankos.
[SPEAKER_01] Čini se da smo živi, ali duboko u sebi smo mrtvi.
[SPEAKER_01] I zbog toga moj zadnji govor je upravo zbog o tome da se mi pomaknemo iz stanja blankosti u djelovanje.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja osjećam kako je dio duho svetoga koji se odnosi na karizmatski pogled zakazao.
[SPEAKER_01] Jav, žako mi je žao što moram to reći.
[SPEAKER_01] Ali mislim kako trebam otvoreno vama karizmaticima to reći.
[SPEAKER_01] Jer kada je duh sveti započeo ovaj moćni pokret u crkvi,
[SPEAKER_01] on nije mislio samo na dvanest posto katoličke populacije.
[SPEAKER_00] All over the world, if you take the statistics,
[SPEAKER_01] if you take the statistics,
[SPEAKER_00] čak i danas se radi o samo dvanest posto katoličke populacije koju je dotakao duh sveti ili ljubav Božja.
[SPEAKER_01] ja osjećam kako je duh sveti tužan.
[SPEAKER_01] Jer vjerujem onda kada je započela obnovao duh u crkvi, duh sveti je imao to na umu.
[SPEAKER_01] da će cijela crkva biti obnovljena.
[SPEAKER_00] To je bilo kao kap soli, zrno soli koje je stavljeno u crkvu.
[SPEAKER_01] Sol je tu kako bi sve ostalo zasolila.
[SPEAKER_00] Ili kao kvasac koji je stavljeno crkvu.
[SPEAKER_01] I taj kvasac je trebao uskvasati čitavu crkvu.
[SPEAKER_00] I Otac Cantalamesa upodno to ponavlja.
[SPEAKER_01] Karismanski pokret nakon što je počeo sa sve odno samo mali dio ljudi, mali dio populacije.
[SPEAKER_00] U naše župja koji ima tisuću ljudi.
[SPEAKER_01] Koliko ljudi je dio vaše zajednice?
[SPEAKER_01] 10%.
[SPEAKER_01] 15%.
[SPEAKER_01] 30%.
[SPEAKER_00] And now it's 52 years since the Catholic charismatic renewal started.
[SPEAKER_00] I do not believe that it was plan of the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_00] For the Catholic charismatic renewal to have a separate entity.
[SPEAKER_01] It is not expected to meet here in a separate room.
[SPEAKER_01] It is expected to meet in the parish hall itself.
[SPEAKER_00] Parish itself.
[SPEAKER_01] And that happens only when everyone is renewed.
[SPEAKER_01] That happens only when the whole parish is renewed.
[SPEAKER_01] That is why the Holy Father is telling us take this Life in the Spirit seminar to your schools.
[SPEAKER_01] U vašim sjemenišnjima.
[SPEAKER_01] Ponesete ih u vaše institucije.
[SPEAKER_01] U vaše žumpe.
[SPEAKER_01] Možemo li mi to učiniti?
[SPEAKER_01] Da li mi to učinimo?
[SPEAKER_00] Nitko ne želi ovome aplaudirati.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja ne pokušavam pretirivati dok vam ovo kažem.
[SPEAKER_01] I želim vas samo podsjetiti.
[SPEAKER_01] Od samog početka do sada.
[SPEAKER_01] Da imali smo stalno podsjetnike, svako malo, zna ovo sve.
[SPEAKER_02] Da je katolički karismanski pokret nešto što se tiče cijele crkve.
[SPEAKER_01] Mi smo to zanemarili.
[SPEAKER_01] I ja kažem, mi mislići na nas voditelje.
[SPEAKER_01] Na vrene i na vas.
[SPEAKER_01] I upravo radi toga se nismo dovoljno potrudili.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja mogu razumijeti i stvariti kako postoji ponekad odbijanje.
[SPEAKER_01] I ja se nosim s tim odbijanje u svojoj državi.
[SPEAKER_00] Ja to imam čak i unutar sebe.
[SPEAKER_01] I znam s čime se nosite.
[SPEAKER_01] Ali ja bih rekao, idemo mi kao zagovaratelji udružiti s nami od skupiti ruke zajedno i moliti da se to ostvari.
[SPEAKER_00] Čak i kada je nacionalni tim u Indiji to splanirao kao veliki projekt.
[SPEAKER_01] Nikad nismo očekivali da ćemo primiti toliku pomoć i potporu.
[SPEAKER_01] Ali kada smo to prihvatili kao nešto što je Sveti Otac uputio svećenicima i biskupima.
[SPEAKER_01] Mi sada imamo veliku pomoć od biskupa.
[SPEAKER_01] Biskupe nas pozivaju da dođemo u njihove biskupi, u njihove župe.
[SPEAKER_00] Mi to moramo učiniti.
[SPEAKER_01] Znate kao što je Papa Franjo rekao.
[SPEAKER_00] Problem u crkvi je
[SPEAKER_00] Neki krišćani izgleda kao da su oni parkirani.
[SPEAKER_01] Kao parkirana vozila.
[SPEAKER_01] Čini se da smo nekih od nas parkirali na auto cestu.
[SPEAKER_00] i blokiramo promet.
[SPEAKER_01] Da mi nismo tu, blokiramo taj promet, netko drugi bi već prestigao nas.
[SPEAKER_01] I Papa Franjo kaže, postoje ljudi koji su sve parkirali.
[SPEAKER_01] Oni su zatočeni u kamezima.
[SPEAKER_00] Oni ne znaju kako bi letjeli.
[SPEAKER_01] I mi, kao voditelji karizmatskog pokreta, moramo se zapitati:
[SPEAKER_00] jesmo li mi dio te skupine koja je se parkirala?
[SPEAKER_00] No.
[SPEAKER_01] Želim s vama podijeliti jednu prispodobu.
[SPEAKER_01] Matij 24 poglede.
[SPEAKER_00] Ovo ću podijeliti s vama jer je ovo jedna prispodoba
[SPEAKER_01] koja me doista dodinula.
[SPEAKER_01] To je prispodoba koja me pokrenula.
[SPEAKER_02] jer kad sam preučavao ovu prispodobu
[SPEAKER_02] svatio sam
[SPEAKER_01] kako nam je Gospod dao neke darove.
[SPEAKER_00] I ti darovi su tu kako biste koristili.
[SPEAKER_00] Meni je Bog dao dar vodstva.
[SPEAKER_01] ako ne koristi dar vodstva
[SPEAKER_00] zaradnjeg dana kada dođem pred njega
[SPEAKER_01] kada Bog uzme račun svega onoga što sam učinio za svog života
[SPEAKER_01] on će me sigurno pokaviti zbog toga.
[SPEAKER_01] nećemo prečinati četavu prispodobu i duga.
[SPEAKER_01] To je Matij 24 poglede Matij
[SPEAKER_01] verset 14-13.
[SPEAKER_00] prije.
[SPEAKER_01] želio vam samo objasniti.
[SPEAKER_01] Bio je jedan bogataš
[SPEAKER_02] i taj bogataš je bio na dugom putu.
[SPEAKER_02] I prije nego što je otišao na put pozvao svoje sluge.
[SPEAKER_01] i oni želio svakome od njih dodijeliti zadatak.
[SPEAKER_01] Želio im dati darove i talente
[SPEAKER_00] svakome pod njegovim sposobnostima.
[SPEAKER_00] jednom je nao pet ale nata
[SPEAKER_00] jednom dva
[SPEAKER_02] jednom jedan.
[SPEAKER_01] I tako je gospodar odišao na dugo putovanje
[SPEAKER_01] vratio se nakon izvjestnog vremena
[SPEAKER_01] pozvao svoje sluge
[SPEAKER_02] i tražio da mu prilože račun.
[SPEAKER_02] i tada došao prvi
[SPEAKER_02] i rekao je
[SPEAKER_01] gospodaru dao si mi pet talena
[SPEAKER_01] ja sam upodrijevio tje talente
[SPEAKER_01] trgovao sam s njima i umnožio sam
[SPEAKER_01] sadati donosi ih deset
[SPEAKER_01] izvoli svoji deset talenata.
[SPEAKER_01] Što je rekao gospodar?
[SPEAKER_01] valjaš slugo dobri.
[SPEAKER_02] Valjaš slugo dobri.
[SPEAKER_02] You have been faithful in small matters.
[SPEAKER_02] I am going to make you responsible for bigger things.
[SPEAKER_00] Then the second one comes.
[SPEAKER_02] And then he had two talents.
[SPEAKER_00] So he presents it to Jesus.
[SPEAKER_00] double.
[SPEAKER_00] Because he too traded with this.
[SPEAKER_00] He had made it four.
[SPEAKER_01] So the master says
[SPEAKER_01] good and faithful servant
[SPEAKER_01] I will give you greater things
[SPEAKER_01] than the one who had one talent comes.
[SPEAKER_02] and he said
[SPEAKER_02] Master I know you very well.
[SPEAKER_02] I dug this talent.
[SPEAKER_00] I hid it.
[SPEAKER_00] Here it is.
[SPEAKER_00] And what did the master say?
[SPEAKER_02] You wicked and lazy servant.
[SPEAKER_02] Hallelujah.
[SPEAKER_00] Now we need to ask ourselves
[SPEAKER_01] I am sure all of us who are here
[SPEAKER_02] are in some or the other responsible position.
[SPEAKER_01] All of us are being given talents.
[SPEAKER_01] Some five, some two, some one.
[SPEAKER_01] What are we doing with this?
[SPEAKER_01] Now sometimes there are leaders who become leaders.
[SPEAKER_01] And after sometimes they don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01] They just sit there.
[SPEAKER_01] And they are the cause of destruction.
[SPEAKER_01] And here
[SPEAKER_00] the Lord is very very strong
[SPEAKER_00] with the third servant.
[SPEAKER_01] Because this servant had got one talent.
[SPEAKER_01] And he did not put that use.
[SPEAKER_01] But I appreciate that servant.
[SPEAKER_01] Because he got one.
[SPEAKER_00] But he preserved that one.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know if it happens in your country.
[SPEAKER_00] In my country
[SPEAKER_00] I find a lot of charismatics
[SPEAKER_00] who come to the renewal.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know if it happens in your country.
[SPEAKER_01] But in my country
[SPEAKER_01] there are many charismatics
[SPEAKER_01] who come to the renewal.
[SPEAKER_01] Who are there for a few years.
[SPEAKER_01] Then they don't see.
[SPEAKER_01] They are not seen anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01] So what happens to those?
[SPEAKER_01] Because here
[SPEAKER_01] the Lord is very severe
[SPEAKER_01] with the third servant.
[SPEAKER_01] Although he produced
[SPEAKER_00] that one talent
[SPEAKER_00] that was given to him.
[SPEAKER_01] There are many
[SPEAKER_00] who received these talents.
[SPEAKER_01] But who lose
[SPEAKER_00] these talents on the way.
[SPEAKER_01] and go to the Lord
[SPEAKER_01] empty heart rate.
[SPEAKER_00] And what is going to be
[SPEAKER_01] the Lord's response?
[SPEAKER_00] I was wondering
[SPEAKER_00] why there is no mention
[SPEAKER_00] of this fourth servant
[SPEAKER_01] in the Bible.
[SPEAKER_00] because definitely
[SPEAKER_00] there is a fourth category.
[SPEAKER_01] Then I realized
[SPEAKER_00] that the language
[SPEAKER_00] that the master
[SPEAKER_00] is going to use
[SPEAKER_00] and that
[SPEAKER_00] to that servant
[SPEAKER_00] is going to be
[SPEAKER_00] so harsh.
[SPEAKER_01] that it cannot be written
[SPEAKER_00] in the Bible.
[SPEAKER_00] Amen.
[SPEAKER_01] Amen.
[SPEAKER_01] So to which category
[SPEAKER_00] do I belong?
[SPEAKER_00] The Lord has entrusted to us
[SPEAKER_01] big responsibilities.
[SPEAKER_01] the Lord has given us talents.
[SPEAKER_01] Yesterday we saw
[SPEAKER_01] that Jesus said
[SPEAKER_01] John 15:16
[SPEAKER_01] you did not choose me.
[SPEAKER_01] But I chose you
[SPEAKER_01] to go and bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_01] Fruit that will last.
[SPEAKER_01] So the Lord wants
[SPEAKER_01] every one of you
[SPEAKER_01] to bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_01] are we really
[SPEAKER_01] wearing fruit?
[SPEAKER_01] Are we really
[SPEAKER_01] multiplying the talents
[SPEAKER_01] that we have received?
[SPEAKER_02] We need to nearly
[SPEAKER_01] move from maintenance
[SPEAKER_01] to mission.
[SPEAKER_01] There is a passage
[SPEAKER_00] in the Bible.
[SPEAKER_01] that we have to
[UNKNOWN] be able to do
[UNKNOWN] the same thing.
[UNKNOWN] We have to do
[SPEAKER_01] the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01] We have to do
[UNKNOWN] We have to do
[UNKNOWN] the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00] Mark 11, 12 to 14.
[SPEAKER_01] Mark 11, 12 to 14.
[SPEAKER_00] You can read that.
[SPEAKER_00] now.
[UNKNOWN] Here is an interesting
[UNKNOWN] incident.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, here is an interesting incident.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, Jesus was hungry.
[SPEAKER_02] And he goes to the fig tree.
[SPEAKER_02] The fig tree full of leaves.
[SPEAKER_01] Thinking that there will be fruit.
[SPEAKER_01] And the word of God says
[SPEAKER_02] there was no fruit.
[SPEAKER_01] But it also says
[SPEAKER_02] it was not the season of fruit.
[SPEAKER_01] But, Jesus
[SPEAKER_01] curses that victory.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, was he fair in doing this?
[SPEAKER_00] Is he fair in doing this?
[SPEAKER_01] Is he fair in doing this?
[SPEAKER_00] Now, in Croatia, I believe this is not the season of fruits.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't think there is apple now.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't think there are grapes now.
[SPEAKER_01] I can't see those gardens there.
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00] Suppose we go to the grave and say
[SPEAKER_00] I curse you because there is no fruit now.
[SPEAKER_01] Is that fair?
[SPEAKER_00] Why did Jesus do something like this?
[SPEAKER_01] Why?
[SPEAKER_01] I was reading this passage again and again.
[SPEAKER_00] And then at the end I realized
[SPEAKER_01] this is the only passage
[SPEAKER_00] of which it is written.
[SPEAKER_00] And his disciples heard it.
[SPEAKER_02] Everything that Jesus said
[SPEAKER_00] was heard by the disciples.
[SPEAKER_01] Why is specifically recorded
[SPEAKER_01] and his disciples heard it?
[SPEAKER_01] That means
[SPEAKER_01] Jesus was not speaking to the fig tree
[SPEAKER_01] but Jesus was speaking to the disciples.
[SPEAKER_01] Telling you and me
[SPEAKER_02] I may come anytime
[SPEAKER_02] looking for the fruits
[SPEAKER_01] now do not tell me
[SPEAKER_01] it is not the season of fruits.
[SPEAKER_01] So you are to wear fruit
[SPEAKER_01] in season
[SPEAKER_01] and out of season.
[SPEAKER_00] So we are all called to bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_00] Whether the circumstances are good or bad.
[SPEAKER_00] So we cannot say that
[SPEAKER_00] you know
[SPEAKER_00] I have a very important and busy job.
[SPEAKER_01] I have my family.
[SPEAKER_02] And my parish priest is not good.
[SPEAKER_02] My leader is not good.
[SPEAKER_02] My life partner is not supportive.
[SPEAKER_02] My parents are not supportive.
[SPEAKER_02] The Lord said
[SPEAKER_01] every one of you
[SPEAKER_01] is called to bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_01] In our own circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01] So we need to be really committed to this.
[SPEAKER_01] We need to understand this.
[SPEAKER_01] That is why
[SPEAKER_01] we cannot stay stagnant in one place.
[SPEAKER_01] We need to move from maintenance to mission.
[SPEAKER_01] We need to move from maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01] Many of us
[SPEAKER_00] in the renewal
[SPEAKER_00] are doing maintenance work.
[SPEAKER_00] Many of us
[SPEAKER_01] in the renewal
[SPEAKER_01] are doing maintenance work.
[SPEAKER_01] Some places
[SPEAKER_01] we have 20 people
[SPEAKER_01] in our community.
[SPEAKER_01] For the last 10 years.
[SPEAKER_01] And we are very happy and proud.
[SPEAKER_01] That we have 20 people in our community.
[SPEAKER_01] But the Lord is asking us.
[SPEAKER_01] From this 30
[SPEAKER_01] you move to 200.
[SPEAKER_01] And you need to do something about this.
[SPEAKER_01] That is what the Lord is asking us.
[SPEAKER_01] To put to use those gifts
[SPEAKER_01] that He has given us.
[SPEAKER_01] To bear the fruit.
[SPEAKER_00] Whether the circumstances are good or bad.
[SPEAKER_00] Many of us
[SPEAKER_00] remain self-centered.
[SPEAKER_01] We think that by giving our time
[SPEAKER_00] and our energy
[SPEAKER_00] our talents
[SPEAKER_00] our resources
[SPEAKER_00] we will
[SPEAKER_00] like something.
[SPEAKER_00] light something.
[SPEAKER_01] But by giving ourselves to the Lord
[SPEAKER_00] and for His mission
[SPEAKER_00] He always
[SPEAKER_00] multiplies things.
[SPEAKER_00] things.
[UNKNOWN] But
[UNKNOWN] only
[SPEAKER_01] I would like to give you the example
[SPEAKER_00] an example from the whole land.
[SPEAKER_01] You know there are two seas
[SPEAKER_00] in the land
[SPEAKER_00] where Jesus
[SPEAKER_00] Jesus lived.
[SPEAKER_02] One is the sea of Galilee.
[SPEAKER_02] The other one is the dead sea.
[SPEAKER_00] Both the seas have the same source.
[SPEAKER_00] the same source.
[UNKNOWN] The river Jordan.
[SPEAKER_01] The river Jordan flows down.
[SPEAKER_00] And it first comes to the sea of Galilee.
[SPEAKER_00] the sea of Galilee.
[SPEAKER_01] Now if you are going to the holy land.
[SPEAKER_01] The sea of Galilee is full of life.
[SPEAKER_01] It is there that Jesus was doing the voting.
[SPEAKER_01] Where Peter did the fishing.
[SPEAKER_00] And the sea of Galilee gives so much of water to Israel.
[SPEAKER_01] That Israel has become number one
[SPEAKER_00] agricultural producer in the world.
[SPEAKER_01] There is a lot of fish in the sea.
[SPEAKER_02] There is a lot of greenery around the sea.
[SPEAKER_01] There is a lot of greenery around the sea.
[SPEAKER_01] People live all around.
[SPEAKER_01] We can see people boating.
[SPEAKER_00] And this river Jordan flows down from the sea of Galilee.
[SPEAKER_01] And it goes to the dead sea.
[SPEAKER_00] The same water that comes to the sea of Galilee goes down to the dead sea.
[SPEAKER_01] Now the sea of Galilee is small and the dead sea is much bigger.
[SPEAKER_00] Three times bigger than the sea of Galilee.
[SPEAKER_00] But.
[SPEAKER_01] With all this water going down.
[SPEAKER_01] Ali sa svom tom rijekom koja se ulijeva, vodom koja se ulijeva, u mrtvom moru ne živi niti jedna jedina riba.
[SPEAKER_01] Bilo koja riba koja uđe u tog more, završi mrtvo.
[SPEAKER_01] Nema ništa zelenog što raste u tog mora.
[SPEAKER_00] A voda u tom moru ima deset puta veći salinitet nego obično more.
[SPEAKER_00] Sve to zato što mrtvo more prijima i prijima i prijima.
[SPEAKER_00] Voda iz mrtvog mora ne otješe nikje.
[SPEAKER_01] Ono ne daje ništa.
[SPEAKER_00] Jesmo li mi ljudi koji samo primaju, primaju, primaju?
[SPEAKER_00] Ili smo mi ljudi koji daju?
[SPEAKER_01] Kao što i primamo, moramo davati.
[SPEAKER_01] Moramo davati, moramo posebice biti u službi gospodinovoj.
[SPEAKER_01] Moramo dati svoje vrijeme.
[SPEAKER_01] Moramo dati svoje talente.
[SPEAKER_01] Moramo dati svoje resurce.
[SPEAKER_01] I mi moramo dati gospodinu i to mora biti minimum, minimum bi trebalo biti deset posto onoga što smo mi primili.
[SPEAKER_01] I rekao sam vam kako je mene ta prispodova o talentima toliko zadivila.
[SPEAKER_00] I baš spok toga kad sam radio u parlamentu,
[SPEAKER_01] tamo sam imao stalni posao.
[SPEAKER_01] Imao sam jako važne zadatke.
[SPEAKER_00] No čak i tada nikad nisam prestao raditi za gospodina.
[SPEAKER_01] I sjećam se kako sam jedno vrijeme uzimao slobodan dan petkom.
[SPEAKER_01] jer su subota i nedelja bili sveti dani.
[SPEAKER_02] And then travel on Thursday night.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja bih onda počeo putovati četvrtkog navečer.
[SPEAKER_01] U udaljena mjesta.
[SPEAKER_01] Gdje bi onda bio na misijskom radu petak, subotu i nedjelju.
[SPEAKER_00] i nedelju navečer bi se vraćao nadrav.
[SPEAKER_02] I nekada bih šao izradno u ured.
[SPEAKER_01] Možda bi sam nekada putovao po četamu noć.
[SPEAKER_01] jer sam uvijek usjećao
[SPEAKER_01] gospodin mi je dao neke talente.
[SPEAKER_01] Gospodin mi je dao darove.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja trebam početi upotrebljavati te darove
[SPEAKER_01] kako bi izrađivao Božje kraljevstvo.
[SPEAKER_01] In between all this I used to write my books.
[SPEAKER_00] I zadnja knjiga o kojoj smo govorili je moja šesta knjiga.
[SPEAKER_02] Ljudi bi me pitali gdje nalaziš vrijeme?
[SPEAKER_01] Kako nalaziš vrijeme?
[SPEAKER_01] I used to wake about two o'clock in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] At two o'clock in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] Sit and write my book.
[SPEAKER_01] jer sam usjećao
[SPEAKER_01] kako bi je Bog dao te talente.
[SPEAKER_01] Te darove.
[SPEAKER_01] I kada bude od mene zadražio račun.
[SPEAKER_01] Ne mogu mu baš doći i reći
[SPEAKER_01] gospodine, ja sam bio zauzet svojim poslom.
[SPEAKER_01] Dakle moramo naučiti upotrebljavati svojim poslom.
[SPEAKER_00] svojim poslom.
[SPEAKER_01] I nemojmo biti kao mrtvo more
[SPEAKER_01] koje prijima sve blagoslove.
[SPEAKER_01] Nikad ništa ne daje.
[SPEAKER_00] Budimo kao Galilejsko more.
[SPEAKER_01] Galilejsko jezero koje prijima
[SPEAKER_02] i koje daje.
[SPEAKER_01] Baš kao što i prijima,
[SPEAKER_01] daje.
[SPEAKER_01] I zato je puno životom.
[SPEAKER_00] I mnogi ljudi prijmaju blagoslove preko toga.
[SPEAKER_00] But the dead sea
[SPEAKER_00] doesn't give anything.
[SPEAKER_01] When you go to the dead sea
[SPEAKER_00] you can see that there is no life there.
[SPEAKER_01] So do you want to end up as the dead sea?
[SPEAKER_00] You need to answer this.
[SPEAKER_00] So all of us have to take a decision.
[SPEAKER_01] What we want to be.
[SPEAKER_00] No, we need to stay committed.
[SPEAKER_00] One of the things that the Lord is asking us
[SPEAKER_01] jedna od stvari koju gospodi traži od nas
[SPEAKER_00] be committed.
[SPEAKER_01] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] when we look at the life of Moses
[SPEAKER_01] something beautiful that we see
[SPEAKER_00] in the book of Deuteronomy
[SPEAKER_01] the last chapter of Deuteronomy
[SPEAKER_01] It says
[SPEAKER_02] the chapter 34
[SPEAKER_02] verse 7
[SPEAKER_02] says
[SPEAKER_00] Moses was
[SPEAKER_00] 120 years old.
[SPEAKER_01] He said
[SPEAKER_00] anyone here?
[SPEAKER_00] 120 years old.
[SPEAKER_01] But the word of God says
[SPEAKER_00] yet
[SPEAKER_00] his eyes were
[SPEAKER_00] undimmed
[SPEAKER_01] and
[SPEAKER_02] his vigor
[SPEAKER_02] unabated
[SPEAKER_02] still he was on fire
[SPEAKER_02] for the Lord.
[SPEAKER_01] That is
[SPEAKER_00] bearing fruit
[SPEAKER_00] to the end.
[SPEAKER_01] One thing
[SPEAKER_00] I have been telling
[SPEAKER_00] the Lord is
[SPEAKER_01] Lord help me to serve
[SPEAKER_02] you
[SPEAKER_02] may not be as a preacher
[SPEAKER_01] may not be as a leader
[SPEAKER_02] even if I am lying on my bed
[SPEAKER_01] to serve you
[SPEAKER_00] till I breathe my last
[SPEAKER_01] I need to bear fruit
[SPEAKER_00] that is what Moses did
[SPEAKER_01] even when he was
[SPEAKER_00] 120
[SPEAKER_01] he was still
[SPEAKER_01] full of bigger
[SPEAKER_01] for the Lord
[SPEAKER_01] and when the Lord
[SPEAKER_00] appointed
[SPEAKER_00] his successor
[SPEAKER_01] Joshua
[SPEAKER_00] you will find
[SPEAKER_00] in Joshua chapter 1
[SPEAKER_01] the Lord telling Joshua
[SPEAKER_01] be firm
[SPEAKER_00] and steadfast
[SPEAKER_00] be firm
[SPEAKER_01] be firm
[SPEAKER_00] and steadfast
[SPEAKER_01] we need to commit
[SPEAKER_00] our lives
[SPEAKER_00] to the Lord
[SPEAKER_01] can you please stand
[UNKNOWN] can you please stand
[SPEAKER_01] Možete da biste molim vas ustati.