[SPEAKER_01] Hvala Isus i Marija, dragi pratitelji YouTube kanala Udrugi Hrvatska za Život.
[SPEAKER_01] Mi se ovdje nalazimo u župi Svetoga Josipa na Trešnjivci u sklopu naše šeste konferencije za život, Život dakle biraj.
[SPEAKER_01] Nama je danas u gostima Patricia Sandoval, ona je svjetska Pro-life govornica i govornica o čistoći.
[SPEAKER_01] Patricia, welcome.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you so much for having me on the show and greetings to everybody watching.
[SPEAKER_01] It was a really pleasure to spend some time with you these days and to heard something about your life.
[SPEAKER_01] And I would really love if you can share some of that to our listeners and watchers.
[SPEAKER_00] So I travel the world telling my story in reparation for the damage I've caused in the pro-abortion industry.
[SPEAKER_00] So when I was a little girl, the pro-abortion industry came into my school.
[SPEAKER_00] My family and I did not practice our faith.
[SPEAKER_00] I had no formation at home on sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't know that my virginity and my purity was something that I had to protect and take care of.
[SPEAKER_00] that it was a treasure.
[SPEAKER_00] My parents can give me that formation because they themselves didn't receive it when they were little.
[SPEAKER_00] And so the abortion industry basically gave me a disordered sexual education course called Responsible Sex,
[SPEAKER_00] which doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00] And they spoke about abortion being a woman's right.
[SPEAKER_00] They spoke about, you know, it's a woman's body, it's her choice.
[SPEAKER_00] And they gave us a lot of condoms and birth control pill to make us curious about sex.
[SPEAKER_00] And they encouraged us to start experimenting sexually.
[SPEAKER_00] But it's all a trap because they need a certain amount of abortions every month.
[SPEAKER_00] And what they do is they go into the schools.
[SPEAKER_00] They go after the little ones.
[SPEAKER_00] They say, ah, since parents aren't educating children on sexuality at home, we will be their sexual educators.
[SPEAKER_00] And what happened to me when I was a teenager is I met my first boyfriend.
[SPEAKER_00] I was not a virgin and I was pregnant three times.
[SPEAKER_00] And the three times I decided to have an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] So I had three abortions in a year and a half.
[SPEAKER_00] Number one, I thought that a baby destroyed your dreams.
[SPEAKER_00] I, you know, as a straight A student, I wanted to travel the world.
[SPEAKER_00] I wanted to be successful.
[SPEAKER_00] And the first time I was pregnant, I thought my life is completely over.
[SPEAKER_00] I believe that a stay at home mom, a mom that just cooked and cleaned all day.
[SPEAKER_00] That's what I thought was a domestic slave.
[SPEAKER_00] My parents divorced when I was little.
[SPEAKER_00] And my mom, she left because she said that she was just serving everybody.
[SPEAKER_00] And she was throwing her life away.
[SPEAKER_00] And she wanted to live her life.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I believe the same thing when I was pregnant, that my life was over.
[SPEAKER_00] And when I went to go have abortions, they lied to me at the abortion clinic.
[SPEAKER_00] They told me that it was just a sack of tissue.
[SPEAKER_00] It's a clump of cells.
[SPEAKER_00] And they never told me about post-abortion syndrome.
[SPEAKER_00] And after each abortion, I suffered depression, anxiety, sadness, suicidal thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, there was times I really wanted to take my life.
[SPEAKER_00] Eating disorders.
[SPEAKER_00] My emotions were like a roller coaster.
[SPEAKER_00] I'd be angry all the time all of a sudden.
[SPEAKER_00] I'd cry all the time.
[SPEAKER_00] And my boyfriend also was going through post-abortion syndrome.
[SPEAKER_00] He was experimenting nightmares, anxiety, deep sadness.
[SPEAKER_00] He felt like there was something missing.
[SPEAKER_00] And at one point, he even started drinking alcohol and he started to try drugs, cocaine.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's also symptoms of post-abortion syndrome is drugs, alcohol, gambling, even suicidal thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00] 80% of women after an abortion, they want to take their life.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was experimenting these things, but I didn't connect it to my abortions.
[SPEAKER_00] And then I went to work for the abortion industry.
[SPEAKER_00] Still thinking that abortion was a woman's choice.
[SPEAKER_00] It's a woman's right.
[SPEAKER_00] But it was there where I saw the truth about abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] It was in the abortion industry where I thought I was helping women.
[SPEAKER_00] And I didn't think there were babies until you were five months pregnant, because I learned that in school.
[SPEAKER_00] And they trained me how to hide my words.
[SPEAKER_00] I had to never say baby, father, mother, he, she.
[SPEAKER_00] I couldn't use the word fetus because that gave human dignity.
[SPEAKER_00] And I couldn't help women if they were crying.
[SPEAKER_00] I had to ignore their tears.
[SPEAKER_00] And it was when I had to assist the abortionist for the first time that I saw truth.
[SPEAKER_00] We did 50 abortions a week.
[SPEAKER_00] But the first abortion I assisted was a young girl that was 15 years old and she was three months pregnant.
[SPEAKER_00] And I stood behind the abortionist and he took out very, very sharp instruments.
[SPEAKER_00] And she was kicking and screaming and crying.
[SPEAKER_00] And during the abortion, it looked very unsafe because she was kicking.
[SPEAKER_00] And I thought, oh, he's going to take the sharp instrument out, the vacuum machine.
[SPEAKER_00] And I just saw the abortionist ducking.
[SPEAKER_00] And I thought, wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_00] Why isn't he stopping?
[SPEAKER_00] Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_00] He can't see inside of the womb and what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00] He can't see if he took out the whole clump of cells.
[SPEAKER_00] He can't see if he's perforating her womb.
[SPEAKER_00] And then I realized how unsafe abortion is because it's a complete blind man surgery.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's why millions of women die.
[SPEAKER_00] Millions of women have died after an abortion throughout many years.
[SPEAKER_00] That's why women can't have children.
[SPEAKER_00] They're infertile.
[SPEAKER_00] There's women that have their womb perforated after an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] There's women that even have their intestines perforated after an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] I've heard many testimonies like that.
[SPEAKER_00] And since he couldn't see what he was doing, I had to be his eyes.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was taken into a little room in the back of the clinic.
[SPEAKER_00] And I literally had to look for the body parts of the baby, which was very shocking to me.
[SPEAKER_00] And I saw little hands.
[SPEAKER_00] I saw legs and little feet.
[SPEAKER_00] And when the head was held up to the light, I saw that the baby had little eyes, nose, ears.
[SPEAKER_00] And the baby's mouth was wide open because his baby was screaming to defend its life.
[SPEAKER_00] But the baby was completely voiceless.
[SPEAKER_00] And she threw that baby away in the garbage.
[SPEAKER_00] And the five parts were found.
[SPEAKER_00] We had to find five parts.
[SPEAKER_00] And working behind the doors was a complete holocaust of killing of children.
[SPEAKER_00] Women would bleed to death, faint.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was just looking for body parts all day.
[SPEAKER_00] And I realized that they lied to me.
[SPEAKER_00] That I didn't abort three sacs of tissues.
[SPEAKER_00] I aborted my three children.
[SPEAKER_00] And that they lied to women.
[SPEAKER_00] They lied to men.
[SPEAKER_00] And they destroy families.
[SPEAKER_00] And it was very, very devastating.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't remember God.
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, I knew who God was when I was little because I was baptized Catholic.
[SPEAKER_00] So I started to use drugs to numb the pain.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was so addicted to cocaine and crack.
[SPEAKER_00] I lost everything.
[SPEAKER_00] And I lived three years with the Mexican cartel on the streets.
[SPEAKER_00] And one day I thought I was going to die.
[SPEAKER_00] And I had nothing to eat.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was crying because I thought my life was going to be over.
[SPEAKER_00] And that was the first time in my life that I felt the presence of God, the Father, look down on me with pity.
[SPEAKER_00] And I felt his presence very strongly.
[SPEAKER_00] And I cried out to God.
[SPEAKER_00] And I asked him to forgive me.
[SPEAKER_00] And very quickly, a woman, a waitress came out of her job, her restaurant.
[SPEAKER_00] And she looked at me with so much love and mercy.
[SPEAKER_00] And she said, Jesus loves you.
[SPEAKER_00] I was praying for you in the restaurant.
[SPEAKER_00] And I saw you crying on the street.
[SPEAKER_00] And God told me that he will never abandon you and that he will always be with you.
[SPEAKER_00] And he forgives everything you do.
[SPEAKER_00] And thanks to her, I came back home.
[SPEAKER_00] But it was really my mother's prayers.
[SPEAKER_00] My mother prayed for me three years on her knees before the Blessed Sacrament, fasting and praying.
[SPEAKER_00] And it was God's divine mercy, my mother's prayers, that I was rescued and that I'm here today.
[SPEAKER_01] We are so happy to have you here.
[SPEAKER_01] I've noticed that you also had some kind of disorder with your hair.
[SPEAKER_01] Can you please explain this and how many kilos did you have and everything because of the post-abortive syndrome?
[SPEAKER_00] Right. When I was little, when my mom left, I was 12.
[SPEAKER_00] The divorce of my parents, and I still suffer from that as an adult.
[SPEAKER_00] The divorce of my parents really wounded me.
[SPEAKER_00] So I started to pull out my hair as a child.
[SPEAKER_00] And once the post-abortion syndrome started to happen, it got worse to the point where when I was on drugs on the street, I completely was bald at the end of like when I hit my lowest point.
[SPEAKER_00] And because I was always on drugs, I was bones.
[SPEAKER_00] I was literally like a skeleton walking through the earth, lost, dead with no life.
[SPEAKER_00] I was a dead woman walking.
[SPEAKER_00] And now you can see that Jesus has given me full life.
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, I just feel like I'm full of life.
[SPEAKER_00] And so, you know, I think couples that are together and that are having issues or marriages that are having difficulties have no idea how much divorce affects a child.
[SPEAKER_00] It really wounds you.
[SPEAKER_00] I could say, I mean, I know abortion is terrible and it's horrible.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't know what I was doing when I had abortions, but I could tell you that the greatest wound in my heart till today is the divorce of my parents.
[SPEAKER_00] It's very, it's very hard.
[SPEAKER_01] And I remember that you said that you were pregnant four months for your first abortion, that your boyfriend was very happy about that.
[SPEAKER_01] So he didn't, he wasn't put in this group of people who are not supportive, the partners who don't want a child and everything.
[SPEAKER_01] He was the opposite of it.
[SPEAKER_01] Can you tell us more about that?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So I told my boyfriend about the first pregnancy and he was very happy to be a father.
[SPEAKER_00] So all the fear that I had that my life is over.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I am not successful.
[SPEAKER_00] When he's told me, you're not alone.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm going to take care of you.
[SPEAKER_00] You don't, don't worry.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm going to be responsible.
[SPEAKER_00] That, that gave me so much comfort and encouragement to keep, continue my pregnancy.
[SPEAKER_00] And I feel like most women have abortions because they feel alone or they're abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00] Or they're forced to have an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Or their male partner is very passive.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, men today want to support women so much.
[SPEAKER_00] And I feel that it's gone over the limit.
[SPEAKER_00] Like, you know, men are, I'll support what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_00] And sometimes they're, they're not good things like abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Right?
[SPEAKER_00] So there's men that are indifferent or passive and working with women and men who have had abortions.
[SPEAKER_00] I could tell you that 90% of abortions are probably because the man is in crisis and he's scared to be a father.
[SPEAKER_00] And he doesn't want, he doesn't want that, you know, pregnancy to continue.
[SPEAKER_00] And he wants that abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] So I feel that, you know, abortion is also a male's issue, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00] And men also need to go heal.
[SPEAKER_00] But when he comforted me, my boyfriend, that gave me the power to continue my pregnancy.
[SPEAKER_00] Until my friends came over one day and then the fear came back.
[SPEAKER_00] They told me I was making the worst mistake of my life.
[SPEAKER_00] What are you doing?
[SPEAKER_00] And then I decided to have an abortion without telling him the truth.
[SPEAKER_01] So Patricia, you said about your boyfriend, that he was supportive.
[SPEAKER_01] He wanted to take care of you and everything.
[SPEAKER_01] And you choose to have an abortion because someone told you that it is your right and that you should do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's your choice, your body.
[SPEAKER_01] Those were also arguments for doing abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Right.
[SPEAKER_00] I think the root of all abortion is fear.
[SPEAKER_00] So a lot of women, they think my parents are going to get very angry.
[SPEAKER_00] They're going to kick me out of the house.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't have a job or I can't financially support this child or I'm alone or even for shame.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, there's shame.
[SPEAKER_00] What are people going to think about me?
[SPEAKER_00] I'm not in a stable relationship.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I feel like the root of it all is fear.
[SPEAKER_00] And if women only knew that there's a lot of help, there's a lot of pregnancy centers,
[SPEAKER_00] in different parts of the world and cities.
[SPEAKER_00] We just don't know where they are.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, we need to know where they are.
[SPEAKER_00] And these centers offer spiritual help, emotional help, financial help, you know, for mother and baby.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I think, you know, these women don't know all the help that they and support that they have, that there is help.
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, yes, I tell women that are pregnant and they're thinking about having an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] I say, yes, your parents might get mad at you.
[SPEAKER_00] They might be angry.
[SPEAKER_00] And yes, people will judge you and point you.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] But once you have that baby, it will all change.
[SPEAKER_00] That baby will be the light and the joy of your family and your parents will forget.
[SPEAKER_00] Your parents will be the best grandparents and they'll forget.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's what usually happens, you know, during the pregnancy of the young girl that's in crisis.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes, her family members are mad.
[SPEAKER_00] But when that baby is born, it's the light of the family.
[SPEAKER_01] And I also think that maybe they're not mad.
[SPEAKER_01] They're also fear or disappointed.
[SPEAKER_00] They're disappointed because that's not what we want for our children.
[SPEAKER_00] Right.
[SPEAKER_00] But unfortunately, it can happen to anybody.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I, you know, I always tell parents, we want the best for our child.
[SPEAKER_00] But if your child, you need to tell your child if I don't want to, I don't want, you know, to you to get pregnant at an early age, you know, teach them about chastity.
[SPEAKER_00] But if this were to happen, I will support life.
[SPEAKER_00] Right. And I had a friend of mine.
[SPEAKER_00] She's a single mother.
[SPEAKER_00] She has a daughter.
[SPEAKER_00] And she said, the reason I did not have an abortion is because when I was a child, my father said, I want you to be pure until marriage.
[SPEAKER_00] I want you to live a chaste life.
[SPEAKER_00] But if you were to get pregnant, never have an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Always come to me and I will always support you.
[SPEAKER_00] No matter if even though I'm disappointed, I will support you.
[SPEAKER_00] And she remembered those words of her father 20 years later.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's why her child is alive today, because her father said that.
[SPEAKER_00] And so we, you know, yes, we were disappointed.
[SPEAKER_00] We're angry.
[SPEAKER_00] We have to remember that life is a gift, no matter what the circumstances and that we need to support these women.
[SPEAKER_01] And so you came back home and your mother told you that she was praying in front of the Blessed Sacrament.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] For your life and for you to come home.
[SPEAKER_01] And what then?
[SPEAKER_00] My mother took me to a confession, thank God, and I went to daily mass.
[SPEAKER_00] But, you know, God healed me through the power of the sacraments.
[SPEAKER_00] He healed the wanting to kill myself, the drug addiction, the depression, anxiety, all that, even the hair pulling.
[SPEAKER_00] It's been, I mean, I still do it sometimes, but it's been much, much, much, much, much healed.
[SPEAKER_00] But I couldn't forgive my abortions.
[SPEAKER_00] That was very hard because not only did I know that I killed, but I saw it.
[SPEAKER_00] I saw what goes behind the doors of an abortion clinic.
[SPEAKER_00] It's hell on earth, literally.
[SPEAKER_00] And I couldn't forgive myself.
[SPEAKER_00] I knew the priest forgave me because I would confess that over and over.
[SPEAKER_00] I could hear that God forgave me, but I just, there was something missing.
[SPEAKER_00] And when I went to this healing retreat and it's for men and women, usually all post-abortion healing retreats are for men and women.
[SPEAKER_00] because men need to heal too.
[SPEAKER_00] I actually, during a prayer, saw my three aborted children.
[SPEAKER_00] I saw my daughter, Mariana, my son, Emmanuel, and my little girl, Rosario.
[SPEAKER_00] And they said, Mama, we are alive in God's glory and we're praying for you.
[SPEAKER_00] And they just, when I woke up from that vision to feel from murder to mama, I thought that God's mercy was so great and that my children forgave me.
[SPEAKER_00] That gave me the confidence to forgive myself.
[SPEAKER_00] And I healed so much.
[SPEAKER_00] If it wasn't for that healing retreat, I wouldn't be doing what I'm doing today.
[SPEAKER_00] That retreat changed my life.
[SPEAKER_00] And that retreat gave me my purpose.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, sometimes we don't know what our purpose in life is.
[SPEAKER_00] We don't know what God's will is.
[SPEAKER_00] But out of my misery, God used my misery to give my life salvation, my life purpose.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I'm really grateful for that healing retreat.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm also doing a healing retreat for the women who have had an abortion.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's really fruitful and it's really blessed when they gave names to their children.
[SPEAKER_01] So can you please explain to us the symbolism of the three names?
[SPEAKER_00] Right.
[SPEAKER_00] So the scripture says, God says that I called you by your name before you were even born.
[SPEAKER_00] So God gave us an identity.
[SPEAKER_00] He gave us a name.
[SPEAKER_00] We have a name.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's, you know, women have to remember that those souls, those souls are their children.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, they're children and they have an identity.
[SPEAKER_00] And so by praying to God, okay, I recommend women to pray before the blessed sacrament or during mass.
[SPEAKER_00] Ask God, what is the sex of my child?
[SPEAKER_00] Was it a girl or a boy?
[SPEAKER_00] And God will let the woman know.
[SPEAKER_00] God will let the woman know.
[SPEAKER_00] And then name your children.
[SPEAKER_00] Give them that identity.
[SPEAKER_01] And how did you choose yours, your names?
[SPEAKER_00] So Mariana, I chose because it's the name of the Blessed Virgin Mary and her mother, Saint Anne, Mariana.
[SPEAKER_00] Emmanuel means God with us.
[SPEAKER_00] And Rosario is in honor of the rosary, the Holy Rosary.
[SPEAKER_00] That is a powerful weapon.
[SPEAKER_01] So about the rosary, you pray the rosary.
[SPEAKER_01] You think it's a source of wisdom and source of peace and everything.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] So the rosary is non-negotiable for me and my family.
[SPEAKER_00] We actually pray it as a family because it has more power.
[SPEAKER_00] There are priests and bishops that said that the evil one cannot attack the little children as much when the family prays the Holy Rosary at home together.
[SPEAKER_00] And you actually, there's a book called The Secret of the Rosary by the Saint Louis de Montfort.
[SPEAKER_00] And in this book, Our Lady reveals to Saint Louis de Montfort that if you pray your rosary by yourself, you gain the merit of one rosary.
[SPEAKER_00] But if you pray the rosary with a community or with your family, say, you know, we're a family of five or four, I gain the merit of four rosaries.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's much powerful.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you pray the rosary with a hundred people in your church, it's like you gave Our Lady a hundred rosaries.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's a powerful weapon against evil.
[SPEAKER_00] There's promises that Our Lady gives if those who are devoted to the rosary.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's also a way to talk to your mama every day.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, most of us are married and we don't live with our mothers and we call them on the phone.
[SPEAKER_00] And so the rosary, it's like calling your mama to heaven, right?
[SPEAKER_00] And when you hold the rosary in your hand and you have the rosary in your pocket, it's like Our Lady is holding your hand all day.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's just after the Holy Mass, I think it's the most powerful prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] That's so good.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01] I really love this.
[SPEAKER_01] So can you please tell us how old were you when you were going to the healing retreat?
[SPEAKER_01] And after that, how long has it passed when you felt ready to go outside and how it all started for you to have this public speaking and everything?
[SPEAKER_00] So after my mother and, you know, started to pray for me and I was rescued off the street, I was 22 years old.
[SPEAKER_00] And I feel that from I did my healing retreat at 27, but I was healing all of the abortion, going to healing masses retreats.
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, I was going to daily mass.
[SPEAKER_00] So I felt like a lot of healing was going on in my life.
[SPEAKER_00] But then when I was 26 years old is when I went to my healing retreat and that completely healed me from from abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] It was it was it was amazing.
[SPEAKER_00] So I didn't know that I was still angry at many people, you know, or at myself.
[SPEAKER_00] I had to learn to forgive my abortionists that lied to me.
[SPEAKER_00] I had to forgive all the educators, the sexual educators and the abortionists that came to my school.
[SPEAKER_00] I had to forgive the workers that lied to me also, even the people that I worked with in Planned Parenthood, the manager that lied to me.
[SPEAKER_00] I had to forgive people that were involved with my abortion because it's murder.
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, it's really, really important that men and women go to a healing retreat because it took me five years to go.
[SPEAKER_00] My mother would say, you need to go to an abortion healing retreat.
[SPEAKER_00] And I would say, no, mama, I already went to confession.
[SPEAKER_00] I went to all these healing masses.
[SPEAKER_00] I go to daily mass.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't need that.
[SPEAKER_00] That's not for me.
[SPEAKER_00] But there was still shame.
[SPEAKER_00] The reason I didn't go is because I still felt so much shame.
[SPEAKER_00] Even when I drove got arrived on my healing retreat, I arrived on a Friday.
[SPEAKER_00] I was in the parking lot and I put reverse on my car and I was going to leave.
[SPEAKER_00] And I said, this is not for me.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't need this.
[SPEAKER_00] And a priest stopped me in the parking lot and opened my car door and opened my trunk and took my luggage out.
[SPEAKER_00] And he said, welcome.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was, I had no, I was stuck.
[SPEAKER_00] Right.
[SPEAKER_00] But it's so important because abortion damages the five senses of the woman.
[SPEAKER_00] So when she goes into abortion clinic, she sees everything around her.
[SPEAKER_00] She hears the vacuum sound.
[SPEAKER_00] So the sight, the, you know, the hearing, she touches the abortionist hand.
[SPEAKER_00] She touches abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] She hears abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] She sees abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] She smells abortion because abortion has a smell.
[SPEAKER_00] It smells like death in that clinic.
[SPEAKER_00] So when a woman goes to confession, you know, she's receiving God's mercy through one sense.
[SPEAKER_00] But the other, all the other is damaged, right?
[SPEAKER_00] Her memory, her motion is damaged.
[SPEAKER_00] And so just, you know, a five minute confession, it's not enough, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] And so these abortion healing retreats help heal the whole, the whole woman and the whole man.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's very important that they specifically go to a healing retreat for abortion, not just a regular general healing retreat.
[SPEAKER_00] It has to be for abortion.
[SPEAKER_01] And what were you doing through all these years?
[SPEAKER_01] Were you working or studying or something else?
[SPEAKER_00] After my healing?
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] What was life through those years?
[SPEAKER_00] So when I was healing, I felt terrible.
[SPEAKER_00] Like, because, you know, I was, thank God, you know, that I, he forgave me, but I still felt like a failure.
[SPEAKER_00] Like I, you know, hit my lowest point.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm never going to get a good job.
[SPEAKER_00] No one's ever going to marry me because I had three abortions.
[SPEAKER_00] And when the moment a man finds out, he will reject me immediately.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't see much for my, like for my life.
[SPEAKER_00] I accepted God's mercy.
[SPEAKER_00] I was happy.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, but I, I'm very surprised at what God has been in my life.
[SPEAKER_00] So I have a beautiful husband.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, he's like a Saint Joseph.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, he supports me on this mission and God gave me two, uh, little girls.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't know if I can have a child after three abortions, because when you have one abortion, you run the risk of being infertile.
[SPEAKER_00] So God's given me two little girls and I'm still trying to have family.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, so he's given me a beautiful family and now I'm doing his work.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's really funny because I had abortions because I wanted to travel the world.
[SPEAKER_00] I wanted to be successful and it was all about me.
[SPEAKER_00] And God gave me those desires, but for his glory.
[SPEAKER_00] So now I am traveling the world.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, but it's not about me anymore.
[SPEAKER_00] I just tell my sins and my misery.
[SPEAKER_00] Now it's about him and his glory.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, so he does fulfill the desires of your heart in a more amazing way.
[SPEAKER_01] And what can you tell about the prayer, your prayer life, spiritual battle or everything that you've gone through?
[SPEAKER_00] So when I started to come to God and I went to my first confession, the spiritual battle was terrible.
[SPEAKER_00] I would have demonic influence at night attack me, physically attack me.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and, uh, I still go through spiritual warfare.
[SPEAKER_00] I think a lot of us do when we serve God, especially in the pro-life movement.
[SPEAKER_00] Youth have felt this also.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, because, um, first, uh, St. Faustina said this, the abbess of hell, the abbess of hell, all hell goes against the priest.
[SPEAKER_00] They want to, uh, you know, knock the priest out of his vocation.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and then the enemy in all hell goes against, uh, humans with the sin of lust and sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00] Abortion is a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00] It's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00] The problem is disordered sexuality that we have.
[SPEAKER_00] Abortion is just a symptom of that.
[SPEAKER_00] So we have to go to the root.
[SPEAKER_00] We have to fix the root.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, we have to tell people that they need to be virtuous and, and chaste.
[SPEAKER_00] They need to live purity again, right?
[SPEAKER_00] That will solve abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] If everybody lived purity and waited for sex until marriage, how it was created to be, there would not be no abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] That's, that's, that's the, you know, the solution to abortion is chaste, being chaste.
[SPEAKER_00] And, um, so the attacks have been great.
[SPEAKER_00] The spiritual warfare, the persecution is great also when you defend life.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and, but, uh, we have to remember that the triumph is our lady's triumph and the victory is Jesus.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, we get overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_00] We want to stop abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] And we think, oh, the laws are getting worse or, you know, abortion is spreading like cancer.
[SPEAKER_00] But God doesn't call us to fix the result.
[SPEAKER_00] He calls us to be faithful and the result is his.
[SPEAKER_00] And we know the result.
[SPEAKER_00] He's victor victorious because he died on the cross.
[SPEAKER_00] So the triumph is Jesus and our ladies.
[SPEAKER_00] So we just have to be faithful and serve pro-life.
[SPEAKER_00] But my prayer life as a mother has changed.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, of course I have less time to pray, but little prayers throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_00] But very, with my whole heart.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and I pray now with a family.
[SPEAKER_00] So yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Those are little arrows in the sky.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] But the pro-life, the pro-lifer, the person that defends life, very important that they're
[SPEAKER_00] in a state of grace.
[SPEAKER_00] You cannot defend life.
[SPEAKER_00] You cannot go into this battle without literally going to confession frequently, taking the Holy
[SPEAKER_00] Eucharist and being in a state of grace.
[SPEAKER_00] Because what you do in the pro-life movement is that you're taking Satan's food away.
[SPEAKER_00] Because abortion, the sacrifice of abortion is Satan's food.
[SPEAKER_00] The baby, the soul goes to God.
[SPEAKER_00] But the killing, the murder on that abortion table, Satan's at the end of that table.
[SPEAKER_00] He is there.
[SPEAKER_00] He's ready to take that sacrifice.
[SPEAKER_00] So as pro-lifers, we can't go into battle being weak or think, you know, or what happens
[SPEAKER_00] sometimes that if we get too involved in activism, you know, we talk about God, but we are not close
[SPEAKER_00] to God.
[SPEAKER_00] And so we have to be very careful that we're in a state of grace and that we're, we are fueled
[SPEAKER_00] and we're covered with the sacraments so that we can continue this battle.
[SPEAKER_01] So this is so good.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's so good to know how to battle this and how to go through this and not to become active,
[SPEAKER_01] just active and good and like Pharisees.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] But to be like apostles.
[SPEAKER_01] Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01] That's so good.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01] I really love this.
[SPEAKER_01] So you were talking yesterday about the communion of Satan, like those babies and their blood
[SPEAKER_01] and everything that he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] So I feel that the root of violence and country and Mother Teresa Calcutta has, she said this,
[SPEAKER_00] there will never be peace in the world until there's peace in the womb.
[SPEAKER_00] And she said, don't be, and she said in another quote, don't be surprised when you're here
[SPEAKER_00] of war in your country and people killing each other and violence.
[SPEAKER_00] He said, it's because it's those countries that have accepted abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, you know, when, when our lady Fatima was speaking about the conversion of Russia, Russia,
[SPEAKER_00] you know, communism, Russia is the first country in the world that we're having many abortions
[SPEAKER_00] in hospitals, even before it was legal.
[SPEAKER_00] Russia is the first country that accepted abortion into their country.
[SPEAKER_00] That's what our lady Fatima was also talking about.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and then after the abortion started, communism started.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, so, you know, Croatia, we, you know, you guys have experienced war here, but now war
[SPEAKER_00] is still going on in Croatia.
[SPEAKER_00] It's the, and it's the bigger than the one that happened in the nineties, because now it's
[SPEAKER_00] children being killed by their mothers in the womb.
[SPEAKER_00] There's nothing more awful than that.
[SPEAKER_00] than that.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's still going on.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you know, uh, a country that does not have abortion is a country that will have more peace.
[SPEAKER_00] A country that accepts abortion, like Mother Teresa Takahara said, is the poorest country,
[SPEAKER_00] and there will always be violence.
[SPEAKER_01] And what did you say about the friendship with the unborn children?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] I like that.
[SPEAKER_01] It's so sweet, but it's very strong.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] You know that the unborn, uh, they don't have many friends.
[SPEAKER_00] They have many enemies and John 15:15.
[SPEAKER_00] And the Bible says that there's no greater love than to give your life for a friend.
[SPEAKER_00] And when you serve pro-life, you give your life.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, we don't have to die physically, but we are called to die to ourselves every day.
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, when you, when you serve pro-life, you give your all, you know, you're tired.
[SPEAKER_00] You're, you're, um, you know, you're being judged.
[SPEAKER_00] You're being criticized.
[SPEAKER_00] You're being bullied.
[SPEAKER_00] You lose family members.
[SPEAKER_00] You die.
[SPEAKER_00] Things of you die.
[SPEAKER_00] And, but you're giving your life, uh, for your little friends that don't have a voice.
[SPEAKER_00] And I, I believe that in Jesus' eyes, there's no greater love than to give your life for
[SPEAKER_00] the pro-life movement.
[SPEAKER_01] And what is the sacrifice of being in a pro-life movement?
[SPEAKER_01] Do you lose your family, your friends?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] The Bible says, Jesus says, I did not come to unite.
[SPEAKER_00] I caught, I came to cause division.
[SPEAKER_00] Mothers and fathers between daughters and sons and sisters and brothers.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and that's what exactly what happens when you start to defending life.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you figure out who are your friends and who, who, where, and where they stand on life.
[SPEAKER_00] And even your family members.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, to this day, I have controversy with my closest family members.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, were divided on the issue.
[SPEAKER_00] And many of them don't speak to me.
[SPEAKER_00] I've lost a lot of friends.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, I've had a lot of persecution from the abortion clinic.
[SPEAKER_00] Also, they tried to throw me in jail.
[SPEAKER_00] And I knew this when I went public.
[SPEAKER_00] But you know, um, there, you know, when you have peace in your, in your heart.
[SPEAKER_00] I always thought that peace was being on a beach in Croatia maybe and having alcohol and resting.
[SPEAKER_00] And I thought, Oh God, give me that peace.
[SPEAKER_00] But then a priest said to me, no, that's not real peace.
[SPEAKER_00] Peace actually equals strength.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, he said the martyrs.
[SPEAKER_00] They, they, they, they, they, you know, they, with standard their martyrdom.
[SPEAKER_00] Because they had peace that they were doing what God was asking them to do that they were in God's will.
[SPEAKER_00] And so when you defend life and it's really hard.
[SPEAKER_00] And everything is going wrong around you and your family members are against you.
[SPEAKER_00] And it just feels like everything's falling apart.
[SPEAKER_00] At least you can have peace knowing God, this is what you've asked me to do.
[SPEAKER_00] And if I die tonight and you come for me, I have peace because I know where I'm going.
[SPEAKER_00] And I'm doing what you're asking me.
[SPEAKER_00] That's great peace.
[SPEAKER_00] Peace is not relaxing. Peace is strength.
[SPEAKER_01] And I, um, I just knew something, um, there is a difference between, um, keeper of a peace and peacemaker.
[SPEAKER_01] Because the Bible says blessed are a peacemaker.
[SPEAKER_01] They should be called the son of God.
[SPEAKER_01] And what I realized through my life that someone who is a keeper of a peace.
[SPEAKER_01] He just said, don't move.
[SPEAKER_01] Let it be peace.
[SPEAKER_01] Don't talk too much.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, he's indifferent.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] And when you peace, want to be a peacemaker, you have to go where the war is and make peace.
[SPEAKER_01] Oh, that's beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's really making a difference.
[SPEAKER_00] Because when you're a keeper of the peace, you are silent.
[SPEAKER_00] You don't want controversy.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you're indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00] You don't want fun, fight.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, you're passive and you are part of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00] So people that are indifferent about abortion are part of the problem, not the solution.
[SPEAKER_01] So, uh, what can you tell, uh, to men who needs to defend life, who have to go to the
[SPEAKER_01] healing retreat and everything about the men population?
[SPEAKER_01] What can you tell to them?
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, men, you were created for greatness.
[SPEAKER_00] You were created to be the authority and the head of the family.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you will be held accountable by God.
[SPEAKER_00] Did you protect the purity of your wife?
[SPEAKER_00] Did you protect your own purity?
[SPEAKER_00] Did you protect the way you looked at women?
[SPEAKER_00] Did you protect the purity of your children?
[SPEAKER_00] Did you protect the way your daughter was dressed?
[SPEAKER_00] Or what your children saw on TV or what music they heard?
[SPEAKER_00] Were you the great protector of their purity?
[SPEAKER_00] St. Joseph was the great protector of purity, of his own purity, of Our Lady's purity,
[SPEAKER_00] and of Jesus, of the whole family.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is your obligation to protect your family from the evil one.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is your obligation that your family become saints just as yourself.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, it's, it's, it's important that, uh, that men, they regain their authority
[SPEAKER_00] and that they become virtuous because they are the spiritual leaders of their family.
[SPEAKER_00] And when this happens, a whole family is healed and a whole family is powerful.
[SPEAKER_00] And when a family is powerful, the society starts changing.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I believe that to change the world and to change society, it always has to start at home.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, it's the family is the most important, the nuclear, the nuclear.
[SPEAKER_00] That's why, that's why, um, uh, Lucia from Fatima said that the final battle between God and the kingdom of Satan will be against the family.
[SPEAKER_00] Because it is through the family that a whole nation can heal.
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, for men that have had abortions, it's so important.
[SPEAKER_00] You need healing.
[SPEAKER_00] You have to get healing.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, we've, we, uh, we've come to an era where there's a crisis in fatherhood.
[SPEAKER_00] Where 80% of households around the world are, the head is the woman because she's a single mother.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, we have many men that are wounded by abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you don't heal that, you're never going to be a good husband.
[SPEAKER_00] You're never going to be a good father.
[SPEAKER_00] There's always going to be a wound there.
[SPEAKER_00] And so in order to have a strong man, a strong husband, a strong father, um, guiding their family to holiness and to wholeness, you need to, you need to, you need to heal first.
[SPEAKER_00] And so, you know, many kids today, how many kids thought they have a father wound?
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and it's a big crisis that we're facing today.
[SPEAKER_00] Fatherless nation, fatherless generation.
[SPEAKER_00] And we need men to take responsibility for their actions and to step up and be leaders once again.
[SPEAKER_01] And what about the women who have had an abortion or who want to abort their babies or something like that?
[SPEAKER_00] So for women who are pregnant and they're contemplating abortion, I just want to say congratulations.
[SPEAKER_00] You are a mother already.
[SPEAKER_00] It's not that you're going to be a mother or you're not ready to be a mother.
[SPEAKER_00] I need to be a mother.
[SPEAKER_00] You are a mother.
[SPEAKER_00] And I feel we don't congratulate women enough.
[SPEAKER_00] We always come with, you're so young.
[SPEAKER_00] What are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_00] You don't have a job.
[SPEAKER_00] It's, we always instill fear.
[SPEAKER_00] And so congratulations.
[SPEAKER_00] You're not alone.
[SPEAKER_00] There's so much help and support.
[SPEAKER_00] There's so many people in the pro-life movement, um, around your area.
[SPEAKER_00] You can find, you can Google, um, that will help you with all of your needs.
[SPEAKER_00] And you know, it's going to be hard, you know, during your pregnancy.
[SPEAKER_00] It's not going to be easy.
[SPEAKER_00] That's, that's truth.
[SPEAKER_00] But that child is going to be the light of your life.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and for women who've had abortions, there is hope and there's forgiveness after abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] and there's healing and there's restoration.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, God can restore your life and God can give you a beautiful family.
[SPEAKER_00] Once again, if that's his will, um, and to look for healing, that's very important.
[SPEAKER_01] Do you have maybe some testimony?
[SPEAKER_01] Because I know that for many years you were at a post-abortive healing retreat.
[SPEAKER_01] Do you have some testimony?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So I, I've had, uh, many testimonies on, uh, on women who've had abortions because their parents forced them to.
[SPEAKER_00] Right.
[SPEAKER_00] And that, that happens a lot because the parents are ashamed because what will they say?
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, I think when I am in those retreats, it's harder for the woman to forgive the parents more than the abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Right.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I've seen just miraculous healings with the whole family together.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, with the parents really repenting that they actually, uh, killed their own grandchild.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, you see these women walk into the retreat on a Friday afternoon.
[SPEAKER_00] You could see it in their body.
[SPEAKER_00] They're, they're, they're looking down, their bodies hunched over with, with shame.
[SPEAKER_00] No confidence.
[SPEAKER_00] You could see it in the face.
[SPEAKER_00] And I see God's transfiguration in them on Sunday when they leave.
[SPEAKER_00] Their body is up.
[SPEAKER_00] Their face is glowing.
[SPEAKER_00] There's a smile.
[SPEAKER_00] There's hope.
[SPEAKER_00] And you can see, you can actually physically see a miracle in two days or three days with these women.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, even just the way they're, they reflect, you know, light and, and, and healing.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, I have seen women who have had abortions by their own biological father that, you know, many women that have been raped.
[SPEAKER_00] Usually rape, uh, happens within the families, either the stepfather, the father or the uncle or the brother.
[SPEAKER_00] That's very common.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, impose abortion healing.
[SPEAKER_00] There's a big link between rape or sexual abuse and abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Always.
[SPEAKER_00] Most women who've had abortions.
[SPEAKER_00] There's some type of leak with sexual abuse in their childhood.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, that's very common.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, I've seen healing with that, you know, with incest and rape and these abortion retreats, not only heal the abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Cause like I mentioned, abortion is a symptom of something, something happened to you in your past or in your childhood that led you to that abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] And what I see at these healing retreats is that not only do they heal from their abortion, but they heal from wounds and trauma from their childhood as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, so, uh, Patricia, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, do we have, um, something that you would love to say to the post-abortive women and men, and also to all the people.
[SPEAKER_01] Why should I get involved in a pro-life movement?
[SPEAKER_01] Maybe here in Croatia with 40 days for life.
[SPEAKER_01] And how do you see us here now that you spent some days?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So I want to tell the men and women who've had an abortion to not be ashamed, uh, to not fear.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, God's waiting for you to heal.
[SPEAKER_00] He wants to heal that part of your life.
[SPEAKER_00] He wants to set you free.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, so do everything possible.
[SPEAKER_00] The enemy will try to keep you away from a healing retreat like he did with me for five years.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, but please seek a more healing, um, on your abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, I can guarantee you that, that you are going to be so grateful that you did it.
[SPEAKER_00] And for everybody watching, you know, abortion exists in Croatia.
[SPEAKER_00] I think it's until the first trimester, but you only need, uh, the first trimester or a little lot of come into a country for it to get extreme.
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, my country in the United States, abortion is legal until the moment of birth.
[SPEAKER_00] Abortion is, uh, you know, legal.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, when a woman has an abortion at nine months, eight months, if the baby survives, it's legal in a couple of states to kill the baby after.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, California legalized infanticide.
[SPEAKER_00] A baby is born.
[SPEAKER_00] The mom doesn't want the baby anymore.
[SPEAKER_00] Up to 28 days.
[SPEAKER_00] The baby can actually die and be killed.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, many people didn't believe me in my talk, but this is true.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, we've legalized infanticide.
[SPEAKER_00] It's, it went from having an abortion.
[SPEAKER_00] If you were raped first trimester in our country, 1973 to babies now born being killed.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and so it's so important that you are involved in the pro-life movement to pray for the women and men who are scared.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, when there's a pregnancy, uh, to pray for the conversion of abortionists and everybody that works in the abortion industry and Croatia to actually go to these abortion clinics.
[SPEAKER_00] If you know where they are to pray outside, many miracles happen.
[SPEAKER_00] When you pray the rosary outside, many miracles happen and to speak because God will hold you accountable.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, don't be indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, if you know a friend that's had an abortion, maybe just say, I'm praying for you.
[SPEAKER_00] I, you know, if anything that could do for you to help you because she needs to speak to somebody.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and if somebody talks about, you know, being in favor of abortion, don't be scared to speak against it.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's so important that you have formation and education.
[SPEAKER_00] So you have to actually defend life, you know, and actually defend your Catholic faith.
[SPEAKER_00] And then you can actually talk to your children about these things of the world that they're learning in school that are not true and that can harm your children.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's just important that you're active in your formation, education, and that you're bold.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, God vomits the lukewarm.
[SPEAKER_00] So we're living in such hard times where you can't be gray.
[SPEAKER_00] Either you're black or you're white.
[SPEAKER_00] You got to be, you know, either you're for God or you're not for God.
[SPEAKER_00] And you just need to be bold and not worry about what people think.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you for being bold.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you for coming to Croatia.
[SPEAKER_01] And I really appreciate having you here.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you, Patricia.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00] I love this country and I love your people.
[SPEAKER_00] I have so many gifts.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know how I'm going to take them home from everybody in Croatia that's been gifting.
[SPEAKER_00] Not only me, but my children and my husband.
[SPEAKER_00] And so your country is beautiful and your people are beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN] Hvala što pratite kanal.