!!!!
So thank you.
So now we have the last session of this admin conference.
Which is probably not the least important topic, which is the financial aspect of this.
So I am the chair of this panel and I have a couple of slides on my country, Iceland,on the current situation.
Which I think that fit very neatly with the discussion previously on the labour market.
So this is the policy rate in Iceland.
And in fact, just before I came to this conference on Wednesday,we raised the policy rate by 125 persons.
And this is a policy response.
We are using one policy to basically to cool on overheating economy.
As you can see inflation in most of the countries is beginning to slide.
But it's starting to rise in our country.
Or not going down.
Inflation in Iceland is now about 9.5%.
And has been on this level now for like six months.
One of the main problems is the labour market.
Because we have seen Iceland is probably the only country in Europe where the people have not taken a real wage cut.
People's nominal wage increases have kept up with inflation.
And what we are about to see might be the beginning of an wage inflation spiral.
And that is one of the reasons for why we decided to take this very drastic message.
And this comes on top of a situation that we have an economy that is growing very rapidly.
And the turn of events in the world in the past one or two years has actually been a very positive supply shock for us.
First of all, the price of our exports are increasing.
Our main exports are actually aluminum, fish.
And then the tourism sector is booming.
And especially visitors from the US.
But it's more than that because what has basically happened is that the value of our resources has increased.
Because Iceland is mostly carbon free.
Ninety percent of our households use thermal energy with heating.
So what we are now seeing is an increased interest in investment in our country.
And in various aspects.
But this is a slide just telling about the population increase.
Iceland is a very young population.
The population growth has been very rapid by natural causes.
Icelandic women tend to have many kids compared with what is in Europe.
But also we have seen a huge inflow of labor.
We are part of the European economic area.
And we have seen -- I mean all of Western Europe has seen an influx of foreign labor.
But Iceland is basically exceptional.
Population is growing very rapidly.
And this is our natural growth path.
We have a much higher rate of long-term growth.
And growth last year was about six, seven percent real.
And we project it to be five percent this year.
And what we've seen -- also see that -- I think there was this phrase yesterday by -- I think that --
a quote in Max Fritz that we imported labor.
But what we got was people.
Because the foreign workers, they need a place to stay.
And increasingly people, foreign workers that come to a country, they increasingly are buying houses.
And want to stay in a country.
And that is creating a huge housing shortage.
And, you know, rising housing prices.
And now currently about 20, 25 percent of our labor force is foreign born.
And so far this has been going quite well.
There hasn't -- haven't been any serious problems.
Well, xenophobia or anything like that.
We -- most of the people that we -- that are in our country are just --
-- it is basically recognized in Iceland that these foreign workers are -- basically have a positive impact on our economy.
After the financial crisis, we -- as I will tell you about, we have been quite focused on keeping leverage down.
Because we got into this financial bubble, a huge inflow of foreign capital, which then ended in a crisis.
So as I will show you, we have been following a policy of very strict macroprudential measures to keep leverage down.
Also to keep the foreign exposure of the economy at a minimum.
And just to recap, we had -- in 2008, we had a financial crisis, systematic banking collapse.
And I would like to quote Giovanni in a pun yesterday, saying that there are financial stabilizers if the system is closed.
Of course, if the -- if the -- if the -- if the system is open, and money is trying to flee out to the country, it becomes a disaster.
As it -- as it was to the -- so -- so in order to -- to take control over financial system, we did two things.
Capital controls and also complete deposit insurance.
Which basically gave us time to reorganize the banking sector.
And which was basically cut down -- you had the banking system that was ten times our output.
And basically, we took force mature rights to cut the banks in two parts.
Foreign part that was put into liquidation and the domestic part that was recapitalized.
And behind capital controls, we basically built a new financial system.
The controls were basically abolished.
And I would like to mention that the -- we were in a -- the capital controls, they were operated with -- within the care of the IMF.
And the leader of the IMF contingent in Iceland is here, Paul Thomson.
He was actually sent to Iceland in 2008.
And it's basically the Iceland case also proved to be kind of a policy change with the IMF.
So -- so what have we done since?
First of all, it was very clear that we had to integrate and distribute responsibility for monetary policy, finance stability, and supervision.
Which basically means giving it to the central bank.
And so the central bank, which I represent, has basically a full mandate in financial stability, supervision, and monetary policy.
So if something goes wrong, it's very clear who is to blame.
It will just take me away, I guess.
But that has given us a level of control.
We have also accumulated a lot of foreign reserves.
We used the tourist boom to accumulate reserves, which are now about 35% of our GDP.
We have been using these reserves to manage the currency market, to keep it stable.
And there are very strict controls of how you can take one external debt.
Because in a small open economy, accumulating foreign debt can become an externality to others.
And also we limit also the use of FX futures, which are the main vehicles for carry trade or that.
Secondly, we enforce very high capital ratios of the banks, between 20-30%.
We have borrower-based measures.
You cannot get a mortgage in Iceland unless that you have, there is a 75%, you have 25% equity to being able to get a mortgage, for example.
And then very strict financial regulation.
And there are actually a couple of lessons I would like to take.
And so I see that the, essentially, that the American banking system is, there are, is in a, I think, in a kind of a systematic trouble, given that the banks there, they have, always when you implement a monetary tightening, there is a loss.
That is created.
It is just a question of who, who pairs the losses.
And so I am very clear that, given the bond holdings, or the US banking system, that, that the, the, um, um, equity ratios, or the market, or the market value of other equity is, is low or even zero.
And secondly, uh, as we've seen, there, there is a, um, lack of credibility, or, that the supervision is sufficiently, um, effective.
So I see, like, the, so-called systematic risk, um, exception, which, uh, which the, uh, which the, uh, which the, uh, has been, um, implemented, is basically, and in fact, a complete deposit guarantee.
And, uh, which I think that, um, cannot be basically abolished unless that there are done some structural changes in the, in the, um, in the American system.
Hvala što pratite kanal.
što pratite kanal.
hvala što pratite kanal.
Hvala što pratite kanal.
što pratite kanal.
hvala što pratite kanal.
Hvala što pratite kanal.
što pratite kanal.