Good morning, distinguished guests, ladies and gentlemen. Thank you so much for joining us for this very specific conversation as we talk about energy security and energy transition. We do have a short video to play for you first, and I will ask our speakers to join us on stage right now, but we are going to just do a little bit of scene setting for you as we roll out this video.
Thank you.
I'll see you next time.
Let's look back. Russia's invasion of Ukraine brought an end to abundant and relatively cheap natural gas imports to Europe. Energy prices in Europe spiked, and the continent experienced its biggest energy crisis in 50 years. Though prices have since fallen, they remain about three times higher than before the COVID-19 pandemic. Now, Europe's reliance on Russian natural gas has come to a grinding halt.
CESI countries were among the most dependent on gas imports from Russia before the war. Indeed, for some countries, these imports were the only source of gas. So, it's not surprising that the energy crisis has fueled inflation, especially in Europe's CESI economies, reduced household purchasing power, and slowed economic activity sharply across the continent. European governments responded swiftly with a range of measures
with a range of measures to diversify supply, improve trans-European energy infrastructure, and reduce demand. Gas producers, such as Norway, Qatar, the U.S., and Algeria, stepped in to fill the supply gap left by Russia.
Motivated by higher prices, policy changes, and helped by a warmer winter, households and firms reduced their gas consumption. Most EU countries introduced or extended tax breaks, price caps, targeted transfers, or energy vouchers. These measures
successfully reduce the energy costs passed through. But they come with undesirable side effects. They delay the necessary adjustment in demand. And while they benefit consumers in the country where they are introduced, they may lead to higher wholesale prices across the continent, hurting consumers in other countries.
So, these measures should be carefully designed and phased out as energy prices fall. Challenging times lie ahead. Energy-intensive firms that are bound by long-term contracts signed during the height of the crisis will likely remain strained for some time.
While EU countries have emerged from this past winter with higher than average levels of stored gas, replenishing those stores without Russian supplies could be harder this year.
At the same time, the world's largest gas importer, China, has ended its Zero-Covid strategy and the periodic shutdowns and reduction in Chinese energy demand it created. This could lead to tighter global markets.
Due to infrastructure bottlenecks, any gas shortage next winter may be distributed unequally, with the landlocked countries in Central and Eastern Europe being the most vulnerable. Energy security will remain a top priority in the years ahead.
The crisis also highlighted the complex interactions between energy security and climate objectives. Faced with emergency, some countries have substituted gas with much more carbon-intensive fuels,
such as coal, at the cost of increased greenhouse gas emissions in the short term.
In the medium term, however, there are clear synergies between energy security and the green transition, as reducing greenhouse gas emissions requires more renewables and less reliance on fossil fuels.
That's why it's critical that governments ramp up policies to incentivize the transition, including carbon pricing, which remains in its infancy across SESI.
With so many moving parts, questions remain: Are there signs or risks of deindustrialization as Europe loses competitiveness against other regions of the world with reliable access to cheap energy?
What more can be done to secure sufficient energy supplies from reliable sources over the medium term?
How best can the green energy transition be shaped to also enhance energy security?
So key questions already addressed there.
Now let me welcome to the stage our panel today.
Alfred Kammer, Director, European Department, International Monetary Fund.
Jan Svejner, Director, Centre on Global Economy and Governance, School of International and Public Affairs at Columbia University.
Paula Pino, Director for Just Transition: Consumers, Energy Efficiency and Innovation, Director General for Energy at the European Commission.
And finally, Olga Hakkova, who is Deputy Director, European Energy Security at the Atlantic Council.
So we're just going to start a little bit broad and take a little bit of a litmus test from the audience, that is you, as to where you think we're at this point in energy security.
I mean, there have been so many deep and complex topics and we cover them every day on CNBC.
What is very much in the backdrop at this point is where we go to from here.
I mean, we've been debating macroeconomic policy, where the Fed, where the ECB are going, what that does in terms of tightening credit conditions more.
I don't know whether you follow this, but we're talking about AI, generative AI and how disruptive that will be on economies, but also front and centre.
What happens next when it comes to energy security?
Who in this room thinks that we're through the energy crisis?
I'll ask you to stand up.
Does anyone believe we're done?
We're through winter.
We're through the height of the prices.
Do you think we're done when it comes to energy security?
So everybody then by default means that they believe we're all in an energy crisis still.
That is overwhelming or nobody felt like standing up.
So I guess you have to stand up now.
So the room does actually believe we're in an energy crisis.
Feel free to stand up.
You can't sit on the fence here.
You have to take a position.
So that means everybody has to stand up.
Okay, this is a good start because we are going to kick off a discussion here first up.
And we will be taking some questions from the audience.
So that does require you to be engaged and listen very attentively to the panel here.
I'm just going to let you know too that we have a special guest in the audience.
We have Peter Wood, who is Chief Energy Advisor at Shell.
Peter, if I can ask you to stand up.
So we might just bring a microphone over to Peter as well if we can.
We've got a live microphone here and if Peter could have that microphone
because we're going to ask him to weigh in too to some of the discussion.
Well, welcome everyone.
Thank you so much for joining us.
Alfred, if I can just switch to you on this topic as we discussed and just start a little bit broad here.
How have countries in Europe adjusted to dwindling gas supplies from Russia?
Where do you think we're at on this journey to achieve energy security and energy transition?
I think as the previous speakers have pointed out, we were faced with an unprecedented set of crises.
We came out of the pandemic and we had a very strong exit.
And I think one of the hallmarks of this exit was it was a result of very strong policies during the pandemic.
And then we were hit by the Russia's war in Ukraine with a massive energy crisis.
And we are still living through these repercussions and low growth this year.
The high inflation we are seeing is a large result of this intervention.
But it could have been worse and if not for policy action.
When you're looking at the outset last year, natural gas dependency of Europe, 84% imported.
40% of that coming from Russia.
The biggest concern was for the landlocked countries, Slovakia, Czech Republic, Hungary, but also Austria, Italy and Germany.
Because in the case of a Russian gas shutdown, they could actually have experienced a physical shortage.
And that meant rationing of gas.
That was avoided.
That would have led to a much worse outcome.
And it was avoided because of policy action.
On the supply side, what happened was a concerted effort to keep increased gas imports through pipelines.
But also to expand on the LNG side.
And when you're looking at what happened is Russian gas was reduced by 80 billion cubic meters.
55 billion cubic meters of that was made up by new supply and new imports.
That was part of the equation, but it was not all of the equation.
And the other part was really on the demand side.
And what happened on the demand side was largely going through the price mechanism.
And therefore it's important that prices speak and prices cause action.
What we had was a response on the demand side, which was also a reduction of 55 billion cubic meters.
And that came from a shutdown of production of some of the energy intensive products, like a fertilizer.
25% of that was made up.
40% came up from efficiency gains by households and firms.
And then we were lucky.
And a third of that demand shortfall was explained by a mild winter.
And what it helped us to do is not only come through the winter, but at the beginning of this year, storage levels were double as high as they were usually coming out of a winter.
And so we are set up, I think, going into the next winter with a relatively good way.
We just kicked off the session talking about the challenge that lies ahead.
I think about how much prices have moved, even on the oil side, Brent at 125 in June last year, trading either side of 80 these days.
When you look at the European gas price, we peaked at 3.22 dollars per megawatt hour, returning to more normal levels.
The price action looks like it's crisis averted.
But what's the risk from here?
What keeps you awake at night as you look forward in coming months?
I think what we need to focus also on was part of the government response, which was dealing with the cost of living crisis.
That was an important part for government to think about protecting the most vulnerable population.
And government overall have done a good job, too much so to some extent.
When we are looking at energy packages, the cost for 22, 23, 2.7 percent of GDP.
When we are looking at protecting the most vulnerable, 40 percent of the population, we could have done that in a targeted way with 1.5 percent of GDP.
more cheaper, better targeted, reaching the most vulnerable.
And why is that a concern? Not only because of the fiscal side.
It is also a concern because that adds to demand, that adds to inflation, that adds to centre bank needing to fight inflation.
And I think that is a concern we have.
Olga, let me switch to you.
We've got fiscal subsidies at play.
Market pricing has come down.
We've diversified supply chains.
We've ramped up storage.
Why are we still in an energy crisis?
Because there's a lot that can happen in the next several months, even the next three to four to five months.
So a couple of unpredictable variables that we're keeping an eye on.
There is no guarantee that Russian flows will keep going through Ukraine or I would even push as far as even Turkey.
Russia could be in a position where there could be some additional decisions made if they are in a certain desperate spot to create additional pressure on Europe.
There is a scenario where these supplies stop flowing through Ukraine.
Now, compared to last year, we are nowhere in the same position in terms of the transformation that needs to happen.
But when we're talking about shortages and multiple variables happening at the same time, it could still put additional strain.
Let's take a look at exacerbated impacts on weather patterns driven by climate change.
We got lucky.
This was said multiple times today with the warmer winter.
We could still have heat waves.
We could have cold snaps.
We could have impacts on hydro or other energy production.
And of course that interconnects to nuclear production across Europe.
That even interconnects on how well coal is delivered across Europe and across the world sometimes too.
There could be some technical outages that have nothing to do with malign actors or climate implications.
There could be cyber security concerns or cyber attacks on and there could be further critical infrastructure threats or even on the extreme.
You know, look at what happened in North Stream 1, North Stream 2.
There could be threats to the critical infrastructure across the world.
So we can't over-prepare for the upcoming winter.
So all of these things do keep me up at night.
All of these things, I don't feel like we can say that we're fully ready.
I think we need to continue over-preparing and looking at every single scenario and assuming that everything will go wrong.
And then we prepared for that and then we're going to be okay.
Jan, let me bring you in.
There's another layer here and that's the macroeconomic dynamics.
We've just seen a whole bunch of survey data suggesting that we have manufacturing contraction.
Even in core economies in Europe from France to Italy, Germany in recession.
We are now setting up for a challenging few months with interest rates also going up.
The challenge of energy security on top of that with already shrinking growth.
Just set the scene for us.
How difficult an environment are we looking at as we battle an energy crisis still?
It is a very difficult environment.
I agree with what Alfred and Olga mentioned.
Those are very important points and we have to realise that Europe is one of the slower growing or more vulnerable regions of the world.
The US is doing quite well compared to Europe and has been doing in the past.
China, as we saw, may be coming out of a slow period.
So if demand goes up from these countries, we can expect that prices of energy will go up with that.
OPEC is meeting in Vienna as we speak, trying to figure out can they somehow manage to raise prices by withholding production.
So I think that we are in a very difficult situation and Europe in particular is quite vulnerable and CSE parts of it are indeed under pressure and will be under pressure.
So the demand conditions will be important, supply will be crucial and development of alternative sources of course will be very, very important.
So I would say we are in a very uncertain type situation and going back to the earlier speakers, I think the question of adaptability, dynamism, resilience will be crucial.
And in Europe we have to count on the possibility of countries teetering on the verge of recession during this year.
Paula, let me turn to you. An energy crisis still looms. What are the biggest risks? How will the impacts be felt from here?
How will the impacts be felt from here if we don't get it right?
Well, we really need to look back and also see lessons learned, right?
And when you see where we started from and we were faced with a second crisis and we were in a context of Green Deal, European Green Deal transition to the first climate neutral continent in the world and then hits COVID.
And that was the first time that the Green Deal was put into question and said this is the end of it.
And then we had the next generation EU which really put forward unprecedented financial means as was said already today including by the Prime Minister which created unprecedented possibilities.
And then hit the energy crisis and again this is the end of the European Green Deal.
And not really. And Alfred described very well what were the sort of measures that were put into place in terms of short term but also in terms of longer term, the structural measures but also the emergency measures.
and we're not out yet but what we learned from last year is that through this combination of emergency measures on the supply, on the demand, on the infrastructure, on the prices, we came out and we survived the winter.
We're not out of the woods yet but hopefully we also learned a number of very, very valid lessons during this winter.
For instance we all of the sudden discovered the potential of energy efficiency.
Very interesting to hear from industry that they now looked into how can I manufacture more efficiently.
There hadn't been an incentive to do so before because gas prices were pretty low.
So why even look for alternatives?
I want to hope that these lessons are here to stay and lead to structural changes which will really allow us to be on a much more resilient path as we go forward.
Also when we see the deployment of renewable energy over the past year we have broken records.
We have added 47 percent of additional capacity in solar power, 46 percent in wind compared to the year before.
Really massive that we had not counted on.
This is here to stay.
So this will have a long lasting structural impact on our resilience and will make decarbonization converge with energy security interests.
The theme of the conference is policy making in choppy waters and it's felt like choppy waters for a long time I think in Europe.
More recently perhaps even a storm.
So setting course in a storm.
The direction we're going.
Europe is heading towards net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050.
When you consider the dynamics that we've faced war in Ukraine, very tough economic conditions as well.
Is the current energy crisis helping speed up the transition?
Or in fact, is it providing hurdles to achieving the goal?
As said, Karen, twice already this path was put into question, right?
Through COVID and then through the energy crisis.
And every time we seem to come out stronger and having really, instead of de-accelerating, we have actually accelerated.
In terms of the structural measures, we had in place already the negotiation of the energy efficiency directive, the renewables directive.
And we proposed, the European Commission proposed to increase the targets.
And so is that actually, as a result of the negotiation with the Council, with the European Parliament, we came out with more ambitious targets than was initially foreseen as a result of the repower EU, as a result of the need to accelerate the independence of inputs of fossil fuels.
The same in terms of targets for deployment of heat pumps, for instance, of solar, of wind.
And so we really are putting into place also structural measures, which will actually accelerate.
I think nobody dared to believe only one and a half year ago that we would manage to accelerate the energy transition in the way we have.
And this is the irony of this war in Ukraine and of the perpetrator of the war in Ukraine, that it's having an impact which is absolutely contrary to the interests of what was the main supplier of fossil fuels to Europe for many, many years and decades.
Alfred, it did feel as though Europe had the jump on energy transition.
There was a window of hope there.
Then the Americans came up with a very big package, the Inflation Reduction Act, and it felt as though they've stolen the lion's share of investment now.
They have the jump on Europe.
What do you make of where we stand at this point?
Do you think that the conditions are helping energy transition, or are we now effectively overtaken by the Americans?
Yeah.
First of all, good that we got a push on the green transition, because we needed to move.
Russia's gas shutoff triggered an acceleration of that move.
Good.
Good also that the U.S. is moving, because Europe cannot do it alone.
Europe has global emissions of between 7% and 9% of the world total.
You need the U.S. to move, and the U.S. is moving.
That is also good.
But we also need to remember this is a global common good we are trying to protect, and we need to have more than just Europe and the U.S.
We are advocating globally as a coordinating mechanism, as Kristalina said, a global carbon price to give certainty to investors, but also to have a multilateral response, a common response, including China, including India, and other emitters, in order to have a global solution.
Subsidies, as in the IRA, they can help in particular circumstances, but we need to avoid a subsidy war.
So in the end, we need global coordination.
That's utopia, though.
When we've got the director of the CIA flying into China, trying to reset relations with the Chinese, we don't have global coordination.
We have a trade war playing out, one that could get worse from here.
So there is no global coordination on this.
I think we, especially the IMF as a multilateral organization, we are driving to avoid fragmentation.
Fragmentation, economic fragmentation, is going to be costly for everybody.
If you are looking at the global common good trade, if you're looking at the payment system, if you're looking at dealing with climate change, you need global solutions.
And that means even after you have geopolitical tensions, you need to come together in order to tackle these problems.
I need to strive to get this done and not to have economic fragmentation.
Jan, come in here.
Yeah, sure.
Look, I think that as much coordination, as much cooperation as we can achieve, obviously very, very desirable.
I think that there are centrifugal tendencies.
I think that some countries are definitely sort of going their own way.
We see it in the lack of agreement on how to approach the war in Ukraine on the part of big economies, be it Brazil, be it South Africa and so on.
So a lot of uncertainty there as well.
I think that the U.S. is moving now very decisively.
Europe has to take that into account and hopefully collaborate, cooperate, but there will be some competition.
There are some European firms that are already moving to the United States and that may continue.
So it's something that's for Europe to lose, so to speak.
But I think that hopefully it will be more positive than negative.
But we have to realize that Europe has been losing competitiveness for a while, for a long time.
We are talking about it now as a phenomenon, but it's been here for decades, right?
The European economy was more than a quarter of the world economy, now heading towards 15%.
While the U.S. is keeping for 40, 50 years at a quarter, 25% of the world economy, China and other countries growing dramatically.
So Europe really is facing a challenge both in the immediate sense and in the sense of, you know, what do we do in the long run?
How do we achieve the dynamism?
How do we, in fact, create the next wave technologically, et cetera?
Or at least how do we ride the crest of the wave rather than being behind, right?
So that's, I think, really a big challenge here.
Paula, you wanted to jump in there.
Yes, because this is the right transfer.
In fact, as we've been dealing with this trilemma between decarbonization, energy security, just transition, which is really difficult to reconcile, as we've seen.
And as we're finding a way to reconcile it, and then comes the fourth aspect, which is, well, and how do we ensure competitiveness of EU industry within this?
And that is what's triggered the European Commission recently to put on the table legislation, so-called Net Zero Industry Act, which is precisely about identifying the technologies where we do need to have industry in place in Europe, which boosts the production, and which onshores some of the production of some of the technologies needed for the energy transition.
Before the energy transition, in terms of clean energy.
Now, the starting point is challenging, because we know energy prices still remain higher than compared to other parts of the world, so that's clearly not a benefit.
So we need to create a set of conditions which make it attractive, and we have the seeds, we have the quality, we have the size of the market, we have a whole of the European Union within a single market, but we need to now also tackle this fourth element, which is the competitiveness of the European industry.
Olga, let me get you in here.
Yeah, so a couple of thoughts here.
I don't think this needs to be a zero-sum game in terms of, you know, either a business continues thriving here in Europe, or they shot operations and they move to United States.
I think it's all of the above, but I think it's also diving into the realities of some of the features, and there's cooperation and talks happening at the highest level on incentives coordination, and figuring out where are the areas where actual tensions exist, and how do we mitigate them in tangible ways.
And one of those conversations is around making sure that the local content requirements for Aira, that some of the European production of critical minerals can participate in that, in that way European business, US businesses, US consumers can purchase, you know, whether it's vehicles or other solutions, other clean energy solutions, that can participate in the critical mineral supply chain that's produced in Europe as well.
And that's just one example of where we can use treasury guidance to fine-tune Aira.
To a certain extent, there's, of course, only so much that you can do.
It's not going to be re-legislated.
You know, it's there to stay, but we can find ways to make it better and to work better together across these.
Because there's no way that things like the critical mineral supply chain issues will be solved by the US or by Europe on its own.
And to be frank, if we look at the projections even this year and next year, clean energy deployment is set to increase by a third in the next couple of years, just the next couple of years.
So we're going to have shortage of materials, not just, you know, in terms of issues with decoupling from Chinese supply chain, but globally, we're going to have to do all of the above.
We're going to continue to figure out a way to work with Chinese supply chain while establishing our own in US, in Europe, and working together in third countries.
And that includes improving labor standards, and that includes improving environmental standards of how these critical minerals not only are mined, but also produced, manufactured, processed.
And some of that will have to happen in US and Europe.
And that's a tough conversation for communities that might not be ready to see some of those plants or mines in their backyards.
They might want to see the clean energy products, but they might not be ready to see that full supply chain conversation.
Olga, let me ask you directly then, is the trade war with China detrimental for energy transition in Europe?
If we let it, if we let it become a true war, right, or we can take a different approach and once again, take a realistic look at where we need to be in our supply chains for clean energy, critical minerals, critical materials.
How much of that China will continue supplying?
And realistically, how much of that can be ramped up here?
Because we have to do these things in parallel.
We can't pick one or the other and say we will fully decouple, and in two years we're going to produce all of our critical materials at home.
That is just, that's not feasible.
You know, it would be wonderful to live in the world with that.
There is a real pathway to get there.
But I don't see one.
We also can't just sit on our hands and say, you know what?
China is just too efficient.
You know, these products are way too cheap for us to ever even consider competing with them.
So we must just give up and not even try to supplement it with our own production at home.
I want to turn to Peter and get the industry perspective because you're dealing with the Inflation Reduction Act of a day.
You are considering where those investment decisions go as a corporation.
Just weigh in here on some of the things we've been talking about, and of course, this trade war between the United States and China.
Thank you.
I don't like to talk about wars, so we'll leave that to one side.
Look, industry moves where the returns are.
So clearly there's strong signals from the United States at the moment.
But there are also signals that Europe is moving as well.
And these sorts of things don't play out overnight.
They play out over a decade or more.
You know, a typical large industrial investment has got, you know, three to seven years of gestation period,
and then it's going to be around for 25 years.
So you need a bit more than just, you know, one overnight signal.
So, you know, I think we're expecting a bit of a response from Europe, and I think the capital market will kind of respond to that.
What I think is we need to be a bit more careful of is just how long all this is going to take to play out.
So if we come back to natural gas, the production of natural gas in Europe is declining at a far faster rate than demand will decline,
even in a rapid decarbonization scenario.
So there's going to be a gap to fill.
So Europe is going to be dependent on LNG imports for a while more to come.
And that leaves Europe exposed, as long as it's buying on short-term contract basis, which it is at the moment.
It leaves Europe exposed to higher prices, and particularly weather.
So I can't emphasize enough the weather this winter is going to be really important.
In fact, it's the weather within about 500 kilometers of Brussels.
It's as simple as that.
If you have a very cold start of the winter, November, December,
and those storage levels fall lower, and you become dependent on just-in-time delivery of LNG,
and the market tightens.
And if it was a cold winter in China, for example, all of a sudden you're really in a steep competition.
And that could drive prices higher.
And this sort of threat of higher prices could be around for the next two or three winters.
Before, the policy levers that are in place now have had more time to have a bigger impact.
So the efficiency methods will continue to improve.
The build-out of renewables will continue to grow.
Sourcing of alternative forms of natural gas, a bit more pipeline from here and there.
Those will all improve.
But we remain exposed.
That's extraordinary, because there is some market chatter that intraday prices could flip to zero, below zero, over the course of the next couple of months.
It's not the base case scenario, but it's a possibility, right?
That's right.
But let's be, let's be, we've got intraday prices, spot prices here and now, and then we've got the futures curve.
So if you look at the futures curve, I haven't checked on my phone this morning, but you see the prices are higher for this coming winter and for the two winters ahead.
So the markets are signaling, could be tight.
They're not very high, but of course a lot of natural gas is bought in longer term contracts.
But if it gets cold and you have to go out and start buying boatloads of LNG, that's what drives your price right back up again.
And it transmits the price all over the world.
So Europe bid up LNG prices last year and those who are less fortunate weren't able to afford it and they didn't have energy or they moved to coal.
Before we let you just take a rest for a minute, can I ask you about the interconnections in Europe?
We just heard from the Prime Minister talking about some of the decisions that have been made at a government level here in Croatia.
But we know that those decisions have been happening right across Europe.
Big debate around the Iberian Peninsula, how gas flows are being brought into Europe from that side.
Also from Azerbaijan through Turkey into parts of Europe.
How far do you think the interconnection story has gone at this point and how much more work is there still to do?
So on the gas side, you had gas coming into the center of the continent from Russia, which is where it's cold.
And of course that's stopped now and LNG comes into the coastline so you need to get the gas from the coast back to the interior.
I think that that can be done small amounts of investment.
What bothers me more now is the electricity grid.
Because the demand for electricity is likely to more or less double in the next 30 years as we electrify cars and home heating and so forth.
And that is going to require large scale distribution systems offshore, bringing it onshore, not too difficult.
Across countries, pylons, very difficult.
And then strengthening of the local distribution grid, which is not difficult per se.
People see the wires, but it's a lot of activity.
So we need to be thinking about distribution companies, which many have not seen large increases in power demand for a long time.
They need to reconfigure themselves from maintaining the grid to expanding the grid.
Paula, this puts the ball on the tee for you.
Thank you, Karen.
And building on that, I mean, on the interconnection, be it for gas, for electricity, it's been years that the European Union is working on that.
And we have reaped the benefits of all that work precisely over the last year.
What the Prime Minister mentioned today, the Kirk LNG terminal, for instance, which is playing a decisive role now to bring in LNG,
but also interconnected between Poland and Lithuania.
The Klaipeda LNG terminal is now helping bringing in.
The interconnector between Greece and Bulgaria, which was long on discussion and construction and now is commissioned,
really now brought the benefits of all this long-term investment.
And we're not done yet.
And that is still one of the issues we need to complete, both on gas and electricity.
Gas were practically done.
Electricity, there's still a lot to be done.
And we need to learn the lessons.
Precisely as we increase the need to electrify with all this renewable energy that we want to bring in,
we will have to match it in terms of the grid capacity.
So we need to act swiftly and now because we know these things do take time.
So we need to now really focus on investing in the electricity grid to really make it possible for this decarbonisation to take place
and for this increasing electrification of the energy system that we are preparing.
Again, in order to ensure our resilience in terms of both decarbonisation but also energy security.
Olga, where does that investment come from?
That is the billion-dollar question, right?
Or several billion-dollar questions.
In the past, and I don't think the Commission gets enough credit for, I mean, the massive amount of work that was done over the last couple of decades and the built-out of infrastructure.
But I agree with you, you know, there's still some gaps, particularly for land-locked countries.
And the trick there is you do need kind of either EU level or some kind of a broader level risk management and investment mechanisms because at a national level, you know, if you were to build your part of the pipeline and then just hope that, you know, the other countries in that network continue doing so in a timely manner and do it right, you know, that's when it becomes complex.
And we're not done yet, you know, like Hungary, Slovakia, Czech Republic, and a lot of this area, they're still hungry for interconnections in order to truly diversify permanently, not just for a couple of years, but truly permanently diversify and be interconnected.
And I agree on the great conversation.
I do think it's a sleeping crisis.
I think that's going to catch us off guard.
I completely agree here in a couple of years.
Yeah.
Just to add on that, we need European solutions because we are talking about a single market.
We are talking about electricity grid.
We are talking about gas infrastructure.
And I think that requires not national responses, but European responses, including through European funding.
I think that's one very important part.
But I would add one other element when we are talking about the private sector.
The private sector needs to have certainty in terms of where we are going in order to make the investments.
And when we are looking at the total investment required in Europe to do the energy transition, we are talking about 4 trillion euros in this case.
Three quarters of that has to come from the private sector.
And what is there also needed is much stronger action on a capital market union because these funds need to be raised.
Europe is still very fragmented in terms of raising capital.
If we want to compete with the U.S. in Europe, the U.S. has fantastic capital markets.
Europe needs to push there in order to help the private sector to finance.
Jan, I want to turn to you because the fragmentation, we can tackle this from a number of angles.
If you consider large chunks of the region, from the Czech Republic, Poland, Bosnia, Herzegovia, Serbia, Bulgaria, a lot of these countries still rely on fossil fuels versus others that are pivoted to say hydro, others using nuclear.
It's a very different playing field across the board.
A lot of these countries, I mean, Slovakia, a great example, large chunks of GDP are derived from fossil fuel industries.
No guarantee that they'll be the forefront of industry down the track around electric vehicles unless there is a transition that works for that country.
How do we think about ensuring all the nations in lockstep are moving together and that fragmentation doesn't deepen?
Right.
So look, they definitely want to move alongside with Europe and the rest of the world towards a greener, healthier way.
But yes, they are starting from a point where they indeed are relying very much still on coal, oil and so on.
So that's going to be a big transition where they themselves have to start acting more decisively and Europe as a whole has to be instrumental in enabling them to do so.
In the midst of all of this, we have to realize that these huge investments that we are talking about are taking place when the debt of all these countries indebtedness has increased.
So to borrow even more and go further in that direction obviously has macroeconomic implications.
And again, going back to the fact that Europe is a continent that's growing slower or does not perform as well as China or the United States over the last years and decades,
is really crucial.
So I think that these countries depend very much on Europe as a whole becoming more competitive and they moving along with it.
I think a great example is Poland.
Poland has done so well over the last decades during the Great Recession.
It didn't even go into a recession if you look at annual data.
So yes, it is possible for these countries to do well.
But they face a greater challenge in fact than the rest of Europe and than the rest of the world.
So this is where some coordinated, concerted action is really important.
Kristalina Gorgieva was talking about fiscal policies supporting the vulnerable.
We've seen enormous fiscal policies in the form of subsidies handed out to protect mainly consumers but also businesses from high energy prices.
What's the role of these expensive handouts in future?
I think they have to become much more targeted.
Alfred already mentioned it and I think that you see it all over.
That yes, during the pandemic and with the war, et cetera, the first action needs to be decisive and is not necessarily targeted.
But I think now these types of measures will have to really target the very poor, enable businesses to grow, but businesses have to adjust and they are adjusting and operating in much more uncertain environments.
I think we'll talk about investments in the next session, but precisely there is a question.
Will they be able, will the private sector be able to undertake the type of investments together with the assistance of the public sector?
And that's, I'm just not sure, frankly.
I mean, I think Europe has incredible potential, but it has shown that it also is unable to realize it.
I mean, take for example, let's remember in 2000, the so-called Lisbon Declaration and Agreement.
Europe in 10 years will become technologically the most advanced region in the world, right?
2010 came, it didn't happen.
So the agreement was, it's going to be 2020.
Well, we're past 2020 and we see where we are, right?
So one has to, in some sense, really design strategies that are much more effective going forward in Europe.
And this region is part of Europe.
So it will depend very much on what Europe as a whole is able to do and really, you know, become sort of the leading part of the world, which it can.
I mean, Europe really has the human capital, it has the possibilities, it is handicapped as we see with this in terms of energy situation right now.
But it can certainly tackle it if it proceeds smartly and smoothly.
You say that these policies should be more targeted in future.
We are rolling around to an election cycle.
Spain is on the cusp of voting, again, much sooner than anticipated.
Targeted can be used in very different manners in these countries that are trying to shore up an outcome when we've got fragmentation of politics.
Yes, indeed.
But on the other hand, I think the social cohesion, you know, political cohesion in these countries really depends on the bottom half of the population feeling that they are not losing or not losing too much, that they are benefiting in some sense from what's going on.
And the political aspect is very crucial in that, yes.
Alfred, do you want to weigh in on this?
Yeah.
You really want to protect the most vulnerable, and you don't want to waste precious fiscal resources by just spreading them out.
So that I think we all agree, and I think governments agree too.
But it's sometimes difficult to do, and it's just quicker and easier to do it all across.
The same thing applies to subsidies.
When I'm thinking about subsidies for enterprises, you want to go in there where there is market failure.
You want to address infrastructure need in order to create an enabling environment for enterprises.
You don't want to just open the floodgates and use fiscal resources very inefficiently.
Because in the end, we have a fiscal constraint in Europe in more general.
So you need to think about being targeted everywhere.
I did promise to take some questions from the audience.
So we do have a microphone here.
Does anyone want to pose a question to the audience?
If so, please raise your hand and we will bring a microphone to you.
It's a very intelligent audience here.
So I'm assuming someone's going to want to jump in with a question.
No pressure.
Front row.
Second row.
Oh, we have a gentleman over here.
If you can just state your name and where you're from too, so the audience has some context, please.
Thank you.
Nate Arnold from the IMF.
I just wanted to ask a bit more about the Net Zero Industry Act.
I know a lot of that is aimed at sort of streamlining regulatory and permitting processes, but most of those are national or even local competency.
Can you just talk a little bit more about how you envision actually implementing that part of the Net Zero Industry Act?
Well, thank you for the question.
Indeed, so in the Net Zero Act, there were a set of clean energy technologies that are identified, which are absolutely decisive for the transition to take place.
And then the idea is to create a favorable regulatory environment, for instance, by accelerating permitting, by putting together the necessary skills which are required,
because this is a factor that we sometimes underestimate.
We can have the targets, you can have the policies, and then you don't have the people who are qualified to implement it.
So the idea is to tackle it across the system and see what can be the barriers to the deployment of this clean energy technologies
and create such a conducive environment within the European Union.
Now, this piece of legislation is now being discussed, negotiated with the European Council, with the European Parliament, so we'll see where we land.
But clearly, the idea is to have a number of elements which will allow to have a more favorable context for clean energy technologies to be manufactured in the EU,
while recognizing that we will have to have the partnerships that Olga mentioned, and that we cannot do it all by ourselves, right?
If you look at the journeys in terms of energy transition that the whole world is engaging in, we see that the need for clean energy technologies is massive.
So obviously, cooperation will be key, and the question is to identify where and with whom can we best cooperate.
Can I follow up on that?
Fresh from a technology event, you know, speaking to all of the innovators in the space, and one of the views is that there's been so much cheap credit for so long.
There have been so many players wading into this space, but nobody has scale, and that there's so much time spent on talking about solutions.
There's not the rolling forward with development, or the clock is ticking, we don't have scale in some of these new industries to make any difference at this point.
How do you change that narrative?
It's interesting, I've been faced with that same question earlier this week, in the sense that we have a number of excellent small and medium enterprises within Europe,
which are there ready to make the next step and the next jump.
And the issue there is that they may not have access to capital precisely.
So the de-risking of it.
So we need to look into that.
It's something clearly that we do need because we have extremely good SMEs in these areas of clean energy technologies.
So we need to identify what are the barriers and tackle them.
And clearly this is an issue where we need to look into and act.
Can I just chime in just half a second?
I think a really specific unique area that doesn't get enough attention is some entities, especially in Europe,
some businesses that don't have a great credit rating, but they're legitimate, fantastic companies that have proven themselves to have developed all sorts of projects.
Sometimes they have a hard time partnering with US businesses or financial institutions because they don't have that credit rating.
So if there is some kind of EU level or a broader scale risk management, we have literally seen that be an impediment to some of the broader scale
that's really scaling up these massive projects here when we're talking about specific companies that might just not have it look really great on paper,
but they do have the expertise and they're legitimate and they're trustworthy.
Peter, do you want to jump in on this as well?
I mean, I was talking to the boss of one of your competitors in recent months.
And while there's interest in these technologies, it's almost a slight eyebrow raise as to how it impacts the overall corporate
because some of these activities are so small, they don't have any long-term impact at this point for revenue for a big business like yours.
So it's very clear that the most rapid pace of decarbonization is occurring in the power sector with wind and solar.
But you have to think what comes next.
So whether that's decarbonizing home heating with heat pumps, hydrogen, biofuel, so forth.
So I think a large corporation has to think not 5, 10, but more like 25, 30 years out.
So if I look at what Shell's doing, we are looking at sustainable aviation fuel.
It is considerably more expensive than the standard stuff.
However, if we want to fly around the place and get anywhere close to net zero in 2050, we're going to need it.
So we need to start thinking how can we drive down costs.
Same with hydrogen.
Now, I think I'd be doing the room a disservice if I said some of these things were going to completely transform the world in the next 10 years.
I don't think they are.
But over the next 30 years, who knows?
And the fact is, if we don't start trying now, we definitely will not get there.
Sort of hoping and praying, right?
I was talking to the CFO of Ryanair early in the week, and it was a very similar conversation,
that these sustainable fuels are just not economical at this point.
If you had to use them today, it would be hugely detrimental for the quarterly earnings that they produce.
So something needs to change between now and execution down the track, right?
How do you get that critical mass that we're talking about?
How do you get the economies of scale?
So you have drive from policymakers, so European Union mandates for something like sustainable aviation fuel.
But also, I don't want to offend anybody, but I'm not big on praying for this sort of thing.
I'm much more on investing in R&D.
And we will surprise ourselves.
We always have done.
I work in Shell Scenario Department.
We try and think about the future.
If I look back at what my predecessors have done, we always miss technological breakthroughs.
I don't know where they're going to come from, but I'm confident that we will find them if we invest.
So in particularly decarbonizing industry and aviation and certain areas of heavy road transport,
we need to be experimenting and seeing what works.
It's no good trying to predict.
We just try different things, and then something will emerge.
We can take some more questions from the audience.
Does anyone else want to chime in with a question or a comment on some of the discussion points that we've been having here?
Feel free to raise your hand.
Okay, we'll kick it back over here.
We've got plenty more to discuss then.
But if you do want to get involved, please do raise your hand.
Do we have one?
Oh, fantastic.
Again, I'll ask you to state your name, please.
Yes.
Romain Duval from the IMF2, which is why I didn't want to ask a question, but you know.
I have a question for Olga, which is regarding the prospects rate for gas next winter.
There was a slight difference of view maybe with Alfred.
And so, you know, what's your, you know, thinking about the likelihood of shortages vis-à-vis a renewed price spike, right?
I think lots of the factors you listed would, you know, lead to a renewed price spike.
But do you also see any kind of risk of shortages?
Because, you know, I think our assessment was more that you would take, you know, a combination of risks to materialize for any shortages to, right, to materialize next winter.
So is that also your assessment on that?
Yeah.
So, I mean, I think there's two different risks, right?
There's risks around the price spikes, but there being enough gas in Europe because Europe would be able to purchase enough gas on the global market and attract enough supplies.
But are really, really high price, just like we've seen over the last year, especially in August, right?
Really expensive, but the supplies were here.
So, overall, there was enough gas.
Just really, really expensive.
And you had to have all of these different national and EU-level schemes to support businesses and households.
So there is that risk.
There's also, like, overall shortage if you do get enough demand pulled in Asia.
If there are some, you know, we have another Freeport situation where there are some exporting facilities that are not working for whatever reason, there's always that risk as well.
But I think the pricing risk is always higher for Europe because there's still regionality around the markets, even within Europe.
And when you have differences in prices, and you have differences in prices when you don't have fully fluid infrastructure, right?
So that means that there is still a risk for internal competition across Europe.
And there is still -- and this doesn't get talked about enough -- there is still a risk around competition for storage.
You know, over 100 BCM of storage Europe, which is fantastic.
But there isn't, you know, a guarantee in terms of how equitably that will be spread out and purchased across Europe if things get really, really tough.
We didn't get to that point last winter because we didn't have to, and we came out with really high storage levels.
But I do see a worst-case scenario now.
This is really, really bad.
Like, everything going wrong.
All of the things that I've mentioned, a couple of those things going wrong at the same time.
I'm hoping that we don't get to that.
I'm hoping that everything goes smoothly again.
But there is a scenario where maybe countries that have more resources will be able to have access to that storage, these supplies, perhaps slightly easier than some of the other countries that are -- that don't have the same financial backing.
We've mentioned the lack of Chinese demand and how that's taken some heat off the price.
But we haven't mentioned the lack of German demand.
And if we think about what played out last winter, in Germany, the Bundestag drew up blueprints on how to wind down certain industries.
Heating was turned down.
But the pointy end of this was that we could see large-scale shutdowns across industry if prices got out of control.
We didn't quite get to that point.
And now the Germans are talking about an electricity subsidy that changes the playing field where manufacturing, industry, consumers have access to cheap energy at a price that could be different from the rest of Europe.
What does that do as we talk about fragmentation of this policy moves forward?
So there's always risk when you do have these different pricing schemes.
And I think for Germany, it's a very unique case because the demand destruction that led to businesses shutting down or scaling down production, that should not be celebrated.
I think it should be celebrated in terms of the solidarity.
Yes, we got through last winter, but that is not -- that should never be the long-term goal, long-term solution.
In the long-term, we should figure out a way to keep these businesses running, even when there are price spikes, even when the market situation gets tough.
So the fragmentation in terms of national support, that's why I agree with the comments earlier in terms of the long-term goal is to get back to that competitive, integrated, interconnected market across Europe.
All the efforts that were done over the last several decades through the third energy package and all the other -- and, of course, they had to be scaled back because we had an extremely tough year.
Last year, last year, last 15, 16 months, some of the companies became nationalized.
Some of these structures had to come in place to support businesses.
But there is that risk when you have national support schemes that are different, that incentivize different production, different sources.
And it is more confusing for the private sector in terms of even coming in and saying -- even predictability, even long-term investments.
So great, you have that support scheme right now.
But what does that mean for 5, 10, 15, 20 years if you're a private sector and you're looking into a specific project, right?
Yeah, it's a good point.
I mean, the ownership structure has changed on major companies from EDF to Uniper over the course of this time.
But I know you both want to jump in.
Please.
Quickly, one of the biggest achievements in Europe is the creation of the single market.
And that calls, when it comes to energy policy, energy security policy, it calls for European solutions.
And an element when we are looking at financing climate change in order also to deal with fiscal constraints is a climate fund, one should think about, which is addressing common infrastructural issues.
But also is putting the euro where you get most out of it in terms of decarbonization.
So preserve the single market.
Don't go alone.
Don't fragment Europe.
And we need a European solution for that.
So are you saying Germany should avoid this electricity subsidy?
I think we should be very careful in general when we are thinking about subsidies.
They have a place.
But subsidies provide a particular incentive.
Subsidies over a very long time are questionable.
Paula?
Yes, and this is precisely what we, well, last year we put into place a set of emergency measures, as I said, including in terms of what types of schemes and subsidies could be put into place
in a context of emergency.
And now we are precisely looking into what are the measures that need to still be prolonged, because we are not out of the crisis yet.
And we are, for gas, we have actually prolonged the gas demand reduction regulation for another year.
For electricity, we are now coming out with a proposal on how to go about it.
But we also learned the lessons and we have put on the table the electricity market design proposal, which is precisely to address in a structure
manner how to go about this and to make sure that we do not have this fragmentation across the EU and that we are actually speaking of a genuine single market in terms of electricity, where we allow regulated prices only under exceptional circumstances when certain conditions are met, and that we create the conditions, for instance, through context for difference, to integrate the renewables more and more in the system in a level playing field.
So that's where we bring in and now are looking into what are the structural measures that need to be there precisely to also allow for investment certainty and for a level playing field across the EU.
So what would you say to Chancellor Schultz about the electricity subsidy?
We are in discussions on all of those measures which require state aid and which need to go through the appreciation of colleagues in the European Commission so clearly.
It's something that we are looking into, not just for Germany, but for all those who are looking into it.
It's a diplomatic language on stage at the moment.
Jan.
I think we have to be ready for major price fluctuations.
They were in the past, they recently, and so, you know, be ready for price increases.
I think that governments and EU in particular can smooth, provide some smoothing over time, but otherwise there has to be restructuring.
And so, for instance, the fact that Europe still doesn't have an integrated capital market, even banks are basically country by country, that's been known for a long time.
Politically, there hasn't been any significant sufficient will really to move in that direction.
And I think it's time to consider those kinds of issues as part of the energy strategy going forward.
That, indeed, the US has been more successful because its private sector capital is moving faster, smoother to places where it needs to go.
In Europe, we don't have it, and unless Europe takes concrete steps of that kind, it will not be able to face the challenge as well as other parts of the world.
It's a very challenging crossroads where we talk about intervention, what's the right sort of intervention, what's too much, and what destabilizes market forces.
The managing director just a moment so early before the session pointed out carbon pricing, that she was encouraging it.
What does that do to market forces? Is it the right move?
I think that will be the right move.
I think it's a political question whether it can be adopted, but having a carbon tax, carbon pricing, I think is exactly the right way to go.
And forcing and forging agreement on that would be a major step forward.
Why doesn't it just add more complexity around doing business in Europe?
Well, actually, it would simplify things.
I think if people know and understand that there is a price, and price that is to a significant extent predictable,
I think that will make private sector be more efficient and able to make the big investments that were mentioned.
Olga?
So, I think, first of all, it starts at the accounting and having a global system where we can agree on how we're counting carbon emissions,
whether it's LNG, whether it's, you know, methane, whatever it is, or products that are being shipped to Europe and from Europe.
With CBAM coming online, I actually think that could trigger, almost force a global way to start counting carbon emissions for certain products that perhaps have not been as clearly assessed in the past,
and force us to, in a way, to start applying that carbon pricing in an indirect way, even places like United States.
It's actually interesting.
There is some bipartisan support for it in U.S. in some corners, but it's not something that will be popular across all voters to get it across the line anytime soon on the U.S. side.
But I think, once again, it starts with accounting.
And you have to be able to count carbon emissions from the different products and the value chains in order to have a meaningful conversation.
And we still, globally, do not have those standards on how to count, verify, and report.
Peter, business loves regulation. Carbon prices, a good thing?
It's very difficult to imagine getting something like carbon capture and storage moving without carbon prices, in some way, shape, or form.
I think the key thing, which has been mentioned, is the durability, the outlook for the price.
If we'd all been sitting here a few years ago, European trading scheme was, you know, in the teens of euros, there wasn't really a price signal in the U.S.
Today, you have the 45Q in the U.S. at $85 a tonne.
You have the EU ETS at somewhere in the 80 euros per tonne.
That's starting to make carbon capture and storage look interesting.
It's incentivizing moves in the power system away from fossil towards renewables.
It works.
The question is, will it be there for the next 10, 20 years?
I can see everybody's needing a bit of caffeine and sunshine, so I'm just going to get a quick takeaway message from our panelists today.
We've had a very broad discussion.
Something that you just want to leave the audience with, something you want to highlight about the challenge, the risk, something to think about from here.
Olga, do you want to kick it off for us?
Sure.
30 seconds.
Yeah.
We haven't talked about Ukraine, which I think is a missed opportunity for this conversation in terms of kind of what's happening right now and how Ukraine can support European energy security and climate goals in the long term.
Tremendous nuclear expertise, tons of natural gas resources, a lot of, you know, areas where you can try out new technologies and innovation, but it needs support in the short term to maintain the institutions, maintain the energy sector functioning.
So just and kind of thinking through that robust natural gas system in Ukraine, you know, what do you do with that in the future?
How do you integrate maybe cleaner, lower carbon fuels into it that can support then clean energy transition in Europe as well?
So I just want to make sure that we don't forget about that and then we support Ukraine in the short term and cooperate on that and also think through the big ambitious reconstruction goals for the clean and not just reconstruction, but transformation of the energy sector in Ukraine.
Jan, see if you can top that.
No, I would say, look, Europe is facing a much greater challenge and this part of Europe in particular than many other countries, U.S. in particular, has been thinking about it.
It's been taking steps in the direction of how to solve it.
So in a way it's ahead and it's up to Europe in particular to sort of chart the direction and take some of the major steps, hopefully in coordination with the United States and other countries.
And I think, as we mentioned in the conversation, China will be a crucial player, is a crucial player and will be an even more crucial player.
Alfred.
Yeah.
Climate change is a global problem.
That means we need to have a discussion globally on policy and we need to harmonize and talk about those.
Second part, when you look at energy security, supply chain security, diversification is key.
Whenever you fragment, it's becoming risky and becoming more expensive.
Third, Europe has the single market.
That single market needs to be protected.
More can be done, banking union, capital markets union, in order to allow small and medium enterprises to get capital in order to do these important climate investments.
More needs to be done at the European level because energy security, energy transition, it's not a national problem, needs to be handled much more at the European level.
And Paula.
Well, over the last year we saw impossible things made possible.
We have phased out fossil fuels from Russia in a way that nobody could have believed a year ago.
We have accelerated the energy transition.
And with Ukraine, we even went for synchronization of the electricity grid of Ukraine and Moldova with the EU in something that was not foreseen immediately and did happen to a point that Ukraine is in a possibility and has exported electricity to the EU.
Many may not know this.
So we made impossible things happen.
I want us to all learn the lessons and we have to learn the lessons also for the energy security of the future, which is not fossil fuel related, but also not to commit the same mistakes that we did in terms of non-diversification.
Now we have to look into that precisely with the critical raw materials, with the critical minerals and ensure that we have the necessary grid in time to make this vision a reality.
Thank you very much.
What a terrific discussion.
Now, before we wrap up, I'm just going to tell you whereabouts you're going, what's happening in your foreseeable future.
We're taking a coffee break now.
So that'll be roughly about 30 minutes.
There is a second panel that will start at 11:50.
So just take a look at your watches.
11:50, we're back in here.
But also there's a lovely big group photo, a moment in history that'll be on the terrace straight away now.
So if you can wander out that way, but please put your hands together for the panel.
Thank you so much to Alfred, Jan, Paula and Olga.