[SPEAKER_02] We are in the presence of a leading expert in this particular field, he is a professor at the University of Virginia and we couldn't be more delighted to have him with us here to talk about employment and income policies in an era of AI today. Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the one and only Anton Korinek.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you very much for the kind introduction and for the opportunity to speak to you all today. So I want to start by something that was like that went viral on social media while we were all traveling to the conference yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01] Dario Amode gave an interview, so Dario Amode is the CEO of one of the leading AI labs of Anthropic and he gave an interview a couple days ago
[SPEAKER_01] and Axios wrote the following article: "Behind the curtain, a white-collar blood path."
[SPEAKER_01] What does the article write about? Well, Dario Amode has a blunt scary warning for the US government and for all of us
[SPEAKER_01] AI could wipe out half of all entry-level white-collar jobs and spike unemployment to 10 to 20% in the next one to five years.
[SPEAKER_01] It's quite a range of uncertainty there, right? Well, that's one of the stories that we hear out of people from Silicon Valley on a regular basis these days, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And then on the other hand, if we listen to the traditional economic experts, he actually has the same initials as Dario Amode, right?
[SPEAKER_01] But our very own Daron Acimoglu predicted just last year in the simple macroeconomics of AI that AI will increase economic growth by 0.07% a year.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's a little bit of a divergence between these predictions.
[SPEAKER_01] I actually call his paper "The Simple Macroeconomics of Judge GPD 3.5".
[SPEAKER_01] I think that's more appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01] But in any case, so our goal in this session today is to try and uncover what's behind this stark divergence in views among people who are obviously extremely smart.
[SPEAKER_01] Daron is, by some measures, the most renowned economist alive today.
[SPEAKER_01] And I want to start by focusing on the technology side of everything and emphasizing the rapid technological advances we are experiencing.
[SPEAKER_01] Here on this slide, you can see an illustration of the so-called scaling laws of AI.
[SPEAKER_01] What are scaling laws?
[SPEAKER_01] Scaling laws basically tell us that intelligence is a function of the amount of computational power that you put into training our AI systems.
[SPEAKER_01] So a function of compute, as people in Silicon Valley would say in shorthand.
[SPEAKER_01] And this is a logarithmic scale on the y-axis.
[SPEAKER_01] So it means if we have a straight line here on a logarithmic scale, that means there's actually exponential growth.
[SPEAKER_01] The exponential growth is at a kind of mind-numbing pace of more than 4x per year.
[SPEAKER_01] So over the past 15 years, this graph goes from 2010 to 2025.
[SPEAKER_01] The amount of computational power that has been going into our leading AI systems has quadrupled every single year.
[SPEAKER_01] However, at the same time, there have also been tremendous advances in algorithmic efficiency at a rate of estimated to be 2.5x.
[SPEAKER_01] If you multiply those two, the effective computational power going into AI systems has been rising at 10x a year, year after year after year.
[SPEAKER_01] And you know, just as a side remark, my poor brain is staying the same size or maybe starting to slowly deteriorate year after year after year, in part because I rely so heavily on chat GPT.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay, now this was kind of the last 15 years.
[SPEAKER_01] If we look a little bit more into the weeds, I want to suggest that there's been actually four main paradigms during that period that I want to focus on.
[SPEAKER_01] In the 2010s, that was when deep learning started to take off.
[SPEAKER_01] And when this whole graph that I showed before started, deep learning was amazing in some very narrow applications, like for example, image recognition or stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01] But it wasn't really world shattering and nobody among us missed anything if we didn't pay particular attention to what's going on in AI.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, that changed in 2022 when we had the chat GPT moment.
[SPEAKER_01] And we suddenly had these large language models, which are systems that have suddenly these general purpose capabilities.
[SPEAKER_01] They can help you write emails or solve economic models or advise you on recipes and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] They are truly general purpose in their nature.
[SPEAKER_01] However, in 2022, they weren't very good yet.
[SPEAKER_01] They could do things that Daniel Kahneman would describe as system one thinking.
[SPEAKER_01] So things when you shoot off the hip, but if you ask them anything mathematical, they failed spectacularly.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, that changed significantly last fall with the advent of reasoning models.
[SPEAKER_01] And I want to spend a couple slides talking about these reasoning models.
[SPEAKER_01] So those are models that were explicitly designed to remedy the shortcomings of the first generation of LLMs.
[SPEAKER_01] They are optimized for analytic tasks, for system two tasks, for things like coding, mathematical derivations.
[SPEAKER_01] And the way that they do that is the systems are trained to produce a chain of thought, which kind of mimics when we humans think hard about something.
[SPEAKER_01] They break down the problem into smaller steps, try multiple strategies.
[SPEAKER_01] If they make a mistake, they can go back and correct themselves.
[SPEAKER_01] And that has suddenly led to significantly more powerful AIs.
[SPEAKER_01] And in particular, also AIs that are very relevant for us as economists, central bankers, Ministry of Finance employees, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] So I wanted to briefly give you a few examples of what this latest generation of AI systems can be used for.
[SPEAKER_01] Because it's starting to come closer to home for us economists.
[SPEAKER_01] So I have this line of papers, Generative AI for Economic Research, with the Journal of Economic Literature.
[SPEAKER_01] And my agreement with the journal is that I write an update every half a year.
[SPEAKER_01] And that means I have kind of observed the advances very closely because I need to describe them publicly.
[SPEAKER_01] And the latest advances in reasoning, this is all from the December edition.
[SPEAKER_01] There's going to be a new edition coming out in the next month.
[SPEAKER_01] So the December edition focused specifically on those reasoning models.
[SPEAKER_01] And here I don't even want to bother to read the equation.
[SPEAKER_01] But this is essentially, it's a fairly complicated mathematical equation, right?
[SPEAKER_01] It's an arbitrage relationship between short-term and long-term interest rates.
[SPEAKER_01] And for some of my old projects, I needed to log-linearize that.
[SPEAKER_01] It took my co-author, who is very experienced in that, two and a half hours.
[SPEAKER_01] It took chat GPT 53 seconds and it solved it no problem.
[SPEAKER_01] Here, something else that AI models struggled and failed at a year ago.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm asking a reasoning model to write code to solve the Ramsey growth model.
[SPEAKER_01] It's kind of a complicated, subtle path, stable system.
[SPEAKER_01] A year ago, traditional language models were absolutely unable to do this.
[SPEAKER_01] Starting last fall, this was kind of a breeze.
[SPEAKER_01] And here is the simulation, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, you may have also heard last fall that there were concerns
[SPEAKER_01] that this process of just scaling language models had come to an end,
[SPEAKER_01] that models had already basically learned everything they could,
[SPEAKER_01] and that there was going to be a ceiling to any additional capabilities.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, in some sense, you can say it's probably true that these traditional models,
[SPEAKER_01] like the 2022-style models, started to experience a ceiling,
[SPEAKER_01] but then with the advent of these reasoning models,
[SPEAKER_01] we suddenly have two new ways of scaling them,
[SPEAKER_01] meaning of using more compute to making them more intelligent
[SPEAKER_01] and receiving additional returns.
[SPEAKER_01] We can optimize that reasoning process by spending more compute,
[SPEAKER_01] and we can let them think longer,
[SPEAKER_01] and both of these has made the systems significantly more powerful,
[SPEAKER_01] and that's behind the rapid progress that we have seen over the past half year now.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, what's the next paradigm that's emerging right now?
[SPEAKER_01] The so-called AI agents.
[SPEAKER_01] What are AI agents, actually?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, they are language models coupled with other computer systems,
[SPEAKER_01] so we call them not AI models, but AI systems,
[SPEAKER_01] that can autonomously pursue goals by combining the most cutting-edge language models
[SPEAKER_01] with external tools like, for example, internet search or transactions or coding.
[SPEAKER_01] And I will give a quick kind of example of that.
[SPEAKER_01] They are expected to lead to yet another paradigm change and another revolution
[SPEAKER_01] in how useful AI is going to become,
[SPEAKER_01] and to provide significant value to companies across the economy,
[SPEAKER_01] but also to us as economists.
[SPEAKER_01] So, how should we think of these agents?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, traditionally, if you are in a big organization,
[SPEAKER_01] you used to have an org chart, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Now, a friend of mine recently told me,
[SPEAKER_01] IT is the new HR.
[SPEAKER_01] Instead of creating new human positions to fulfill different roles,
[SPEAKER_01] we can now put AI agents into the org chart,
[SPEAKER_01] and these individual agents,
[SPEAKER_01] they are essentially language models that talk to each other.
[SPEAKER_01] Usually, there's like an orchestrator agent who is the manager
[SPEAKER_01] and who assigns tasks to all the other agents,
[SPEAKER_01] and there's some workflow like in a traditional organization.
[SPEAKER_01] And this, surprisingly, already works for some things.
[SPEAKER_01] But I guess what's most important of all things is it is improving very rapidly.
[SPEAKER_01] To give you an example, I thought,
[SPEAKER_01] let me ask the current version of chat GPT-03.
[SPEAKER_01] So, 03 is the one that has these agentic workflows.
[SPEAKER_01] Let me ask you the question that's relevant about the Croatian economy.
[SPEAKER_01] Can you draw and analyze the beverage curve for Croatia using data from the past 25 years?
[SPEAKER_01] So, that's a very short prompt, right?
[SPEAKER_01] What did the model do?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, first it thought for six minutes and six seconds.
[SPEAKER_01] Then, it showed me the graph of the beverage curve.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, actually, let's click into what it did during the thinking.
[SPEAKER_01] If you click on this little arrow here, it shows you the thoughts of the model.
[SPEAKER_01] It starts out by saying,
[SPEAKER_01] "The user is asking to draw and analyze the beverage curve, yada, yada.
[SPEAKER_01] I need to search for historical data from sources like Eurostat or the Croatian Bureau,"
[SPEAKER_01] and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01] And it spent a significant amount of time thinking.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I will scroll through only one-third of the thinking because we don't have time.
[SPEAKER_01] It did all this and this and that and tried new data sources and yet another thing.
[SPEAKER_01] Then, it wrote computer code to plot the graph.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, at the very end, it showed us the beverage curve that I already showed you before.
[SPEAKER_01] It also gave a pretty impressive interpretation of everything.
[SPEAKER_01] So, here it tells us what you're seeing, the beverage curve for Croatia and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] How Croatia's beverage curve evolved and it describes the different basically economic periods that the Croatian economy went through from pre-crisis to global crisis and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] COVID post-pandemic rebound and then the cool down and ECB tightening and what was happening in the economy and how that was reflected in the curve.
[SPEAKER_01] Then, the takeaways and that was essentially the analysis.
[SPEAKER_01] At this point, these systems are already better than any human RA we would usually hire.
[SPEAKER_01] They're probably not quite as good yet as a seasoned economist who knows the beverage curve well.
[SPEAKER_01] But, you can see that these systems have become incredibly powerful and that's just from over the past half year as we have rolled out these reasoning models.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, where is this all going?
[SPEAKER_01] The declared goal of Frontier AI Labs is not just to create AI agents.
[SPEAKER_01] No, they want to create artificial general intelligence which they define as AI systems that can perform essentially all economically valuable tasks or valuable cognitive tasks depending on which lab you talk to.
[SPEAKER_01] So, the business strategy of all the leading Frontier AI Labs is to raise to HEI their timelines have repeatedly compressed over the past few years.
[SPEAKER_01] In 2020, they thought, "Oh, we are going to reach this in 20 years."
[SPEAKER_01] Now, they think we are going to reach this in one to five years.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, based on my personal contacts at various labs, my impression is most people think within one to two years.
[SPEAKER_01] But, everybody appreciates there is a lot of uncertainty so they don't really know.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, what I can see with a lot of confidence is that we as economists and economic policy makers are not sufficiently alert to that possibility.
[SPEAKER_01] Because it would be a complete game changer for our economic systems.
[SPEAKER_01] So, in the face of this massive amount of uncertainty, I want to propose that the best approach is to engage in scenario planning.
[SPEAKER_01] In an issue of the IMF F&D magazine, which is essentially the same magazine that the managing director distributed this morning,
[SPEAKER_01] I published the following three scenarios.
[SPEAKER_01] The conventional wisdom scenario that we'll just have regular progress and, you know, AI is going to be like the internet that is going to give us a bit of a productivity boost,
[SPEAKER_01] but otherwise, it's not going to fundamentally change the world.
[SPEAKER_01] So, that's one scenario, and I think it's one that we do want to keep an eye on, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Like, there is no certainty about where this is going.
[SPEAKER_01] But then the second and third scenarios are that we will actually reach AGI, Artificial General Intelligence.
[SPEAKER_01] And that could be a more conservative timeline would be in 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01] But increasingly, labs believe that we are going to face this on a much more accelerated timeline within the next one to five years.
[SPEAKER_01] And there is going to be a rapid transformation.
[SPEAKER_01] And we saw that reflected in the initial article that basically reported on Dario Amode's interview here.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay, well, I just want to, you know, step back and observe that there's also rapid progress in robotics.
[SPEAKER_01] And when you combine the robotics and the artificial intelligence, then they can do not only all the cognitive tasks, but also all the manual tasks.
[SPEAKER_01] So, people sometimes say, well, okay, we humans, we have to do the physical labor, but the robots are going to be better at that too relatively soon.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably a little bit more slowly than AGI, but nonetheless.
[SPEAKER_01] All right.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, let's first focus on the bright side of everything.
[SPEAKER_01] What are the productivity implications of this?
[SPEAKER_01] And I want to start with a specific focus on the CC region.
[SPEAKER_01] I guess, obviously, the CC region is not a leader in AI development.
[SPEAKER_01] We don't have open AI or anthropic or deep mind.
[SPEAKER_01] But what I want to emphasize is that we all can still reap a lot of benefits from using the AI.
[SPEAKER_01] We don't need to produce the most advanced system.
[SPEAKER_01] The example I gave you before with the beverage curve, anybody can run it on your laptop and can personally reap tremendous productivity gains.
[SPEAKER_01] All it takes is a $20 a month subscription to use the currently best AI models that are publicly available in the world.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'll say one thing: using these systems and becoming more productive is going to place us in a better position to deal with all the disruptions that I will talk about in a few minutes.
[SPEAKER_01] This here is from an excellent paper by the IMF that basically tries to estimate AI and the productivity gains in Europe.
[SPEAKER_01] And the paper goes through a whole range of scenarios.
[SPEAKER_01] And these box charts try to kind of illustrate, first of all, the wide range of different forecasts.
[SPEAKER_01] And secondly, what like the median forecast is.
[SPEAKER_01] This is based on the same methodology that Daron Achimoglu was using.
[SPEAKER_01] But, of course, not with the most low-ball conservative estimates, but with a whole range of reasonable estimates.
[SPEAKER_01] I will say the scenarios are excellent, and I think it's a fantastic paper.
[SPEAKER_01] If we reach artificial general intelligence, it's going to be way beyond that, though.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, this kind of illustrates how far apart the predictions of Daron and, like, some other leading predictors are.
[SPEAKER_01] That just gives us a sense of how much disagreement there is in this debate.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, what I want to emphasize is that there's really two channels through which AI, or ultimately HEI, will affect productivity.
[SPEAKER_01] The first one is it's going to make everything that we can use it for more productive.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's kind of a level shift.
[SPEAKER_01] But the second thing is one of the most important cognitive activities that we can engage in is innovation.
[SPEAKER_01] And it makes innovators more productive.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's also going to lead to an increase in the growth rate.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, last December, I contributed to a report to the G7 finance ministers and central bankers on AI and economic and financial policy making.
[SPEAKER_01] And in that we identified three key roles for government.
[SPEAKER_01] One of them, enabling AI in R&D, education, infrastructure, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] The second one, and I think in some ways that's like the most straightforward one, using the AI.
[SPEAKER_01] We can use them within our central banks, within our finance ministers.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think we should, not only to be more productive, but also to have kind of our fingertips on the pulse of what this technology can do.
[SPEAKER_01] And then the third one, and I guess as Europeans who don't have these leading systems in their borders, we can do only so much on that.
[SPEAKER_01] And there is a risk if we do too much, then they won't even roll out their systems in Europe.
[SPEAKER_01] But ultimately, we also want to align the AI with our societal objectives.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, I'll say there are some special benefits of the current generation of Gen AI for the CZ region.
[SPEAKER_01] First of all, these LLMs are really good in overcoming language barriers.
[SPEAKER_01] They're really good in upskilling their users.
[SPEAKER_01] And even if you use the free version, they are already quite powerful and getting more and more so.
[SPEAKER_01] What are the barriers to adoption?
[SPEAKER_01] In the CZ region in particular, the industry structure is dominated by small and medium-sized enterprises.
[SPEAKER_01] So that means we need to get the message out to every actor in the economy that using these systems gives you a competitive advantage.
[SPEAKER_01] The AI skills are in short supply.
[SPEAKER_01] But you know, I myself, I'm an economist, right? I'm not a trained computer scientist.
[SPEAKER_01] And whenever I don't know something, I just go to chat GPD and ask it and say, "Explain it for an economist."
[SPEAKER_01] And the AI is pretty good at doing that.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, what are the drivers of adoption?
[SPEAKER_01] So I think unlike earlier general purpose technologies, we don't need any new hardware.
[SPEAKER_01] We can just use these systems on the computers that we all have.
[SPEAKER_01] And we don't need to learn, you know, like how to use office packages or how to do programming or anything.
[SPEAKER_01] We just need to use our natural language.
[SPEAKER_01] And that makes it a lot easier to adopt this technology.
[SPEAKER_01] I think our goal in the region should be to avoid that little bit of a digital divide will transform into an intelligence divide.
[SPEAKER_01] So, and I want to kind of rub this in a little bit more.
[SPEAKER_01] What are the risks of falling behind?
[SPEAKER_01] Because oftentimes I hear people say, "Well, you know, we have an all right standard of living in Europe.
[SPEAKER_01] Why should we bother hustling and adopting this new technology?
[SPEAKER_01] Why can't we just wait a bit and enjoy our standards of living?"
[SPEAKER_01] But the risks are threefold.
[SPEAKER_01] First of all, I mean, are the lost opportunities.
[SPEAKER_01] If you have something that can give you 10% or 20% extra opportunity,
[SPEAKER_01] it's like not taking the 100 euro bill that's lying on the floor.
[SPEAKER_01] But the second more insidious thing, and I think we have already been feeling a little bit of that,
[SPEAKER_01] not from AI, but from things like the rapid advances in various industries in China in recent years.
[SPEAKER_01] We will experience more and more declining international competitiveness if we don't participate in this.
[SPEAKER_01] So, from my perspective, a lot of the reason of the competitiveness problems of Europe are not necessarily regulation,
[SPEAKER_01] but just the slowness of adoption of technology, some of which is cultural.
[SPEAKER_01] And then ultimately all of these will be reflected in terms of trade losses.
[SPEAKER_01] They will be reflected in just Europeans being less able to afford all the goods that we need on the international market,
[SPEAKER_01] including energy in many cases, including computer hardware, robotics and so on.
[SPEAKER_01] If you don't have good terms of trade, your standard of living just goes down the river.
[SPEAKER_01] And so I think it is really an imperative for our region to pursue AI integration, but of course thoughtfully.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, in the third part of my presentation, I want to focus a little bit more on the labor market challenges.
[SPEAKER_01] And in order to kind of set this up, I want to take a step back.
[SPEAKER_01] Because this technological change is so fundamental that I think comparisons like the internet or electricity don't do it justice.
[SPEAKER_01] I think we need to go back further in history to see anything like it.
[SPEAKER_01] And I want to go as far back as before the Industrial Revolution.
[SPEAKER_01] So, before the Industrial Revolution, economically, we lived during a Malthusian age.
[SPEAKER_01] What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, at the time, and you know I'm using here the typical letters that economists use for the factors of production and production functions,
[SPEAKER_01] We had a pretty stagnant technology.
[SPEAKER_01] The most important factor of production in the Middle Ages was land.
[SPEAKER_01] That's what all the wars were about, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And in some sense, you can say, sadly, labor was pretty dispensable.
[SPEAKER_01] The marginal worker produced just enough to satisfy their subsistence needs.
[SPEAKER_01] There was no extra surplus for them.
[SPEAKER_01] And so, in that sense, for the economy, that was dispensable.
[SPEAKER_01] And, of course, standards of living were very poor.
[SPEAKER_01] You were at constant risk of starvation.
[SPEAKER_01] And life was not particularly enjoyable in those situations.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, then something magical happened.
[SPEAKER_01] The Industrial Revolution, driven by things like the scientific method, we suddenly started to experience much more rapid technological change.
[SPEAKER_01] But not only that, in addition, we suddenly developed machinery that became the second most important factor of production.
[SPEAKER_01] Our technology suddenly relied not so much on land.
[SPEAKER_01] Land kind of became, you know, ubiquitous.
[SPEAKER_01] That wasn't the limiting factor anymore.
[SPEAKER_01] But capital and labor were the two factors that really mattered in the industrial economy.
[SPEAKER_01] And the beautiful thing about capital is that you can just reproduce it.
[SPEAKER_01] So that means capital was accumulated, and technology advanced, and the bottleneck was suddenly labor.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, if you're a bottleneck, you're scarce.
[SPEAKER_01] If you're scarce, your relative value goes up.
[SPEAKER_01] And as a result of these developments, our standards of living today are 10 or, I guess, in the U.S. and U.K.,
[SPEAKER_01] I would say 20 times what they were during the pre-industrial times.
[SPEAKER_01] So this industrial age, it was really a golden age of labor because the human worker was the scarcest and most valuable thing.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm speaking in past tense.
[SPEAKER_01] I guess it still is, but I don't know for how long.
[SPEAKER_01] The age of AI, which is rapidly approaching, will see technology grow even faster.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, capital will still be important and will still be reproducible.
[SPEAKER_01] And part of that capital is going to be robots.
[SPEAKER_01] Part of that capital is going to be compute, meaning server farms.
[SPEAKER_01] However, the crucial difference from the industrial age is that labor will also be rapidly reproducible.
[SPEAKER_01] If you need another cognitive worker, you just spin up another agent on your server.
[SPEAKER_01] If you need another physical worker, you produce another robot.
[SPEAKER_01] And who will do that?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, the robots will produce another robot.
[SPEAKER_01] And that means labor is no longer fundamentally scarce, and it will lose its position as being the most economically valuable factor that it has today.
[SPEAKER_01] So what are the implications?
[SPEAKER_01] In this F&D magazine paper, 2023, I simulated in a very simple competitive model what the implications for output growth and for wages are going to be.
[SPEAKER_01] And I should say this is not taking into account the diffusion lags.
[SPEAKER_01] This is just a competitive economy.
[SPEAKER_01] But what you can see is as soon as we have HEI, output growth would skyrocket and wages would at first slow down and then decline.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, in a recent paper of mine, I'm diving even further into what would drive the advances in growth.
[SPEAKER_01] So in the past, we had essentially this right column here.
[SPEAKER_01] We had growing factor productivity and accumulating capital, and that would increase output.
[SPEAKER_01] In addition to that, in the AI economy, we are going to have all these massive amounts of AI labor that can solve cognitive problems and physical problems with robotics.
[SPEAKER_01] And there's going to be two more feedback loops, which are that the AI is going to create better AI to improve its own software and improve its hardware.
[SPEAKER_01] And each of these feedback loops is going to feed back into higher growth.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, it's incredibly difficult to try to put actual numbers on this.
[SPEAKER_01] If you listen to people in Silicon Valley, some of them talk, oh, sure, we'll have at least 20% growth.
[SPEAKER_01] Others say, oh, we'll have 100% growth.
[SPEAKER_01] I'll tell you honestly, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's plausible that we are going to see a step change with significantly higher growth rates.
[SPEAKER_01] But I have absolutely no idea how much higher.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, let's look at skills.
[SPEAKER_01] The main story of the 20th century that we economists have been preaching for decades now is that there was skill-biased technological change or progress.
[SPEAKER_01] And that was something that was first advanced by Jan Tinbergen.
[SPEAKER_01] Jan Tinbergen observed that the skill premium, which is the extra pay that you get for a higher education, was the equilibrium outcome of a race between education and technology.
[SPEAKER_01] And Tinbergen observed back then, and this has held throughout the 20th century, technology needed more and more skilled workers and education could not keep up with that increasing demand for skills.
[SPEAKER_01] And as a result of that, we, the skilled, saw ever rising incomes.
[SPEAKER_01] And that essentially led to this mantra that economists have been preaching for decades, that we need more education and that kind of solves all problems.
[SPEAKER_01] This is just, this is from the US where you can see how much the highest skilled versus the lowest skilled workers saw their incomes diverge over the past 50 years.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I will say that AI puts this whole 20th century narrative fundamentally into question.
[SPEAKER_01] The rapid advances in AI imply that cognitive, white-collar workers, the ones who have been the big beneficiaries of skill-biased change, are suddenly at the front line of automation.
[SPEAKER_01] And there is plenty of empirical results that show that generative AI helps lesser educated workers more.
[SPEAKER_01] The only paper that said the opposite was just retracted two weeks ago, because it was a fraud.
[SPEAKER_01] No, I think that there's obviously more details to it.
[SPEAKER_01] And we will come to that in a slide.
[SPEAKER_01] But AI substitutes for a lot of skills that we no longer need.
[SPEAKER_01] So David Autor is suggesting AI will rebuild the middle class because of that.
[SPEAKER_01] But I think another pretty plausible storyline would be, well, it may just devalue labor in favor of capital, in favor of the server farms.
[SPEAKER_01] So this is a study from mostly open AI researchers that asked how much are the different occupations exposed to AI.
[SPEAKER_01] And this is ranked by the log annual wage.
[SPEAKER_01] So the higher paid professions are on the right, lower paid professions on the left.
[SPEAKER_01] And the higher paid professions, which are predominantly cognitive, are significantly more affected by AI than the lower paid professions.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I just said, I don't think skills are going to be as valuable as they were in the past.
[SPEAKER_01] But there is one skill which I predict will be really fundamental in the next one to five years.
[SPEAKER_01] You see I'm using the same time frame that Dario Amode used.
[SPEAKER_01] And that will be AI fluency.
[SPEAKER_01] So for all of our economies, the most valuable skill in the near term will be to know how to collaborate with AI,
[SPEAKER_01] because AI is really fundamentally a force multiplier.
[SPEAKER_01] If you use these systems effectively, if you use them at the frontier,
[SPEAKER_01] you as an individual can do the work of 10 individuals in some cases.
[SPEAKER_01] And that will hopefully lead to a lot of productivity gains,
[SPEAKER_01] although the diffusion requires our organizations to adapt.
[SPEAKER_01] And so there's a long and arduous process in front of us.
[SPEAKER_01] But ultimately, the current AI systems, even if we didn't make any progress in addition, would give us a lot of productivity.
[SPEAKER_01] I'll also emphasize that they allow us to leapfrog.
[SPEAKER_01] Just like, you know, countries that didn't have an extensive set of telephone cables could just install cell phone towers and jump ahead of others.
[SPEAKER_01] Those who use AI will be able to leapfrog those who may have been more advanced two years ago and who are not using AI.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, if we fast forward one to five years, whenever we have AI, we have to ask ourselves, what will labor look like post-AI?
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's plausible that AI and robotics will ultimately have the capacity to perform essentially any valuable economic task.
[SPEAKER_01] And as Dario Amoday predicted in the beginning, that that will lead to widespread labor displacement and significant wage declines.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think even if wages somehow, you know, manage to keep up but not quite at the pace of economic growth overall, I think what is very likely is that we will see a shift from human labor to AI and robots as the primary drivers of economic growth.
[SPEAKER_01] And the labor share in output will decline.
[SPEAKER_01] So, well, and that forces us to fundamentally ask, what is the role of labor in our society?
[SPEAKER_01] We already covered that labor currently is one of the main factors of production.
[SPEAKER_01] But in addition, it's also the main source of income for most people.
[SPEAKER_01] And a lot of people believe it's also the main source of meaning.
[SPEAKER_01] So, we are going to face fundamental income and meaning challenges.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, let me cover the income distribution part first.
[SPEAKER_01] There is the possibility that those who own and create the AI will see a vast majority of the gains,
[SPEAKER_01] so that there will be fundamentally unprecedented income concentration.
[SPEAKER_01] And, of course, that the benefit may accrue primarily to the capital owners.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think that requires that we rethink our system of income distribution, of social insurance,
[SPEAKER_01] in a way that is not tied to labor as the primary distributive mechanism.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, this is hard even if you are in a country where you have a frontier lab.
[SPEAKER_01] But it's even harder if you don't.
[SPEAKER_01] But, again, let me go back to the observation that even if you are not producing these systems,
[SPEAKER_01] you can still derive substantial productivity gains
[SPEAKER_01] and then hopefully use some of that to make sure that we compensate the losers.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to switch to a paper which says May 5th, but it actually only came out yesterday,
[SPEAKER_01] at the Institute for New Economic Thinking,
[SPEAKER_01] on steering technological progress together with my former advisor, Joe Stiglitz.
[SPEAKER_01] And my takeaway from working on this paper is, well, how should we steer technological progress
[SPEAKER_01] in this wild age of rapidly advancing AI?
[SPEAKER_01] In the short to medium term, I think it is crucial that we kind of flip the incentives,
[SPEAKER_01] that we try to emphasize that the AI systems as we roll them out are complementary to workers as much as we can make them,
[SPEAKER_01] and that we incorporate that in our funding decisions, in our tax systems which currently disadvantage labor, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And that is essentially what people generally call pre-distribution.
[SPEAKER_01] In the longer term, if technology just can substitute for all of labor,
[SPEAKER_01] I think we need to not only steer technology, we don't want to hold back those productivity gains,
[SPEAKER_01] but we will need fundamentally new ways of income redistribution.
[SPEAKER_01] We'll also have to rethink our macroeconomic frameworks.
[SPEAKER_01] Aggregate demand will, first of all, be severely challenged
[SPEAKER_01] if there is a lot of people who lose their jobs.
[SPEAKER_01] And secondly, the human unemployment rate may matter a lot less.
[SPEAKER_01] So we are going to be living in this world where one part of the economy is exploding
[SPEAKER_01] and another part is experiencing demand problems.
[SPEAKER_01] And that was the main material I wanted to cover.
[SPEAKER_01] But I wanted to invite you to a conference that I'm actually organizing
[SPEAKER_01] at the Austrian Central Bank together with the CEPR on June 12th on preparing for the AI revolution.
[SPEAKER_01] So all of you in the room today are invited if you are interested in coming.
[SPEAKER_01] This is a conference that basically takes a deep dive into this topic for a day.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I want to kind of part with a few predictions for the short to medium term.
[SPEAKER_01] Although I will emphasize, like all of us and including like people like Dario Amode,
[SPEAKER_01] I do feel that there is this tremendous uncertainty about how rapidly this will evolve.
[SPEAKER_01] I do expect that over the next year, AI agents are going to rise up and become economically very significant.
[SPEAKER_01] And that will lead to noticeable productivity effects, but also labor market effects.
[SPEAKER_01] And then whenever HEI is reached, which could be as soon as within a year or maybe five years,
[SPEAKER_01] the digital AI part of the economy will skyrocket.
[SPEAKER_01] But you know, this part is starting from a small pace.
[SPEAKER_01] And that means until we see the full macro effects, I expect it to actually take a couple years.
[SPEAKER_01] And during that time, compute and robotics will be one of the major bottlenecks,
[SPEAKER_01] meaning also one of the most valuable things for our economies to have.
[SPEAKER_01] So, in the tradition of our conference, I want to leave you with a Latin sentence here:
[SPEAKER_01] Intelligencia Artificiosa Universalisque Ante Portas.
[SPEAKER_01] And, sorry, one more slide.
[SPEAKER_01] And this is now, I guess, the question that I hope to invoke in all of you.
[SPEAKER_01] If you knew that this Intelligencia Artificiosa is Ante Portas, within just a few years, what should you do?
[SPEAKER_01] What should your organization do?
[SPEAKER_01] What should your country do to prepare for this disruption?
[SPEAKER_01] What do we need to understand better?
[SPEAKER_01] Because that has to be the first step in any well-informed plan.
[SPEAKER_01] And also, what can you personally do to prepare?
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01] Hvala što pratite.
[SPEAKER_00] Hvala što pratite.
[SPEAKER_01] što pratite.
[SPEAKER_01] Hvala što pratite.