[SPEAKER_03] To call it a success but suffice to say we have a few more points to discuss thank you so much managing director for your input and we will take a deep dive on many of the points and lessons that you have just shared with us you see three more tables and rather three more chairs want to be filled here first up please join me in welcoming the commissioner Valdis Dombrowski ladies and gentlemen good morning good morning commissioner
[SPEAKER_03] also with us is the governor of the estonian central bank please welcome madis muller ladies and gentlemen
[SPEAKER_03] and last but certainly not least delighted to join us here up on stage is the minister of finance of slovenia clemen bosančić ladies and gentlemen
[SPEAKER_03] what a spectacular panel we have here today and so very much looking forward to hearing from all of you managing director you've already pointed out that the policy makers in this region have acted decisively in response to the many shocks that we have faced in recent years namely the pandemic of course and russia's war in ukraine and by and large you said yes the grade i would give and and the evaluation i would give these countries is a job
[SPEAKER_03] well done but you've also pointed out very clearly a lot of challenges still remain let's go through them one by one of course these countries despite their good performance are still are still suffering and and dealing with lingering inflation and wage pressures i was wondering if you could share with us some lessons that can be drawn from the recent inflation episode for monetary policy here in this region
[SPEAKER_02] thank you thank you thank you thank you very much and really great to to see you again my remarks on inflation are going to be framed by a review of this inflation episodes we have done
[SPEAKER_02] we looked at some hundred of those episodes and what did we learn from it
[SPEAKER_02] number one monetary policy matters when monetary policy is well informed and decisive the disinflation takes place without too much pain for businesses and households when monetary policy is slow to act
[SPEAKER_02] and monetary policy is slow to act or is inconsistent that leads to a more painful process of disinflation and this is why in my opening remarks i made the point that monetary policy is going to be essential factor for the region to steer through
[SPEAKER_02] and we are going to be able to see the future of the region and this is why in my opening remarks i made the point that monetary policy and that central bank independence is a source of strength for monetary policy
[SPEAKER_02] we have to protect it when we look at the inflationary environment today globally what we observe is that the disinflation process continues but it has slowed down a bit as a result of the tariffs
[SPEAKER_02] and that we observe in this region as well with very very few exceptions most countries are still above their target on inflation they have to persist in bringing inflation down the second thing we observe and we see it in this region as well is that the impact of tariffs
[SPEAKER_02] the impact of tariffs is different and the environment to fight inflation or the situation center banks find themselves is quite different from a country to a country when we came out of covid it was easy because covid hit everybody the same way and it led to the same policy response monetary policy accommodation fiscal policy accommodation fiscal policy accommodation fiscal policy accommodation and
[SPEAKER_02] now we are in a very different place in fact tariffs can create a supply shock
[SPEAKER_02] that is the case for example for countries that are on the side of kind of putting tariffs on others like united states
[SPEAKER_02] what it means is that the supply of goods is reduced and that puts pressure on prices up or it can be a demand shock and that is pretty much the situation for the european union because the countries are now being put in a more difficult position should these tariffs
[SPEAKER_02] and the demand for european union because the demand for european goods goes down so my point here is that universally when we are in at the time of higher uncertainty that's not good investors don't invest consumers don't consume
[SPEAKER_02] in different countries the situation is different so policy has to be adjusted but what is universal for all countries is the strength of monetary policy depends on the competence professionalism and the
[SPEAKER_02] and the independence of central banks and the independence of central banks and the independence of central banks and since we now know central banks are the majority
[SPEAKER_02] in the audience i want to say to you central bankers all the power to you
[SPEAKER_02] well i think that's a message that is very well received here
[SPEAKER_02] in this part and we will hear from another central banker of course maris muller in just a moment but i want to bring in the commissioner here for just one moment
[SPEAKER_02] commissioner we heard the managing director saying despite the many shocks and challenges this region
[SPEAKER_03] the cc region have weathered the storm fairly well a job well done would you concur
[SPEAKER_03] uh well good morning everyone and it's a pleasure to be here in the browning for this conference
[SPEAKER_03] uh well uh all in all if you would like to be here if you would like to be here if you would like to be here
[SPEAKER_03] in this part and we will hear from another central banker of course maris muller in just a moment but i want to bring in the commissioner here for just one moment
[SPEAKER_03] commissioner we heard the managing director saying despite the many shocks and challenges this region the cc region have weathered the storm fairly well a job well done would you concur
[SPEAKER_04] well good morning everyone and it's a pleasure to be here in the browning for this conference
[SPEAKER_04] so all in all if we look at the development in a region indeed one can say that this storm is weathered quite well but it's also worth noting that the storm is not over yet
[SPEAKER_04] so it's too early to get relaxed we are still facing the hard security threats from Russia Russia continues for a fourth year its full-scale war in Ukraine
[SPEAKER_04] and it's also a very important issue that the government is not over yet and it's also a very important issue that the government is not over yet
[SPEAKER_04] so we need urgently to strengthen also our defense capabilities defense industry and that's obviously is even more important in central eastern Europe and obviously especially for countries bordering with Russia and at the same time we need to continue to address our economic vulnerabilities
[SPEAKER_04] strengthen the resilience of our economy and there we have a lot of work to do in the EU as a whole and that fully applies also to this region
[SPEAKER_04] that's why one of the first initiatives of the new European Commission was Competitiveness Compass where we outline all the factors which are affecting EU's competitiveness and how we are going about to addressing them including addressing the innovation gap ensuring the right skills for workforce addressing high energy prices
[SPEAKER_04] and how we are going about to solve the crisis dealing with administering burden cutting red tape and I would say all of those challenges equally applies also to this central eastern and south eastern region of Europe
[SPEAKER_04] yes indeed and defense spending you've already mentioned this one of many challenges trade policies of course on top of that minister you've listened to the managing director speak about this region and impart some valuable lessons as a minister who's representing this region I was wondering if you have any concerns about this region and impart some valuable lessons as a minister who's representing this region I was wondering if you have any concerns about this region and you have any concerns about this region
[SPEAKER_03] I was wondering if you have any concerns about this region and if you have any concerns about this region and you have any concerns about this region and you have any concerns about this region and you have any concerns about this region and you have any concerns about this region as a minister who's representing this region I was wondering what your immediate response and reply would be
[SPEAKER_03] I agree that central Europe or this region responded quite swiftly but you know
[UNKNOWN] I think this region is one of many challenges of many challenges trade policies of course
[SPEAKER_06] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] Hvala što pratite kanal.
[SPEAKER_06] Na sviđanju sviđanju, što pratite kanal.
[SPEAKER_06] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[UNKNOWN] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_05] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[UNKNOWN] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_05] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_05] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_01] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[UNKNOWN] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_00] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_00] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_00] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_05] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_06] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju?
[SPEAKER_04] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_04] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_02] što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Hvala što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[UNKNOWN] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.
[SPEAKER_03] Što pratite kanal na sviđanju.