[SPEAKER_00] Dobar dan i dobrodošli u Moneteru. Ja sam Ines Merkvenić, direktorica Monetere.
[SPEAKER_00] Drago mi da mogu predstaviti ovu seriju predavanja, izlaganja, razgovora
[SPEAKER_00] o Međunarodnim monetarnim institucijama i središnjim bankama, recentnoj povijesti
[SPEAKER_00] i njihovom odnosu i kako će to izgledati u budućnost.
[SPEAKER_00] I puno hvala Dubravko Mihaljeku, kojeg vidim po licima mnogi već znate,
[SPEAKER_00] pa ga neću posebno predstavljati, koji će voditi ovu seriju predavanja
[SPEAKER_00] i njegovom prvom gostu, gospodinu Mekoliju.
[SPEAKER_00] Vidim da vam se privuklo njegova tema, mislim da će biti vrlo zanimljivo.
[SPEAKER_00] Dalje će se ovo predavanje odvijeti na engleskom jeziku,
[SPEAKER_00] pa neće biti prijevoda, ali vjerujem da svi možete pratiti.
[SPEAKER_00] Evo, započnijemo i hvala Šinom Dubravkovi.
[SPEAKER_03] Hvala. Dobrodošli, welcome all to this money museum.
[SPEAKER_03] We are starting today something new.
[SPEAKER_03] We are trying to be innovative.
[SPEAKER_03] It's a series of six lectures on the history of the international monetary system
[SPEAKER_03] and central banking.
[SPEAKER_03] Normally we would go chronologically.
[SPEAKER_03] We would start with the classical gold standard,
[SPEAKER_03] then interwar period continuing with Bretton Woods and so on
[SPEAKER_03] until current contemporary issues.
[SPEAKER_03] But we are fortunate to have with us really a top expert on current monetary system
[SPEAKER_03] and the role of the dollar in the global economy.
[SPEAKER_03] So we decided to reverse the order and start with contemporary issues.
[SPEAKER_03] Next time mid-November we will go with classical gold standard.
[SPEAKER_03] But again, we want to make history very lively.
[SPEAKER_03] and we will start with early proto central banks.
[SPEAKER_03] And we will link their activities to stable coin.
[SPEAKER_03] So that's just the preview of coming attractions.
[SPEAKER_03] And each time we talk about past experiences and challenges that central banks are facing,
[SPEAKER_03] we will try to relate them to current issues that central banks today are facing.
[SPEAKER_03] Not just here in Europe, but around the world.
[SPEAKER_03] So without further ado, it is my great pleasure and honor to welcome Bob McCauley to this lecture.
[SPEAKER_03] Bob has worked from the early 80s until 1994 for the Federal Reserve Bank of New York,
[SPEAKER_03] where he has had a distinguished career.
[SPEAKER_03] He worked at the BIS.
[SPEAKER_03] Bob is known at the BIS as the most prolific contributor to our flagship publication quarterly, BIS quarterly review.
[SPEAKER_03] It is hard to find an issue of this quarterly in the 2000s where Bob hasn't contributed the paper.
[SPEAKER_03] Bob is also known for his deep knowledge in BIS, International Banking Statistics.
[SPEAKER_03] And he is the one who has really advertised to the world academic community the values, the use of these possible uses of these statistics.
[SPEAKER_03] Currently, Bob is affiliated with Boston University and Oxford University.
[SPEAKER_03] He is a frequent contributor to columns in well-known global newspapers and newsletters.
[SPEAKER_03] You will find every now and then his op-eds.
[SPEAKER_03] And Bob is also active in our professional community.
[SPEAKER_03] I will not waste our time any longer because the topic is really interesting and contemporary.
[SPEAKER_03] So, Bob, please take the floor.
[SPEAKER_04] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04] Well, I passed the first test, flying colors.
[SPEAKER_04] Well, thank you, Dubrovko, very much for that very kind introduction.
[SPEAKER_04] This is an ambitious and timely set of lectures, discussions that you're staging here.
[SPEAKER_04] And to start instead of the American way with a joke but with the Japanese way with an apology, you deserve to have a very well-prepared and practiced opening discussion in this ambitious and timely series.
[SPEAKER_04] But what you've got is me instead.
[SPEAKER_04] And I want you to know I'm very much presenting work in progress and all I can say is I very much appreciate the opportunity to speak to you and hear your questions.
[SPEAKER_04] That's the real value added.
[SPEAKER_04] So, I thank Dubrovko for the subtitle here, "Fading Away" or "Here to Stay."
[SPEAKER_04] Pretty good.
[SPEAKER_04] It even rhymes.
[SPEAKER_04] So, this is the plug for Mania's Paddocks and Crashes.
[SPEAKER_04] The eighth edition came out in 2023.
[SPEAKER_04] But the serious thing on this slide is my deep regret that Bob Alibur, my co-author and teacher and friend, died in June.
[SPEAKER_04] And so, if you're wondering whether I always wear a bow tie, I hardly ever do, but Alibur was well-known for his bow tie wearing.
[SPEAKER_04] And so, in his honor today, I stand before you bowed out.
[SPEAKER_04] Just as an amuse-bouche here, let's just remind ourselves where the dollar is, the dimensions of its predominance.
[SPEAKER_04] A lot of people talk about dollar dominance.
[SPEAKER_04] I think that's a little overstated, because the Euro is in a sort of uneven duopoly with the dollar.
[SPEAKER_04] And I think that comes out in this graph.
[SPEAKER_04] So, on the left, the point is that the U.S. economy, which used to be, you know, half the world economy right after the war, is down to something like a quarter of the world economy now.
[SPEAKER_04] And even less when it comes to international trade, the U.S. is a pretty closed economy, in fact.
[SPEAKER_04] But you can see, so we have keyed the U.S. in green and the dollar in green.
[SPEAKER_04] And you can see that in trade invoicing, for instance, the first column in the right-hand panel, that about half the world's trade is denominated in dollars.
[SPEAKER_04] Not just the little bit of trade that the U.S. does, but also all the commodity trade.
[SPEAKER_04] The supply lines in Asia are very heavily dollar supply lines.
[SPEAKER_04] And in foreign exchange reserves, that's official holdings of other people's currency that you can use for various purposes.
[SPEAKER_04] The dollar is down to about 58% these days from somewhere in the '70s not so long ago, but still very much predominant in that use.
[SPEAKER_04] And if you look at international bank claims, external debt, international bonds, turnover of interest rate derivatives, foreign exchange turnover, unfortunately I haven't had time to digest the data that just was published by the, were just published by the BIS at the end of last month.
[SPEAKER_04] The headline was 10 trillion a day instead of 6 trillion a day, but I don't expect that, sorry, I don't expect that it'll have a big effect when I do update.
[SPEAKER_04] So, what's to conclude?
[SPEAKER_04] So, the dollar is in a predominant position in the world of finance, and people wonder, is it in the process of losing that favored position?
[SPEAKER_04] And certainly one of the events that made people wonder about that was the freeze of the Russian, the Bank of Russia's assets back in early 2022.
[SPEAKER_04] Although most of those assets frozen, in fact, were held in euros and mostly held outside the United States as well.
[SPEAKER_04] But that's, the so-called weaponization of the dollar is the buzzword.
[SPEAKER_04] I think that's a bit over the top too, but just to introduce the term, has the willingness of the U.S. government to use the position of the dollar in diplomatic, strategic fashion,
[SPEAKER_04] has that been pushed to such an extreme in current events that countries will look around and say, hmm, let's re-denominate.
[SPEAKER_04] Let's do this some other way.
[SPEAKER_04] And certainly the Brazilian president has been outspoken in that regard.
[SPEAKER_04] So, my contention here is that the things that people are mostly talking about that would knock the dollar off its position probably will not have that effect.
[SPEAKER_04] But there is one thing that could happen.
[SPEAKER_04] I'm going to sit down if you'll forgive me.
[SPEAKER_04] Maybe I should move aside here.
[SPEAKER_04] So, there is something that could happen, I think, that would really disturb the dollar's position.
[SPEAKER_04] And I'm not being original here.
[SPEAKER_04] Joseph Nye, who himself just died several months ago, coined the phrase "The Kindleburger Trap."
[SPEAKER_04] His colleague at Harvard, Graham Allison, coined the term "The Thucydides Trap."
[SPEAKER_04] The Thucydides Trap is all about rising and falling powers and the worry on the part of the incumbent that the rising power is just getting stronger and stronger.
[SPEAKER_04] So, therefore, better now than next year.
[SPEAKER_04] And you know how that can go very badly.
[SPEAKER_04] No, I've gone too far ahead, sorry.
[SPEAKER_04] So, by contrast to the Thucydides Trap, the Kindleburger Trap is a problem of a vacuum, the hazard of a vacuum.
[SPEAKER_04] And it's the old hegemon, many would like to say, the old leader not being capable of carrying the burden, and the new leader either not knowing what to do or not caring to do it.
[SPEAKER_04] And that's the way Kindleburger read 1931.
[SPEAKER_04] And in particular, he drew from his study of the world in depression that there were these important public goods that the leader could provide the whole world economy.
[SPEAKER_04] And most important for today's discussion would be the lender of last resort, but there are other good things that the leader can do as well.
[SPEAKER_04] And a lender of last resort means that you're there for other economies in their moments of difficulty, let's say.
[SPEAKER_04] So, here's how it played out in 1931.
[SPEAKER_04] Austria came under attack.
[SPEAKER_04] Credit Anstalt had made some very bad lending decisions.
[SPEAKER_04] And then it was eventually a run both on the biggest, I guess it was the biggest bank in Austria at the time, and on the currency.
[SPEAKER_04] And there were a couple of rounds of efforts to support Austria organized at the Bank for International Settlements, which had just opened its doors the year before,
[SPEAKER_04] but was really intended by those who conceived of it in the first place as a form for central bankers to get together and work on their common problems.
[SPEAKER_04] And so there were efforts on behalf of Austria, but it got to a certain point.
[SPEAKER_04] And the governor of the Bank of England said, "We have done all that is convenient for us to do."
[SPEAKER_04] And New York Fed was sort of nowhere to be seen.
[SPEAKER_04] And you know the story, the run move from Austria to Germany, it toppled a Jewish bank, Donat.
[SPEAKER_04] And recent research by now our former colleagues at the BIS has shown, in fact, that the Nazis did particularly well in the places where Donat Bank had its biggest footprint in terms of lending and deposits.
[SPEAKER_04] So there's, you could really connect the dots between this decision in Austria and the rise of Hitler.
[SPEAKER_04] Back in the Austrian case, the Banque de France had lots of gold and could have stepped up to the plate.
[SPEAKER_04] It was worried about Austria getting together with Germany, worried about a customs union and wanted reassurances that that was not going to happen in exchange for its gold.
[SPEAKER_04] The reassurances were not forthcoming, the gold equally not forthcoming, and the French had an opportunity there to pick up the slack that the Bank of England no longer felt it could carry, but did not do so for basically political reasons.
[SPEAKER_04] And as you will be aware, the story did not end well for France, the run eventually toppled the pound in September of 1931, eventually got around to the French francs linked to gold as well.
[SPEAKER_04] And the unwisdom of those political conditions attached to that might have been loaned to Austria became very clear when the panzers came across the French border in 1940.
[SPEAKER_04] So what goes around comes around.
[SPEAKER_04] So my punchlines, and you can see how early a stage, to be generous, this effort is just from the fact that I have so many punchlines here, the process of distillation is far from complete.
[SPEAKER_04] And what I want you to take away from this evening's discussion is that there's tens of trillions of dollars outside the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] And it's not completely an accident.
[SPEAKER_04] And U.S. policy, sometimes thoughtful, sometimes neglectful, sometimes out to lunch, helped get us into that position.
[SPEAKER_04] And given that large footprint of the dollar outside the United States, when something happens, as in 2008 and 2020, there can be real problems with all those dollars, the liabilities of banks that don't have access to the Fed's domestic discount window.
[SPEAKER_04] And in those cases, as I'll argue, the Fed did well by doing good.
[SPEAKER_04] That is, was helping its own policy process and transmission, but at the same time lending hundreds of billions of dollars to non-U.S. banks.
[SPEAKER_04] And there's been much discussion of the central banks that the Fed chose to do business with in these swap lines, which is really just a kind of loan of dollars on a short-term basis.
[SPEAKER_04] But it turns out, if you were sort of the global planner looking at the problem, you would choose very, very closely to what the Fed actually did choose.
[SPEAKER_04] So, you know, the notion that U.S. military arrangements or the exposure of U.S. banks were sort of the key factors, I think, doesn't really survive close scrutiny.
[SPEAKER_04] So, we know how these things work. We know they can work. The Fed knows how to do them.
[SPEAKER_04] But the concern, and this is not a personal concern, but the concern more broadly is that there could be people at the Fed who wouldn't do what was needed in circumstances where something was needed.
[SPEAKER_04] And so, my response to that is to queue up the dollar coalition of the willing, by which I mean that the central banks, not including possibly the Federal Reserve, that have banks that have dollar liabilities that can be hard to roll over under certain circumstances, those central banks can all get together and by pooling their resources ensure each other.
[SPEAKER_04] And I think it's uncomfortable prospect, but to some extent due without the Fed as the international lender last resort, even in dollars.
[SPEAKER_04] I think it's uncomfortable.
[UNKNOWN] So, I think it's uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_04] So, just to run the numbers past you, and I was very grateful to my former colleagues at the BIS who I visited recently and got some updates on these graphs.
[SPEAKER_04] So, if you just look at the left of the graphs here, that's non-banks outside the United States, done on a residence basis, to be sure.
[SPEAKER_04] And you would prefer to have non-financial firms rather than just non-banks.
[SPEAKER_04] But all that said, we have something like $12 trillion of dollar debt owned by companies, governments, and even some households outside the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] Now, some of them would be U.S. multinational companies, to be sure, and we have a hard time sorting through all of that.
[SPEAKER_04] But that's a lot.
[SPEAKER_04] That's in the teens, something like 15% of the rest of the world's GDP.
[SPEAKER_04] So, it's not an inconsiderable footprint of the dollar looking at it from the standpoint of the obligors.
[SPEAKER_04] And even perhaps of greater relevance, when one thinks about the lender of the last resort, is the non-U.S. banks.
[SPEAKER_04] When the Eurodollar market first came along, there was a guy named Alexander Sorbodo studying with Jim Tobin at Yale.
[SPEAKER_04] And in his thesis, he talked about the privileged position that U.S. banks would have with this Eurodollar market because, you know, they could kind of collect rents because, after all, who is going to deposit dollars in a non-American bank?
[SPEAKER_04] Well, it turns out the rest of the world was perfectly happy to deposit lots and lots of dollars in non-U.S. banks.
[SPEAKER_04] And focusing on them as consolidated entities in the left panel, the lower bit shows the dollar liabilities of non-U.S., non-U.S. headquartered banks in the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] Now, since 1978's International Banking Act, they have access to the Fed's discount window to the extent they have U.S. operations and suitable collateral in those operations.
[SPEAKER_04] But you can see in the blue area that the predominant place of the debt that non-U.S. banks have in dollars is outside the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] So there's no backstop there.
[SPEAKER_04] There's no easy access to the Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] And we'll come back to this graph to discuss the right-hand panel in a bit.
[SPEAKER_04] So that's the on-balance sheet bit.
[SPEAKER_04] And then there's an off-balance sheet bit, as well.
[SPEAKER_04] This foreign exchange, when I first got into the foreign exchange business, it took me a long time to realize that most foreign exchange transactions, or the modal foreign exchange transaction,
[SPEAKER_04] really did not change the foreign exchange position of either counterparty.
[SPEAKER_04] The modal, probably the biggest single transaction in the foreign exchange market would be somebody with euros, or some bank, some company with euros, going to a counterparty with dollars and saying,
[SPEAKER_04] let's exchange these today, actually for settlement in a couple of days, but let's exchange these right now, and then a month later we'll reverse the transaction at a price we set right now.
[SPEAKER_04] And so if you think about that, you're getting, say you're a European bank swapping euros for dollars, you're getting some dollars, but you need to pay them back at the end of the contracting period.
[SPEAKER_04] And so it's not like you're now long the dollar in some sense that you're exposed to the exchange rate of the dollar versus the euro.
[SPEAKER_04] You've changed the funding that you have from euros into dollars temporarily.
[SPEAKER_04] So if you think about it, it's really more like a loan, borrowed dollars, than it is bought dollars.
[SPEAKER_04] And that's, as I say, probably the biggest single transaction out of the 10 trillion per day that was recorded in April of this year.
[SPEAKER_04] Of course, April this year was a pretty wild month from a lot of standpoints, and so no big surprise that there turned out to be a lot of foreign exchange activity there.
[SPEAKER_04] So you can think of these numbers as dollars that somebody mostly outside the United States is borrowing against the collateral of their own home currency.
[SPEAKER_04] And I think that's a useful way of looking at it.
[SPEAKER_04] And then, in a certain sense, these numbers can be added to the on-balance sheet outright dollar borrowing we were just talking about.
[SPEAKER_04] But I need to look at the screen.
[SPEAKER_04] So we're talking real money here, 26 trillion in foreign exchange swaps.
[SPEAKER_04] That's non-banks, non-US banks outside the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] And then there was, I think I have this wrong here, non-banks, no.
[SPEAKER_04] Yes, that's it.
[SPEAKER_04] The non-banks outside the United States, remember the 12 trillion, they owe another 26 trillion in these kind of off-balance sheet loans.
[SPEAKER_04] And the non-US banks, who also had something over 10 trillion dollars in dollar debt outside the United States, have another 39 trillion in these kind of off-balance sheet.
[SPEAKER_04] You can call them footnote dollar loans, because they're not on the balance sheet, but they show up in the footnotes.
[SPEAKER_04] So there's a lot to get thinking about when you consider the offshore dollar.
[SPEAKER_04] And oddly enough, the US policy role in this, right from the get-go, has been one thing and the other, but cumulatively vastly encouraging.
[SPEAKER_04] So the biggest reason for the dollar to have moved outside the United States to such a large extent is what economists call regulatory arbitrage.
[SPEAKER_04] And what was that?
[SPEAKER_04] Well, back in the day, there were limits on how much a bank in the United States could pay a depositor in terms of the interest rate.
[SPEAKER_04] Let's say in 1955, it was 2%.
[SPEAKER_04] And so when the Fed got into a tightening cycle, suddenly those limits would bind and the banks would lose deposits and money would flow around outside the banking system because the banks weren't allowed to keep up with the market interest rate.
[SPEAKER_04] That was one source.
[SPEAKER_04] Then there were reserve requirements, which would be non-interest-bearing, then non-interest-bearing deposits at the Federal Reserve, which were required in some measure, say, 10% against an outstanding dollar deposit from a real customer.
[SPEAKER_04] And so that's, well, you could get fired from the Fed in the day by calling that a tax, but certainly it was a tax on bank intermediation.
[SPEAKER_04] And that was another reason for the dollars to move outside the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] And there's still, in the US, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation fees, which is yet another reason to hold your dollars outside the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] So that's sort of how the dollar got loosed from the US.
[SPEAKER_04] Let me just give you an example, if I may, and if I don't explain this well, it's not key to what follows, but just to give you a flavor of how this euro dollar got going.
[SPEAKER_04] So here's a British bank, and it finds that it can get funding in a rather elastic fashion.
[SPEAKER_04] They've raised a lot of funding in a little short period of time by taking dollars from US multinationals abroad.
[SPEAKER_04] Actually, we don't know who the depositors were, but they're certainly one of the early players in this game.
[SPEAKER_04] So say the 50 million is from, you know, the likes of DuPont or whatever that have foreign operations or oil companies, whatever.
[SPEAKER_04] And what they found was that they could use those dollars, they could use them to buy sterling and then use the sterling to buy local government paper in Britain.
[SPEAKER_04] But to put, to keep them, their balance sheet from suddenly having this exposure to the sterling dollar exchange rate, at the same time they were buying the sterling, they were selling them back for dollars through this swap mechanism.
[SPEAKER_04] And so this is sort of the way it would look on day one of the deal where the British bank had turned the dollars into sterling, but really in a certain sense had taken the sterling paper of the UK local government and turned it into kind of synthetic US dollar asset.
[SPEAKER_04] And what was, one of the drivers of this was the 2% limit on what deposits could be paid in the United States at the time.
[SPEAKER_04] And so this British bank, without taking on any first order foreign exchange risk, basically gotten around the limitations that the Bank of England was trying to administer in terms of keeping the credit from growing too fast in the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] They got around the chummy arrangements among the British banks themselves, not to pay too high an interest rate in sterling, and they got around mostly, they got around this limit in the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] And they also got around, of course, the deposit insurance and the reserve requirement cost.
[SPEAKER_04] So this is sort of how it looks.
[SPEAKER_04] And these sort of transactions still go on today.
[SPEAKER_04] So let me go back for a second.
[SPEAKER_04] No, I'm going wrong, excuse me.
[SPEAKER_04] I'm going wrong, excuse me.
[SPEAKER_04] So some research that Catherine Schenk and I did when she visited the BIS in my last months there was looking into the BIS archives.
[SPEAKER_04] And the swaps among central banks were pioneered by the head of the foreign department at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York against considerable resistance among the European central banks,
[SPEAKER_04] including, oddly enough, the Bank of England, which proved to be the biggest beneficiaries of these swaps.
[SPEAKER_04] But something that had been lost from view was that the Fed had another swap with the BIS.
[SPEAKER_04] It really wasn't about getting Swiss francs from the BIS, but was really about getting U.S. dollars to the BIS.
[SPEAKER_04] And when things were tight and the Six Day War in 1967 was one such instance, but even the end of the year in 1966,
[SPEAKER_04] the usual sort of window dressing transactions that still go on today looked like there was going to be a big squeeze in the dollar market in London and Paris.
[SPEAKER_04] And so the Fed lent dollars to the BIS, which took them on as a principal.
[SPEAKER_04] And then the BIS banking department people rang up their buddies at banks in Paris and London and deposited those dollars
[SPEAKER_04] and kept the U.S. dollar interest rate in London from going, say, to seven, seven and a half percent at a time when the Fed was actually going in the other direction,
[SPEAKER_04] trying to hold down, get U.S. interest rates down.
[SPEAKER_04] So that was a very early case where the swap was used not in order to fund some intervention in the foreign exchange market,
[SPEAKER_04] which is the way most people think about these central bank swaps, but rather was there to manage the liquidity in this offshore market.
[SPEAKER_04] So the Fed could manage things in New York, but it needed help and it got help to manage things in London and Paris.
[SPEAKER_04] So that's precedent for 2008 and 2020.
[SPEAKER_04] In 1974, some number 20 bank in the U.S. run by a pretty dubious guy got into trouble doing foreign exchange transactions and betting the house on the way the dollar was going, got that wrong.
[SPEAKER_04] And so there was a run on this Franklin National Bank and the Fed actually lent dollars to Franklin National in New York to the limit of the collateral that the bank had that it could post to the New York Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] And then they enlisted the Bank of England to sort of be the custodian of some more collateral loans that Franklin National had made in dollars out of their London branch.
[SPEAKER_04] And in that case, the Fed was in effect through one bank being a lender of last resort to the offshore dollar market.
[SPEAKER_04] And most recently, there's the interesting case of Silicon Valley Bank, which had a branch ostensibly in the Caribbean, but that had deposits from, I think, mostly private equity types in Hong Kong and some on the mainland.
[SPEAKER_04] And the bailout by Silicon Valley Bank by the U.S. banking authorities did not include these branch liabilities.
[SPEAKER_04] And I've asked around, and to the best of my knowledge and to the best of understanding of people I've spoken to, no one else can remember anybody being a depositor in an American bank branch outside the United States and not getting paid off when push came to shove.
[SPEAKER_04] So these various ways that the Fed over the years encouraged is too strong a word, but sort of after the fact validated this development of the offshore dollar.
[SPEAKER_04] And so in 2008 and 2020, we have the Fed as a lender of last resort to the whole market.
[SPEAKER_04] And you've seen, we're talking about tens of trillions of dollars of liabilities of foreign non-U.S. banks, I should say.
[SPEAKER_04] And my argument is that the Fed did well by doing good.
[SPEAKER_04] It was not just helping global financial stability big heartedly, but indeed, if you look at it carefully, the Fed needed to hold down what was then the benchmark interest rate in the dollar, LIBOR,
[SPEAKER_04] for its own purposes.
[SPEAKER_04] So we start the story with the announcement by BNP Paribas that they couldn't price a batch of something like mutual funds, I guess, that had U.S. housing paper in them hedged back into Europe.
[SPEAKER_04] So with this forward sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_04] But basically, BNP Paribas says, we don't know what this stuff is worth.
[SPEAKER_04] And that meant nobody knew what any of it was worth.
[SPEAKER_04] And that meant you didn't even know how much your counterparty in the interbank market had of this sort of paper.
[SPEAKER_04] And so you can imagine how this deteriorated rather quickly.
[SPEAKER_04] And the Fed brings out in December of 2007 a sort of stigma-free discount window arrangement where it would auction off dollars to banks in New York that had proper collateral.
[SPEAKER_04] And that was seen as involving less possible admission of difficulty by an individual bank to join in an auction with everybody else rather than having to go bilaterally to the Fed and borrow against your collateral.
[SPEAKER_04] So that was a great success.
[SPEAKER_04] And introduced sort of in parallel to it was the swap lines with some of the major central banks where they would more or less follow the same procedure to auction off or somehow price the dollar loans to their own banks in their own jurisdictions using their own collateral requirements.
[SPEAKER_04] So it was like the Fed and the partner central banks, most notably the ECB, the Swiss National Bank, Bank of England, Bank of Japan, Bank of Canada in principle was involved but never really participated.
[SPEAKER_04] It was as if they were running an international global version of a dollar discount window for all the banks in the world where the Fed benefited from the ECB being the one that looked at the collateral and took the risk of lending to the bank and the money went out.
[SPEAKER_04] And after the Lehman failure, we had a money market fund in the U.S. so-called break the buck announced that their liabilities were only worth 98 cents on the dollar instead of a dollar.
[SPEAKER_04] There was a run on this whole industry.
[SPEAKER_04] And at that point, because the non-U.S. banks were big borrowers from these money market funds, there was a huge demand for the Fed credits and the Fed eased up on the conditions and increased the frequency.
[SPEAKER_04] And we ended up at the end with, what was this, about $600 billion of swaps between the Federal Reserve and the ECB, Swiss National Bank, Bank of England and Bank of Japan.
[SPEAKER_04] And remarkably enough, on October 3rd, 2008, the Fed basically said, we're not putting limits on this.
[SPEAKER_04] So the only limits in this would be the collateral that the ECB or the Bank of England would find acceptable, which could be obviously in its own currency.
[SPEAKER_04] So that really opened up the floodgates.
[SPEAKER_04] And the $600 billion sounds like a lot of money, but remember the on-balance, just the on-balance sheet amounts are in the tens of billions.
[SPEAKER_04] And then there's all the swap loans in dollars as well.
[SPEAKER_04] So actually the Fed got a lot of leverage.
[SPEAKER_04] It put up something like 5% of the liabilities that were being run on, and that was enough to calm things down.
[SPEAKER_04] That's sort of the quantity version of the story.
[SPEAKER_04] Here we come to the price version of the story.
[SPEAKER_04] And you can see the blue line there, which is expected overnight rates that the Fed was targeting as traded in a sort of side market of derivatives.
[SPEAKER_04] And then the black line is three month LIBOR.
[SPEAKER_04] Now the key thing to know about three month LIBOR was that most of the action in the US housing market had been with adjustable rate mortgages.
[SPEAKER_04] And there the borrowers were easily persuaded to shift all their short-term borrowing from other benchmarks like treasury bills to LIBOR.
[SPEAKER_04] And the game had been played where a household would get a loan for a couple of years and have a lock, steady interest rates.
[SPEAKER_04] And then after two years they would start adjusting.
[SPEAKER_04] So about the time you get to October 2008, we're looking at a huge cohort of underlying loans about to be repriced off of LIBOR.
[SPEAKER_04] And while the Fed is bringing down the interest rates that it controls, as indicated by the dotted blue line, the market is pushing up those LIBOR loan rates.
[SPEAKER_04] And my argument is that the Fed needed to get those rates down.
[SPEAKER_04] I mean, these were rates also that were paid by the non-US banks.
[SPEAKER_04] And they're also the rates that US companies, especially small and medium-sized companies, pay that don't have access to the bond market.
[SPEAKER_04] So the Fed needed the offshore rates to come down and finally threw enough money at the problem that succeeded.
[SPEAKER_04] And it was basically after the Fed went unlimited that you finally see LIBOR coming down.
[SPEAKER_04] And something similar happens in 2020.
[SPEAKER_04] We get a big run.
[SPEAKER_04] There's a so-called dash for cash.
[SPEAKER_04] Companies want to have cash.
[SPEAKER_04] They don't know whether they're going to have revenues.
[SPEAKER_04] They still have costs.
[SPEAKER_04] Companies are raising money.
[SPEAKER_04] So banks are holding off lending to each other because they might be asked for dollars from their corporate customers.
[SPEAKER_04] And again, there are runs on the money market funds.
[SPEAKER_04] This time, even without one of them having, in effect, defaulted on its soft commitment to have its shares traded $1 par.
[SPEAKER_04] And this time, the Fed really knew the playbook and just dusted off the facilities from 2008.
[SPEAKER_04] And so the picture looks quite different.
[SPEAKER_04] You have a very short period there from, say, the 9th of March, where things are going the wrong way with LIBOR from the Fed standpoint.
[SPEAKER_04] And the swaps are extended in time to the three-month period, which matches the benchmark rate.
[SPEAKER_04] daily operations are finally started by the third or fourth week of March.
[SPEAKER_04] And the Fed does, in a matter of weeks or days, what it took months of sort of fumbling around in 2008.
[SPEAKER_04] So by now you could say the technology or the technique is pretty clearly laid out.
[SPEAKER_04] And there was an additional wrinkle that we often forget about these days.
[SPEAKER_04] The Fed at one point announced that it was going to be buying U.S. corporate bonds.
[SPEAKER_04] And so some people call this a dealer of last resort.
[SPEAKER_04] I call it a buyer of last resort because they weren't just making markets at two-sided prices or something.
[SPEAKER_04] They were just saying, "Gimme, gimme, gimme."
[SPEAKER_04] Well, actually, you know, it wasn't all that much they said they would buy, but it worked very quickly.
[SPEAKER_04] And maybe I shouldn't dwell on this in the interest of time.
[SPEAKER_04] But it's interesting that if you were a holder of, say, Brazilian dollar bonds in 2020,
[SPEAKER_04] when the Fed made its announcement that it was going to be buying U.S. corporate bonds,
[SPEAKER_04] with U.S. corporate bonds, the price of the Brazilian bonds went up as well.
[SPEAKER_04] So the Fed, without trying, turned into the buyer of last resort for the whole global dollar bond market.
[SPEAKER_04] Here, I take on these series of articles where people are trying to reverse engineer the Fed's choice of partner central banks.
[SPEAKER_04] And the list gets pretty long of plausible variables of political as well as economic.
[SPEAKER_04] But here's my perspective on it.
[SPEAKER_04] I promised you we'd come back to this graph.
[SPEAKER_04] Now you should look at the right-hand panel.
[SPEAKER_04] And the big five, the ones that the central banks and the Fed engaged with earliest and in the most sustained fashion,
[SPEAKER_04] Canada, Switzerland, Euro area, Japan, the U.K.
[SPEAKER_04] The banks from those countries, headquartered in those countries, account for a very high fraction,
[SPEAKER_04] something like two-thirds of the dollars borrowed offshore by non-U.S. banks.
[SPEAKER_04] I know that's a mouthful.
[SPEAKER_04] And then the Fed then temporarily extended swaps to Australia, Denmark, Norway, and Sweden.
[SPEAKER_04] They're in the sort of blue area in the right-hand panel.
[SPEAKER_04] And even went so far as to open lines with Brazil, Korea, Mexico, and Singapore.
[SPEAKER_04] Although back in 2008, only Korea and Mexico drew.
[SPEAKER_04] I think Singapore drew in 2020.
[SPEAKER_04] But they kept the same cast of characters in 2020 as they had chosen in 2008.
[SPEAKER_04] And so that leaves some very important banking systems out.
[SPEAKER_04] You can see pulled out China.
[SPEAKER_04] And we don't really have comprehensive data on China.
[SPEAKER_04] This is kind of using partner data.
[SPEAKER_04] So what does the Bank of England say the Chinese banks are doing in London?
[SPEAKER_04] For instance, what does the Hong Kong Monetary Authority say they do in Hong Kong?
[SPEAKER_04] And so on.
[SPEAKER_04] But it turns out that something like three-quarters of those liabilities,
[SPEAKER_04] if you classify it by the headquarters of the bank and whether its central bank has access to the Fed,
[SPEAKER_04] it turns out the Fed has a pretty good coverage.
[SPEAKER_04] And if you just look at the kind of who's who and do a standard two-by-two contingency table,
[SPEAKER_04] the chi-square is sort of mind-numbingly large.
[SPEAKER_04] It was almost a perfect match between the swap transactions on a daily basis in currency X
[SPEAKER_04] and the choice of that central bank to be a swap partner by the Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] And if they had just strictly gone down the list of the size of the dollar borrowing
[SPEAKER_04] in the swap market by banking system, by currency in this case, sorry,
[SPEAKER_04] they should have had the Hong Kong Monetary Authority and just a bit,
[SPEAKER_04] just very much at the edge of the Reserve Bank of India back in 2008.
[SPEAKER_04] And the two central banks they did extend swaps to that didn't really qualify
[SPEAKER_04] on a strict quantitative basis were the Central Bank of Brazil
[SPEAKER_04] and the Reserve Bank of New Zealand.
[SPEAKER_04] But again, if a planner with a sort of global utility function or something were to make this decision,
[SPEAKER_04] it wouldn't have made it very, very differently from what the Fed did.
[SPEAKER_04] And that hasn't changed over time.
[SPEAKER_04] And again, this needs to be updated with the 2025 data.
[SPEAKER_04] But there's a very high coverage by the Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] So you may know that there was some hanky-panky, put it, possibly rising to the criminal level.
[SPEAKER_04] But on reflection, at least some of the courts have decided, no, it didn't rise to the criminal level.
[SPEAKER_04] By the traders of this LIBOR, frankly, my guess is that perhaps with the exception of UBS,
[SPEAKER_04] most of the banks weren't well enough internally organized to know which side their bread was buttered on,
[SPEAKER_04] whether they wanted LIBOR to be higher or lower on a daily basis,
[SPEAKER_04] because that requires a very thorough understanding of your position that I don't think many bank management's information operations can sustain, actually.
[SPEAKER_04] But anyway, because LIBOR was involved in the hanky-panky, it's essentially the dollar bit of it has been domesticated.
[SPEAKER_04] And now the short-term rates in U.S. mortgages, in U.S. corporate loans are based on overnight repos,
[SPEAKER_04] overnight collateralized, overnight loans.
[SPEAKER_04] So you might say, well, now that the dollar is not using, or dollar lending contracts are not using this offshore rate,
[SPEAKER_04] and maybe the Fed can just let the offshore market take care of itself.
[SPEAKER_04] And I guess I come down on this one saying, no, the Fed will still be interested because if things go badly outside the United States,
[SPEAKER_04] then the non-U.S. banks will come into the U.S. repo market and end up pushing up rates there in a way that the Fed will have to resist.
[SPEAKER_04] So my suggestion is that the change in the benchmark from an offshore benchmark to an onshore benchmark won't change the Fed's interest in keeping things stable for the rest of the world's banks that are dealing in such large amounts in dollars.
[SPEAKER_04] So if we face the kindle burger trap, and the way that Joseph Nye thought about it was that the U.S. would somehow become unable and the Chinese would become unwilling or not knowing or whatever.
[SPEAKER_04] But that's not actually what we're talking about. We're talking about a situation where the Fed is able but chooses or has chosen for it perhaps not to do its job of stabilizing this offshore dollar market.
[SPEAKER_04] I don't know whether I can -- can I get some help in calling that one?
[SPEAKER_04] I don't know whether I can do it.
[UNKNOWN] I don't know whether I can do it.
[SPEAKER_08] There's a table on page 26 which consists of your balance sheet.
[SPEAKER_08] And one of the increases of the balance sheet is under assets,
[SPEAKER_08] the central bank liquidity swaps,
[SPEAKER_08] which shows an increase from the end of 2007 from $24 billion
[UNKNOWN] to $553 billion in change at the end of the day.
[UNKNOWN] What's that?
[SPEAKER_07] Those are spots that were done as part of central banks.
[SPEAKER_07] Many of our banks are short dollars.
[SPEAKER_07] And how do we work?
[SPEAKER_07] It's the number of dollars in private interest rates
[SPEAKER_07] and the great volatility in our markets.
[SPEAKER_07] What we have done is with a number of major central banks,
[SPEAKER_07] the European Central Bank, for example,
[SPEAKER_07] we saw our currency of dollars with their currency of euros.
[SPEAKER_07] They take the dollars, lend it out to the banks
[SPEAKER_07] in their jurisdiction.
[SPEAKER_07] That helps bring down interest rates in the global market of dollars.
[SPEAKER_07] And meanwhile, we're not lending to those banks.
[SPEAKER_07] The central bank is responsible for the KMS.
[SPEAKER_07] So who does that?
[SPEAKER_08] To make institutions in Europe and other countries.
[SPEAKER_08] Which ones?
[SPEAKER_08] I don't know.
[UNKNOWN] Half a trillion dollars.
[UNKNOWN] The loans go from the central banks,
[UNKNOWN] and they then put them out to their institutions.
[SPEAKER_08] They're trying to break down short-term interest rates
[SPEAKER_08] and double the markets around the world.
[SPEAKER_08] Well, let's go.
[SPEAKER_08] Which central banks are coming from there?
[SPEAKER_08] There's 14 of them, which are listed in our --
[SPEAKER_08] I'm sure they're listed here somewhere.
[SPEAKER_08] All right.
[UNKNOWN] So who actually made that to the pandemic?
[SPEAKER_08] Who made that decision?
[SPEAKER_08] The federal government.
[SPEAKER_08] Okay.
[SPEAKER_08] And was it done at one time or in a series of meetings?
[SPEAKER_08] A series of meetings.
[SPEAKER_08] And under what legal authority?
[SPEAKER_08] We have a long-standing legal authority to support the central banks.
[SPEAKER_08] It's not an emergency authority at any time.
[SPEAKER_08] Anything specific about it?
[SPEAKER_08] You know, my account is still section 14 of the general.
[SPEAKER_08] Let me hear that.
[SPEAKER_08] All right.
[SPEAKER_08] Can we actually look at the arrangements?
[SPEAKER_08] And one of the arrangements is $9 billion in a museum.
[SPEAKER_08] That works out for $3,000 for every single person who lives in a museum.
[SPEAKER_08] Seriously, we live with that.
[SPEAKER_08] And it's definitely kind of credit to Americans rather than museums.
[UNKNOWN] It's not costing Americans anything.
[UNKNOWN] If your agent comes back, it comes back.
[UNKNOWN] It's not at the cost of the American credit.
[SPEAKER_08] You aren't spending credit for Americans.
[SPEAKER_08] Paul?
[SPEAKER_08] It wouldn't necessarily affect the credit points
[UNKNOWN] if you instead of having to do a dollar tax credit anyway.
[UNKNOWN] We're looking to all of the rest of the nation's institutions
[UNKNOWN] in the same way.
[UNKNOWN] Well, look at the next page.
[UNKNOWN] The very next page has the U.S. dollar
[UNKNOWN] number of exchange rate.
[UNKNOWN] It shows a 20% increase in U.S. dollar on exchange rate
[SPEAKER_08] at exactly the same time.
[SPEAKER_08] if you're handing out half of $20,000 in farms.
[UNKNOWN] Do you have any questions?
[UNKNOWN] Yes.
[UNKNOWN] All right.
[UNKNOWN] Well, the Constitution says
[UNKNOWN] no money should have a contract
[UNKNOWN] with a consequence of appropriations made by law.
[UNKNOWN] Do you know?
[SPEAKER_04] So, the staff member for Congressman Grayson obviously missed here
[SPEAKER_04] because the right question was not $3,000 per every man, woman, and child in New Zealand.
[SPEAKER_04] but there are, I looked it up in 2008, there were 34 million sheep.
[SPEAKER_04] So, the right question would have been, you know, is there any good reason for us
[SPEAKER_04] having lent a quarter of a million dollars for every man, woman, child, and sheep in New Zealand.
[SPEAKER_04] Actually, the New Zealanders did not draw, which Bernanke might have entered into his response in a useful way.
[SPEAKER_04] But you can see how it's kind of, can be fun in the right sort of context to go after this sort of lending arrangement.
[SPEAKER_04] And I called to your attention the leaked, I forget what soft, what, it wasn't, anyway,
[SPEAKER_04] there was a conversation among high officials in the government about the attacks on the Houthis.
[SPEAKER_04] And the Vice President said, you know, I just don't want to be bailing out Europeans again.
[SPEAKER_04] So, you could see how things could go very bad with respect to these swaps in the wrong sort of environment.
[SPEAKER_04] And I guess I got on this reading this apparently very well sourced Reuters story in March.
[SPEAKER_04] Let's see.
[SPEAKER_04] And he got writing on this.
[SPEAKER_04] And this is kind of a poignant one.
[SPEAKER_04] Can you hit that at 3549 if it doesn't land there?
[SPEAKER_06] So, that means we can go on for a longer amount of time.
[SPEAKER_06] And we'll be able to read kind of very carefully what we think is the right level of sort of still not applying reserves.
[SPEAKER_06] What about the world's national dollar basis?
[SPEAKER_08] With all these disruptions, do you stand ready to supply dollars to the central banks as we've done in the past?
[SPEAKER_08] When there's been a majority of dollars?
[SPEAKER_06] Sure.
[SPEAKER_06] Absolutely we do.
[SPEAKER_06] Just for everyone's knowledge, we have standing dollar spotlines with five large central banks.
[SPEAKER_06] And they go to the jurisdictions where there are big overseas dollar funding markets.
[SPEAKER_06] And in fact, those are overseas markets where, for example, the European or Asian institution is buying an asset-backed security that is backed by loans to American consumers.
[SPEAKER_06] So, in fact, these are loans to American consumers.
[SPEAKER_06] And we support that.
[SPEAKER_06] We want to make sure that dollars are available in dollar funding to hold those dollar assets.
[SPEAKER_06] So, the way it works is, when needed, we land to the central bank in dollars and they pay us back in dollars.
[SPEAKER_06] They then, in their currency, they land on in dollars.
[SPEAKER_06] And so, we take no credit risk or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_06] And it supports dollar funding markets.
[SPEAKER_06] Dollar funding markets are very sensitive during times of crisis.
[SPEAKER_06] And it's very unfolding.
[SPEAKER_06] And the reason we do it is it's really good for U.S. consumers.
[UNKNOWN] So, we'll continue to do that, just as part of the dollar being a reserve currency.
[UNKNOWN] And the reserve currency is most important.
[SPEAKER_06] And we will do that.
[SPEAKER_06] You mentioned amongst these--
[SPEAKER_06] This is important.
[SPEAKER_04] Disappointing Q&A because when Professor Rajan was head of the central bank in India, he was not pleased with the result, the answer that he got from the Federal Reserve when he asked for a swap line.
[SPEAKER_04] And here's President Lagarde answering sort of the same question.
[SPEAKER_04] We will continue doing so in an undeterred and unchanged manner, I'm sure.
[SPEAKER_04] So, since entering the debate with this dollar coalition of the willing idea, I've had various questions.
[SPEAKER_04] One of them was, can the 14 central banks trust each other?
[SPEAKER_04] I guess my answer is the Fed trusted them.
[SPEAKER_04] Although it may be that an arrangement among Asian central banks has never been activated for some such reason.
[SPEAKER_04] And it is--can they actually do it?
[SPEAKER_04] Well, more digging is required here, but it looks like $2 trillion could be assembled by just the 14.
[SPEAKER_04] Of course, there's no necessity to limit it to 14.
[SPEAKER_04] And this was an interesting question.
[SPEAKER_04] Well, only the Fed can print dollars.
[SPEAKER_04] So, you know, how's this going to work?
[SPEAKER_04] And that allowed me to do some fun history, including the so-called Silberzug that left Vienna for Hanover.
[SPEAKER_04] The Austrian monetary management was of such quality that they were no longer actually exchanging their currency for silver.
[SPEAKER_04] So, it was just kind of sitting around and they loaded it onto a train.
[SPEAKER_04] And it didn't actually calm the market until it showed up in Hanover.
[SPEAKER_04] And the ship captains who were waiting to unload their ships until they could have some assurance of payment.
[SPEAKER_04] When they saw the train coming into town, they started unloading the ships and Hanover was back in business.
[SPEAKER_04] There was a case in 1890 where the Bank of France ships gold, trying to figure out how it actually happened.
[SPEAKER_04] But it had to be loaded and unloaded more than a few times.
[SPEAKER_04] But when the Bank of England sent it back to the Bank of France, apparently the cases had not been opened.
[SPEAKER_04] So, anyway, obviously, if you're lending a commodity, you can't just print it up.
[SPEAKER_04] You're not an alchemist.
[SPEAKER_04] And so, it turns out that most of the international lending of last resort among central banks in the last two centuries has been somebody else's money, in fact.
[SPEAKER_04] Here is the FT picture of the Silberzug.
[SPEAKER_04] And then some former colleagues said to me, "Well, it's not like the people at the New York Fed are going to lose their mind.
[SPEAKER_04] Why are you worried about this?"
[SPEAKER_04] And I dug in, and as Bernanke said, it's the FOMC, the Federal Open Market Committee, that makes the call.
[SPEAKER_04] And there's been some extraordinary additions on the side of the Bank presidents, people who wouldn't, in the past, have ended up in those jobs.
[SPEAKER_04] The woman at the bottom, Beth Hammock, for instance, used to be the global treasurer for Goldman Sachs.
[SPEAKER_04] And she's now at the Cleveland Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] So, it's as if there were some sort of prepositioning of people who would know what to do in an emergency.
[SPEAKER_04] And if you look at the job applicants for Powell's job, it's, I guess I would say, not uniformly reassuring.
[SPEAKER_04] And ask the question, who would be the Paul Volcker who got sent in if one of these candidates proved not to work out so well in the job?
[SPEAKER_04] So, I conclude that the dollar's predominance is there.
[SPEAKER_04] It's very strong.
[SPEAKER_04] I didn't tell you the story about how the Bank of Russia changed its reserve composition,
[SPEAKER_04] how long it held onto the dollars in one way or the other, moving them out of the United States.
[SPEAKER_04] But I might read that situation to say that the dollars were necessary for the Bank of Russia
[SPEAKER_04] because the private markets, the credit markets, and especially the currency market in Moscow, continue to operate against the dollar.
[SPEAKER_04] And only in the last two years has it all shifted over towards the Chinese currency.
[SPEAKER_04] So, the dollar is a very sticky superpower in this view.
[SPEAKER_04] But you can't imagine something being done or something not being done that would deliver a real blow to the dollar's status.
[SPEAKER_04] So, I hope we avoid that.
[SPEAKER_04] I think we can avoid it even if the help from the Fed gets to be intermittent.
[SPEAKER_04] So, the answer to the question -- what was the question again?
[SPEAKER_02] Here to stay or fade away?
[SPEAKER_04] So, not fade away.
[SPEAKER_04] It could go away with an ugly bang whimper.
[SPEAKER_04] But otherwise, it's here to stay.
[SPEAKER_03] Thank you very much, Bob.
[SPEAKER_03] So, this is a broad landscape of several centuries of central banking and most recently the role of the dollar.
[SPEAKER_03] Let me turn to the public for questions.
[SPEAKER_03] I'm sure there are some people here who prepare the questions.
[SPEAKER_03] Yes, please.
[SPEAKER_01] I'll just introduce myself, Christian Kodarsky from Faculty of Political Science at the University of Zagreb.
[SPEAKER_01] So, thank you for your excellent lecture.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, when it comes to outsourcing dollar empire, it's a great article in international studies quarterly recently published by German scholar Andrea Binder.
[SPEAKER_01] And she basically maps out the process of offshore dollar credit.
[SPEAKER_01] So, basically, we have outsourcing of the money creation to the London and other financial capitals, but London primarily.
[SPEAKER_01] So, in a nutshell, she says US financial empire is a combination of public hardware procured by the US military.
[SPEAKER_01] And secondly, private software.
[SPEAKER_01] So, basically, offshore dollar system.
[SPEAKER_01] But as we all know, all systems, well, from time to time tend to disequilibrium.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I see three things and I want to hear your take on the matter.
[SPEAKER_01] So, first one is an endogenous process of fiscal incontinence.
[SPEAKER_01] I really like the quote from your recent piece for Central for Economic and Policy Reform, where you say that the bond markets are giving Uncle Sam plenty of rope to hang himself on.
[SPEAKER_01] So, definitely, this is one major threat, fiscal incontinence.
[SPEAKER_01] But I would like to hear more about two other exogenous threats to the system, to this equilibrium of dollar hegemony.
[SPEAKER_01] The first one is technological change.
[SPEAKER_01] So, you worked at the BIS and I would like to hear whether Enbridge, as a project, could serve as a way to avoid the weaponization of US dollar in global finance.
[SPEAKER_01] So, could this technological solution provide to other central banks in the world a leeway to avoid the swift and dollar clearinghouses?
[SPEAKER_01] So, this is my first question.
[SPEAKER_01] And my second question, we all know that security is really important.
[SPEAKER_01] And we see geopolitical order fraying.
[SPEAKER_01] So, we see a lot of central banks that invested a lot of money in the US market like Saudi Arabia, Qatar, United Arab Emirates.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, Saudi Arabia recently decided not to extend the agreement with the US to take only dollars for oil shipments.
[SPEAKER_01] So, we see they are also taking other currencies such as Chinese yuan.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I would like to see your take on the matter.
[SPEAKER_01] And maybe stable coins.
[SPEAKER_01] It's also in the domain of technology.
[SPEAKER_01] So, basically, there is no secret.
[SPEAKER_01] Paolo Arduino, who is at the helm of the Tether.
[SPEAKER_01] He says that the mission of Tether is to prolong US financial hegemony.
[SPEAKER_01] So, how do you see it?
[SPEAKER_01] Is this just a con to actually attract investors?
[SPEAKER_01] Or there is some way financial statecraft, if you want to label it like that, that could help US to keep dollar in place by ensuring that the world runs on financial rails called stable coins, which are linked directly to US dollar assets.
[SPEAKER_01] So, plenty of things.
[SPEAKER_01] But I would really like to hear your take on the matter.
[SPEAKER_03] Other questions from the public, please.
[SPEAKER_03] So, that you give Bob some time to prepare.
[SPEAKER_03] Any other burning dilemmas that you have?
[SPEAKER_03] Whether you should keep your savings in dollars, switch them to euros?
[SPEAKER_03] No?
[SPEAKER_03] Okay.
[SPEAKER_03] Maybe you will be less shy in a second.
[SPEAKER_03] Bob, please.
[SPEAKER_04] Well, thanks for the questions.
[SPEAKER_04] To start with your conclusion, it's amazing to me that Tether is where it is today, given its record.
[SPEAKER_04] It broke the buck.
[SPEAKER_04] Not just once, I think.
[SPEAKER_04] It suffered indictments and prosecutions.
[SPEAKER_04] In short, it did things that no proper US money market fund could do and still have any shareholders.
[SPEAKER_04] So, I conclude from that that there's really a great demand for something that allows you to trade in crypto and never go back to real money.
[SPEAKER_04] And it is very heavily traded, this Tether, as sort of the, what you would say, vehicle currency for that whole business.
[SPEAKER_04] So, as I understand the new US law, the Genius Act?
[SPEAKER_04] Yes.
[SPEAKER_04] They, it more or less requires them to be, or the set up, I don't know what enforcement there is, but the set up, the desired set up would be for Tether to have nothing but treasury bills.
[SPEAKER_04] And there's even been some conversation out of the US Treasury that leads you in the direction of this is going to be the demand for US Treasuries.
[SPEAKER_04] And so back to your first question, we're going to, we're not going to stop the fiscal incontinence, we're just going to get some more customers by hitching the dollar to this, this newer technology.
[SPEAKER_04] I remain to be convinced that crypto has much of a future as a payments mechanism outside of the world of crypto itself.
[SPEAKER_04] But there's a very nice paper that was written for the European Parliament by three authors, including a guy named Eric Monet in Paris.
[SPEAKER_04] And I heartily recommend that paper.
[SPEAKER_04] I think he has a, he has a, they have a pretty catchy, he had a CEPR piece, I think, where he talked about it as crypto mercantilism, I think, so the US peddling dollars by wrapping them in crypto paper.
[SPEAKER_04] So the Saudi oil question, I think the more significant judgment by Saudis is to link their currency because they were originally going to link their currency to the special drawing right of the IMF.
[SPEAKER_04] So they're going to have a multi currency sort of anchor for their currency and they shifted to the dollar.
[SPEAKER_04] I always think that decision was more important.
[SPEAKER_04] And I think who, one of the reasons they liked that arrangement, first of all, it's very simple to operate compared to linking to a basket.
[SPEAKER_04] Although Singapore proves you can, you can operate that second system.
[SPEAKER_04] But it's, it's not only easier, but what are they importing?
[SPEAKER_04] Well, yes, it doesn't fit very well with the pattern of imports of goods where they get lots of goods from Europe.
[SPEAKER_04] But it does match well their imports of workers who come from South Asia and so on, where the, where $100 bills have a, have a particular function.
[SPEAKER_04] And at the New York Fed, I remember learning that the dollars went out, out of the East Coast Federal Reserve banks and came back in, in Los Angeles and San Francisco.
[SPEAKER_04] So the $100 bills have a kind of regular direction to them.
[SPEAKER_04] And I think a lot of that is the dollars going to the Middle East and then getting paid out to people who take them back to the Philippines or wherever.
[SPEAKER_04] And then they eventually get, get turned into, into deposits in banks and the cash comes into the, to the San Francisco Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] So I think, I think back on the Saudis, I think the, the important decision they have to make is, is, is how they orient their own, their own money.
[SPEAKER_04] And there's been no suggestion they want to change that.
[SPEAKER_04] Russia, you may know, operated a system there for a while where they were sort of half dollar and half euro, which to me technically is probably the right answer for an oil producer.
[SPEAKER_04] And, and, and whether something like Enbridge can be used to avoid the US payment system and the, and the sort of potential use of, of that payments system.
[SPEAKER_04] I, I, I don't, I don't know to tell you the truth.
[SPEAKER_04] I, I, I kind of doubt it because to me payments have a credit just, just to let people know Enbridge, I guess would be something between central banks where you could, where you could pay.
[SPEAKER_04] I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04] You could somehow move from tether like products into, into central bank money and then things would, would settle that way.
[SPEAKER_04] Um, so that's a very different, different model for payments in general.
[SPEAKER_04] We have basically banks in the business and you operate with a bank that you think will be there tomorrow and the day after.
[SPEAKER_04] Uh, so that's, that's a, that's a very, very, uh, strange.
[SPEAKER_04] And you'll, you'll have to give me the international studies quarterly piece.
[SPEAKER_04] I definitely should, should, should read that.
[SPEAKER_03] Any more comments?
[SPEAKER_03] Uh, no?
[SPEAKER_03] Yes, please.
[SPEAKER_02] VELMIR SHONJA ARCHIVA ANALYTICA.
[SPEAKER_02] Former central bank here many years ago.
[SPEAKER_02] Um, of course, uh, I thought about coalition of, uh, uh,
[SPEAKER_02] of, uh, the billing for, for, for dollar.
[SPEAKER_02] But let's, uh, talk about the, one step before that.
[SPEAKER_02] And this is your speculative scenario, either by, uh, new fat head who come, who comes May next year,
[SPEAKER_02] or some strange disbalance within FOMC.
[SPEAKER_02] Uh, can you try to imagine a scenario how you see it?
[SPEAKER_02] What would happen if they stop or substantially cut the, uh, swap lines?
[SPEAKER_02] Uh, because the, it would take a long time for that hypothetical coalition to, to organize.
[SPEAKER_02] probably it wouldn't, they wouldn't be able to organize at all.
[SPEAKER_02] But, uh, what's, uh, triggering my thoughts at the moment is those initial few weeks when we have a shock.
[SPEAKER_02] Okay?
[SPEAKER_02] For example, exchange rate.
[SPEAKER_02] Uh, could we have a kind of reverse currency crisis with, uh, very strange strengthening of the dollar, uh, instead of, uh, I'm talking about very short term, about a few days or weeks.
[SPEAKER_02] Uh, what would be your hypothetical scenario in such an event?
[SPEAKER_04] Well, you're right, of course, that it could take a long time to organize.
[SPEAKER_04] And someone made an analogy to me that it was like in the old days when you would try to have a concerted intervention in the foreign exchange market.
[SPEAKER_04] And so to get, you know, the Europeans and the Americans and the Japanese all on the same page and perhaps intervening simultaneously, uh, or, or on a kind of continuous basis around the 24 hours, you know, was, was just an incredible amount of work.
[SPEAKER_04] What somebody reminded me.
[SPEAKER_04] And, and this would have some of that character.
[SPEAKER_04] Uh, but there, there are precedents.
[SPEAKER_04] The, the Nordic central banks in 2020, uh, eventually Sweden got a swap line from, uh, the Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] But, uh, they started auctioning dollars to their banks against the Swedish Kroner credit before the Fed announced.
[SPEAKER_04] And then they never drew on, on the Fed.
[SPEAKER_04] So they were using their own resources.
[SPEAKER_04] And then they got involved in, um, sort of concerted, uh, auction where, you know, the central bank in Norway and Denmark.
[SPEAKER_04] Um, I guess that was, I guess it was, you know, they were all, so Sweden, Norway, Denmark, were all auctioning dollars, not with exactly the same procedures.
[SPEAKER_04] And clearly with different collateral, but in a, in a concerted way.
[SPEAKER_04] So it's, it's, it's not impossible.
[SPEAKER_04] Of course, there's years and years of precedent of cooperation among central banks in, in that, in that part of the world.
[SPEAKER_04] I mean, uh, on, on the side of, it ain't gonna happen, Bob, it would be, you know, why is it that Chiang Mai initiative, you know, billions and billions of agreed swap lines out in the far east
[SPEAKER_04] have never been, been used.
[SPEAKER_04] Why isn't the bank of Korea end up coming to the Fed for dollars?
[SPEAKER_04] And why didn't it, hasn't it ever, uh, gotten them from the bank of Japan or the people's bank of China?
[SPEAKER_04] I, I don't, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04] Um, but I, I think you're right.
[SPEAKER_04] And, and, and frankly, that seems to me to be a reason to be thinking about it now, or even thinking about it when you think it's very unlikely.
[SPEAKER_04] I think it's probably on balance gotten more likely.
[SPEAKER_04] Since, uh, the discussion started, I said, back in February of, of this year.
[SPEAKER_04] And I think the, the worst thing is about plausible in, in, in the meantime.
[SPEAKER_04] And, therefore, the, the value to, trying to plan for, uh, a, a still unlikely, but, uh, deeply uncoured, uh, adventure hour.
[SPEAKER_04] I think it's contingency is still, uh, still very high.
[SPEAKER_04] Yes, Lisa.
[SPEAKER_05] So I, I'm, I'm trying to understand why the potential, the danger of the Fed reducing or cutting these SWAT lives.
[SPEAKER_05] But why isn't that a self-correcting problem?
[SPEAKER_05] And the reason that they want to suppress the interest rates in these foreign dollars is, as you described it anyway, it was the controlling interest rates in the U.S.
[SPEAKER_05] So if they fail, they stop.
[SPEAKER_05] And the interest rates in the U.S. go up.
[SPEAKER_05] And then there's a big political revolution after that.
[SPEAKER_05] And won't that solve the problem without needing to go to some European consortium?
[SPEAKER_04] This question was planned.
[SPEAKER_04] That man is my brother.
[SPEAKER_04] Clark R. McCauley, a student of terrorism, a social psychologist by training, who's clearly stepped out off piece with this question.
[SPEAKER_04] No, when I argued that, that the Fed will still be concerned about the offshore dollar, even with the new benchmark that is ostensibly strictly domestic, um, I was, I was agreeing with the premise of the question.
[SPEAKER_04] That yes, eventually the Fed will have to get around to doing something.
[SPEAKER_04] But that intervention could be strictly in the, in the repo market, uh, in, domestically, uh, which wouldn't necessarily help the foreign banks all around.
[SPEAKER_04] So I, I think you're, you're right.
[SPEAKER_04] Eventually, the, the, the, the interest rates that people actually pay, starting getting out of control, the Fed would have to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_04] Uh, but I think a lot of damage could be done, um, before, before, before you get there.
[SPEAKER_04] Uh, and, and to say something is kind of self-destructive, self-correct, and, and, and foolish, is, unfortunately, not necessarily saying that it can't happen.
[SPEAKER_03] Any more questions or comments, uh, if not, uh, let me, uh, let me thank, uh, Bob, uh, McCauley-Mormley, uh, on behalf of all of us here.
[SPEAKER_03] Thank you for staying so long, which was interesting in, in the, in the topic.
[SPEAKER_03] I, I, I, I know that some of you may think we didn't get any straightforward answers, but I, I, I, I think we are clear enough.
[SPEAKER_03] Um, uh, no worries, uh, here to stay.
[SPEAKER_03] Here's my mind.
[SPEAKER_03] So thank you, Bob.
[SPEAKER_03] Uh, uh, uh, thank you so much for, uh, sharing your knowledge with us.
[SPEAKER_03] And, uh, um, to the rest, uh, of you, please, uh, come again, uh, mid, uh, November.
[SPEAKER_03] We will, uh, talk about another interesting topic in, uh, international, uh, finance.
[SPEAKER_03] Thank you.
[UNKNOWN] Thank you.