Ante,ja mislim,koliko mi se čini da je dosta,dosta dobro.Sviđa mi se atmosfera,ol tako?Sviđa mi se atmosfera.
Sviđa mi se atmosfera.
So this is a first Fireside chat.Is it?Fire what?Fireside.Fireside chat.
It is a really popular type of chat because have you heard about the Startup Grind?
Startup Grind?Startup Grind.Startup Grind.
Yeah,it's a big organization for developing of startups and entrepreneurship minded things.
Never heard about it?No.I think that...I heard about Grindr.
Grindr?What is Grindr?You don't know what Grindr is?No.That's funny.
Grindr is like the tenor for gay people.Oh my God.I was pretty sure...Do we really need to start like this?No.I was just mentioning it.Probably you knew it.I don't know.
You know what?I don't usually I don't have a format for the show.So usually I start off really open.
There is...there is a blank space in front of us and we can really put whatever paint we want on it.
We can use whatever style we want.And we just make it a fun.
Okay.But...every time I start a podcast with saying like this and after it I say...but there is some kind of a structure.
Okay.I'm confused.No?You are confused.Yeah,a lot of people are confused.
So usually I start with the question of...usually I start with the question of...whether you can say to the audience...what is your background story?
Where were you born?Can you say something about your parents, about your siblings, about the city that you were born in, your early days, your childhood?
What kind of a memory...memories do you have?What impact does this part of your life had on your life right now?
That's awesome.That's really awesome.Because you don't think about this situation a lot in your life like...I was never thinking about that since the last couple of years.
Very,very good.So...I'm born in 1986 in Osijek, which is a pretty small town in Croatia.
So...it's actually the third biggest...correct me please.
It's the fourth.The fourth biggest city in Croatia, which is kind of crazy because it's just about 100,000 people there.
And so my parents moved from Bosnia and Herzegovina because they are born in Bosnia and Herzegovina.It's in Livno.
It's pretty close to the coast of Croatia but on the Bosnian side but mostly populated by Croatians overall, which is pretty interesting.
And they moved in the 80s, they moved to Osijek and yeah, that's the city where I was born.
And I think...I'm always thinking about this city because I left this city when I was five years old.
I mean, I met there a lot of great people and most of my family also lives there.
My cousins, my uncles and aunts and so on.
And so it was for me also kind of hard to leave this place.
So we left during the war in '92.
We left to Germany, to Munich actually because my father, my dad worked in Germany as a "gastarbeiter".
For the people that doesn't know, for the people that doesn't know what this term means.
A "gastarbeiter", it's a "guest worker".
So it's kind of, you know, you're working on a...how is it called? Baustelle?
Baustelle?
Yeah.
I don't know.
What was it?
Mostly he was working for the sub-train in Germany, for the sub-trains.
Metro?
Metro, yes.
Okay.
In Germany.
So there was kind of also a lot of interesting stories.
So he also cut his finger.
That's one of his most famous characteristics from my dad.
Yeah, so he worked there since the 70s and then during the war he just told the whole family,
"Okay, we will move now to Germany, to Munich."
And so we moved.
And that was kind of a crazy, crazy experience.
People don't know how we lived in our first years in Munich.
So we lived together with the family, with the brother from my father, with his family together
in a...wow...let's say it was 10 or 15 square meters apartment.
In Nossack?
No, no.
In Munich.
Oh.
Yeah, for about one or two years.
So we lived...we've been, I don't know, probably 10, 12 people in this small room for one year.
So this was really the first moments when you arrived there?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah.
The first...first year.
Let's say the first two years, I would say.
So I think in the second year we moved to...in between the house, like just one floor underneath.
But actually we've been also six people in a 15 square meter apartment.
It was.
Crazy.
Just something completely unbelievable.
I mean, I was also five years old and my whole center of my life was in Ossiek until this point.
I had friends, I had family and so on and they just moved me out of this center of my life.
And it was, yeah, well, very interesting, very hard in the beginning.
So, as I said, my dad worked a lot, like crazy, crazy as fuck.
And, yeah, just making money for the family because I have one, two, three siblings.
There's a story probably, I don't know, probably we can talk about that later.
So we are not anymore three siblings.
Four, excuse me.
So we're now just three, which also hit our family actually very hard.
Yeah, so that was what my dad was working and my mother, well, she was cleaning a lot.
And that's a lot of families and companies and, yeah, from six in the morning to eight in the evening.
And they also had four children to feed their stomachs in between, so…
Not an easy task to do, man.
It was tough.
Not an easy task.
So why you moved to… I'm just asking this question, I know the answer, but it is funny for me to interview someone that I really, really know really good.
It's funny for me, but it is also refreshing somehow.
So for the audience that doesn't know you, Ante is my cousin.
And he's one of my favorite people on planet Earth.
I don't know anyone on planet Mars, but…
So not on Mars.
He is one of the most popular for me, in my eyes.
And what was the question?
I asked you, why did you move from Osik when you were five years old?
It was because of the Yugoslavian war in the 90s.
So I think my dad was very afraid about his family.
And he just saw the chance to move the family from Croatia to Germany into a safety, a very safe place.
And Germany at that time opened their doors for immigrants at that time, at that point.
And so we moved.
I still can remember some scenes, some things happening at that time.
So when we played in Croatia on the street, like where our house was, that we played soccer on the street and we were just starting like the alarm, like…
Yeah.
Or no.
How was it?
It was…
It was like…
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
It was.
It was not like an emergency.
And then you heard like people are shooting like…
And we're just running into the house.
Yeah.
And some very bad things happened at that time.
Those times were really, really tough.
Really tough times.
We were kids when those things were happening.
Yeah.
I was around six.
So the war started in 1991.
I was six then.
You were five.
And it is really hard for us to make a vivid picture of it.
To make a vivid picture of it.
But for sure I can remember those feelings.
Yes.
I can remember those moments.
Fear.
Yes.
I can remember the fear.
Yeah.
It's probably also something that people don't understand.
Probably we don't understand it either, right?
What we have like…
I mean, it was real, right?
It was dangerous.
It was not fear.
Yeah.
It was real, real danger.
Real danger.
Like people are shooting people two kilometers away from where we live.
Like…
Wow.
That's interesting.
That's really crazy.
Yeah.
I'm thinking now like 25 years ago.
Is it 20…
Yeah.
Something around that.
25…
27 years ago.
Yeah.
When the war started.
27.
Oh fuck.
We are old.
Oh yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah.
In the best years.
But…
Oh my God.
When you think about it, if the war starts right now, when two of us are in our thirties,
in our early thirties…
Yeah.
If it starts right now, to be a completely different experience, to be… I don't know.
I suppose that it left some kind of impact on us subconsciously that we are not really aware
of it maybe.
Yeah.
But I think that something could be there.
Sure.
Something could be there.
Yeah.
So, you moved… Did your whole family moved when you were five or four?
Did your…
Yeah.
Most of them, I think.
I can't remember.
I was very young.
What I can remember is that my sister stayed in Croatia.
She moved at some time, at some point.
She was also in Germany.
But she stayed, which was kind of crazy also for my parents.
But, yeah.
But let's say the whole family moved, yeah.
Yeah.
You know, when I think about the product that we are, when I think about the product that
you are right now, mentally, emotionally, I always think of those early days.
I always think of parenting.
I always think of the environment and the experiences that really… that we were… that
we dive in… that we are tagged in since this early age.
So, you said you were born in Osijek and your parents moved from Bosnia to Osijek for a better life.
And then the war starts.
And then you moved all together in Germany, where you live in a small apartment, almost 12…
Was it 12 of you in the beginning?
Something around that, yeah.
And your parents are working really, really tough jobs, blue-collar type jobs to really…
Just to stay alive.
Just to sit… just to stay alive.
To have bread and water at home and…
And what kind of a… so if you think about the context of the story or about the environment,
about everything that was happening around you and what kind of an impact do you think that this left on you?
The whole situation at the time you mean?
The whole situation, the struggle.
The struggle at the beginning when we moved to Germany.
Well, now I would say, huh, at that time it was hard to describe how hard it was.
Now I'm very grateful for that time because one thing I know that I'm now a lot, lot tougher because I know the…
How do you explain it?
The best is…
The value?
To have nothing.
I know how it…
How it feels.
How it feels to have nothing and to fight to gain something.
Yeah.
And that's… that's an experience I'm very, very proud and very grateful to have that.
It's… it groans me always.
If I'm going too far in my mind and everything with my experience with my… whatever I'm doing in my life and I'm going too far, I know…
I just know how it is and I know how to fight and how much I need to fight.
You know, you said to me that you have some kind of a drive inside of… inside of you to really help other people.
And I always think to myself, why do we cling to someone… something in life?
Why do we wanna do some particular thing?
And right now when you are speaking about this, I see that for me that the person that is most empathetic is… is the… is the person that struggled the most.
That felt the struggle that was going on through some hardships, some hard times.
And he can really… he can really reverse it and he can put himself in the… in the shoes of other person.
Yes.
Absolutely.
And really feel his pain.
Sure.
Because, I mean, the pain you're feeling like inside of you… you don't want that other people are feeling like this.
You know what I mean?
So, it's for me hard that… that somebody… that somebody should make the same experience as we or as I, me personally, did.
And I want to avoid it for other people.
You want to free them from that pain.
Yes.
It is… it is really interesting that… we humans, we always try to avoid pain.
But then, after the pain passed, we always say to… to ourselves, I'm the most proud of that moment because I survived.
Yeah.
I survived and I learned.
So, I'm much tougher.
Very… okay.
Why… why do we want to help others to avoid pain?
You see, in this… in… in… in all interviews so far, I asked… I asked my guests the questions of parenting.
So, this is a… this is a right moment to ask that question.
You know, those experiences and your parents really tried their best in… in given circumstances.
They really tried best.
And a lot of parents today, they really… they really try to… to do the thing that… that you said right now that you wanna… do.
You wanna help others to be free of pain, to be free of struggle.
But if you put someone in incubator, then there is no growth there.
Hmm.
They cannot grow as a people.
So, what do you think about… about that?
Isn't that a right balance?
Like… you know, there is this… I think we say that in… say that in… in… in… in… in Croatian that…
Um… stupid people… learn… from their own mistakes.
And, uh… intelligent people, uh… learn from, uh… the mistakes, uh… from the others.
Right?
From others, yeah.
Um… so, I think it's… it's… it's kind of a good balance.
I… I know the points, uh… I know what you want to point out.
But, uh… I think we live here to help always each other to make the best.
Um… or to avoid mistakes or to help each other in, uh… you know, moving forward to avoid mistakes and so on and so on.
Um… but I think in that point you are absolutely right that people need to do mistakes to… to grow.
As I said, to just let people doing mistakes is just… you know, they would just do mistakes.
Well, then why are people writing books and making vlogs and podcasts and so on and so on.
So, what's the point of that?
Right?
Uh… or why do big companies exist because they are solving a lot of problems.
So, you know, they're helping me to avoid doing mistakes.
So, why do I have today email and so on like…
There is also the… the right…
Or autocorrect or autocorrect on the keyboard, you know…
I hate that.
Autocorrect.
It always corrects the wrong for me.
It always corrects you because you're always wrong.
He's correcting me.
I don't like to be corrected at all.
So, yeah… you know… but there is… excuse me…
Um… well, as you know me, then I'm a very pretty religious and then spiritual person.
Um… and, um… that I have some crazy… crazy beliefs.
So, people thinking, you know… play crazy because I believe in Jesus.
And, uh… but there is, uh… for me, a very, very… a lot of philosophy… philosophical… uh… outcome from… from that whole story.
And the Bible and so on.
Um… and there is always the one thing that through pain… to freedom.
It's always the same, same, same story.
It's just repeated from… from the Old Testament to the New Testament to the… what's called… the resurrection…
Uh… of… of Jesus and so on.
So, it's always true pain to freedom.
True pain to freedom.
It's kind of something, um… that's kind of a rule in this world.
How it's built.
That we always need to suffer to, uh… to get, uh… to get free.
Which is pretty interesting.
And one thing is always… as you said, isn't it… is it good or is it bad to avoid it?
I would say.
I think it's, you know, accepted that it's worked that way.
Um…
That you need to suffer.
Accept it.
Accept it as something positive, as… as something good.
Which is when I was… well… as you know, I was kind of this Catholic guy and so on.
But… but… I lost completely my… my… my beliefs, my faith and my religion and so on.
And when I turned around at some point in my life, uh… and, uh… you know, was reading, uh… this whole Bible through it.
And I think one of… one of my best takeaways is… accept the suffer.
Because it will make you free.
It will set you free.
And since then my state of mind based on suffering is like, you know… awesome.
I'm grateful to suffer right now.
You know, it just changes my perspective on suffering completely.
Like, crazy. Crazy.
Well, I'm not happy if I suffer.
I'm not happy but… I'm like… calm down, it's okay.
Just… just… just go to the process, you know.
And if it's done, you will be much better than you was before.
Awesome.
Hmm.
Yeah.
I guess that, uh… we need to find the right balance there.
If the balance, uh… exists in… in this… in this spectrum of… of pain and pleasure.
I don't know.
Someone is really, uh… I… I suppose unlucky to have pain most of the time and then some pleasure.
But if you think about it, if someone has pleasure 80-90% of the time and a little bit of pain, or maybe if someone had 100% of pleasure all the time, then I think that…
this will not be a good state for… for us.
Mm-hmm.
Just like, uh… one author said that… that I was reading his book, uh… about… he said that, um…
uh… first two, uh… needs of a human is certainty and uncertainty.
So it is pleasure and pain.
Mm-hmm.
We are… there is a real paradox here because we want certainty, want too much of a certainty, it's not good anymore.
We want uncertainty.
Yeah.
We want variety.
Okay.
We are really, really complex.
We… we… yeah, we are very complex and, uh… we… we talked about that yesterday.
Uh… also to… to refer to the Bible again, uh… is, uh… what I was talking yesterday to you.
You know, that the beginning of the whole… of our sufferer story as it… is written in the Bible.
Um… is that they eat it from that, uh… from the tree of the wisdom between good and bad.
And that's my personal point.
That I don't want to, uh… to judge about what is good or bad.
So… when you say suffering is good for us.
You… you told us, right?
So…
Yep.
Why do I judge that suffering is bad if it's not?
It hurts.
It's not like joy.
Sure.
But it's good.
Yeah.
And I don't want to judge that.
Right?
Yeah.
I want to, in the best case, I want to judge it as something… as something good.
And this is what we people are doing, so… uh… yeah.
All the time.
So this is also something which is for me very, very interesting that one of the first written
things ever is that the biggest mistake people are doing is, um… you know, judging between
good, good and bad, which is… creates the most evil things in the world.
So let's move a little bit to…
That's the…
It is.
I…
I knew that we're going to go really…
That deep, that…
That…
Deep and philosophical about it.
Yeah.
But what I'm really, uh… surprised about… I'm not surprised, but a little bit.
Uh… that, uh… you know, we spent four, three, three days here together in Berlin.
And we really covered a lot of topics.
Mm-hmm.
As always.
And going…
Really, really big, uh… philosophical on it.
Mm-hmm.
And we still have, uh… things to cover, which is really interesting.
Which is really interesting.
Yeah.
So let's… let's move a little bit, uh… further in your story.
So, uh… your whole family moved, but your sister stayed in Osijak.
And then, there… there you are.
Uh… so it was five of you.
Uh… your brother and your sister and your parents are… you went to Munich.
Mm-hmm.
And you really struggled there.
You lived in a small apartment for a few years.
Mm-hmm.
And, uh… then, really, your parents worked, uh… really tough, blue-collar jobs.
And you and your siblings…
We helped them.
Yes.
You helped them.
And can you… can you go in… in the story a little bit further?
When you started to go to… to… to school?
How was it?
Uh… would you, uh… did… did you have, uh… I don't know, problems of being accepted
there or really being understood?
Yeah.
Uh… did you help your parents really, uh… go… go by day in and day out and…
Mm-hmm.
Just… just tell the audience a little bit more about it.
Yeah.
Well… our parents… so my parents, uh… were… as you said… said, uh… all those blue-collar
jobs and… you know, they were cleaning, uh… like, uh… what it's called from a doctor,
the place…
I don't know.
It's okay.
His office, whatever.
A lot of offices, uh… we cleaned the house where we were living, uh… and stuff like
that and, uh… so when I was going, uh… to school and after the school, we… we shouldn't
help, uh… our parents at some places, you know, go to some offices and cleaning those offices,
you know, like cleaning the garbage, which was actually my job or, uh… it's called, uh…
Shoveling.
Oh, yeah.
Shoveling and, uh… whatever.
Stuff, stuff, stuff like that.
Oh, cleaning the floors.
Yeah, cleaning the floors, um… and so on.
Uh… and, uh… yeah, it was, you know, uh… also a language gap, uh… you have the first
years.
It's also losing your identity, you know, uh… you're also a foreigner.
You're immigrant.
You're not that accepted, uh… at the first moment, uh… from, from all people.
Uh… which was also pretty, pretty interesting.
Um… then… which was… we had probably also one point when we moved from that first apartment
to another apartment, which was also Munich.
And, you know, Munich is a pretty snobby place.
And there have been some, you know, the new place was in a pretty snobby area of Munich.
Which was, uh… kind of interesting.
And, you know, people always had more than we had.
And it was, for me, you know, like… why do they have more than we?
And why can we have that, you know?
It was… you know, you're a child, you don't think about things and, you know, we've
been pretty… I mean, from the perspective of my parents, we've been rich.
Okay.
Like, really rich.
But from, uh… you know, our perspective, our parents are telling us always, we had everything,
you know.
But I know that we didn't have everything, you know.
And, uh… yeah.
And that was, that was, uh… very, very interesting.
So… and, you know, people are judging you.
Uh… kids are very, very bad.
Right?
Because they're very honest.
Yeah.
And it could be very hurtful.
And I had also a lot of hurtful experiences, uh… in that point, you know.
And, uh… yeah.
You're right.
So, uh… you're not that accepted, right?
As you want to be accepted, right?
As you want to be accepted.
And, uh… you don't look that cool and that good as other people do, you know.
Wearing these cool brands, uh… always.
And, uh… at our time was actually FUBU, South Pole and Buffalo shoes and whatever.
It's so ugly, it's unbelievable.
And we didn't have that, you know.
We were just wearing completely different brands, which was not so cool, you know.
And you were judged by those people and hurted by those people.
And with their, uh… with their mouth and with, uh… you know, yell… not yelling at you, but, you know…
Yeah.
Making fun of you.
A lot of fun of you.
Bullying.
And, uh… they were fighting you also, you know.
Because…
They were fights also, yeah.
Right.
So, I think that a lot of people enjoy speaking about their childhood, uh… because, uh…
I… I don't know if we think about it that often, but… but… it can bring some…
I hate it.
Good…
Good and bad memories.
I don't like…
I don't like to talk about bad porn at all.
Really?
I just want to forget it.
Yeah.
Uh… for me personally, yeah, I think my parents would shoot me if they hear this.
But, honestly, I… I don't have a good childhood.
Hmm.
Could you think about, uh… something that was good from… from the childhood?
Some memories that were really nice?
Hard.
Hard, really.
When you… when you, uh… came back to Osijek to… to visit your family…
That was good, actually.
Was it?
Right, right.
I was coming… coming back to Osijek and also coming back to leave now and to see the
family and then… and actually you're also your friends like your real friends because,
you know, you're a Croatian and you live with this mentality, uh… and with this culture
inside of you and you can live that in Germany like this, right?
Uh…
Yeah, that was good.
That was great.
Yeah, that was a great experience.
Uh…
Yeah.
Tell me… so when we were speaking about your childhood in these early days, uh… could
you tell me maybe, uh… could you tell me what was your relationship with school then?
So what was your relationship with education then?
And we will see what kind of a relationship with education do you have right now?
It was something, uh… I have to do.
It wasn't a choice.
Who said that?
Me!
Your parents?
Your father?
Yes, sir.
Of course.
There wasn't a choice.
To do it.
And I did it.
And, uh… that was also my… my performance.
So poor performance in school, huh?
Well, I was…
It wasn't poor, but it wasn't good.
So erase the whole childhood.
Yeah, it was hard.
Yeah.
Okay, it was hard.
But right now, looking back on everything that you really went through, uh… what are
the biggest takeaways, uh… what are the biggest lessons from this part of your life?
Um… that I really need to be tough.
Really.
Like, really.
Um… you need to understand that my parents were always working.
And then they were tired.
You know, they didn't play with me.
And taking time and going swimming or up to a sea or like skiing or whatever.
They were just fucking tired.
Yeah.
All the time.
You know, and… when I'm thinking about that time and judging my parents at that time,
I was a fucking asshole because I didn't understand it.
But now it's just like, wow, yeah, sure, of course.
It just makes absolutely sense how they live.
And that's how you've been also treated, you know.
I mean, I'm so lucky because they pushed us always to the limits also in school.
It was never enough, you know.
If you were good at school that there was a… you know, you could be better.
And also, I came back and I was like, wow, look, I have a great note.
And I was like, no, why don't you have a plus, you know, or a star or whatever.
And I'm like…
It's arriving for progress.
Yeah.
And always working, working, like working hard and working hard and working hard and working
hard and working hard.
So, that was my childhood.
This is also how I started to work, you know.
I helped my parents and… yeah.
Yeah, but what is really important to you…
Life is tough.
That's the outcome.
That's like the takeaway.
And I'm pretty, pretty happy to not live in a family like in a wealthy family.
And so, this is probably or could have been a point where I don't know how it is to,
you know, working hard for the things you want to achieve.
I think this is something for wealthy families or children growing up in wealthy families,
which is what's the opposite of benefit, which is…
Yeah.
And I think that you really learned the benefits of the hard work.
Because you could really, you could really take advantage of it right now in your career.
So, whenever I was… whenever I think of you, whenever I speak to someone about you,
I always tell them… one key point that I want to tell them is…
Oh my God.
I was always so jealous of him because when he was 11 years old,
he already knew what he wanted to do in life.
So, he fell in love with the design when he was 11 years old.
He started studying about it, reading books about it and really educating himself about it.
And it's a big privilege, it's a big fucking privilege to find your calling that early in life.
So, it is a… it is, like I say, it is… you found… you found your element, you find your strength,
the thing that you can really shine in and be of a greater service to the community around you.
And do you know how this happened?
Could you maybe give a tip, advice to someone listening right now?
How this… how this came about?
How… how did you know that this is your thing?
Yeah, as you said, it's a… it's a privilege and for me it's… it's a blessing, it's a gift.
You know, I received… it's something I didn't choose, honestly.
It was… actually, it was just… there.
I think it starts… because I'm questioning a lot.
Like, this is what I do, this is how my brain works.
I don't know how to live different than to question everything.
And… the question everything is… so, to be very… it's called that…
Znati želen?
Curious.
Yeah, very curious.
And… when I was… I still can… can… really remember those… those points in my life.
It was… I was six or seven years old.
Really, I mean, I can… probably 99% not remember what happened at that time.
But there was this… this… this moment when I was… sketching myself.
Okay.
With a beard.
It's fascinating, right?
Because you know me, that I'm a guy who's wearing a beard.
Yeah.
Now it's very short.
But in my… whatever.
And… I can't remember this.
So, I can remember that I was… that I was sketching and that… that… I was like… this fascination to creativity was like… born inside of me.
And I started to… questioning objects.
Like… how they… effect… and what's the effect of this… like… object like… from this orange juice.
Or why is Fanta like… or Coke… why they're designing their bottles… how they do, right?
Why is this… flyer looking like this?
And… that happened… like… really… when I was 8, 9, or 10 years.
That was very, very crazy.
And this is something, you know… I was so… so curious about those things.
Like… why is this orange?
Why is this like… in this material?
Why does that work that way?
And so on… and so on… and so on… and my mother told me… a few years ago… probably… three… three or four years ago… she told me…
"Wow, Ante, you know what?"
So… we had to see… the whole family was… like… in the same room.
And she was like… oh… you was… just annoying child.
Just an annoying child.
It was crazy because you asked so much questions.
And I… I… I… I couldn't answer all of those things because I didn't know that, you know…
But you… you… you asked everything.
Why is this like that?
And… this is the most… for me… the most…
the most important question is always this.
Why?
Until there is no why, there is the answer.
Right?
There is the solution.
A lot of the why's before…
Because… if there is no why, there is the answer.
There is like the core of the thing and the thing you do.
And this is for me so… so unbelievable, fascinating.
This is like my whole excitement, like my whole passion is like… just to answer.
it.
And… how do I express it is the true design.
So… if we are… if we are thinking in terms of… Simon Sinek's… what is your why?
Could you tell?
My why?
Yeah.
Designing people happy.
Ah, cool.
Yeah.
That's my…
Cool.
Yeah.
This is… this is… this is actually my personal message.
This is how I work and what… what my goal is.
is… what… what I want to achieve with the thing I do is really to… in the end…
It sounds pretty pathetic like… oh, maybe creating or designing people happy or making
people happy.
But in the end it's like the… the goal you… like the ultimate goal you can achieve with
and through design and design has the power to do it.
So, design… probably very important to know.
We are not talking about physical products and mostly digital products.
and… yeah, so… it's called user experience design, user interface design and so on.
So, I know that… it would be really, really hard to explain to your mother what you do for
work then.
Mm-hmm.
But… could you explain to the people listening maybe?
So, can you pinpoint and you… can you go a little bit more narrow and say to… to the
what is it that you do every single day?
Um… so… very, very easy to explain is that I am a product designer for digital products.
So, a digital product designer actually.
What does that mean?
First of all, it means that I need to understand people, how they think and how they use things.
Um… then I need to set the whole logic, like the whole usability, how people will use
this product.
Where to place, you know, a button, a menu bar, an image, a text and so on.
So, this needs a lot of work to figure that out.
Clicking, tapping past and so on.
And, uh… in the end, um… you need to give that a kind of a face, like a design, uh… which
you're putting on, like, uh… with… fill it up with colors and forms and uh… stuff like
that.
So, that it… yeah… becomes a design and being usable.
It sounds super simple.
Right.
It is, actually.
But… well…
Doesn't it?
Yeah.
We talked about it yesterday that, uh… to me, your work looked, uh, really measurable
and really objective, but you really made a clear statement to me that it is a really,
really subjective thing to do because…
It's most subjective.
Because you are… you are doing a service to the… to your clients and, uh… it is on… based
on their opinions, uh… they feel something is right or wrong for them.
Mm-hmm.
Something is fit or unfit for them.
And your job is to do a really, really great work.
Mm-hmm.
And really, uh, also, uh, make sure that the… that the client is on the same… on the same
page as you.
So, you need to…
Convince them.
Convince them that this is… my job is to convince people.
That…
That's…
That's what I do.
95%.
You gotta be the… the person that is more certain.
Yeah.
I just, you know, I'm working… if I'm working on a project with, I don't know,
10, 15, 20 people from, uh, several departments.
Mm-hmm.
Um…
Everybody has… has an opinion and everybody is just pointing at you, right?
And judging your design and judging your judgment.
Mm-hmm.
And, uh, stuff like that.
And this is really, really, really hard, you know.
And then you're not in the position to say, no, you're wrong, you're wrong.
It's just like, okay, you're right.
I will take that with me and I will think about it and I will share my decision tomorrow with
you.
Mm-hmm.
Kind of, uh, this, uh, this way.
Because people, everybody, mostly, uh, I'm pretty sure that nine of 10 people would say,
I'm creative.
You know, I'm a creative person because nobody will.
We say, oh, no, I wouldn't say that I'm not creative.
I know those persons.
Mm-hmm.
Tell them this.
And, uh, this is one of the main problems we have.
Yeah.
But it's not like also people, uh, saying that I'm a creative person.
They're also, as in every other business, a lot of political bullshit.
Yeah.
So, uh, you said that you started to, to play with it really, really early when you were
really young, young boy.
Eleven.
Eleven?
And, uh, can you maybe tell us, uh, so how the story really developed?
Učinušiši o to, učinušiši slo, učinušiši slo.
Učinušišiš projekci...
-O ne, učinušiši Kromunik i stvari. -Kromunik, tako.
Oooo!
Pogledajte s njegovima veđanje.
Pogledajte za svojno sviđočenje.
Sviđe svojno sviđočenja.
Sviđočenje i sviđočenje.
Sviđočenje.