Jeff Gotlieb:
Okay. Hello everyone. My name is Jeff Gotlieb. I'm with the International Monetary Fund.
I'm the IMF's res rep for Central and Eastern Europe, based in Warsaw, and I cover Central and Eastern Europe out of Warsaw.
It's great to be here, and thank you very much to the Croatian National Bank for the invitation.
The only thing more amazing than the beauty of Dubrovnik is how much of Croatia actually looks like this.
It's really not a one-stop, one-trick pony, and it's a good reason to keep Croatians close to you in life.
It's really great to be here, and I think labor is an excellent time to discuss the labor issue.
As many of you know, there were two main ways that much of the profession got the inflation thing wrong.
The first one was to not expect inflation to be such a problem in the first place.
The second one was that even if you did think that there was too much demand and it was going to come to inflation,
many people thought that it would come through wages and tension in the labor market, not through goods, which is what we've seen.
So thus far, the labor market has not been the key player in the inflation process, but now it seems like things are turning.
So the initial shock has started to fade in terms of the components.
The labor market is still very tight.
Core inflation is very high.
So when I talk to policymakers, most of them seem to agree that to the degree they get inflation wrong going forward,
it might be because they're misestimating what is happening in the labor market.
So just to frame the discussion for my colleagues here today, I'll just briefly touch on three questions.
Where are we now and why?
Where are we going?
And what should policymakers do about it?
So on the first, when we talk about labor market resilience, we're usually talking about the quantity side, basically employment.
And there's two parts of this story.
The first is the vacancy unemployment story, where we basically saw a shift up in the beverage curve.
People have different reasons for this, from matching to people leaving the labor force.
But this is the key reason that people think the unemployment rate understates the true tightness in the labor market.
The second, which is a bit less discussed, is that employment growth is actually positive in many of the major and emerging market economies.
So it's not a story where employment is falling, but slowly, or employment is steady and there's hoarding.
We have a situation where even with falling output, we have firms adding employees.
So you see a fall in labor productivity.
You can come up with a variety of stories for this, but labor productivity growth in many countries is negative,
depending exactly on how you measure it.
So well below trend, and surprisingly so.
It can't be sustained.
Either you would expect output to start to recover, or employment to fall.
But now moving on to the price side, wages.
Wages, as I said, have not been a big player.
You wouldn't describe them as wildly resilient.
So as many people have cited, in advanced economies, real wages are negative.
In emerging markets, they're a bit closer to even, but they have turned negative in the last two quarters.
And so you have an inflation process where, consistent with maybe what you would expect, prices have been far more flexible than wages.
So if you decompose inflation thus far, you see a big increase in imported prices.
You see a big increase in markups by firms, and that has led to the inflation, while real wages have remained negative to flat, resulting in high corporate profits.
So again, this resilience story, I think one needs to separate.
And depending on the country, in some cases the employment story I talked about has overwhelmed the negative real wage story, keeping demand overall strong.
But again, I think it's important to separate these two, and I'll come back to that on the policy recommendation side.
Okay, the second part is where we go from here.
And there's kind of two broad stories.
There's a benign scenario, which is where this vacancy unemployment rate issue solves itself, in kind of a soft landing respect.
Which is basically that, rather than the vacancy unemployment ratio reflecting a deep matching problem, that might need a big increase in unemployment to solve.
You basically have people come back to the labor force, and vacancies come down, without a rise in the unemployment rate.
And so you get less concerned about the tightness of the labor market.
The second component is that you do get some increase in unemployment.
So basically, you have weaker pricing power by firms consistent with the slowing economy.
You get rising real wages.
These two components drive profits down.
And eventually, you see some uptick in unemployment.
So if you got these two components, basically a fall in the vacancy unemployment ratio, some increase in unemployment because of the slowing economy and profit margins.
Combined with no new shocks, that would be an environment in which I think we would all feel more comfortable about the inflation pressures.
But then there's also a significantly -- there's a less benign scenario, basically.
I mean, one is that our star, to reference the previous presentation, is different from where we thought.
So monetary policy is not as tight as we thought.
The credit cycle turns.
Pricing power is weaker than what we thought.
Basically, profits stay somewhat high, and you're able to pass on higher prices, and inflation stays much stronger.
At the same time, perhaps, we're exposed to new shocks.
And it's -- there's obviously other scenarios, but these are kind of a benign and a much less benign scenario for where we go from here.
But I think there's -- there's lots of questions in between those two scenarios.
So just one last comment on -- in terms of what this all means for policymakers.
I think outside of the profession and conferences like this, the framing about the labor market is not about resilience.
So in the newspaper, it would be framed far more negatively.
It would be framed as a cost of living crisis, combined with extremely high corporate profits.
And I think that this angle, rather than the more positive angle of labor market resilience, is very important to consider for two reasons.
One, on its own front, I think we need to be aware of the distributional consequences.
There is the temporary issues of cost of living, and there's the more structural issue of the labor share of income.
And I think that this is a fair angle that policymakers should be considering.
The second is a bit more pernicious, which is that -- and I've had this in conversations with policymakers so far -- it's possible to take that diagnosis and get to policies that, at least we would think, are far more dangerous.
Which is that the angle can be put that this is not something for monetary policy to do, but it's something for finance ministries and regulators to attack profits directly.
And this can lead to consequences that ultimately don't address the underlying inflation problem while still compromising the fiscal.
So we can maybe come back to some of those issues, but I think that this framing, both the macroeconomic, how much tightness do we need to address the inflation problem,
and the more distributional issue of how we make sure that labor is supported over the course of this crisis, is important to consider.
So I will stop there and pass to our first speaker, Christian Kopp.
Christian Kopp: Yes, thanks very much.
Great honor to be invited again to Dubrovnik.
So I have -- I'm going to follow the agenda that Joff laid out, and start out with where are we now, and then have three thoughts on where we're going,
and then maybe just one thought on what to do.
So where are we now?
I think the resilience of the labor market, first thought, has something to do with the strength of the service economy.
And you can see that here in the picture from the beautiful dinner we had last night.
That is one of the reasons why we have such a resilient and strong labor market.
Now, in the short run, it is true that the labor market is surprisingly strong.
We just heard in the previous presentation that we had a 200 basis point shock to real interest rates in most advanced economies.
And I think most in the room, including myself, would not have expected such a resilient labor market in the face of that up drift in real interest rates.
So we have in the U.S. an unemployment rate of 3.4 percent, which is the lowest level since 1969.
And in the Euro area, we have an unemployment rate of 8.5 percent, which is the lowest level on record.
Even if you go back to the pre-Euro area period, we haven't had an 8.5 percent unemployment rate, I believe, probably since the 1950s or '60s.
So it's a very resilient labor market.
And if you look at the U.S., the early indicators on the labor market are not really pointing to a rapid decline in employment growth.
We still have a lot of job openings, a lot of positions which companies are unable to fill.
So then on the short run, two more thoughts.
I think there is an element of labor hoarding, especially in the United States.
So what I'm plotting here is the change in the private sector employment and the final sales to domestic consumers in constant prices.
And you can see that the growth rate of the final sales to domestic consumers is much higher than the employment growth on trend.
And that is indicative of labor productivity growth.
But you don't have that since the pandemic.
So index that back to December 2019.
We can see that both time series are growing to the same extent.
So that could be indicative of labor hoarding because, you know, I'd be surprised if productivity growth had suddenly fallen to zero.
So I think that there is an element here of U.S. companies being unable to find the workers they need in the market.
And therefore they are deciding to hold on to those workers because they feel that they were not able to find them again if they fire them now.
Now that may at one point in time unravel.
And there is a risk that if we do see a continuation of very weak domestic sales growth in the U.S.
At one point in time, all of those U.S. companies at the same time start to, you know, fire people.
And then that could backfire.
But for the time being, there is some labor hoarding here.
And I hope that the economy will recover and companies can hold on to the people they have.
Now for the euro area, I don't think that we have an overheating labor market.
These are two charts that I borrowed from Robin Brooks at the IAF.
And you can see on the left-hand side the changes in core prices versus the changes in wages.
And you can see that in most countries wage inflation is lower than core inflation in the euro area with the exception of Belgium and Greece for whatever reason.
So we really don't have a wage price spiral here.
I think core inflation in the euro area is driven by other factors, probably by profit inflation, but not so much by wage inflation.
And then another reason why I don't really think that we're facing an overheating EU labor market has to do with the labor force participation rates.
And you can see that the employment to population ratio in most countries in the euro area is still below the previous peak, which was achieved in 2007.
So I don't really think that we have an overheating labor market here, with a few exceptions.
Maybe in Germany we have an element of that.
But most other countries still have scope to increase the employment ratios.
Now that's the short run.
And the long run, here I would like to borrow an analysis that Daniel Gross has just presented, has just published.
And that looks at the structural changes in the labor force participation rate.
And what Daniel has done here, he's here in the room, and he'll speak later on.
What Daniel has done here is he has attributed or he has related those changes in employment to changes in the education level.
And it turns out that population cohorts with high levels of inflation tend to have a high level of education.
And the increase in the educational achievement levels can explain around two-thirds of the increase in the EU labor force participation rate.
So I think that the increase in employment, basically, you know, it's not that we had a lot of idle people before, especially women who were not part of the labor market.
But what we're talking about here is labor market.
So once you enter into, you know, into the division of labor, into formal employment, you need to have some form of specialization.
If you do reproductive work at home, you're not idle.
You do a lot of different things, you know, childcare, looking after whatever, you know, things in the household.
But in order to become part of the formal labor market, I think you need some form of formal education in order to be able to contribute to this division of labor.
And we see that the levels of formal education are rising rapidly in the EU area.
And the consequence of that, we also see an increase in the employment to population ratio.
So the longer run trend of the resilience of the labor market has to do with the fact that with the increase in education levels,
with the participation in the labor market increases on trend.
And that, I think, is something that will continue.
The second point is related to the fact that we face very different patterns in different countries.
So I've picked out three countries here, Hungary, Czech Republic, and Germany.
And you can see that each one of those countries has very different patterns.
You know, in Hungary and in the Czech Republic, we had a decline in employment in the years,
following, you know, the end of communism because of the economic transformation.
And that, in the beginning, led to negative employment and growth.
What also happened is that in Hungary, at least, we had negative employment growth --
sorry, negative labor force growth because we had a lot of outbound migration from Hungary.
Now, Czech Republic is one of the countries that stands out for not having had that outbound migration.
But I think in most CE countries -- I'll show that in the following slide -- we had that outbound migration,
which is a big contributor to the tightness in the labor market.
And then from 2000 -- you know, I suppose from 2010 onwards, we've had this rapid increase in employment in all Central European countries,
which to some extent was export-driven, you know, so you have a very rapid increase there.
And that now leads to a situation where we have relatively tight labor markets in Central and Eastern Europe and the need to attract an inflow of migrant workers,
which is something that we discussed here yesterday and which leads to problems in many of those countries.
Now, Poland has had it easier.
They've been able to attract people from Ukraine and Belarus even before the crisis.
Other countries, such as Hungary, are having a tougher time increasing the labor force.
And that has to do with some of the things we discussed -- which Joel Mocker discussed here yesterday,
that he said phenotypical differences can lead to -- how did he put it -- there was a word that he used.
It was not racism, yeah, but it was -- homophilia.
Homophilia was the word.
Yeah, exactly.
So I think some of the countries find it difficult to attract and to, you know, integrate foreign workers.
And Hungary is a case in point.
And as a result of that, you have a very tight labor market in some of those countries.
Other countries have been more open to migrant flows, and that has helped to mitigate the tightness in the labor market.
Now, in Germany, you see a very strong rise in employment from 2005 onwards.
And that was not related to migration.
It was not related to economic transformation, but to a policy change.
The HALS reforms were implemented in September 2003.
And then from 2005 onwards, we've seen a rapid increase in employment because unemployment benefits were cut dramatically.
by the German government, and that, you know, that contributed to this decline in the unemployment rate and also the rise in employment.
So I think that, you know, the resilience of the labor market is a global phenomenon.
Most of it can be attributed in advanced economies by structural changes, such as the increase in education achievements.
And then within the individual countries, you have a lot of diversity, and the diversity is related to policy changes, such as, you know, labor market reforms.
And also to, you know, the attitude towards migrant workers, which really differs from country to country.
And here, there's another chart which shows the outbound migration, which has had a massive impact, especially in Eastern European countries.
The chart that I borrowed from an analysis published by George Safari a couple of years ago.
And you can see the, you know, the big outflows that all of those Central European countries have seen, both as a share of their labor force and as a share of the economically active population.
In Romania, it was dramatic, you know, the outflux of people.
And the Czech Republic stands out as one of the few countries which hasn't had much of an outflow of workers following the fall of the communist regime, you know.
So really, there seem to be big differences in the individual countries.
Final point on where we are going.
So the first point is that we have a structural increase in education, which is one of the reasons why we have a very resilient labor market and growing labor force participation.
Second point is the diversity that we have in the different countries, which is related to policy choices and unemployment benefits and to migration flows.
And the third point is a little bit looking forward.
And that has, that's just a question, whether we are at the threshold of a new area of very strong productivity growth driven by the increased use of artificial intelligence.
Just, you know, an anecdote, I read a report recently that programmers at Microsoft have seen an increase in the productivity of their work by 50% through the use of large language models such as, you know, the ones that have been popularized now in a very short period of time.
So, you know, the coding has become much faster for them and the debugging is now done by those artificial intelligence models.
Therefore, the output per hour worked for an individual computer program has increased by 50% in a matter of one or two years, yeah.
So this is, of course, just a small segment of the population, of the economically active population.
But I think that we may be at the threshold, at the start of a new productivity cycle, which could also lead to, you know, labor savings in the years ahead.
And it remains to be seen how this plays out.
I mean, we can see that in the past, whenever there was a big increase in -- whenever there were big technological innovations, with a lag of two, three years, we've seen a trend increase in U.S. productivity growth.
And we may be at, you know, at the start of another one of those eras, driven by artificial intelligence.
And, you know, it remains to be seen how this will impact the labor market.
And then, final question on what to do, yeah.
So I don't have a quote here on that, but frankly, I think that the developments that we're seeing are extremely positive, no?
I mean, so we see a larger participation, especially of women in the labor force, yeah, driven by higher levels of education.
And we have the chances, you know, all the opportunities that arise from the use of those technological innovations.
Many of us have experienced that during the pandemic, that we can now work from home, yeah?
I actually think that probably the productivity numbers which are published here underestimate the actual productivity growth.
I mean, if I look at my office, yeah, people don't tend to work on Mondays and Fridays.
They look at the computer from time to time, but they only come to the office three days a week.
And they still get the same salary, yeah?
So I actually think, you know, the number of hours worked has -- the effective number of hours worked in those office jobs has declined substantially, yeah?
And that probably doesn't show up in the national accounts or in the statistics.
So we may have just seen a massive increase in productivity through this working from home and teleconferencing and all that kind of stuff.
And I actually think that we're moving to a world which is, you know, pretty close to the world that Karl Marx has described in the German ideology,
where in one famous paragraph he talks about communism as the status where you can be a hunter and a, you know, philosopher in the morning.
You can be a hunter in the morning, you can be a philosopher in the afternoon, and you can do whatever else during the rest of the day.
And you don't have to be confined to just one job, yeah?
So I think that we're moving to a much more diverse, you know, working life and employment status,
and one that will afford much greater liberties to most of us.
So I think it's actually great development that lies ahead.
Thank you.
Hvala vam.
Good morning. Let me start by thanking Boris and the National Bank of Croatia for inviting me again to this very interesting conference.
As a starter, I would also like to make two kavits. Not a customary institutional one, but more on substance.
One is that I'm not a labor economist. There are people in the room who are, so they are potentially better placed to look into this issue.
So I'm a macroeconomist and I look into the labor market from a macro perspective.
And second, I will talk essentially about the European labor market, which doesn't exist because the European labor market is a patchwork of around 50 clusters of regional labor markets.
So what I'm telling is very aggregated and generalized, but gives you some picture, but as already as the speaker has indicated, one has to look into country differences in order to be able to understand what's happening in the countries specifically.
In recent months, European policymakers has often and with a lot of praise referred to resilient labor markets.
The commissioner, when he presented the forecast on the 15th of May, also President Lagarde, on various occasions on the press conferences, was referring to resilient labor markets, which were welcome because they supported household spending and confidence.
In the same way, I shared that view, but I was always a little bit irritated because nobody was really defining what are you meaning by resilience, what are you measuring, what is the concept that you are using.
And so I will start very briefly, only two slides, and I will very quickly go over it, but just to place a little bit what is labor market resilience and what is not according to me.
Then I will look into a number of topical issues on the labor market, the employment situation after COVID, the personal coexistence of tightness and slack, and then wage developments, how they are, and then a number of concluding remarks.
On the concept of labor market resilience, in science, there is a very long history of the word resilience.
It is used very long and very detailed in physics and engineering and psychology, but it has, the term resilience has become fashionable by policy makers in Europe since Euro area crisis.
To some extent, in my view, it's worth otherwise than using flexibility or structural reforms, and so the resilience term, to some extent, was useful to that extent.
In economic terms, economic resilience refers to the ability of a country to withstand adverse shocks and to recover quickly to potential after adverse shocks.
That is the general definition of economic resilience.
Labor market resilience, on the contrary, I haven't found a shared definition or even a general shared understanding of what is meant by labor market resilience in the literature.
Again, I'm not a specialist.
I only have a week or two to look into that, but so if it exists, it's fine.
But the principle one can distinguish between two concepts.
One, which is very broad and is essentially due to the OECD, a seminal paper of 2014, where they have a very excellent paper, and where they defined the capacity, labor market resilience, as the capacity of the economy to limit persistent deviations from output and labor outcomes.
From pre-crisis trends and aftermath of adverse economic shocks.
That is a very broad definition, which I'm not very keen of, because you are mixing various elements, and in particular, you are mixing policies with labor market functioning.
And so I'm much more in favor of the more strict definition of resilience, which is the capacity of the labor market itself, independent of any policy support or withdrawal, to adapt and respond to economic shocks.
I come back to this at the very end, and I will also explain the title, somewhat provocative subtitle, of my presentation.
I will go very quickly over the next two slides, just a theoretical consideration on labor market resilience and how to define it and how to look into that.
From a political economy perspective, the extent to which the labor market is regulated and in the way it is managed influences the resilience of the economy.
And here, these slides present very simplistically and very generally, two types of labor market models, a competitive model and the cooperative model.
The competitive model argues that the institutional framework should formally and primarily be based on market principles of labor and supply.
And so this school of thought attaches a lot of importance to flexibility and deregulation of institutions, and certainly of the labor market.
The other concept is cooperative model, and it's much more on the way mechanisms are foreseen and required in the labor market,
to protect workers from structural inequalities in the relative power of the different shareholders in the market.
I will not go into the details and further explanations of that.
I'm happy to do that overrange with those who are interested.
There is an ongoing, very rich debate academically and politically on these two concepts, and to what extent one has more merits than the other.
But that is not the purpose of the discussion today.
What is important from this discussion is that, in principle, you need to take the two schools of thoughts.
What they say, and then look into the variables that determine labor market resilience.
And so here, this table, schematically, gives you three indications.
Institutional structure, socioeconomic structure, and demographic context.
All of these variables, in principle, have one way or another a bearing on the resilience of the labor market.
I will not go into the details here.
Very, very roughly, I could say that the first category in the last couple of, over the last decade, there has been quite a number of improvements in the institutional structure in European countries.
So, which would suggest to have some improved resilience, and that's certainly true in the crisis countries, where there has been quite a lot of labor market reforms, to a lesser extent in other countries.
While on the other two factors, socioeconomic and demographic factors, the outcome is more mixed, and you have improvements and deteriorations.
So, just this to put a little bit in the framework of resilience.
Let me now move to a number of developments in the labor market in the EU.
And the first one is developments in employment.
The left handslide is employment and unemployment in millions, so it's not in percentages, it's in millions.
And the graphs indicate that after the widespread job retention schemes that shielded workers from a pronounced slowdown in 2020, the labor market rebounds quite strongly after the pandemic.
It also indicates that despite the weakening of economic activity towards the end of 2021, unemployment again rebounded.
The same is true for unemployment.
You can see that employment slightly increased, but not that much, and then rapidly came down.
That development in the labor market over the last couple of years is quite different from the period after the 2008 crisis,
where it took six years in order to achieve employment and unemployment levels of before the crisis.
And here, already in late 2022, we achieved again the levels of employment and unemployment that we had.
So, that's the positive picture.
The somewhat less positive picture is indicated with a dotted line, and the dotted line gives the
trend increase in employment and unemployment, the trend over 2013-2018, and what if that would have been continued without the pandemic.
And there you can see that in terms of employment, we are still around 3 million of persons employed less than the trend would have suggested.
So, we have not yet fully recovered from the pandemic, and also unemployment has not yet fully recovered.
It has come down to 6%, but has not recovered to and still 1.6 million more than the trend would have suggested without the pandemic.
So, from that perspective, it's positive.
It's also positive that we no longer have this ratcheting effect of unemployment, that after every crisis, unemployment gets higher.
That was in the '80s and the '90s the case.
So, from that perspective, we have seen quite a more resilient labor market than we have seen before.
Let's move to the vacancy rates, and here the graph you can indicate, you can see that despite the slowdown, we have a very strong increase in vacancy rates over the last couple of years.
There has been a very slow and small reduction at the end of 2022, and from that perspective, we can see that a high vacancy rate can act as a buffer for unemployment in terms of, over in times of economic crisis.
This questioning effect from vacancies only functions to the extent that the labor market works efficiently.
If that is not the case, then you will not have this dampening effect from vacancies on unemployment.
Already, the chair has referred to the beverage curve, and that's the standard model or the standard concept to look into
the efficiency and the degree of mid-smatch in the labor market.
So, the labor, the beverage curve, the relationship between unemployment and vacancies, or labor shortages.
Here is labor shortages, but that's the same as vacancy rate.
And what we can see here is that over, during the previous crisis, these are the blue dotted lines,
we got an outward shift in the beverage curve, which means that it was deterioration in the match on the labor market.
Now, in the latest couple of years, which are the gray dots, and it's somewhat shown by the green line,
we can see that there is no outward movement of the of the beverage curve during the last couple of years.
So, which is indicative that there has been no structural mismatch over the last couple of years in the European labor market.
If there were, if there would have been a deterioration, then we would have followed the upper blue line.
That would have been the beverage curve in terms of mismatches or important mismatches in the labor market.
So, again, that's a positive development that we have seen, but again, we have high vacancy ratios with an unemployment rate of still around 6%.
So, which is suggestive of, nevertheless, some structural problems in the labor market.
Let's move to wages, and also previous speakers have already referred to wages.
So, here we can see different measures of wages over the cycle.
Two graphs are from the ECB.
The most interesting one is on the right hand side, which gives the dryness of wage growth in the Euro area.
And the graph shows deviations from a model implied trend.
So, what you see here, the blue line is a wage compensation per head, and you can see that it is below what the model would have suggested.
So, wage growth has been sluggish compared to what the model would have suggested.
And then the model is used to look into the determinants of this slugginess in wage growth.
And here, three factors are important.
And you can see that the blue column was very important during the period 2013 to 2016.
So, during that period, labor slack in the European Union affected a negative impact on wage developments in Europe.
The second element is past inflation, which is the red bar, and here you can see that past inflation became an important driver as of 2016.
And going further, up to 2018, it stops, but you can see that it was a very important driver of the last couple of years, although it dissipated with the impact in the latter years.
We'll come back later on at the end to what it would imply for the current situation.
And then you have productivity growth, and there you can see that productivity growth has only had a very minor impact on wage developments in the European Union.
So, what does this mean, this wage developments for European labor share?
Because on top of low productivity growth, low inflation, and substantial labor markets lag, there is strong empirical literature which indicates that technological advance and internationalization of goods and services is also impacting on wage development and on the labor share.
The labor share is an issue which has been discussed for potentially two centuries, starting with both this law, so I will not go that long.
But interesting here to see is that I don't have the full graph because the data are not available for all the countries, but we can see that from the 1970s onwards, 1980s onwards, for all advanced economies, European and US, the labor share was on a declining trend up to around the turn of the century.
And since then, we have seen a quite stable labor share, with some variation according to the cycle, but we had a quite low, stable and low weight share in Europe.
I only for, out of courtesy for the guest, I only put Croatia on the graph, and you can see that for Croatia, it's typically for a less developed country, which is later than the other countries.
It's labor share, its labor share started still, and was on a very high level, at around 80%, but is now coming down very quickly.
So, let me conclude.
So, let me conclude somewhat atypically with four questions.
Labor market resilience, boon or bane?
So, of course, the labor market, if it is resilience, it has to be welcomed, because it means that the labor market is adjusting to economic shocks.
Where I'm a little bit more skeptical is that the extent to which that resilience is temporary, or is due to policy measures, like very extensive job retention schemes, or temporary work, that could, not say it will, but that could lead to a kind of blockage of reallocation of labor.
And so, from that perspective, it's good if it is very short-term and targeted, if it is widespread and long, then I'm much less convinced that that type of resilience is good for the economy.
Of course, it is also good to avoid scarring effects on the labor market, that's true, but again, reallocation of labor is very important.
Second one, labor market tightness or slack, that is a very difficult question, and in my view, it's too early to say that what we have seen is temporary, or it could be permanent.
I would not be surprised that it is permanent, so that's my own take, I don't have a very strong theoretical or empirical basis for that, but if I look on what's happening in the labor market, I do see quite a lot of mismatches in demand and supply in the European labor market.
These structural problems in the labor market were already there pre-pandemic, so that is often forgotten, but many structural problems in European labor markets were there.
They were somewhat hidden during the crisis with all kinds of measures and temporary support, but when these things are fading out, the structural problems resurfaces, and there we can see that we have real problems, certainly on the labor supply.
And here, there are, for the policy conclusions, there are two elements, one is to improve skills, if you want to increase the labor supply, there is certainly a need to improve the skills, it's a little bit the same as Christian is saying, my education level, so that's a little bit the same story.
We really have to invest much more in training, education, active labor market policies in order to get people back into the labor market with the required skills, so that's certainly an issue which has been underdeveloped recently.
And third, and secondly, one has to increase the supply of labor itself, by bringing those who are not active in the labor market, again referred to by women, I'm a little bit less positive than Christian, there is still quite a cohort of the labor force for women, which can be used, and so it's too small, and we really have to look into immigration as well.
That's not an issue, not discussed by the chair neither, but immigration, not only from Eastern Europe, but immigration from outside Europe, in order to fill, importantly, low-skilled jobs, where the price and the wages are up, is very important.
Last point, because the chair is putting some signals to me, we moved from wage inertia, to concern about wage price developments.
Wage inertia was very strong over the last decade after the crisis, and I have seen papers saying that wage inertia is a bad thing and should be activated.
Part of it was a problem with Germany and the current account surplus, and so it was a normative approach to say that wages should increase in order to reduce the current account surplus in Germany.
But that fear of inertia has gone now to wage price spiral.
Three elements, and then I conclude here.
One is, as we have indicated, and in the graph, past inflation is a very important driver of wages.
And so from that perspective, to the extent that policymakers succeed in anchoring price expectations at a low level, that element for the wage curve would not be affected that much.
I'm not sure that it will be the case, because it's not only expectations, it's also actual inflation.
And if that actual inflation remains of four or five percent, that will feed into the wage of the people.
The second one is the labour market tightness, and so there as well I'm perhaps a little bit more sceptical than others.
I do think that labour market tightness is a structural issue, and that it will also fuel wage developments in Europe.
And so from that perspective, I do think that wages can surprise on the positive side.
And the third element, which was discussed very much yesterday, is the profit margins.
And I share the view that profit margins can act as a buffer for wage increases for the time being.
But from a political economy perspective, there is a renewed income distribution struggle potentially before us.
And so from that perspective, if the profit share is so high, that is an invitation for employees, for trade unions, to ask much higher wage increases than they have seen so far.
And that will not be for one year, but that will be for a couple of years coupled with a tight labour market.
I'm sorry if I was too long.
Thank you very much, Savas.
Now we'll turn to Vedran Sosic of the Croatian National Bike.
Thank you, Jeff.
So, Governor yesterday said that this started as a conference on transition economies and then became a general economic conference,
but we could have adjusted the title over the time because we had a period when this was a conference on global financial crisis.
For the past couple of years, this was a conference on pandemic economy.
And now I see that we have moved into the post-pandemic economy.
So we are looking in this new post-pandemic world for a new overarching theme.
And in this new post-pandemic world, labour market is definitely one of the important topics that is a cross-cutting theme for a number of issues.
Much has been said yesterday, also today, so it's not easy to add anything, but it's interesting because two days ago when I arrived,
Radovan said something like we never had more people on Earth, we never had more robots and more automation, more technology,
and the demand for labour has never been greater.
So that's something I can call Radovan Conundrum.
And this panel is, I guess, about Radovan Conundrum.
So, the exceptional resilience of the labour market.
In part, this is definitely a result of the robust economy.
You know, I was here during the pandemic, and by the way, I probably earned a lifetime post in panel for the hard work I put in during the pandemic.
But I remember last year we discussed that recession is six months away, so we were expecting recession.
And the recession is still six months away, a year later.
And you will see that some people call this Godot recession.
So when it comes, it will probably be remembered as Godot recession, the most expected recession ever.
So the economy is still doing quite good, and which is also good for labour market.
But it is more than just the economy, there is more to the strength of the economy.
And the series of beverage curve started yesterday with Mr. De La Riccia, who's first mentioned, and Jeff Servaz.
So you will hear a lot about this beverage curve, the schedule showing relationship between vacancies and unemployment.
And indeed, the number of vacancies shot up.
So this resilience, I guess, for me, it's very low unemployment in combination with exceptionally high number of vacancies.
And actually, the upward move in beverage curve, it is a sign of less efficient matching in the labour market.
So the labour market became less efficient.
But on the other hand, it opens up hope that the reduction in vacancies will not be followed by increasing unemployment,
but rather improved matching in the labour market.
So that's one important thing.
The one thing that has not been touched much upon, and I would like to point it out, is the shape of the recovery.
Some people mentioned.
We had a very uneven recovery.
We had a divergence between the different economic sectors, between activities.
And the recovery was particularly strong in services.
And in services, typically these are labour-intensive activities, particularly contact-intensive services.
You cannot do much automation there.
So it really relies on labour.
So this is probably also one of the reasons why the labour market has been so resilient.
So we know, we have anecdotal evidence about all this skinflation, the reduction in the quality of service.
A hotel can maybe skip making room for a day, but not for two or three days.
So there is limit how much services can spare, optimize labour.
And also, labour market, we have to keep in mind that labour market is a lagging indicator.
So, you know, when the recession, this Godot recession eventually comes, labour market will be the last to know that there is a recession.
It will wake up six months later and realize that something happened.
Also, labour share, a lot has been discussed.
One theory is that employers now don't want, they hoard labour because they are afraid of, when they lose employees, that they will not be able to find other new employees if and when demand increases.
I suspect this is not entirely true.
The robust demand is probably more to wage development.
So we have seen increasing the inflation, declining labour shares.
It became cheaper for employers to keep labour.
Labour is cheap.
So that's probably an important reason behind this hoarding.
This type of inflation was not the same everywhere.
It was particularly present in Central and Eastern European countries.
In core Europe, profits probably did not increase as much according to the data we have.
So this is probably one of the reasons also for particular strength of the labour markets in Central and Eastern Europe.
And finally, demography.
We heard about the demography.
We heard about the demography, but it is really starting to bite.
Demography.
The remarkable thing about the EU is that the population growth came to a halt a few years ago.
So during the pandemic, population in EU did not increase, but it got older.
So there was a reduction in immigration and population.
So it was at about 446, 47 million in 2022.
And it was stable for three years.
Previously, migration compensated or compensated for natural decline of the population.
But during the pandemic, this source of population increase started to dry up.
And the labour force, if you look at the EU labour force declined for the past 10 years by about 5 million.
So with the population becoming older, there is less people that can enter the labour force.
And in CE countries, it's even worse.
We saw the numbers.
I accept a few exceptions.
Slovenia, Czech Republic.
There was a strong emigration from CE countries.
So their population decline was much stronger.
And they got old before they got rich.
So which is also compounding, compounding the problem.
And where do we go from here?
Probably there will be not a major, major change in the labour market.
No one expects that stagnation or maybe slight increase in unemployment.
That's for all the institutions, the IMF, the ECB, the Commission foresees.
For central banks, it's also very important.
What we see, we see immaculate this inflation.
So we see a gradual catch up of wages, real wage growth.
And it's already happening.
I mean, in Croatia, Slovenia, real wages already made up much of the ground lost during the pandemic.
And this is also, so we rely on this downward shift, the gradual reduction, gradual improvement in matching and the reduction in the share of profits and increasing labour share.
But there is a risk.
What if wage growth turns into a spiral?
What if employers decide that they would like to keep their profits, high profits, the level of reach during the, during the, in the aftermath of the pandemic?
So, so there is obviously a risk there.
So all, all, all forecasts rely on a set of, on assumptions that, that is not, that is not given.
Policies, maybe we can leave this further.
I don't know if I'm over time.
One more minute.
So policies, we heard about participation.
It was actually quite good in increasing participation rate.
It compensated for much of, of the, it's overcompensated for, for the declining.
Actually Christian showed the participation rate until, for those under 50.
And it actually increased a lot for those over 50.
With employers, we see automation, which is more probably better, better, greater opportunities are in service, in industry-based economies than in service-based industries.
Education and upgrading of skills.
But this is, this is complicated.
that service show that you need to embed your education and skilling policies into a specific set of labor market policies, social policies.
So you cannot work on that in isolation.
It really needs to be adapted to, to specific, to specific circumstances.
Finally, immigration, we heard a lot about that yesterday.
So this is new, because in Croatia we had a lot of immigration before, but that was from neighboring countries.
And now these neighboring countries dried up and we are seeking immigrants further and further away.
So it will be an interesting challenge.
Thank you.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Okay, now Tina Zumer of the Slovenian National Bike.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks the organizers for inviting me.
Again, last year I was on a panel talking about inflation.
This year it's about labor markets, which is, I would say, quite unusual topic in a sense for us policymakers.
But indeed it's at the heart of our thinking currently.
I will focus mainly on our own Slovenian perspective, also being part of the, let's say, Euro area, but also part of the region.
So I think much has been heard already, but I hope I will add some new insights on that.
So when talking about labor markets, of course, for us the key risk going ahead is labor shortages to actually ensure adequate labor supply, not to be impediment for growth going ahead.
So this is one of our major downside risks for the growth outlook.
And on the other hand, high wage growth being the major upside risk to the inflation outlook.
So quite unfavorable metrics.
And if I say like the main characteristics of the labor market would be that the structure trends that we observed before the pandemic still continue also after the pandemic.
So, and on the other hand, what we saw that this pandemic effect was very short lived and very well absorbed thanks to the large policy stimulus, which we should not forget.
And also maybe better than we thought and expected flexibility and the capacity of the adapt to adapt to such shocks of our economy.
So in that respect, I think we would, we would fit to serve us resilience definition, let's say in our Slovenian labor markets, which actually now stand at really historical numbers, historical low unemployment of 3.5%, which is much better.
And the estimates of Naira historical employment and high historically high vacancy rates.
Two features maybe that I would want to point out that we observed post pandemic is a somewhat more rigidity of the labor market labor hoarding what we heard in despite labor markets firms seem to prefer to retain labor for a bit longer.
So we will see what it means going ahead.
Explaining to some extent, of course, this resilience that we are observing.
And on the other hand, what we observe is more wage bargaining power and this is seen in very high wage growth on the one hand and much more collective agreements.
So they became alive again.
In Slovenia, just to give you a flavor, minimum wage growth increased by 12% and it's very much binding.
So we have a high wage compression due to such wage, minimum wage increases.
And so maybe let me turn to the outlook.
So overall on the structural front, I think that the structural challenges that we have been observing now for a decade since the European crisis will persist and will stay with us for some time.
On the other hand, to the more short term outlook, so we see some moderation in the employment expectations, but we still see strong wage growth in nominal terms coming.
So this is also due to the indexation, backward indexation that is prevailing, either formal or non-formal.
People still want to catch up for the loss in the purchasing power.
And that will also result in the real wage growth, partly reflecting some catch up.
But as Vedran said, also in Slovenia, actually the real wage growth have already recovered from the pre-pandemic levels.
And one should not or could not talk about this without touching about profit margins.
Also in Slovenia, we saw quite some profit margins that we believe would serve as a buffer during our projection horizon.
So therefore, we don't see the full pass on of this real wage increases to the prices.
To conclude with the more medium term challenges, yes, as I said at the beginning, I think it's really touching upon the labor supply.
And this will also have, of course, implication for our medium term inflation outlook, R-STAR and all these structure issues that will stay with us.
And here is really to provide for policies, then I will not go into the policy discussion.
I think they are self-evident and sort of us, I think, also nicely summarized them.
But it's really to supply enough adequate, to supply enough and adequate and productivity enhancing labor supply.
So working age population is expected to decrease significantly in Slovenia and that despite the immigration projections.
So we will need to leave with some immigration over the time.
But nevertheless, the projections don't look good.
So here it's key to increase the participation of the young and elderly.
So there are special schemes that prevent those groups to enter the labor, not prevent, but prevent incentives to enter the labor market.
So in Slovenia, let's say the young cohort, its participation rate is only 30%.
The good news that the elderly have started to increase, to enter the labor market again, but there is, of course, further scope.
Because we should bear in mind that in our region, the exit rate, it's among, also in Slovenia, among the lowest in the OECD countries.
That is from the legacy perspective.
So furthermore, relying on the immigrants or, let's say, foreign workers.
Currently, in Slovenia, 80% of the newly hired are coming from abroad.
I think they're representing about 6% of the employed people currently.
There are mostly low-skilled, low-paid workers.
So another avenue, adequate workforce.
I think here it's very important not to forget the green and digital transformation, which is hindered by the missing skills.
And one could see that by a very high vacancy ratio, a vacancy share in the shortages reported in the ICT services, electrical equipment,
which are key for this transformation and these shortages among, in Slovenia, among the highest in the EU, as well as in construction.
And in this respect, I think it's also important to bear in mind, for instance, that in Slovenia we have very high energy intensive industry employment,
higher than the average of the Euro area, and also higher share of manufacturing.
So this all calls for, let's say, reskilling, upskilling, for re-education.
And then finally, productivity, upskilling, it will be key because I think we all want our wages to grow.
We want to catch up.
But, of course, only with higher productivity growth and here the scores for Slovenia innovation are just medium.
So I think there is scope again here and here.
I think we can go to the policy discussion later on, which I will skip.
Thank you very much for your attention.