[SPEAKER_00] So, hello and good morning dear colleagues and friends. I'm grateful for being invited for the second time to join this conference and also like as the last year again I feel this duty to so to say justify my presence here as a historian I don't really go into debate about the creed itself theological philosophical speculation or whatever but rather try to provide some
[SPEAKER_00] elements of the context in which the creed was preserved through centuries
[SPEAKER_00] Now as also last year
[SPEAKER_00] when I departed from quoting Edward Gibbon
[SPEAKER_00] that the task of a historian is a melancholic one
[SPEAKER_00] that we are unfortunately not to stay in the world of ideas and whatever ideals but rather see how miserable and fragile human beings conduct
[SPEAKER_00] in this light this is something that I feel as my task this year
[SPEAKER_00] Finally, as he stated in conference material I quote
[SPEAKER_00] with the main theme of the conference creed and challenges of the future
[SPEAKER_00] the aim of gathering is to shed light on the ecclesial and socio-political context of
[SPEAKER_00] Nicaea, crucial motives in the emergence of the original creed
[SPEAKER_00] the impact of Nicaea and so forth
[SPEAKER_00] one might ask what does the image of the emperor or political ideologies have to do with the Christian creed
[SPEAKER_00] hopefully
[SPEAKER_00] there aren't that many so naive among us to be surprised or scandalized by the fact that the life of the creed so to say
[SPEAKER_00] inside the life of the faithful through centuries in many ways depended on the political context in which it developed
[SPEAKER_00] and that finally formed the life of the faithful
[SPEAKER_00] it remains so to this day
[SPEAKER_00] okay one doesn't have to justify the position that Constantine's conversion or Constantine's revolution is one of the most important events in ecclesiastical history
[SPEAKER_00] and this is something that the historians still to this day haven't agreed upon
[SPEAKER_00] interpretations of Constantine's motives and whatever
[SPEAKER_00] now saying that in the program today we have another paper which will deal with Constantine and his strategy
[SPEAKER_00] I decided to skip the first part that I intended to present and these are the sources about Constantine and his age
[SPEAKER_00] and rather proceed with the so to say history of reception of Constantine the Great
[SPEAKER_00] okay
[SPEAKER_00] so what does the creed as the obvious source or stem of Christian unity has to do with these external concerns
[SPEAKER_00] while absent from the very documents the state in the person of Constantine was present in the form of imperial involvement
[SPEAKER_00] at the council
[SPEAKER_00] after all the emperor Constantine convened and presided at least ceremonially over the council
[SPEAKER_00] his letters show that he saw himself as a guarantor of ecclesiastical peace and unity
[SPEAKER_00] Eusebius of Caesarea describes him as a bishop of those outside the church
[SPEAKER_00] so obviously what is important from my perspective that Constantine himself is the one who actually saw the seeds of the myth of Constantine
[SPEAKER_00] that will be in different forms continued through the century
[SPEAKER_00] just briefly as in the sort of introduction to remind ourselves what would be the elements for this statement that Constantine himself
[SPEAKER_00] started to create the idea that will one become so to say myth of Constantine
[SPEAKER_00] in the first place this is the first evidence that we have of his conversion or at least the change that happened socio-politically and then perhaps internally
[SPEAKER_00] the elements of this basic text that remind us that he indeed saw himself as a guardian of a mission that was granted to him from above
[SPEAKER_00] and many of these elements to these they remain so to say controversial for us for example the image that he produced in a form of imperial sculpture for example
[SPEAKER_00] this is one of the cases the human the huge sitting Constantine and we have only the fragments which originally according to reconstruction of the experts
[SPEAKER_00] looked something like this so this is Maxentius or Nova basilica and very soon after Constantine's ascent to power he allowed or granted rights that this sculpture would be introduced in the basilica in this position
[SPEAKER_00] now many so to say gentle souls of today are scandalized by this image how is it possible that this person presented as imperial in full imperial Roman power would be pious Christian
[SPEAKER_00] so it was obviously a scandal and it's not only a scandal of our days even the contemporaries as you saw from the quote by Saint Jerome or some others were very skeptical about the possibility of emperor
[SPEAKER_00] displaying all the power that was inherited to the emperor would be also pious Christian
[SPEAKER_00] so in this sense what we might speak of is the some kind of strategies of legitimation that Constantine himself and his cooperators continued after his death
[SPEAKER_00] and it is a building of an image of a perfect emperor or not personally perfect perhaps by the emperor who is the guardian of the deposit of the fate and in a sense not clear from the beginning perhaps the first or second person in the church to so to say on earth
[SPEAKER_00] now in order to analyze the development of this I will use particularly one type of evidence and this is the development of iconography of Constantine the great
[SPEAKER_00] and before plunging into analysis of this iconography and his development I would like to underline something that I find very useful and this is explanation of what the myth of Constantine is namely some of the authors here I primarily rely on Amnon Lindner's
[SPEAKER_00] to my opinion very interesting texts speak of myth of Constantine the great which is based on the following the image of Constantine the great and his role has not come down to us as a pure reflection of the historical Constantine
[SPEAKER_00] Now artificial intelligence will tell us how he looked like and perhaps some people would like to know about his motivations but the fact is that image that we have about him is the fruit of transformation over the centuries in this context it is possible to speak of the mythography and the myth of Constantine the great I just have to underline that by using the word myth I'm not using it in derogative term but rather as explanation of particular type of discourse
[SPEAKER_00] The beginnings of myth making are already present during Constantine's lifetime and we said which is understandable in the context of the pre-christian understanding of the nature of imperial power on one hand in a Christian context this may seem problematic but the fact is that Constantine himself as well as his closest associates gave impetus to the formation of such a memory
[SPEAKER_00] Now what is the myth of Constantine the great
[SPEAKER_00] Amnon Lindner in one of his inspiring papers define it as the following first complex system of historical testimonies legends and folktales even connected with the ritual and based on the historical person of Constantine secondly a successful personification of abstract forces and ideas dominant in medieval civilization
[SPEAKER_00] especially in the concept of the Christian state uniting the concept of the Christian state uniting the entirety of the religious and secular order very important and the thirdly the most significant stages in the development and spread associated with the renewal of political speculation in both east and west
[SPEAKER_00] especially within the ideologies of the Christian Roman Empire with significant centers of the Christian Roman Empire and with significant centers of formation Constantinople Carolingian courts
[SPEAKER_00] Otonian courts Roman court and later Muscovite or Russian court
[SPEAKER_00] Now why is the fact that the state uniting the entire to the religious and secular order and the most significant stages in the development and spread associated with the renewal of political speculation in both east and west?
[SPEAKER_00] Especially within the ideologies of the Christian Roman Empire and with significant centers of formation Constantinople Carolingian courts Otonian courts Roman kuria and later Muscovite or Russian court.
[SPEAKER_00] Now why is this relevant today in particular in particular in this context according to such a mythological reading of the historical role of Emperor Constantine for the idea of the beginning of the Christian Empire or in other variants Christian civilization sometimes even Europe or something else Constantine's personal conversion signifies not only his personal renewal that is the death of all self and emergence of the new man but also the creation of new historical entity.
[SPEAKER_00] Be it Christian Europe or Byzantine Empire or Byzantine Empire or some other empires.
[SPEAKER_00] Although these concepts show incredible vitality during the Middle Ages it has not lost his appeal even for modern historians.
[SPEAKER_00] In other words Constantine has become in many ways a symbol of the relationship between the church and the secular power.
[SPEAKER_00] In this sense it is significant that in Eastern Christianity he was revered as a saint.
[SPEAKER_00] In the Catholic world he was considered meritorous and in the post-Catholic from Protestant through Enlightenment and modernist he became almost a kind of criminal.
[SPEAKER_00] Now what I would depart with is just like a brief overview of the iconographic presentation of Constantin which is in fact outside my field of expertise so I'm quite open to criticism and suggestion especially from those who are more familiar with Eastern tradition.
[SPEAKER_00] I will use all of this as illustration and as I said I'm very much looking forward to comments and suggestions.
[SPEAKER_00] Interestingly according to the extant scholarly literature the first ecumenical councils are not very often presented especially in the early Christian art and interestingly in first few centuries we do not have as I know examples of presentation of the council especially in images.
[SPEAKER_00] But rather in descriptions it only changed after the ninth century so to my research it seems that in tenth or eleventh century we have first examples that we can surely say okay this is the representation of the council.
[SPEAKER_00] So in this estimation the reference to the council in Menologian of Basil II would be one of the earliest presentations.
[SPEAKER_00] So now what I would like to pay attention to is the fact how the so to say relations between church and state are presented here.
[SPEAKER_00] So we have cross in the center on one side ecclesiasticals and on the other side the emperor.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is actually the so to say iconographic motive that continued through the following or subsequent centuries which we can nicely compare with the images from Mira or Demre.
[SPEAKER_00] Eleven, twelve centuries representations of the first council from which then the ideas of other councils developed.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you look for for Council of Nicaea or other councils we have this iconography cross in the center and sometimes holy scripture is added to it at the center of the council while the emperor here for example.
[SPEAKER_00] Constantine the fifth on the right as Constantine the first here on this direction are usually put in this position.
[SPEAKER_00] Now interestingly from my research it seems that the earliest what I would call new iconography at least to what I have been able to trace for today.
[SPEAKER_00] Where emperor is put in the middle actually come from the Serbian monasteries from the Paleologian period 13th century.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is something that I myself still am very uncertain about how is this connected to the later development and especially the question how this new iconography emerged.
[SPEAKER_00] But this is the question that I would put aside and continue with the development of this iconography in the later centuries particularly late 15th 16th century.
[SPEAKER_00] Where I see the renewal of this new iconography where it received very powerful impetus from particular political developments in Russia.
[SPEAKER_00] So what I describe as new iconography is actually representation of the council where Constantine or the emperor if we speak about other councils is put at the center.
[SPEAKER_00] Now why I think this is very very important for even like today contemporary ecumenical discussions and debates.
[SPEAKER_00] If you google first Council of Nicaea you will usually get just let me get to this.
[SPEAKER_00] You will usually get this image I think on the right which is actually a new icon from Greece.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is often even in text that I managed to find and read represented that this is typical representation in the Orthodox world of the Nicaea Council.
[SPEAKER_00] But according to analysis of the development of this iconography it is actually quite late that you cannot find this type of iconography before the 13th century.
[SPEAKER_00] As I said the earliest that I was able to find were the Serbian examples late 13th mid 14th century with the open debate about the dating and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00] Now what is particular about this new iconography that it became very standard during the 16th century particularly in Russian icon painting.
[SPEAKER_00] And these manuals for icons clearly define what particular details mean here.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you just divide it in parts there are three moments or four.
[SPEAKER_00] On the right side we see the cursed Arius vomiting blood and losing his entrails and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00] On the left side we see the story of Saint Peter of Alexandria and little baby Jesus telling him that the Arius was the one who tore his clothes.
[SPEAKER_00] And then finally the main two motives are described like this.
[SPEAKER_00] First we have Constantine who is being confused by Arius.
[SPEAKER_00] Who is telling him all these heretical lies.
[SPEAKER_00] So he is in this lower arrangement here.
[SPEAKER_00] And then Constantine at the center of the council.
[SPEAKER_00] So there is this brief story explaining the story of Arius.
[SPEAKER_00] How this cursed heretic tried to poison with his thoughts the emperor.
[SPEAKER_00] And finally the emperor getting to the position where he became guardian of the fate.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is the way that he is represented.
[SPEAKER_00] Now this became very typical I would say mid 16th century.
[SPEAKER_00] In the context of so to say organization of knowledge in renowned Muscovite state or Tsardom of Russia.
[SPEAKER_00] So this iconography as you see it on the left side entered the description of how to describe or represent the council itself.
[SPEAKER_00] It's always the emperor at the center.
[SPEAKER_00] Now I will back to some of these images in the moment.
[SPEAKER_00] The first known example from Russia comes from famous wall painter Dionysius from Ferrapont of Monastery.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's very early.
[SPEAKER_00] It's beginning of the 16th century 1502.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's very interesting that it was actually made in a very short period.
[SPEAKER_00] The whole program was painted in like 30 days or something.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's very clear from the political context relations between the monastery and the center of power.
[SPEAKER_00] It was actually executed as so to say a program.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is the first Russian example that we know with this representation.
[SPEAKER_00] You see two Konstantines.
[SPEAKER_00] The one who is still confused and one who ascends to the central position.
[SPEAKER_00] Now from this one, one can easily trace the distribution of this motive.
[SPEAKER_00] And it can clearly be detected in athenite monasteries of the first half of the 16th century.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is one of the examples, one of the earliest examples from this Stavronikitan monastery.
[SPEAKER_00] where it is representing this new iconography with interesting difference that the Greek examples don't have Arius losing his,
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, sitting basically on the toilet, but rather put him in this position down there.
[SPEAKER_00] Unlike Russians who insisted on him being basically over there.
[SPEAKER_00] And so this would be something that developed from the mid 16th century as a normal iconography of the council.
[SPEAKER_00] So once again, I would just like to underline this point, then in a, so to say, dialogue between East and West.
[SPEAKER_00] When the East says this is how we represented Sim's time immemorial, this is technically not true.
[SPEAKER_00] And one can trace the origin of this story.
[SPEAKER_00] And if you want to go, so to say, to original, so to say, Byzantine iconography, it would look a little bit different.
[SPEAKER_00] And perhaps provide the ground for more clear understanding of whatever mutual vision of the council and the emperor himself.
[SPEAKER_00] So I would say that the peak of this idea behind the new iconography is the following, represented in this very, so to say, late representation,
[SPEAKER_00] where Constantine actually came in front of all the patriarchs and ecclesiasticals holding the creed with the explanation that he is the one who is responsible for promotion and guarding of the faith and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00] So it became very typical, but the time doesn't allow to go into these details. I could elaborate this.
[SPEAKER_00] The only moment I would like to stop here for a moment is a very interesting example of famous icon painter, Michael Damaskinos, from the mid-16th century,
[SPEAKER_00] who actually worked in Venice and Crete under Venice, who accepted this new iconography.
[SPEAKER_00] You see everything is here as the Athonite monasteries, except for a detail.
[SPEAKER_00] Constantine still hit it here on this side, and the Holy Script is put in the middle of the council.
[SPEAKER_00] So this can help us to, so to say, to trace certain cultural areas of diffusion of this moment.
[SPEAKER_00] So finally, with this, we get to the development of the Russian state of the 7th, 18th century with a very strong image of the emperor,
[SPEAKER_00] who perhaps not completely by chance can remind us on similar political ideas on the West of the total rule of the state with the emperor being and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, this can be put in a particular political context, which I will not elaborate now in the oral presentation, but if once written, this paper will, of course, include this.
[SPEAKER_00] That political context of division between Moscow and Constantinople, division between Constantinople and the West,
[SPEAKER_00] actually gave rise to the particular Moscovite or Russian church at the end of the late 15th, early 16th century.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is actually the context where I see that the development of connections, not only between the Holy Mountain and the Moscow,
[SPEAKER_00] but likewise, the circulation of these ideas offer a place where we can see that the already existing ideology of the emperor,
[SPEAKER_00] of the one who is protector and guardian of the faith, and that as this late Patriarch Antony stated in his letter to Prince Vasily of Moscow,
[SPEAKER_00] already in the 14th century, church is almost unimaginable without a Christian ruler.
[SPEAKER_00] This is, I think, also very important for ecumenical discussions today because recently we were in a situation to hear a talk by an orthodox theologian
[SPEAKER_00] who presented the orthodox vision of the ecumenism, which was for me very interesting, obviously derived from very different tradition,
[SPEAKER_00] and this is this one with whatever.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, I will just briefly, in order to show how this development had its, so to say, mirror image in the West, represent much briefly and more briefly than the Eastern part,
[SPEAKER_00] the ideas that actually informed something that could be called the Great Divide of 1492.
[SPEAKER_00] And I would start with the symbolic image of two representations.
[SPEAKER_00] One is the Columbus getting to the New World.
[SPEAKER_00] On the other hand, the year 1492 in Moscow was then still considered to be year 7000,
[SPEAKER_00] and the year when they expected the end of the world.
[SPEAKER_00] So from the perspective of Moscovite theologians of the day, the world was coming to an end.
[SPEAKER_00] The Rome, Constantinople has fallen, everything is a very, very dark situation.
[SPEAKER_00] And then suddenly the new state with new emperor rises, which is chronologically obviously correspondent with the development of this new iconography,
[SPEAKER_00] which represented this new optimism of the new Tsardom and the new Rome rising in the East.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, this great division can be explained historically, but I would just briefly like to run through development of the relation between the church and the state.
[SPEAKER_00] As seen as, so to say, in the iconography of the West.
[SPEAKER_00] Perhaps the first example of this can be found in the early Carolingian influence or arrival to Rome,
[SPEAKER_00] where the whole notion of donation of Constantine, this forgery and this myth produced its first representation.
[SPEAKER_00] namely in San Giovanni Laterano, so called Triclinum Leonianum hosted the first representation of these relations.
[SPEAKER_00] I can just illustrate them here with Christ handing over the keys to Pope Sylvester on the left side and the flag to Emperor Constantine.
[SPEAKER_00] And then on the corresponding right side of the mosaic, we have sent Peter presenting pallium to Pope Leo, that is the contemporary of Charles the Great.
[SPEAKER_00] And then giving a spear to Charlemagne.
[SPEAKER_00] So this, we might say that on the West, this is the origin of iconography and development of the relation between these two.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, this all builds on the notion developed in the West by Roman bishops in the papacy.
[SPEAKER_00] And that is the notion of two powers.
[SPEAKER_00] We can trace the origin of this idea to the fourth, fifth century.
[SPEAKER_00] And we can see that obviously even before the complete split of the churches, two very different political ideologies developed based on the same narrow, so to say, base of sources on Constantine and his relations to the church.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, I will just sum up with the period of even the terrible and the development of new Russian state, which corresponded, as I said, to the distribution of this new iconography that is the 16th century, to show how it worked in the West.
[SPEAKER_00] Namely, one of the huge papal projects in Vatican was arrangement of the Salah di Constantino, very close to St. Peter, with the whole iconographic program representing a new or completely different vision of these relations.
[SPEAKER_00] And so this Salah di Constantino looks like this.
[SPEAKER_00] You enter the room and you follow these four basic motives: vision of Christ, battle of Milvian Bridge, baptism of Constantine, and then Constantine's donation.
[SPEAKER_00] So if we more, if we cautiously analyze these images, we'll find very interesting details.
[SPEAKER_00] But okay, now I want to go into them.
[SPEAKER_00] But for example, this representation of Pope Sylvester and Constantine obviously shows completely different relations between the emperor and Constantine.
[SPEAKER_00] And interestingly, of course, Pope Sylvester is actually represented as Clemens VII Medici, contemporary pope.
[SPEAKER_00] Likewise, the emperor in the East was represented very often as contemporary rulers.
[SPEAKER_00] And so this is something that can be traced through the 16th and 17th century period of crisis of relations between the church and the state at the beginning of the modern era.
[SPEAKER_00] And basically, this is the image where the pope is either baptizing or donating or whatever with the Constantine put in his place, leading to what I call humanist anachronism of Roman church, where even the council itself is represented as a pope presiding in the center and Constantine being actually one of those guys over there somehow.
[SPEAKER_00] And this continued through the 17th century.
[SPEAKER_00] So I'm just not going into details.
[SPEAKER_00] What we can see here is actually development of completely different historical consciousness, where Constantine is represented in this humanist tradition as a real Roman emperor in Roman clothes, whatever, somehow being contextualized, removed from the contemporary, so to say, church state politics.
[SPEAKER_00] And likewise, in the east, this can be put in a very clear political context of the relations between the church, the papacy and empire in itself, leading to development of these completely very competing two religious and political theories.
[SPEAKER_00] So just briefly, I will sum up that the intention of presentation on analysis of these different developments is not to somehow add to the injuries that we already have, but rather to say, before sitting together, before discussing what we see as points of commitments where we can do something, it's very important to know that historically speaking,
[SPEAKER_00] in Gibbons word, we have this melancholic task of realizing that the development of society's institutions was very different, that even the words today, when we speak about Constantine, creed, church, state might mean different things for experts and people coming from Eastern and Western Christian tradition.
[SPEAKER_00] Hopefully, in the long run, this can help get us closer and not even further than this.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you very much.