[SPEAKER_00] So my paper explores the impact of the Council of Nicaea on Maximus the Confessor's conception of the Logos as Christian formal principle.
[SPEAKER_00] Prior to Nicaea, it was still possible, in originist fashion, to speak of a first god and a second god.
[SPEAKER_00] The father is God himself, Alto Theos, and the Logos is simply God, Theos.
[SPEAKER_00] This enabled some theologians to safeguard the simplicity of the one God,
[SPEAKER_00] while relegating the formal content of the divine mind to the subordinate Logos as a unity and multiplicity.
[SPEAKER_00] After Nicaea, this kind of hierarchical approach to the problem of unity and multiplicity is no longer possible.
[SPEAKER_00] The Logos is declared homo usios with the father,
[SPEAKER_00] and this marks an irreversible break with the Platonic model of mediated terms.
[SPEAKER_00] While the Cappadocians are largely silent on the topic of the ideas,
[SPEAKER_00] St. Maximus embarks upon a daring retrieval of Origen's Logos theology,
[SPEAKER_00] simultaneously restoring the Logos as Christian formal principle,
[SPEAKER_00] while bringing it in line with the consubstantiality proclaimed by Nicaea.
[SPEAKER_00] The result is a divine Logos paradoxically at once, transcendently one and many.
[SPEAKER_00] Joining Pauline Ecclesiology to Porphyrian logic,
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus offers a new model of unity and multiplicity.
[SPEAKER_00] The One Logos is not a radical simplicity in line with the Neoplatonic One,
[SPEAKER_00] but the fullness of wisdom recapitulating all things in his unifying embrace.
[SPEAKER_00] So needless to say, this isn't a Christianity against the philosophers.
[SPEAKER_00] It's in many ways a different philosophical approach,
[SPEAKER_00] which of course has a theological foundation.
[SPEAKER_00] So as Davis notes in his book on the Seven Ecumenical Councils,
[SPEAKER_00] he says, "The problem which would confront the bishops of Nicaea
[SPEAKER_00] had long been a basic question confronting previous Christian theologians.
[SPEAKER_00] It was not simply whether Jesus is God.
[SPEAKER_00] The problem was how within a monotheistic system which the Church inherited from the Jews,
[SPEAKER_00] it was still possible to maintain the unity of God
[SPEAKER_00] while insisting on the deity of the One who was distinct from God the Father."
[SPEAKER_00] Among those who proffered a solution to this dilemma,
[SPEAKER_00] David singles out Origen as a potential source for the subordinationism of Arius.
[SPEAKER_00] While Arius arguably goes beyond Origen in calling the Logos a creature,
[SPEAKER_00] and insisting that there was when he was not,
[SPEAKER_00] he does share with Origen a fundamental assumption, and that is of mediation.
[SPEAKER_00] Just as Origen posits the Logos as a mediator between the absolute oneness of God
[SPEAKER_00] and the multiplicity of creation,
[SPEAKER_00] so Arius insists that the creative act of the transcendent deity
[SPEAKER_00] requires an instrument of creation, Christ the Logos,
[SPEAKER_00] through whom to mediate his creative power.
[SPEAKER_00] While the remnants of Arius's writings are fragmentary,
[SPEAKER_00] it's evident that the theological problem of subordinationism
[SPEAKER_00] is inseparable from the philosophical problem of mediation.
[SPEAKER_00] In terms of the former,
[SPEAKER_00] Yeroslav Pelikan points to the centrality of Proverbs 8:22-23,
[SPEAKER_00] "The Lord created me, and before the ages he established me,"
[SPEAKER_00] as key passages amenable to subordinationist reading.
[SPEAKER_00] Among the extant writings,
[SPEAKER_00] Arius in his letter to Eusebius comments on this verse that,
[SPEAKER_00] "Before he, the Logos, was begotten, or created, or ordained, or established,
[SPEAKER_00] he did not exist."
[SPEAKER_00] Elsewhere, it is said of the origins that,
[SPEAKER_00] "They maintain that Christ is a creature because of what is written in Proverbs 8:22."
[SPEAKER_00] Yet, as Pelikan notes with acuity, the exegist of Proverbs emerges, as he says,
[SPEAKER_00] "in the light of a particular set of theological a prioris
[SPEAKER_00] which produced the Aryan doctrine of Christ as creature."
[SPEAKER_00] To this, I would add only that these theological a prioris
[SPEAKER_00] owe much to the philosophical presuppositions of Platonic philosophy.
[SPEAKER_00] These a prioris, which Pelikan notes and which I intend to focus on here,
[SPEAKER_00] are summed up in the singular problem of mediation,
[SPEAKER_00] of bridging the gap between the one and the many.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, given the constraints of time
[SPEAKER_00] and the fact that I want to focus a portion of this limited time on St. Maximus,
[SPEAKER_00] I offer an extremely abridged treatment of the problem of mediation in Aries
[SPEAKER_00] and its philosophical and theological milieu.
[SPEAKER_00] The starting point is the Aryan insistence upon the oneness of God.
[SPEAKER_00] According to our sources, the Aryans refer to God as monad
[SPEAKER_00] and superlatively as without beginning and most one,
[SPEAKER_00] from this monad emerged the dyad of the sun and the triad of the spirit
[SPEAKER_00] as derivative terms and not co-eternal with the monad.
[SPEAKER_00] The radical transcendence of Aries as God excluded the possibility
[SPEAKER_00] of any kind of consubstantiality with the sun and the spirit,
[SPEAKER_00] at risk of introducing composition, divisibility, and mutability into the divine being.
[SPEAKER_00] While Pelican refers to this as a starkly monotheistic view,
[SPEAKER_00] it is one that is central to the Greek philosophical tradition as well.
[SPEAKER_00] Plotinus, for example, insists upon the simplicity of one for precisely the same reason,
[SPEAKER_00] namely that plurality equals composition and composition equals dependency,
[SPEAKER_00] and this undermines the self-sufficiency of the first principle.
[SPEAKER_00] For everything depends upon it, while it depends upon nothing.
[SPEAKER_00] Now this transcendence creates a chasm between the one God and the multiplicity of creation.
[SPEAKER_00] On the one hand, the simplicity of God forbids any involvement with the world of becoming.
[SPEAKER_00] On the other hand, Aries maintained that the fragility of creatures, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] could not endure to be made by the absolute hand of the unoriginate.
[SPEAKER_00] A mediator was thus required, and Aries finds this in Christ the Logos,
[SPEAKER_00] as the instrument through whom the solitary God creates the world.
[SPEAKER_00] And here we return to Proverbs 8:23.
[SPEAKER_00] Though also created, the Logos is unlike other creatures in his primeval origins.
[SPEAKER_00] He was established, as we read, before the age as the principle of creation of his ways
[SPEAKER_00] for the sake of his works, Proverbs.
[SPEAKER_00] So as a kind of created God, the Logos stands midway between the uncreated and the created,
[SPEAKER_00] the radically simple and the manifold.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's not difficult, in my opinion, to see that Aries' interpretive scripture,
[SPEAKER_00] if not indebted, certainly parallels one of the most basic Platonic presuppositions.
[SPEAKER_00] Plato's Demiage II in the Timaeus delegates the creation of mortal men to the created immortal gods.
[SPEAKER_00] It's a very similar kind of dynamic, that the absolute has to create a kind of created deity
[SPEAKER_00] to create the mortal beings.
[SPEAKER_00] So this philosophical a priori in Aries finds a much fuller development
[SPEAKER_00] in his much more influential predecessor, Origen.
[SPEAKER_00] While it remains a matter of interpretation whether or not Origen deserves the title of subordinationist,
[SPEAKER_00] his understanding of the Logos is profoundly affected by the philosophical problem of mediation.
[SPEAKER_00] A striking example of this are his references to a first and second god,
[SPEAKER_00] which occur in both his Contra Calcium and his commentary on John.
[SPEAKER_00] Reminiscent of Aries, Origen states in Contra Calcium that it is incorrect to attribute work to the first god, the Proton Theon,
[SPEAKER_00] though one may do so allegorically to the second god, Ton Devturon.
[SPEAKER_00] As Origen explains, the first god gives the orders, while the second god, the Logos, carries them out as the instrument of creation.
[SPEAKER_00] This two-fold designation follows that of the second century Platonist Numenius, who speaks of the Protos Theos as a simple, self-directed and free of all labors,
[SPEAKER_00] while the second god, the Demiurgos, is tasked with the work of creation.
[SPEAKER_00] Similarly, in commentary on John, Origen echoes Numenius, referring to the first god as god in himself, Autotheos,
[SPEAKER_00] and the second as simply god, Theos.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, Numenius actually has the good in himself and the good, the Agathos, you know, Auto Agathos, Autotheos, but it's an interesting echo.
[SPEAKER_00] So as with Aries, Origen's one god remains aloof, unsullied by any active involvement with the world,
[SPEAKER_00] while the second god, the Demiurgic Logos, performs the work of creation under the lofty supervision of the first.
[SPEAKER_00] Origen's two-fold distinction plays a key role in mediating between the one and the many.
[SPEAKER_00] Like his philosophical and theological counterparts, Origen too understands God, the Protos Theos,
[SPEAKER_00] as a simple intellectual being whom he terms monas and henas, free of all composition or addition.
[SPEAKER_00] It is Christ, the word and wisdom of God, whom Origen attributes the multiplicity of the ideas,
[SPEAKER_00] the outlines, prefigurations, and narrationes of creation.
[SPEAKER_00] It is interesting to note in this regard that Origen too invokes Proverbs 8:23,
[SPEAKER_00] though in contrast to Aries, Origen interprets wisdom as created and as the beginning of the ways of God,
[SPEAKER_00] as referring to wisdom, not to wisdom per se, but to the formal content of wisdom,
[SPEAKER_00] the createdness of the intelligible world according to which the Logos brings a sensible world into existence.
[SPEAKER_00] So Aries seems to attribute this createdness to the Logos himself,
[SPEAKER_00] whereas Origen seems to say no, the Logos is eternal,
[SPEAKER_00] but the ideas are what's being referred to as created, the ideas in the mind of the Logos.
[SPEAKER_00] So there's a bit of a softening there of the position, I think.
[SPEAKER_00] In the Contra-Calcum, Origen further reveals his hierarchical understanding of deity,
[SPEAKER_00] referring to the Logos as the being of beings and a second God,
[SPEAKER_00] while suggesting in the words of Plato himself that God the Father transcends being in rank and power.
[SPEAKER_00] There's something again, he doesn't quite go there,
[SPEAKER_00] but there's something reminiscent of Plotinus of the One in the noose a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00] Origen doesn't really develop that idea in full, I don't believe that he does.
[SPEAKER_00] So like the condemned Aries and the pagan Plotinus then,
[SPEAKER_00] Origen insists upon the radical transcendence and simplicity of the One,
[SPEAKER_00] while relegating the multiplicity of the intelligible world to a secondary principle, namely the Logos.
[SPEAKER_00] While Origen's condemnation occurred as late as the Council of Constantinople II and 553,
[SPEAKER_00] and there his alleged subordinationism only indirectly censured in the Christology of Evagrius,
[SPEAKER_00] his influence is often assumed in Aries' subordination condemned at Nicaea I.
[SPEAKER_00] Whether or not this is a fair estimation, and there is some suggestion maybe it's not,
[SPEAKER_00] The Credo's statements of Nicaea nonetheless definitively shut the door on any kind of hierarchical mediation typical of Hellenic philosophy.
[SPEAKER_00] In other words, though Origen is not explicitly the target of Nicaea,
[SPEAKER_00] after the proclamation of the Homo Ucyon in 325,
[SPEAKER_00] it is no longer possible for theologians to conceive of Christ the Logos in Platonic terms
[SPEAKER_00] as mediating between God and creation, the one and the many.
[SPEAKER_00] It's scarcely an accident of history that the Logos as an object of sustained theological inquiry
[SPEAKER_00] is conspicuously absent in the period following Nicaea,
[SPEAKER_00] and is revived only by St. Maximus in the 7th century.
[SPEAKER_00] So, this brings us to St. Maximus.
[SPEAKER_00] It is with Maximus that we encountered a renewed preoccupation with the Logos,
[SPEAKER_00] and a robust engagement with the problem of unity and multiplicity.
[SPEAKER_00] While the condemnation of Origen just one century prior exerts an influence in Maximus' Logos theology,
[SPEAKER_00] it is above all the rejection of subordinationism in the person of Arius
[SPEAKER_00] from the proclamation of the consubstantiality of the Father and the Son at Nicaea that is of primary importance.
[SPEAKER_00] In light of Nicaea, Maximus sets himself the unenviable task of reconciling the one and the many
[SPEAKER_00] without recourse to the principle of hierarchical mediation.
[SPEAKER_00] The consubstantiality of wisdom requires a fundamental rethinking of ancient assumptions
[SPEAKER_00] regarding the nature of both unity and multiplicity,
[SPEAKER_00] culminating in what I call Maximus' ecclesial cosmology.
[SPEAKER_00] To begin with, it's crucial to note, as one would expect,
[SPEAKER_00] that Maximus understands the Logos in accordance with Nicaea
[SPEAKER_00] as fully consubstantial with the Father, calling him, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] "the essential and substantial Logos of God the Father."
[SPEAKER_00] More strikingly, Maximus refers to the Logos in the very apophatic terms
[SPEAKER_00] typically reserved for the Neoplatonic One, calling him, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] "beyond being" , while denying that anything, apophatically speaking,
[SPEAKER_00] can be affirmed or attributed to the Logos.
[SPEAKER_00] As Homoousios, the Logos' Son shares the very same transcendent simplicity of the Father
[SPEAKER_00] on par with the Neoplatonic One.
[SPEAKER_00] And yet, cataphatically speaking,
[SPEAKER_00] that is, in the positive terms, Maximus simultaneously affirms that the Logos is manifold.
[SPEAKER_00] For the one Logos, as he says, is many Logi, and the many are one.
[SPEAKER_00] From all eternity, Maximus says further, the Logos, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] "contained within himself the preexistent Logi of created beings,
[SPEAKER_00] according to which he formed out of nothing the substance of the visible and invisible worlds."
[SPEAKER_00] So here we have, in a way, a return of these originist durationes, which is just Logi in Latin,
[SPEAKER_00] and yet somehow they're one.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, this isn't a subordinate Logos, this isn't a noose, this is something on the level of the simplicity of the One.
[SPEAKER_00] So, to the troublesome passage of Proverbs 8, Maximus prefers Colossians 1:16,
[SPEAKER_00] "All things were created from him, through him, and returned unto him."
[SPEAKER_00] The fact that Maximus allows for a kind of multiplicity within the One God marks a striking departure from his pagan and Christian predecessors.
[SPEAKER_00] For Origen, Arius, and Plotinus, the One is radically simple,
[SPEAKER_00] and is only on the lower level of nous, or subordinate Logos, that a unity and multiplicity is affirmed.
[SPEAKER_00] Yet how is this possible?
[SPEAKER_00] How can the Logos be simultaneously one and many, at once simple and complex, without one aspect compromising the other?
[SPEAKER_00] How does Maximus resolve this antinomy?
[SPEAKER_00] He does so by combining the Christian understanding of the Church as a single body composed of many members,
[SPEAKER_00] with the logical categories of the Neopatonic philosopher Porphyry.
[SPEAKER_00] The ecclesial character of Maximus' Logos emerges within the context of his refutation of the originist notion of a pre-existent henad of rational beings.
[SPEAKER_00] Time does not allow me to elaborate upon this further here.
[SPEAKER_00] The crucial point is that this heretical doctrine had been foisted upon Gregory Nazianzus,
[SPEAKER_00] whose reference to beings as portions of God were being interpreted as referring to these pre-existent intellects or logica.
[SPEAKER_00] It is in defense of St. Gregory that Maximus ultimately presents his own transformed understanding of the Logos as simultaneously one and many.
[SPEAKER_00] Indeed, when Maximus says the one Logos is the many Logi and the many are one,
[SPEAKER_00] he is already pointing to the ecclesial character of the Logos.
[SPEAKER_00] As with origin, these Logi represent the prefigurations or predeterminations for creation,
[SPEAKER_00] God's eternal intentions for beings created in time.
[SPEAKER_00] As such, says Maximus,
[SPEAKER_00] A Logos preceded the creation of everything,
[SPEAKER_00] Pantos,
[SPEAKER_00] that has received as being from God.
[SPEAKER_00] Evoking Ephesians 1:10,
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus states that all things,
[SPEAKER_00] the Panta,
[SPEAKER_00] are recapitulated in the one Logos,
[SPEAKER_00] insofar as they have their origin in him,
[SPEAKER_00] and all their diverse existences to him.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's this, Maximus argues,
[SPEAKER_00] that St. Gregory was referring to as portions of God.
[SPEAKER_00] All beings are portions of God,
[SPEAKER_00] insofar as their being corresponds to a particular Logos within the divine mind,
[SPEAKER_00] according to which they were created.
[SPEAKER_00] The whole of temporal creation is, as it were,
[SPEAKER_00] eternally grounded in the word and wisdom of God.
[SPEAKER_00] The ecclesial character of the Logos is one many is made explicit
[SPEAKER_00] when Maximus insists later in Ambiguum 7
[SPEAKER_00] that St. Gregory's reference to portions of God,
[SPEAKER_00] mire theu,
[SPEAKER_00] is equivalent to members of God,
[SPEAKER_00] meli theu.
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus argues,
[SPEAKER_00] For if a member, melos, is a part of the body,
[SPEAKER_00] and a part, meros, is the same as a portion,
[SPEAKER_00] miran,
[SPEAKER_00] then member, melos, and portion,
[SPEAKER_00] miran, are one and the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00] I find that very interesting and somewhat convoluted.
[SPEAKER_00] So to be portions of God, then,
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus is saying,
[SPEAKER_00] is to be members of the body of Christ.
[SPEAKER_00] Not merely, I argue, in the historical and ecclesial sense,
[SPEAKER_00] but in a timeless ontological and cosmological sense.
[SPEAKER_00] Ontologically speaking,
[SPEAKER_00] the whole of creation already exists as the body of Christ,
[SPEAKER_00] as a kind of cosmic ecclesia,
[SPEAKER_00] both transcendently, as ideas in the mind of God, as it were,
[SPEAKER_00] and imminently as the instantiation of those ideas within creation.
[SPEAKER_00] All things are recapitulated, as Maximus likes to say,
[SPEAKER_00] in Christ from the very beginning of the church,
[SPEAKER_00] from the very beginning,
[SPEAKER_00] as the church of the many logi,
[SPEAKER_00] with the one logos as the unifying principle or head.
[SPEAKER_00] Just as the diverse members of the historical church are united in their shared confession of the faith,
[SPEAKER_00] for they are of one heart and one mind,
[SPEAKER_00] so the many logi and the beings created according to the logi
[SPEAKER_00] are one in light of their common origin in their singular reference to the one logos,
[SPEAKER_00] the all-encompassing wisdom which contains everything in its intuitive embrace.
[SPEAKER_00] For this reason, in the mystagogy,
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus refers to the cosmos as, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] "a church made without hands."
[SPEAKER_00] Just as the church is comprised of sanctuary and nave,
[SPEAKER_00] and yet these two form a unified whole,
[SPEAKER_00] so the universe consists of the intelligible and sensible realms united without confusion,
[SPEAKER_00] asin hitos.
[SPEAKER_00] Each of these realms in turn represent a unity in multiplicity,
[SPEAKER_00] insofar as they too are wholes comprised of a diversity of parts.
[SPEAKER_00] And yet this entire diversity of creation, says Maximus,
[SPEAKER_00] is made one, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] by the reference to and oneness with God as their cause and beginning and end.
[SPEAKER_00] This oneness, Maximus makes clear,
[SPEAKER_00] does not involve the destruction of multiplicity.
[SPEAKER_00] Rather, he says that unity, quote,
[SPEAKER_00] "surpasses and outshines multiplicity like the sun outshining the stars."
[SPEAKER_00] The dazzling array of stars do not cease to exist in the light of dawn.
[SPEAKER_00] They simply become invisible in the presence of an infinitely greater light.
[SPEAKER_00] Similarly, when we glimpse the fundamental unity at the heart of reality,
[SPEAKER_00] multiplicity becomes relativized.
[SPEAKER_00] This does not mean that multiplicity is thereby devalued.
[SPEAKER_00] and it means, in fact, that multiplicity is seen and understood from the higher vantage point of the one.
[SPEAKER_00] This transcendent perspective, in fact, perfects multiplicity by rendering it integral, harmonious, and whole.
[SPEAKER_00] In a way, it elevates multiplicity.
[SPEAKER_00] Instead of just seeing, you know, that's just a tree, that's a person, that's a that,
[SPEAKER_00] and you see that everything's part of a grand totality, which in a way, I think, actually elevates particularity within the one.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, in Ambigl 41, Maximus expresses a similar idea in the more abstract language of Porphyrian logic.
[SPEAKER_00] In his Ishigogi, or Introduction to Aristotelian logic, Porphyry explains how every genus and species unifies particulars,
[SPEAKER_00] while particulars divide and multiply.
[SPEAKER_00] So Porphyry says, "For species, and still more genera, gather the many items into a single nature,
[SPEAKER_00] whereas the particulars, or singulars in contrary fashion, always divide the one into plurality.
[SPEAKER_00] For by sharing in the species, the many men are one man, and by the particulars, the one and common man is several.
[SPEAKER_00] For the singular is always divisive, whereas the common is collective and unifying."
[SPEAKER_00] So as genus, humanity is one.
[SPEAKER_00] As individuals, humanity is many.
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus echoes this very same logic when he states that,
[SPEAKER_00] "All things that are distinguished from each other by virtue of their individual differences
[SPEAKER_00] are generically united by universal and common identities,
[SPEAKER_00] and they are drawn together to one and the same by means of a certain generic logos of nature."
[SPEAKER_00] So just as individual beings are united with their common species,
[SPEAKER_00] while manifold species are made one within a shared genus,
[SPEAKER_00] so the many genera are joined together within a single overarching genus.
[SPEAKER_00] strictly speaking, a genus is not divided up by the species and particulars which are subsumed within it.
[SPEAKER_00] For no matter how many species of being or individual beings there might be,
[SPEAKER_00] the genus being remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00] In this way, a genus naturally unifies the diversity which proceeds from it.
[SPEAKER_00] At the same time, the genus is wholly and indivisibly present within that diversity.
[SPEAKER_00] For the diversity of beings are simply the increasing specification of universal being.
[SPEAKER_00] Nor are particulars annulled by their progressive enfoldment within their respective species and genera.
[SPEAKER_00] The eight billion human beings inhabiting this earth are not negated by the fact that they all belong to the common genus humanity,
[SPEAKER_00] while the genus humanity remains one, even as the world's population continues to expand.
[SPEAKER_00] Two minutes, huh?
[SPEAKER_00] Maximus sometimes explains this in the language of expansion and contraction.
[SPEAKER_00] The one genus expands in the multiplicity of genera, species, and particulars,
[SPEAKER_00] and the many particulars contract into species genera and the most generic genus.
[SPEAKER_00] Ultimately, says Maximus, it's the one logos who unites genus, species, and particulars.
[SPEAKER_00] He says, "The logi of whatever is separated in particular are, as they say, contained by the logi of what is universal and generic,
[SPEAKER_00] and the more generic and universal logi are held together by wisdom, Sophia."
[SPEAKER_00] This wisdom, Maximus is clear, is none other than the word and wisdom of God,
[SPEAKER_00] who holds the diversity of creation within his unifying embrace.
[SPEAKER_00] Like the center and circumference of a circle, the logos is both the singular source of multiplicity
[SPEAKER_00] and the expansive embrace which limits, circumscribes, and preserves the many in an unconfused union.
[SPEAKER_00] So this porphyrian model, I think, shows how the many logi are embraced within the one logos
[SPEAKER_00] in a kind of logical hierarchy which simultaneously safeguards unity in its progressive unfolding into multiplicity,
[SPEAKER_00] while preserving multiplicity in its progressive n-folding into unity.
[SPEAKER_00] The one logos is the many logi and the many are one.
[SPEAKER_00] This logical model parallels the ecclesial model which emphasizes how the multiplicity of creatures are all one in their singular origin in the one logos,
[SPEAKER_00] for the many logi are simply the elaboration of a single logos, God's singular overarching intention for the whole of creation.
[SPEAKER_00] Together, the porphyrian and ecclesial models articulate a new conception of unity and multiplicity as two poles of a single reality,
[SPEAKER_00] rather than two realities hypostatically segregated from each other.
[SPEAKER_00] So to conclude, this fundamental rethinking of the problem of the one and the many stems directly from the consubstantiality of wisdom proclaimed at Nicaea.
[SPEAKER_00] For Maximus, the one logos is not a radical simplicity in line with the Neoplatonic one,
[SPEAKER_00] but the fullness of wisdom recapitulating all things in his unifying embrace.
[SPEAKER_00] This leads both to a richer conception of the one as fullness rather than singularity,
[SPEAKER_00] and a more optimistic evaluation of multiplicity as an expression of the all-embracing unity of the Godhead.
[SPEAKER_00] Creation is not a fall or declension of being, but the radiant display of divine wisdom, in a word, theophany.
[SPEAKER_00] So what then mediates between the Trinitarian God, whom Maximus calls the trihypostatic monad,
[SPEAKER_00] and the multiplicity of creation?
[SPEAKER_00] In brief, the logos himself, homoousios with the Father according to his divinity,
[SPEAKER_00] and homoousios with us according to his humanity,
[SPEAKER_00] creates the world immediately by means of a kind of cosmic incarnation.
[SPEAKER_00] Simultaneously transcendent and imminent, the logos himself, fully one, fully many,
[SPEAKER_00] bridges the chasm between creator and creation.
[SPEAKER_00] Thanks.
[SPEAKER_00] applause