Kako možete vidjeti od predstavljenja,Sem ću provoštiti jedan koncept od amerikanskog autora,John_Louis_Geddis,Predstrategy,Zagreb,Konstantin i svojom strategijskog zvrlj.
A simple definition of grand strategy given by Geddes is a plan of action to achieve a long term objective.
More precisely, it entails balancing limitless ambitions with inherently limited capabilities,linking current position to desired ends.
What makes a grand strategy grand is the significance of its goal.
Is the founding of the Roman Empire or Lincoln's abolition of slavery rather than everyday choices like what I will wear today.
Practicality is essential.
As Geddes' account of Pericles suggests one must set a destination,prepare resources,motivate actors and adapt to shifting conditions,controlling some variables while engaging with others.
The central challenge of every grand strategist is sustaining balance without losing sight of the ultimate destination which requires managing enduring polarities.
What then are the central elements of,in my opinion,Constantin's strategy?
the unification or more precisely recentralization of the empire,namely the abolition of Diocletian's tetrarchy and no less importantly the christianization of the empire.
The latter can most reliably be dated to October 312,marking at least the first step toward transforming the empire into a christian one.
For example,Constantin decides to become the sole ruler of the empire.
And after battle at the Milvian bridge,he certainly also aim to be a christian empire.
Desiring from that point onwards that christianity became the empire's primary religion.
Of course,Constantin's relationship with christianity is a complex subject and unlikely ever to be fully clarified.
What appears probable up to the battle of the Milvian bridge is the following:
He first encountered the christian god christianity and christians in his youth,likely under the strong influence of his deeply devout mother Helena.
From his father,he probably received information about the policy of relative tolerance towards christians that they later pursued.
After proclaimed Augustus in 306,Constantin himself adapted a similar policy of tolerance.
By 314th,at the council of Arles,he acted in a manner akin to a bishop.
And by that point may even have begun privately to believe in the christian god.
Or at least to recognize him as equal to the other gods and deities he had encountered in the Balkans,in the army,in the Rome,and elsewhere.
At this stage,Constantin wished to be the sole ruler while maintaining a special though not yet fully defined relationship with christians whom he certainly did not persecute.
What follows is an exceptionally important moment.
The vision Constantine experienced on October 28th when near Rome,he saw a sign above the sun that would glide him to victory over his rival.
This sign is perhaps best described by the English term christogram and combination of letters forming an abbreviation of Christ's name.
There is no doubt however that the victory over Maxentius should be regarded as the moment when Constantine concluded that the time had come for an open public identification with christianity.
Or more precisely with christianity.
He had just won a major battle and entered Rome.
And all could see that this victory had been achieved with the aid of Christ and his divine father.
The christian god had now turned his face towards Constantine and the sign of his son the Christ appeared on the shield of every soldier who secured for him rule over the western half of the empire.
Can we therefore already conclude that Constantine became dependent on the christian god since should he lose that crucial support his earthly successes in this moment the rule over the western half of the empire and with them the vision of a unified christian empire would collapse.
In all probability and as I could see from the sources yes.
The new ruler of the western part of the empire was in contemporary terms a politician on a clear rise.
Yet he ruled territories where christians were a minority despite having just won with the aid of the christian god.
It was therefore the moment for a first major step.
The new ruler of the west presented himself as a man who worshipped only one christian god whose support he enjoyed and to whom he thus owed gratitude.
was not Galerius' edict of toleration confirmed at the milvian bridge.
And more importantly did not the victor under the sign of the cross need to affirm at least the equality of christians and their god with others in the empire.
Hence with the eastern empire weakened Constantine issued a document known as the edict of milan which corresponded almost perfectly to the second goal of his strategy.
Christianity became equal to other religions throughout the empire.
And he publicly thanked Christ for his victory.
Christianity now prospered.
It was legalized and the most powerful man in the empire was its undisputed supporter, protector and promoter.
At this point the sincerity of Constantine's conversion mattered less.
Although in my opinion there is little reason to doubt it.
What kind of christian you may ask issues coinage celebrating the pagan son god or the soul invictus.
And in 321 even establishes a special day in his honor.
At first glance a poor one but it seems only at first glance.
Constantine wished to retain the favor of the pagan majority.
And thus maintain for a time the empire foremost deity.
The sun god.
Yet is it not Christ also the light of the world.
And therefore capable of being identified with the sun.
Here as with the christogram we encounter another in my opinion master stroke of propaganda.
Likewise if speculation is correct that Lysinius has accepted the edict of Milan merely for tactical reason.
And subsequently reverted to milder forms of persecution.
What kind of christian emperor or christ representative on earth would fail to protect christians.
Once again the two central motives in my opinion of Constantine's strategy converged.
Without the east he could not be the sole emperor.
And without safeguarding christians in the east he could not satisfy the god who wanted the security of christians and their church.
By September 324 he had achieved both aims.
He became sole emperor and the first christian emperor.
A shrewd politician like Constantine must have known that state intervention in church affairs carried a less favorable side.
And thus his numerous interventions are well documented.
Beginning with the synod of Ireland in 314 and the Donatist controversy.
The most significant of course occurred in Nicaea in 325.
The precise nature of the creed imposed or agreed upon there can be debated at length.
But there is no doubt that the council confirmed Constantine's new role.
was defined as that of christian knighted apostle or first bishop compelled to resolve a theological dispute that threatened the stability of a newly unified empire.
Constantine appeared conciliatory at Nicaea yet also resolute and clear in his aims.
The council convened in the imperial residence, the emperor was present throughout, and his western bishop played a leading part in drafting the document.
At Nicaea, so we may conclude, religion was politics and both converged in the persons of Constantine.
From the vast body of literature on this subject, Constantine seems best defined by four terms.
Centralization, christianity, syncretism, and propaganda.
In other words, one emperor at the head of one empire from 312 onward after the Milvian bridge,
certainly a christian emperor ruling an empire that was itself becoming christian,
a flexible or pragmatic approach to elevating christianity to the status of the empire foremost religion,
or at least that of the imperial household that can mean the same and masterful use of symbols.
Constantine died in 337.
And if my interpretation of his grand strategy is broadly correct, it can be concluded that he succeeded.
He died near the first christian city of a unified empire, in which christianity has become the primary and the most important religion,
and the most important religion.
Of course, no strategy is flawless.
So, nor was Constantine's.
For example, the biggest strategist in the modern history, let's say, Abraham Lincoln,
who abolished slavery by balancing act or he presented the abolition of slavery as a military necessity during the American Civil War.
And that kind of approach left some consequences that are still felt in American society.
For example, another great strategist of the 20th century, American President Roosevelt,
was undisputably first winner of the Second World War.
American power was spread all over the world.
And the main continental adversaries of the United States of America were, like Germany, like Soviet Union,
on the winning side were, in material ways, ruined.
They were not the real competence for the American power.
So, nor was Constantine's flawless.
He left behind the challenge of Christians outside the empire.
And it can be stated, maybe, that they became the fifth column when the Christianity became, especially when it later became the state religion.
In other states like Persia or some others.
There are, then, the latent adorns of fusing church and state.
And the temptation of defining orthodoxy through political means.
We should never forget that, in my opinion, what was agreed at Nicaea was, first and foremost, a political act.
According to the sources, however, he died as the thirteenth apostle.
Not Christ himself, but the one closest to him.
Standing far above the remaining twelve.
So, you will probably agree with me that all of this is rather successful grand strategy.
Thank you very much.