*sad music*
Welcome to another LUT podcast. So we decided that we're going to do this one in English. Sure. Sure. Why not? Because in front of me is the
Daniel Nesek aka Badboy. Uh, so this is why we decided that we're going to do the content in English because Daniel's, uh, reach. It's, it's not a good idea to only, to only keep it for Croatian or Balkan people. So we're going to go a little bit, uh, abroad further. Daniel, how are you?
Yeah. Good. Great. Yeah. Like, you know, good idea. Uh, thank you.
Daniel Nesek: Thanks for doing so. Definitely. Uh, my audience is like just international. My audience is international. And I would say, I mean yours as well, like, you know, for this podcast, like, you know, as wide we go, like, you know, and, you know, I believe like, you know, what we're going to share here is, should be actually, like, you know, broadcasted around the world, like, you know, without limitations. So let's do English.
Daniel Nesek: I told you when, when, when, uh, when you came here that, uh, I had, I had doubts four years ago when, uh, my friend invited me to, to, to come to your seminar.
Daniel Nesek: I said, what am I going to, to, to do, to, to do there on, uh, dating, uh, coach seminar. And then I went, uh, and, uh, you blew me away with the knowledge, uh, uh, with the organization of this information, with the structure, with everything.
Daniel Nesek: I think that you are giving, uh, unbelievable value to, to people, not, not just to your, uh, core target toward audience, the guys who, who wants to find girls date girls, but even broader.
Uh, I, I find myself looking for content like yours very often and use it in, uh, for example, in business and other areas of, of my life.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah, because I mean, it's, it really comes down to power of communication, you know, power of who are you? Like, you know, self growth, you know, kind of like, you know, of course you can use this in negotiation, any communication, like, you know, business.
Like, so definitely, I would say dating is the core element, like really like the core of your life, you know, the skills that it requires, you know, each of these skills that you develop, you know, kind of manner.
Daniel Nesek: You know, kind of manners, you know, communication, you know, dressing style, every, you know, kind of everything of those things you can use in other areas of the life.
Daniel Nesek: You know, in your personal and, you know, professional life.
Daniel Nesek: So definitely it, you know, can, um, dating is a big topic.
Daniel Nesek: I would say it's the biggest field in psychology is like this kind of male, female relationships, but actually we, we went beyond and above that.
Daniel Nesek: But yeah, so I hope you're going to open some interesting topics today.
Daniel Nesek: So stay tuned till the end because you're gonna learn some really cool shit today.
Daniel Nesek: So let's go first with a question, uh, which is typical.
Daniel Nesek: Uh, who is Daniel or who is bad boy?
Daniel Nesek: So I used to study graphic design.
Daniel Nesek: Okay, but like, you know, very soon, like I was like, okay, that's not for me.
Daniel Nesek: Then I went to psychology.
Daniel Nesek: I had some interesting stories there.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, but very soon I started like, you know, acquiring interest, you know, kind of into girls and going and developing, finding the ways how to, you know, find my way under the sun, you know, relationships, girls.
Daniel Nesek: So within my very soon success, you know, friends, people on forums, asking me, okay, how this, how that.
Daniel Nesek: And basically very soon, like, you know, I started giving lectures, traveling around the world and becoming like, you know, dating coach.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, it's the first kind of pickup coach and dating coach.
Daniel Nesek: Now more moving towards life mentor.
Daniel Nesek: You're doing this for how many years?
Daniel Nesek: 20, 21.
Daniel Nesek: 21.
Daniel Nesek: 20 plus, you know, I started like, you know.
Daniel Nesek: Respect.
Daniel Nesek: 1999 or 2000, you know, so now it's like, you know, 22, 22.
Daniel Nesek: How old were you when you started?
Daniel Nesek: I was like, uh, 20.
Daniel Nesek: 20.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah, 19, 20.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, I started like, you know, kind of going out, playing my first approach as, you know, you know, bars, clubs, you know, trying to get some girls, you know, and then, you know, you know, when you put attention into something and you can use some intelligence and it can go far.
Daniel Nesek: How was, uh, how was your dating life when you were much younger before you started, uh, having interest in this?
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: So basically.
Daniel Nesek: Just, just core talent.
Daniel Nesek: I was introvert, shy guy.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So I couldn't like, you know, I was relying to someone to introduce me to some girls and maybe, maybe hope like, you know, you know, something happens.
Daniel Nesek: So, you know, with a girl, but like, you know, of course, like, you know, that's kind of, you know, one or two girls per year.
Daniel Nesek: That's kind of not enough for like, you know, anyone, not definitely for 20 year old.
Daniel Nesek: So I started exploring other different ways.
Daniel Nesek: How can I meet girls?
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, and, you know, bring them home to my life.
Daniel Nesek: And so, yeah, like it took me many, many, you know, can I took me actually to the point where I was voted as a number one pickup artist in the world.
Daniel Nesek: Like twice in a row, I basically, I really changed the whole community.
Daniel Nesek: There's a whole, there's a whole underground community of the guys who are kind of obsessed with meeting girls, picking them up, you know, kind of using them for sex, you know, whatever, like, you know, kind of like a whole this kind of like, like, we have like, you know, camera guys here, like, you know, on the forums, reading, buying stuff.
Daniel Nesek: That's why, you know, you have like, you know, community of the guys, whose main interests are, you know, the women, and they meet in basements in some like, you know.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, bars kind of like, you know, kind of shady places, like, you know, they exchange knowledge, they go out, like, you know, trying to find the girl of their life on the end of the day, you know.
Daniel Nesek: For me, I was, I was thinking, uh, these few days ago, for me, your skills are very dangerous.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah, no.
Daniel Nesek: Because, for example, this is like, I am the professional fighter, and I fight with someone who is untrained.
Daniel Nesek: Can you make a comparison here?
Daniel Nesek: Yes, but the problem is like, you know, like, I would say, because like, you know, female brain is way more designed for, you know, communication.
Okay, like when we were in a, back in the days in a cave, you know, kind of trying to catch zebra or whatever lion for the food, they were communicating, they were talking, so their brain got developed this kind of a bigger part of the brain.
Daniel Nesek: Much more socially inclined.
Daniel Nesek: Exactly.
Daniel Nesek: Social intelligence.
Daniel Nesek: So you, as an average man, you really need to learn a lot and get your skills just to be equal with them.
So you can, you know, and then, of course, if you go above and beyond them, then, you know, kind of sky's the limit, you know, you can do whatever you want, like, you know, but yes, it's dangerous.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, and, and I'm telling you with these skills, you can meet a girl anywhere and, you know, take a home and, you know, do whatever you want.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, you're going to marry her or you want to keep her for a relationship or just date her or it's up to you.
Daniel Nesek: So what is, what is going to be the average girl opinion or belief about the guys like you, pick-up artists?
Daniel Nesek: What do you think?
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: First, I don't see myself as a pick-up artist.
Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Pick-up artist, I would say is mostly about meet her, have sex with her.
Daniel Nesek: The end.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Next.
Daniel Nesek: And I went beyond it.
Daniel Nesek: I would say like actually the best sex happens within a relationship and like, you know, really like the whole, you can, you're not getting everything from a woman if you just kind of use it for, you know, if you just kind of use it for the sex.
Daniel Nesek: You know, you can get much more from her in later stages in, you know, other areas from emotional, you know, things like, you know, to cooking, to living together.
Daniel Nesek: You know, there's a whole beyond and above that.
Daniel Nesek: Exactly.
Daniel Nesek: This grammar is that the moral and ethics of all these things is important to you.
Daniel Nesek: I mean, it's not moral.
Daniel Nesek: It's the needs.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, my needs are beyond just sex.
Daniel Nesek: I have sex anytime, like, you know.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: So, you know, I don't say I'm a relationship type of guy, but I enjoy, like, I enjoy relationships.
Daniel Nesek: I enjoy being, you know, travel with them, have fun with them, you know, cook at home, like, you know, and have them.
Daniel Nesek: And then like, you know, bring her a social circle and whatever.
Daniel Nesek: It can go to anything like, you know, to threesomes, orgies, whatever, like, you know, so I would say that's more me.
Daniel Nesek: That's more me.
Daniel Nesek: So I overgrew the whole pickup and became more dating relationship lifestyle.
Daniel Nesek: Coach.
Daniel Nesek: They're just kind of, you know, hardcore pickup artists, you know, pickup artists, like, you know, stop a girl on the street, game her, take her home, have bang her.
Daniel Nesek: And you know, this is the beginning.
Daniel Nesek: Exactly.
Daniel Nesek: That's like in business.
Daniel Nesek: It's just the idea.
Daniel Nesek: It's like, it's like you're learning how to drive the car and you can only start the car.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: You know, and then, okay, like, you're not going to enjoy the drive.
Daniel Nesek: I would say the best of women, what you're going to get is actually the process of the drive.
Daniel Nesek: The drive, the relationship.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: That's good.
Daniel Nesek: So you were voted two times as a back best pickup artist.
Daniel Nesek: It was 2013-14.
Daniel Nesek: 13-14.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: What would you say who are the best people in this field at the moment, in your opinion?
Daniel Nesek: If you exclude yourself.
Daniel Nesek: It's like there are plenty of the kids on the market right now.
Daniel Nesek: And that's the problem with the whole community because now everybody thinks he can be a coach.
Daniel Nesek: It's a popular trend to be a coach.
Daniel Nesek: It's a trend to have a podcast.
Daniel Nesek: You know, everybody is doing it.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: So like, it's just like, it's a mess, you know, really like, you know, they, I would say like, there, there are some okay guys, but they're just kind of recycling all stuff that we develop, like, you know, 15, 20 years ago.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, about the real social dynamics.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: They are game over.
Daniel Nesek: They're game over.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: They go like, you know, pandemia and plus they move to like, you know, from the, from the whole hardcore pickup, they move to, you know, to self growth and everything spiritual.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So feminists and pandemia and basic COVID.
Daniel Nesek: I'm just gonna kill them.
Daniel Nesek: So what would you say to the, to the audience?
Daniel Nesek: Uh, what is the game if we are going to focus on this topic?
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So how did you begin your career?
Daniel Nesek: And what, what is this career about?
Daniel Nesek: What is this skill?
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: How do you call this skill?
Daniel Nesek: Is it the game?
Daniel Nesek: Is it the, what is the most common terminology for you?
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, yes, we can call it the game.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, really, you know, but it's not the game.
Daniel Nesek: You're like, it's a game of your life.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: It's the game of your life.
Daniel Nesek: And it's about, it's about mastering the art of dating of love.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So is it like, you know, majority of the guys when it comes, I mean, like, you
know, you want to open a bank account.
Daniel Nesek: You have option number one.
Daniel Nesek: If one bank rejects you go to another one, you have abundance of the banks.
Daniel Nesek: You want to eat somewhere.
Daniel Nesek: You look at this restaurant, burger bar, this place, that place.
Daniel Nesek: When it comes to the girls, you don't have options.
Daniel Nesek: So basically what I do and what I develop, basically, I want like to have abundance.
Daniel Nesek: So I'm the one who can choose.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Do I want to date a blonde or brunette?
Daniel Nesek: I want a supermodel.
Daniel Nesek: I want like girl next door.
Daniel Nesek: You want to go in a relationship.
Daniel Nesek: I want to be a relationship.
Daniel Nesek: I just want to have like, you know.
Daniel Nesek: One stand, whatever.
Daniel Nesek: Exactly.
Daniel Nesek: So how do we call this?
Daniel Nesek: Options, abundance.
Daniel Nesek: I mean, pretty much it should be like what girl, what hot girl has by default.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: A man needs to learn and needs to do like really kind of some heavy lifting.
Daniel Nesek: I mean, training to get to this level where he can be like, you know, I mean, you
Daniel Nesek: You can call it playboy player.
Daniel Nesek: It doesn't have to be.
Daniel Nesek: I just, you know, that's what I'm telling you.
Daniel Nesek: I don't feel myself as a pick-up artist as a player, playboy.
Daniel Nesek: I enjoy life.
Daniel Nesek: If I want to eat banana, I go eat banana, you know.
Daniel Nesek: So the first part of this game, life game, let's call it relationship game.
Daniel Nesek: The first point is seduction, is meeting with someone and getting to know them,
Daniel Nesek: attracting them.
Daniel Nesek: And then it can move.
Daniel Nesek: I would say 80%, 60% of that happens in that spectre.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, because it's first impression.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: You approach a girl, you know, you see two girls in a nightclub, in a bar,
Daniel Nesek: or you see like, you know, kind of two girls walking down the street,
Daniel Nesek: or she's sitting in a cafe next to you, what's very normal here in Croatia.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, what do you do?
Daniel Nesek: How do you gap this, you know, this gap?
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, go there and start conversation, be interesting.
Daniel Nesek: So she is like, wow, this guy is amazing.
Daniel Nesek: I want to like, you know, so basically how to present this, the best side,
Daniel Nesek: not the worst side, but like, you know, the best side of yourself to that girl.
Daniel Nesek: So her first impression is like a wow.
Daniel Nesek: I love this guy.
Daniel Nesek: You know, I want to see this guy again.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: So how do you communicate that?
Daniel Nesek: That's kind of.
Daniel Nesek: So game is actually communicate, you know, it's a mastery of communication.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: And communication is very complicated skill.
Daniel Nesek: It's complex.
Daniel Nesek: Like, like for example, but it's in last two years in whole COVID area and
Daniel Nesek: lockdown, it all went online.
Daniel Nesek: Now the digital image became very important.
Daniel Nesek: How do you present yourself online?
Daniel Nesek: This is the beginning of the funnel.
Daniel Nesek: Exactly.
Daniel Nesek: In marketing terms.
Daniel Nesek: Like for example, back in the days job interview was 100% who you are in
front of, you know, person and almost on CV.
Daniel Nesek: Nowadays, it's, you know, it's kind of 50% who are you there, CV and 50% who
are you online?
Daniel Nesek: Because they all do our, you know, kind of proper research.
Daniel Nesek: What do you post on Facebook?
Daniel Nesek: What have you done?
Daniel Nesek: They a little bit Google you.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So their whole impression is that.
Daniel Nesek: Same thing happens in a dating nowadays.
Daniel Nesek: When she meets you, she goes on Instagram.
Let's see who are his friends.
Daniel Nesek: Let's see where he goes, where he travels, what he eats.
Daniel Nesek: How does he live his life?
Daniel Nesek: So the final decision comes from that.
Daniel Nesek: So basically, my job is to help you how you're going to present yourself in
the offline world and online world in the dating market niche.
Daniel Nesek: So I have one question.
Daniel Nesek: Just one.
Daniel Nesek: I have more.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: But let's start with this one.
Daniel Nesek: To meet a woman, and as you said, it is a fact of first impression.
Daniel Nesek: It is the skill of communication.
Daniel Nesek: Communication is, you can divide it in many different ways, body communication,
Daniel Nesek: verbal communication, gestures, things like that, whatever.
Daniel Nesek: And you said that whatever you did so far in life, it is presented in that
Daniel Nesek: moment when you meet a girl.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: So if it is years of conditioning, years of beliefs, years of all those kinds of
things of reaction of ours to the environment, our processing of this information from outside,
Daniel Nesek: What can you do as a coach in a small amount of time to flip or to change or to disrupt those
Daniel Nesek: beliefs, though that's, I don't know, self-image, whatever is holding this person down.
Daniel Nesek: What can you do in short time?
Daniel Nesek: You can do a lot.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: And my job is just like, you know, what, you know, what care mechanics do.
Daniel Nesek: Take the car apart into the parts, fix them all as much as you have, like, you
know, in that time spectrum, put them all together.
Daniel Nesek: So like it works, you know, your confidence, your inner game, you know, dressing
style, you know, kind of your approach, you're like, you know, insecurities, hide what can
be high.
Daniel Nesek: Like, so like, you know, of course, like in the more time you give us the coaches,
like, you know, you know, the more I can deliver, you know, the more time I have on fixing
something like, you know, is it like, you know, kind of you're walking, you're talking, you know,
how do you, you know, how do you present yourself, you know, confidence, all that takes time,
like, you know, but can you change someone in three days?
Yes and no.
Daniel Nesek: Some guys are changeable like this, some guys, they're going to resist and unconscious
not going to allow the change.
Daniel Nesek: But what changes them?
Does this positive result in the short time changes their beliefs a little bit?
Daniel Nesek: I have changes.
Daniel Nesek: I have ways to change beliefs like, you know, without big side effects, like
of diarrhea and everything, because I have like, you know, when you change too much, the body
just shuts down, like, you know, it gets him sick and, you know, forbids him to come back,
you know.
Daniel Nesek: What kind of techniques do you use?
Daniel Nesek: From NLP to basically like, you know, my toolbox is really big, like, you know,
Daniel Nesek: from, you know, energy stuff, things, but like, you know, I would say like, you know, from
crushing beliefs directly, like, you know, there's lots of things like, you know, some beliefs are
actually, yeah, I mean, this is like a beliefs game, you know, if you, if your mother or father was telling
you don't talk with the strangers, don't talk with the strangers, okay, you know, kind of like, you know,
if you've been trained and brainwashed like that, of course, you're going to feel something 20
years later, like, you know, when you need to approach a beautiful girl in the bar club, like
everything is going, all your beliefs will stop you.
Daniel Nesek: What I did for myself, I cleaned everything.
Daniel Nesek: When I see a beautiful girl, there is nothing in my mind
Daniel Nesek: Stopping you.
Daniel Nesek: Stopping me.
Daniel Nesek: Actually opposite.
Daniel Nesek: I created positive ones.
Daniel Nesek: That's the one for you.
Daniel Nesek: She's here.
Daniel Nesek: You are the only person who can get her.
Daniel Nesek: Do you have any chink in your armor?
Daniel Nesek: Any self doubt, limiting belief or thought when you go there?
Daniel Nesek: After 20 years, I kill them all.
Daniel Nesek: No.
Daniel Nesek: After 20 years, you don't think about anything negative side.
Daniel Nesek: I did hardcore formatting.
Daniel Nesek: Like in like in first like four or five years, like, you know, to the point
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, you cannot imagine like, you know, kind of like thousands of approaches
Daniel Nesek: And whatever I will find that's stopping me.
Daniel Nesek: I went next week hardcore on it.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Like whatever, all the fears I had, I wrote on a paper and I just, you know,
Daniel Nesek: numbers game on them.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, keep doing it like, you know.
Daniel Nesek: Just a numbers game.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Just basically it's exposure.
Daniel Nesek: You expose, expose, expose yourself to the point like where you don't feel anything.
Daniel Nesek: And if you, if you didn't have any results one month, two months, three months,
Daniel Nesek: you still had the persistence.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: I knew I, I knew I'm going to get it.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, I was like, okay, I'm going to, I'm going to crash this field,
Daniel Nesek: no matter what, like, you know, so basically really like, you know, it's just like,
Daniel Nesek: like anything in life, like you do something thousand, ten thousand times,
Daniel Nesek: you will, you know, you will master it.
Daniel Nesek: You know, you'll come to the point where you are, you know, whole and one,
Daniel Nesek: but basically like, you know, it really comes down to the confidence, you know,
Daniel Nesek: and what lots of guys, people actually don't know what is confidence.
Daniel Nesek: Oh, it's like you, you believe in yourself, you know.
Daniel Nesek: How would you say, okay, like, you know, let's, let's, let's like, let's pick your brain.
Daniel Nesek: How would you define the term of confidence?
Daniel Nesek: Confidence for me.
Daniel Nesek: I think that there is a generic, generic confidence, general confidence that you have.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: But I think that confidence is attached to this certain field of life.
Daniel Nesek: For example, if I can, if I do interviews for five years, once a week, I think that I will have confidence.
Daniel Nesek: Okay, good. But why? Let's go into mechanics.
Daniel Nesek: Let's go deeper.
Daniel Nesek: Because, because…
Daniel Nesek: Let's go like this.
Daniel Nesek: Confidence is a feeling that you feel in your body when?
Daniel Nesek: When you can produce, when you can have results.
Daniel Nesek: For example, if I say I'm going to exercise every Monday, Thursday and Friday, and I do it every time, I have belief in myself, I have confidence.
Daniel Nesek: That I'm going to do it because the past and the actions that I had, the execution of mine told me that this is who I am.
Daniel Nesek: So keeping promises to yourself, this is confidence for me.
Daniel Nesek: This is how you build confidence.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: If you keep promises to yourself, this builds confidence.
Daniel Nesek: But there's several aspects of confidence.
Daniel Nesek: How do you see it?
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: You're close, but far.
Daniel Nesek: Close, but far.
Daniel Nesek: If you, okay, you drive car, correct?
Daniel Nesek: You have confidence to drive car here.
Daniel Nesek: Yes.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Would you have confidence to drive now in Ukraine?
Daniel Nesek: It's middle of the war.
Daniel Nesek: Less.
Daniel Nesek: No.
Daniel Nesek: Or let's say in Iraq right now, or some of Baghdad.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Definitely.
Daniel Nesek: Why?
Daniel Nesek: Because of the environment.
Daniel Nesek: You know you can do it.
Daniel Nesek: Environment is different.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So, and that's the crack.
Daniel Nesek: So, confidence is a feeling that you have in your body once you can predict
actions or results of your actions.
Daniel Nesek: Mm-hmm.
Daniel Nesek: So, for example, you said like, you know, you do this podcast 10,000 times.
Daniel Nesek: Pretty much everything that happened 10 times a times, what can happen?
Daniel Nesek: I know all the possible outcomes.
Daniel Nesek: You know all environments and you feel confident because you know you can handle
the shit whatever happens.
Daniel Nesek: Mm-hmm.
Daniel Nesek: You can drive the car down the road like, you know, here confident.
Why?
Daniel Nesek: Because you know all the streets, everything.
Daniel Nesek: What can happen?
Daniel Nesek: Already happening.
Daniel Nesek: You are 10,000 kilometers.
Daniel Nesek: Mm-hmm.
Daniel Nesek: So same thing, why I'm confident with girls.
Daniel Nesek: Because I know I can predict results of my actions.
Daniel Nesek: I can predict, you know, kind of, yeah, results of my actions.
Daniel Nesek: I can go down the street and get any girls for now because I did it like,
you know, 10,000 times.
Daniel Nesek: I know pretty much everything what can happen within this limited experience.
Daniel Nesek: And I come up with solutions for everything.
Daniel Nesek: She has a boyfriend.
Daniel Nesek: She's in a hurry.
Daniel Nesek: Like I pretty much have...
Daniel Nesek: You have the response for every situation.
Daniel Nesek: Response for every situation because I do well, because it happened.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, it's a pattern.
Daniel Nesek: Mm-hmm.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So, and that's what confidence is.
Daniel Nesek: Once, for example, like you go to the toilet to take a pee, you know, at
first you're not confident.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, but then like, you know, with numbers, with things happening,
Daniel Nesek: you must and you become confident because like you control the environment.
Daniel Nesek: You control actions.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So when, when a person says I'm not confident in the way I look, this is how,
this is why I cannot talk with women.
Daniel Nesek: I cannot seduce.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: I don't like how I look.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: I'm not confident.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So now basically there is a way you can build confidence in other things.
Daniel Nesek: That means he's not, what does that mean?
Daniel Nesek: That means he's not confident.
Daniel Nesek: He's not confident.
Daniel Nesek: A person is not confident that he can produce certain emotions in people.
Daniel Nesek: Which means like me.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: He thinks that his looks is stopping him to get the results.
Daniel Nesek: Exactly.
Daniel Nesek: To, to get some kind of a reaction.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: If you don't give a shit, like, you know, like you're fat and like, you
know, nothing is going to, there is no confidence being triggered.
Daniel Nesek: But if you think, okay, if you use your looks to get likes and you, and it's
not producing it, you will feel like you're not controlling that segment.
Daniel Nesek: You feel insecure.
Daniel Nesek: You're not controlling the results of your actions.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So what I can do as a coach, I can give to you or that guy, communication skills,
what to say, how to do, how to actually spark attraction in other way, in a personality,
not in looks.
Daniel Nesek: So no matter what your cards are, you can win with them.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: No matter like, you know, how your nature, like, you know, what gave you, you
know, it's, there's a difference between good looking, which is nature versus, and looking
good.
Daniel Nesek: Mm-hmm.
Daniel Nesek: Not everybody can be good looking, but everybody can look good.
Daniel Nesek: You know, good suit, you know, shaved, clean, you know, kind of like, you know,
Daniel Nesek: Exercise, exercise, whatever, like, you know, health, everybody can invest
time, energy and like, and become, wow, this guy's good looking.
Daniel Nesek: So, like, you know, definitely that's something that, you know, that people
can do to improve.
Daniel Nesek: And like, you know, if you, if something is stopping you in life, it's fixable.
Daniel Nesek: Like, especially, especially in the dating issue.
Daniel Nesek: Like, I know, like for lots of guys, it's like a nuclear science, you know,
Daniel Nesek: Girls are really like, you know, they function and they think they're
Daniel Nesek: on their own way.
Daniel Nesek: But it's possible, you know, to understand them actually like, you know,
Daniel Nesek: I have tons of diagrams and graphs and we need to explain their behavior.
Daniel Nesek: And actually it's very predictable.
Daniel Nesek: So like, you know, there is always a way to improve and get better.
Daniel Nesek: Let's try for the audience.
Daniel Nesek: Let's try to break down what is happening in the moment of a guy sees a beautiful
Daniel Nesek: girl that he likes.
Daniel Nesek: Uh huh.
Daniel Nesek: Uh, he, I suppose that regular guy gets nervous in that moment.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: He brings to himself.
Daniel Nesek: Oh my God.
Daniel Nesek: She's not going to like me.
Daniel Nesek: She's going to reject me.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: I don't look good.
Daniel Nesek: I don't feel good at the moment.
Daniel Nesek: Maybe I will try next time.
Daniel Nesek: Can you, can you, can you break down for the audience?
Daniel Nesek: Usually the brain goes into finding excuses.
Daniel Nesek: Why not to go there?
Daniel Nesek: Let's try it.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: What happens to, from the guy's side, from the girl's side?
Daniel Nesek: What should happen?
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, so first thing, like, you know, what happens in a man?
Daniel Nesek: Because man is in a pressure to do the first move.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, at least in, at least in, uh, part of the Europe world where
we live.
Daniel Nesek: Majority is like, you know, the man has to do the first move.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, first move, first kiss.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, like for sex initially.
Daniel Nesek: Like, Sweden, some like, you know, like countries kind of more kind of, they
went other way.
Daniel Nesek: They can take control.
Daniel Nesek: But I would say, um, I would say like, you know, this part of Europe and
actually majority of the world is like, you know, woman feels passive.
Daniel Nesek: She needs to be seduced.
Daniel Nesek: She needs to be chased.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So your job as a man is to go there and do the first move, you know, break
the eyes approach.
Daniel Nesek: So as you first, when you see a beautiful girl, of course, like, you know,
guys get nervous because they don't know what to do.
Daniel Nesek: There's no script.
Daniel Nesek: You know, once you give a person script, it's much easier when, you know, it's
the action points, bullet points.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: Now I need to deliver the opener.
Daniel Nesek: So as the first thing what you-
Daniel Nesek: Nobody teach them.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah, exactly.
Daniel Nesek: I mean, this should be, you know, taught in a school at one point in a time,
like, you know, because nobody's, you know, it's actually the most important area of your life, you know.
Daniel Nesek: So I would say the first, the very first thing what you have to do is have prepared opener.
Okay, like, you know, so the opener is first sentence or question that starts conversation.
Daniel Nesek: But what do you say to yourself when the negative thoughts start to pop into your mind?
Daniel Nesek: You just, you know, it's like, there's like a 10,000 negative, 1,000 negative thoughts versus like one positive one.
Let me go and do it.
Daniel Nesek: I don't give a shit.
Daniel Nesek: Like, you know, this is a ballsy moment.
You know, it's kind of high risk, high reward, but actually there is no risk.
You know, if you know what you're doing, risk is minimized.
Daniel Nesek: Maybe, maybe a person can think this is exciting.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah, you can like, you know, let me try something new.
Daniel Nesek: I'm not, it's not a fear.
This is exciting.
Let's, let's do it.
Daniel Nesek: I mean, try to do it.
Daniel Nesek: But see, what is behind it's adrenaline.
Daniel Nesek: Yeah.
Daniel Nesek: Okay.
Daniel Nesek: So actually my, my gym coach actually gave me some pills.
I still didn't use them.
Daniel Nesek: It's a blocker, I think, beta blocker for adrenaline.
Daniel Nesek: It's kind of really red pill.
You don't feel anything because adrenaline is not being like, you know, produced.
So probably your brain is clear and you can go approach and whatever.
But there's a problem with like, you know, with people with heart problems can observe.
I didn't use this yet for my coachings, maybe in the future.
I really like, you know, but actually I prefer to actually remove this kind of anxiety and
everything to handle it.
Like in somebody, you get used to your, to your emotions.
So it's logic versus emotion.
Your emotions are telling you, no, no, don't go there.
Like, you know, you know, okay, I have to do this, you know.
So you, you walk towards the girl or girls, group of the girls, even easier.
The more girls there are, the easier it gets.
I know it was, it's counterproductive, but actually, because there always one girl will talk.
You know, the bigger the group.
One is your, you know, blah, blah, blah.
She wants to talk and you open her.
And then you slowly move around the group.
Okay.
Like, you know, so that's kind of easy.
But I would say a first thing, what you have to have, like, you know, busy.
I always like, I have like a two or three openers on my list.
Always like, you know, Hey girls, let me ask you something.
You know, kind of like, you know, some basic question.
Um, and then like, maybe like, you know, one or two direct ones.
You girls are so damn beautiful tonight.
You know, who are you?
I simply have to get to know you.
You know, full direct, you know, I like you.
I want to get to know you.
You know, if it is one girl, I don't know why, but I really like you.
What's her name?
Or if you're going very, very high, you are exactly type of a girl I'm looking for.
I want to get to know you.
What's her name?
You know, full direct.
And I would say basically the whole community started with more indirect, hide your intentions.
I went all direct in or like, you know, why hide it?
You know, she knows why I'm approaching her.
Like, you know, you know, it's, you know, she dressed up and like, you know, she prepared for it.
That's how her game plan is to get me or you to approach like, you know, so use that energy.
You know, I love the way you look.
But I want to get to know you.
Who are you?
What's your name?
Is she looking at how you look?
Is she looking at how you move?
So basically you are, what do you call it, you know, blackboard, tabula rasa.
Okay.
She doesn't know anything about you.
So like this empty screen.
Now your job is to put on that screen, basically she's going to learn about you from the way you talk, the way you talk, the way you talk, the way you talk.
The way you move, the way you are dressed, the way you smell, and what you say.
Okay.
And it's happening very fast.
She's creating an image.
Just first impression and overall impression.
She's creating an image of who the fuck are you and what can you offer.
Every girl in her mind, she's thinking, okay, what can I have from this guy?
You know, is it going to be like the fuck body, you know, relationship tie, you know, kind of future boyfriend, maybe I married, you know, marriage material.
What is this guy for?
What can he give me?
So, so as I said, first is the opener.
It's kind of breaking the ice.
Hey girls, let me ask you something.
Okay.
Like, and then like, you know, there are different things you can ask.
They start talking.
You can go from like, hey, best clubs to go out tonight or like this club sucks, you know, or to something more kind of, you know, I love drum openers, you know, you know.
Hey girls, let me ask you something.
I just came back from, you know, my female friend.
And it's a little bit longer openers.
It's amazing.
Like, you know, female friend, she's at home crying.
She wants to kill herself.
I really don't know what to do.
Okay.
Like, you know, I tried to help her, but like, you know, basically what happened, like, you know, she came home yesterday.
And she found her boyfriend actually, like, you know, like, you know, they're about to get married in a couple of months.
They have a wedding plan and everything like, you know, on a couch, on a sofa with his business partner, you know, in very, you know, dirty position, you know, on his knees, you know, and, you know, because she loves you and he loves to have amazing relationship.
But, you know, he said it just happened accidentally.
They're watching some, you know, Excel on a computer and one thing led to another.
And, you know, so she's crying, you know, she didn't know how to handle it.
She created a whole drama, kicked them both out.
Like, you know, and she doesn't know what to do because like, they have like a wedding plan on September, couple of months from now, everything is paid.
You know, what?
What will you do?
Will you stay to God?
Will you forgive him?
Like, you know, you know, girls loves drama.
You know, they love drama.
Especially when you come, girls, let me ask something.
If you find, how I usually approach, girls, let me ask you something.
If you find a guy cheating on you.
But not with another girl.
With a guy.
Is that cheating?
Yes, of course.
Because, you know, what just happened?
I was from a female friend.
She's crying.
She wants to kill herself.
She doesn't know what to do.
I try to help her.
I need your help.
Okay.
So this is what happened.
And then you do the whole story.
So the bigger group, the more fun, the more show.
One is like, yeah, I will break up.
You know, the other one, like, you know, I, you know, I would stay.
I will forgive him.
If he loves me, it's okay.
I'm like, maybe I'm crazy.
But I don't know.
If I come home and I catch my girlfriend on, on sofa, on couch, making out with her business
party.
I'm like, you know, look, work with her boss.
No one happier than me.
Like, you know, I mean, I'll be crying, but from happiness, not from like, you know, because
now you can move to the threesomes and like, you know, it opens the all.
And that's kind of the beauty of communication from totally, from totally cold.
Who the fuck is this guy?
You create energy of fun, excitement, you know, sexual.
And, you know, you are the one who is navigating this energy.
Maybe they had boring and dull.
Exactly.
And really like, you know, with me, with me, it's going to be probably the most interesting
conversation they had in a month.
You bring some joy in their life.
Exactly.
I bring the spark, the joy and wow.
Like all of those will remember my conversation, like, you know, for months or sometimes years.
And so really, you're a magician.
You can, you know, from this awkward energy of, you know, kind of like, you know, I need
to go out there.
You create the most fun with that crying, you know, kind of like, you know, laughing.
You're high-fiving, then you change the topic.
You look like some crazy girl.
What horoscope sign are you?
You change the topic, horoscope.
So I would say opener.
Number one, good opener, you know, indirect fun, whatever, like, you know, sexual drama,
like, you know, or direct.
Second thing is what you are doing.
You are creating attraction.
Attraction is a feeling they, females say this is a kind of feeling of butterflies in
their stomach.
You know, when they feel like, you know, you know.
But actually, attraction is not only male to female, female to male motion, but you can
be like, you know, you see like, you know, nice car, you feel attraction.
You see, you know, nice house, you feel, fuck, I want this.
Okay.
So basically, just like with confidence, definition of attraction would be when
when, when you are basically, you have internal your wish list.
You know, but how does your ideal woman looks like or ideal man or whatever, you know, kind
of car.
When you're basically, attraction is a feeling that gets triggered in your body once your
internal list, wish list matches external world.
Okay.
So in that moment, you get, wow, I want this.
Your body is telling, you're giving a signal.
It's a signal.
Just like nervousness, just like fear.
It's a signal from your body.
Okay.
It's a signal telling you, you want this.
Go and get it.
So when you see a hot girl and you feel that butterflies in your stomach, it's your unconscious
telling you, go there and get her.
Every guy will fight that with fear or with something like, you know, you can act on it,
you know, and just go with the flow.
It's kind of what, you know, being a natural, natural game is all about.
Okay.
So girls, they have their list in their unconscious mind, what ideal man is.
What they're searching for.
And the good news for men is pretty much all, I would say 90% of women on this planet
are searching for exactly the same type of a guy or attracted to exactly the same type
of a guy.
or brainwashed.
Yeah, exactly.
And the same content.
I mean like, exactly the same, you know, Cosmo and movies.
So basically pretty much, if you break down 12, 13, 15 characteristics of quality men.
Okay.
That every girl out there is searching for.
Confidence, dominance, guy who is, you know, leader.
Humor.
Sense for humor.
Sense style, you know, kind of like, you know, has some style.
Emotional, social intelligence.
Has friends.
Loves to travel.
Educated.
Independent.
Lives alone.
Parents, mom, whatever.
Like, you know.
Successful, has some, you know, kind of making money.
That's 12.
Sexual.
A little bit more, maybe adventurous, interesting.
Can talk about lots of things.
So, this is pretty much what, you know, girls in Croatia call Mr. Normal.
You know, like, you know, to become Mr. Normal, you need to kind of really, you know, kind of work on yourself.
To work on yourself.
Like, like 10, 15 years to become normal.
Yes.
So, pretty much if you manage to convey that.
And let's say, I can do, it just take me half an hour.
Now I can convey that list within three to five minutes.
I really, I go there and I'm like, okay, this guy is dominant, this fun.
Like, with this opener.
Like, in the middle.
Okay, this guy is dominant, fun, interesting, sexual.
I can, with the opener, I can flip half of these things in her mind about me.
Hmm.
So, this is, this is the first.
So, this is the first part of the attraction.
The first part of the attraction.
Okay.
Then what happens?
There are signals.
You know, when a girl likes to, she'll start playing with her hair, leaning in, ask you questions.
So, you, you have a good feedback.
Are you progressing well or she's like looking around and not into you?
So, basically, that's how you know, like, you know, you know, she starts like, you know, kind of biting her nails, putting a lipstick, playing with her hair.
You know, like, you know, doing, you know, everything else on like, you know, you know, kind of exposing sexual parts.
Like, you know, we all experience that.
Like, you know, it's a signal from unconscious.
You like the guy.
Okay.
So, this first part, for example, you, you were with a group of girls, you came in.
You lift up the energy of this.
Yeah.
And then energy.
Then you choose your target girl.
Let's say.
You choose your target girl and you do, you do the stuff.
And maybe you can be vocal about it and say, I like your friend.
Exactly.
Martina, whatever, la, la, la.
And then you start talking with her a little bit more.
And now she likes you.
Her body, her unconscious likes you.
But she doesn't know logically anything about you.
So, if you bring that girl back home and you try to have sex, she'll be like, oh, I don't know you.
This is too fast.
Who are you?
Like, you know, you're going to create last minute resistance.
The main problem of pick up artists.
Pulling the girls home too fast before the sales process is fully finished.
You know, same thing if you try to, you know, sell something like fast, like, you know, you're going to hit some resistance.
So, second part of the game is, I would say, more connection, more getting to know each other.
Okay.
Sharing stories, experiences.
Sharing stories, exactly.
But you are going through, let's say, main five, seven topics.
Hobbies, music, movies, series nowadays, sports, travel, childhood, food, drinks, relationships.
You know, kind of these topics, but you go wide and deep on those topics.
But keep it funky, not boring.
Exactly.
But she needs to learn about you.
Who the fuck are you?
As well, you give her opportunity for her, but it should be 50/50.
Conversation is never 50/50.
It's usually 60/40, 70/30 from the men's side.
So, you need to be able to talk, talk, talk.
But even the introvert, shy guys can learn how to talk.
I'm a perfect example of this, you know.
So, it really comes down to, you know, exchange.
Actually, in seduction, you have two main energies that you're playing with.
Okay.
There's this energy of connection.
Like, for example, you and me, we sit down on a coffee and we talk about it.
We talk about things.
We share who is a good camera guy, not which team do you have, you know.
And we start bonding, exchanging stories, funny things.
Oh, where do you have, you know, summer holidays.
We'll find some commonalities.
We'll find some people that we know.
We'll have some stories and we'll become friends.
So, this is this kind of connection, comfort, finding commonalities.
Rapport.
Rapport, exactly.
And not because of rapport, okay.
What lots of guys do, especially nice guys, they do all their seduction, they create this rapport.
You know, that's the only thing what they do.
But not organically, not on purpose.
It doesn't matter how you do it.
They do it naturally.
But then you end up in a friend zone.
Why?
Because you just spend 90% of your time or 100% of your time creating this.
I get to know you.
Oh, what music do you listen?
Oh, I love it.
What food do you do?
So, you exchange.
She only sees, okay, this guy wants to get to know my personality.
Okay.
He's interested in my personality.
So, how do people don't get into this trap?
Exactly.
Wait, wait, I'm coming there.
She will put you in the box.
This guy is a friend.
But you are the one who created it.
Not her.
Don't blame her.
Because 100% of your content was rapport, was connection based.
You were building the friendship.
Her feedback is, this guy doesn't want to fuck me.
Who wants to be friends?
This is the nice guy problem.
So, what I did, what I introduced into the seduction world is the concept of controlling,
controlled sexual energy.
Just like you have tools to build rapport, there are tools to build sexual energy between
two people.
Okay?
And we'll go deeper.
But basically, like, you know, all tools, techniques, what you have in seduction.
basically comes down into these three categories.
Opening, then creating attraction, sorry, creating connection.
Even though attraction is sexual energy.
Like, you know.
And then creating sexual energy.
Now, what calibration, important skill in seduction is, is knowing how much of rapport
she needs and how much of sexual to go home and sleep with you.
Emotional girls, girls looking for relationships, of course, she needs more rapport, less sexual.
The girls who are looking for one night stand, they need, you know, you don't need to talk
with her about her childhood and everything for two hours.
She wants to get laid.
Yeah.
Open your eyes, recognize that.
Depends on the situation that this woman is in.
Yeah, let's say she's in a bar club.
I mean, I would say more situation.
Part of the life.
Yeah.
I would say period in a month as well.
They're like, you know, days when they are fully crazy and horny.
So that you can actually smell and learn how to smell and learn how to recognize.
So actually, you know, if you just want to get laid, every nightclub bar has like two,
three, five of those girls who came there just to get laid.
So your game can be like, you know, just kind of, you know, I used to play that, like, you know, kind of just go
like, you know, 2:00 AM in the morning, go there, like sniper shot, like, you know, one approach, one girl, go home.
I was in a club 10 minutes.
So from my experience, the typical process is, for example, you find yourself in some situation,
whether it's club, bar, whatever, you meet some girl that you like, you come to her, you start seducting her,
she likes you, you meet each other a little bit, and then you get her phone number, and then you part your ways.
And for example, you text her a few days after it and you say, let's go on a coffee, let's go on whatever drink.
And then you have, for example, few, few dates after something sexually.
A very traditional base game.
This is traditional, this is traditional.
And for example, your, your goal, your aim is that you want to have a relationship with this girl.
Sure.
Let's try to break this process down.
So you will go on a first date after this seduction part of when you met, met her the first time, first night in the bar.
And this is your first date.
And you said you tried to balance this rapport building with the sex, sexual energy, so that you don't end up in the friend zone.
Yeah, yeah.
Basically, you need to maintain, okay, basically, and girls hate this, like, you know, kind of, you know, whenever I'm introduced to some, like, you know, female friends, and like my girlfriend, like, okay, like, he's like, you know, kind of dating coach.
How is that possible?
I'm like, I managed to break down.
It's not possible.
You know, it's the chemistry.
I'm like, I found the formula for chemistry.
What?
No, it's not possible.
Basically, chemistry, you know, what the girls call like, you know, there's a chemistry, there's no chemistry.
It's about two things.
Rapport plus sexual energy.
You create basically, and now let's separate.
What is rapport?
Rapport is brain to brain connection.
It's logical.
We find out common experiences.
You like beer, good beer, I like beer.
We talk, we find out we are both in Thailand in the same hotel.
Oh my God, we'll feel closer.
Oh my God, we both have the same camera.
We both, you know, we had some, you know, we both dated some girl.
We found lots of, you know, connection points.
We will feel some rapport connected.
Okay.
So you do that and you add on it like sexual energy.
How do you do that?
Okay.
So that's kind of my PhD.
Oh, how crazy do you, how deep do you want to go here?
Like, you know, um, okay.
Verbal and non-verbal.
Okay.
So let's first cover non-verbal.
Sex is about being physical.
Okay.
At one point in a time doesn't matter where you need to,
she needs to get comfortable with your touch.
Okay.
Because, you know, end up, you will be touching each other a lot.
That's your, let's say, it's one of your goals.
So slowly, that's why we divided the body into three zones.
Green zone, yellow zone, red zone.
So first you start with like, you know, touching the, you know,
normal non-sexual parts.
High five.
Exactly.
Like, you know, you do like, you know, up the arm, shoulder.
Oh my God, you have something here.
Like, so she gets used to touch you.
Maybe you can dance.
Like, whatever.
So like, dance slowly.
You start whispering.
So you kind of just look at a yellow zone, the neck, you know, the back.
Like, you know, more kind of, you know, lower back.
You know, touch everything.
If you're in a nightclub, you go in, you lean in, you know, kind of,
you talk with her on the ear, whispering, that.
And then basically, you go to the, let's say, the breaking point sort of goes up to the kiss
and then start going down.
Now, basically, after you kissed, you can start kind of, you know, going, you know,
with the boobs part and more sexual things, but it goes, like, down the hill.
That's kind of the word about part.
It takes slow.
It takes time.
But like, you know, you still do high five.
Like, maybe do some palm reading.
Oh my God, I love your necklace.
Compliments.
You touch.
And as well, like, you can put hand, you can do some selfies.
You know, perfect thing for camera.
You take your phone.
You hug.
You're using excuses to create this.
It's okay to touch each other.
She gets comfortable with your touch.
It's a crucial element of seduction.
Then there is a verbal part, which is actually my little baby.
It's a dirty talk.
Okay?
So, it's really my PhD.
Like, you know, I found a way.
I found, like, lots of, like, you know, brain hacking tools.
Let's go like this, okay?
So, what is dirty talk?
What is dirty talk?
Yeah.
You ask me.
Of course.
Or should I ask your camera friends here?
Maybe you can ask him.
Okay, it's usually something what you do during the sex.
You know, maybe you have such a sexy leg.
I love, like, you know, this.
I love the kids, okay?
So...
Who's your daddy?
Exactly.
So, what if, let's say you're in a bar, you're in a nightclub.
Are you familiar with anchoring, NLP?
Terms of anchoring?
I think that I am.
Okay, so let's say...
But you can...
Okay, let's say...
Let's say you drive the car and, like, you know, on this street you had a car crash.
Accident, like, ten years ago.
Mm-hmm.
So, there's some bad feeling every time you come to this street, you know, it gets triggered, some bad feeling.
So, it's a feeling that's connected to this kind of certain place.
Mm-hmm.
You know, it comes from, you know, Dr. Pavlov.
He had his, you know, dog training, like, you know, when he was, like, you know, kind of giving them food with a bell.
They would start salivating because they knew the food was coming.
So, even, like, you know, with just the bell, without food, they would still go crazy.
Okay?
So, it comes from that.
So, basically, you can anchor certain feelings to the body.
Like, for example, you and your girlfriend, you have, like, you know, music that you like.
In your relationship.
And you break up.
Years after that, when you hear that music on the radio, you will remember her.
That's an anchor.
Something, something.
Now, you can use that.
For example, when you use dirty talk lines from the bedroom from her previous boyfriend in the nightclub.
And you start whispering in the ear.
What's you gonna trigger?
You're gonna trigger that emotions.
Okay?
So, I found a way how to...
So, her body chemistry changes.
Exactly.
The other way how to make their panties wet in any place, any time, within, like, five
to ten minutes with a couple of those lines.
Okay?
And it all comes down to very high-tech brain engineering.
So, we have two hemispheres.
So, left hemisphere, right hemisphere.
Okay?
And we know from the studies that right part of the brain deals with emotions, deals with, you know, colors.
Like, you know, it's more kind of female part of the brain.
Like, you know, written, music, you know, kind of...
Left part of the brain is a man's brain.
You know, logic, reasoning, mathematics, languages.
Okay?
Like, you know, all of that.
Like, you know, it's kind of...
Actually, languages are on the right part, like on the female side.
Um...
Right part of the brain controls.
Left part of the body is X.
You know, left part of the right part.
So, everything you whisper to the left ear bypasses the logic and it goes directly into emotional part of the brain.
This is scientifically proven.
It's scientifically proven.
Check it.
It's fucking amazing.
Like, you go to the...
And I tested it.
I was like, holy shit.
I need to test this.
Like, so I took lots of elements like this.
What ear?
Left ear.
Yeah.
So, you whisper same sentence on the right ear.
They argue with you.
On left ear, they just kind of swallow and they go in this kind of feminine energy.
Like, you know.
So, second thing what I did, like, you know.
Okay.
Is...
I took compliments, form of...
Okay.
Do you know why women love compliments?
Because the underlying need of all humans is that we want to be accepted, loved.
Yes.
And what else?
I'm not sure.
We have certain standards what sexy is in the world.
Okay.
So, if she goes to the gym, you know, kind of, she's working out for months, months, like,
she's like, you know, like, sweating and all that kind of pain.
In the moment you say it, it gets triggered.
It pays off for all that work.
Someone tells you, oh, you're slimmer.
Or, you know, you look fit.
Or, you know, kind of, you're stronger.
All that work and hassle pays off in that moment.
Okay.
And because, like, you know, okay, now you're reaching into the box of being sexy or hot or
something, you know, kind of, you know, it means like...
But those compliments are honest compliments.
Sorry?
They're not lies.
They're honest compliments.
The best compliments are the honest.
Okay?
Yes.
So, you don't play with the honest ones.
I mean, you can play with the lies one.
Like, you know, it's scripted, but, you know, they don't work as good as...
So, what I did.
The problem with compliments and women is it's only one way.
You're only lifting her up.
And you're creating this gap between you and her.
Okay?
It's always up, like, you know, especially...
So, if you go, "Oh, she has such sexy legs."
Her nose gets bigger and bigger and bigger.
So, it's one way direction.
So, compliments are good, but actually bad for seduction.
Okay?
You understand that?
Yes.
Okay?
You cannot blame...
You cannot base your game on just compliments.
If she's insecure girl, yes, you're gonna make her feel sexier, more kind of loved, like,
you know, kind of...
But for, like, you know, beautiful girls, you know, compliments are not...
Especially, you're not gonna get her panties wet.
But, if in that sentence, you just look, you know, little change in the sentence, it becomes very sexual.
And you add yourself in the sentence.
Can you give us an example?
You have amazing legs.
You can't stop thinking about them.
I cannot stop thinking about them.
For example.
Exactly.
Yeah, you add yourself "I".
You know, so it's not only her, it's her plus me.
It's us.
Okay.
You know what?
Those legs.
You have such amazing legs.
When I look at them, my blood goes to all wrong places, baby.
I didn't say dick.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I wasn't, like, you know, perverted.
Yeah, yeah.
But she had a...
I created a picture of my dick in her mind.
Yes.
Very subtle, and plus the left ear.
So, what I'm doing, I'm creating images, sounds, and movie clips in her mind every three
to five minutes in conversation about two of us having sex.
After 15 minutes, because they can multitask.
After 15 minutes, you know, things get very hot.
But there's a whole process how to do that.
Like, you know, it's a very dangerous weapon because, like, you know, it can get you into
the problems.
But, like, you know, if you do it well, it's superpowers.
So, we were talking about the first or the first few dates, and then building rapport,
and building sexual energy, giving compliments.
Okay.
But it's not...
Do you want to put this into the dates timeline?
Or, like, you know, I can do all of that in a nightclub, in a bar, in a cafe within, like,
you know, half an hour.
You know, open air, create attraction, build rapport, get your sexual.
So, let's stay in this first scenario, let's say that this guy wants to be in a relationship
with this girl.
Then you're going to postpone the whole sexual party until the first or second date.
Yes.
Okay.
You know, you don't pull your heavy guns.
Don't wait too long.
Exactly.
Don't, you know.
So, basically, it's...
Basically, the...
Guys, can you see this?
Screen.
Yes.
Sexual energy goes like this.
Okay, it goes up.
Basically, this is like a...
The peak is on a second date.
So, this is like a...
Basically, you're meeting somewhere.
First date, sexual energy here.
Second date, there's a peak of energy.
Third date, fourth date goes down.
So, on the date number five, you're already in a friend zone.
If you didn't do something with your data.
So, I would say second or third date.
If nothing happened by a third date, kiss, nothing, nothing, it's game over.
You wasted your time.
What did you do wrong?
Not...
You didn't create sexual energy.
You didn't pull the trigger.
It's like in the sales.
You know, there's a person...
There's a moment, you know, window of opportunity when a person is ready to buy something.
You know, the lead gets called after 24 hours, 48 hours, whatever it is.
Like, you know.
You give him an option.
48 hours, it's game over.
the dynamics here are a little bit different because we're talking about, you know, girls who are very emotional.
They are using their emotions to...
For decision-making process.
With men, we use logic.
Do I want to buy these shoes or not?
Do I need them?
You know, we use logic.
How much it costs.
Female, you know, girls, they use emotions.
How do I feel?
So, let's say you do a good job in those first few dates.
You end up together.
The sex was great.
And when you said that you are, for your clients, that you are giving them service, not in just seduction part, but also in relationship and things like that.
So, you had sex for a few times.
You get to know each other even more.
You like each other.
And then where this goes after it.
What do you say to your clients?
Okay.
Good point.
Okay, so let's move towards a relationship.
Some first problems went on the surfaces.
Okay, great, great.
Whatever.
Okay, after the first, you know, kind of couple of weeks, let's say two months, you need to start engineering the relationship.
It's like running a company, you know, having employees and like, okay, it's more like, you know, partnership level.
I like my girls to be kind of, you know, level where I am.
I usually bring them up and educate them and coach them and just kind of do.
So, we work together.
Basically, a relationship, it really comes down to understanding the needs of other person.
Is this relationship going to be successful or not?
Okay.
So, you as a man, you have your own needs.
What do you need from her?
Okay.
Like, whatever it is, regular sex, you know, that she cares for you, cooks, you need to cuddle, whatever you as a man you need.
Then, there's her needs as a woman to be taken care of, to be taken on dates, to be loved, to, you know, regular sex, to whatever it is, whatever her needs are.
Your job as a architect of a relationship, someone needs to be architect, is to construct, to sit her down, what I usually tell my girls, I have homework for you.
Okay.
I want you to sit down and think about, I want you on a list, you can be written down or WhatsApp, you can send me a WhatsApp message.
Everything what makes you happy.
Everything what other guys did and didn't do to you, and they should be doing to make you happy.
I want to know that.
I want to know what fills your cup.
So, we basically, within, I was the second month, I started exchanging those lists.
I go really deep.
Okay.
This is what I need as a man.
Would they give it to you, the information?
Oh, yes.
I usually.
Yes.
After, not after first month, but second, third month, yes.
I like it.
Because I usually do whole pre, you know, pre play, like, how do I open up?
I'm like, listen, like, you know, you know, in order for us to stay together, it all comes down to this.
You know, I want my relationship to be the best, like, you know, every moment, every second.
So, you know, we are here for each other, and we kind of, we give best for each other.
I want you happy.
Now, I'm experienced with women, and I pretty much know what women want.
But let's, let's play I'm dumb.
I don't know anything about.
Can you please go home and write me this list?
I want to know everything what makes you happy.
What other guys did and didn't do.
And that I, as I'm, as your man, that I should be doing on a regular basis.
So, if you stay on that list.
That's a very good idea.
Yeah.
It's a, it's a splendid idea.
But what it comes down to, in my opinion, in my experience also, for example, I can, I can know consciously what my girl wants, what she needs.
So, we communicated that, but somehow I'm too much self-obsessed.
Egoistic.
Execution.
And I'm only looking at why she's not giving that to me, what I want.
But if she.
And I forgot about her.
Yeah, yeah.
This is, this is, in my opinion, what happens the most in relationships.
What I do, I do reality checks every month.
Okay.
Like, status of relationship.
That's a good idea.
Like, where are we?
On sex, on food, on this, on that.
Like, you know, we give points to each other.
Score.
Like, you know, exactly.
Like, you know, metrics.
Okay.
That's a good idea.
Yeah.
I take it really like, you know, down to the science.
And if it is communicated, but someone needs to be architect.
If you just think like it's going to happen, it's not going to happen.
It's a mess.
If you freestyle.
I like to control, not all, I'm not a control freak, but I'll, you know, it's, it's my house,
my company, like, and I want, you know, everything to work good.
So everybody's happy.
Everybody's getting what they want to, you know, to be there and to kind of give the soul for
this relationship for Orelka.
So we are both into it.
Like, you know, my job is to make you happy.
Your job is to make, to use your resources to make me happy.
So reciprocity.
Exactly.
And it all comes down to that.
If I'll be making you happy and you'll be making me happy, we can stay together forever.
Correct?
It all comes down to that.
Now, most people, they freestyle on that.
Girls, they have no idea how to make men happy.
They think it's sex.
You know, I need to like, you know, give him a blowjob.
Or cook, you know, they, they don't know.
And everybody's guessing.
They're not asking.
Exactly.
They're guessing.
That's like, you know, when I say communication is important.
Yes.
But quality communication, this is quality communication.
Not just kind of literally, let's talk about your problems and let's guess what's bothering you.
You know, talk about shit.
You know, how was your day?
That's bullshit communication.
I want quality communication.
But usually what can happen in relationships that a girl or a man, whatever, they tend to have the problems with expressing their feelings, expressing their needs, because maybe there is some conflict there.
You need to help them.
Like, you know, you can need to sit down.
Whatever you think there's a problem.
You go there, like, you know, and not full force, but like, you know, you sit down and listen, like, you know.
Our relationship depends on this.
Yeah.
So we need to.
Exactly.
We need to do this.
You need to have this kind of uncomfortable talks.
Like.
Don't put everything under the rug.
Yeah.
Like, you know, play everything is fine.
And like, you know, playing like, you know, like, you know, if you see a problem, like, you know, your job is to bring it up.
And, you know.
So how much of your work at the moment consists of this, uh, pickup part, seduction part or relationship part?
Where do you focus the most of your?
I would say, look, it depends, like, you know, like, you know, kind of whatever the client has the needs, the problems.
Like, you know, kind of some guys are already dating.
And you do one on one.
You do groups.
You do seminars.
I would say during the year, I do one on ones during the summer.
More like, you know, kind of this kind of boot camps, like, you know, kind of, kind of, you know, group coaching, you know.
But yeah, I prefer doing like, you know, I prefer dedicating like, you know, sit down with a client and just kind of, you know, focus on his needs.
The best results you can do when you do one on one.
I mean, there is a, there is a big thing with, with a group energy, with momentum, especially in this sport.
When the guys are pushing each other, you can, you know, break all your boundaries, you know, when you see like, you know, kind of, you know, your wingman, you know, kissing, you will try harder.
Like, you know, so it's like, there is group dynamics.
If you know how to control it as a coach, like, they can go beyond that, you know, you can really like, you know, you can achieve much more than one on one in this kind of breaking beliefs and everything else.
Like, you know, so both are good, you know, depends for what, like, you know, if it is fine tuning, of course, one on one is better, like some, you know, very delicate stuff like, you know, if it is just kind of destroying beliefs and kind of pushing, you know, getting as much results as possible.
I would say group trainings is like, you know, good, like, you know, so we focused on the first scenario was the standard scenario.
You met a girl in a club bar, you went to a few dates, you had sex, you wanted a relationship, you get, got into relationship.
And this is, this is ongoing thing.
We even talked about how can you, how can you manage that this relationship is good, that you communicate your needs, and that this relationship flourishes.
So let's focus on the second scenario, where you want to have one night stand, where you want to have sex right away, as quick as possible.
What do you do differently?
Okay, definitely.
How much is dependent on the, the woman being in that emotional state at the moment?
So when it comes to, you know, they call this kind of in community DTF, like, you know, down to fuck, or, you know, girls who are busy, you just focus on one night stands, okay.
There are two segments.
Before me, before I came to the community and after, before it was just kind of, okay, find a girl who is up for that, and go for it.
But then I create the whole process of getting her panties wet.
So you can take a girl who is not sexual and, you know, create this thing.
So basically, pretty much, I wouldn't say every girl, but you know, you, you are the one who is controlling it.
You can control the process of, you know, getting her horny.
There are girls.
So if the girl is in a happy relationship at the moment, can you do it?
Happy?
No.
If she's in a relationship, probably you can do it.
Like, you can find, like, but you know, it's kind of, I don't advise.
I don't because there's so many single girls, like, you know, why to do it.
But it's possible.
It's possible.
It requires a little bit more advanced skills, like, you know, breaking the whole relationship.
But like, you know, it's not ethically correct.
Like, you know, I mean, people are probably in relationships anyway.
So why to break those few relationships that you have on the market?
They're happy.
Like, you know, we know why to do so.
Right.
I prefer creating relationships on the world and, you know, breaking them apart.
So, but, you know, there is the whole, like, you know, the dark side of seduction and like in everything else.
Like, you know, you know, there's a force and there's, you know, kind of the dark side of the force, you know.
But, yes, so back to the topic.
You can, 20% of the bar club are the girls, you know, 50, 20% are the girls who are there looking for one night stand.
For one night stand, you know.
Maybe.
She's horny.
Maybe she, I don't know, the boyfriend cheated on her.
She's looking for revenge.
She's bored.
Whatever.
Like, you know, it is like she's looking for some fun.
You can usually recognize them.
There's a way how to recognize them.
You know, dressing style, position in a club, you know, like, you know, lipstick, high heels, like, you know, shaved legs.
Usually, like, you know, it's, you know, they position under, like, you know, the most bright light in the club.
So, they are visible in the whole unconsciousness game.
They do it very well, you know.
So, if you open your eyes, you can find them.
But, as well, the girls who are kind of more into, you know, let me just have fun and dance.
You can still convert with the proper techniques.
Get her horny and, you know, kind of take home and have fun, like, you know.
So, there's about definitely what is changing is, like, a more focus on sexual energy, less connection, and sorting out logistics.
You know, her friends.
That's kind of what, you know, kind of usually, like, you know, if she came with her girlfriends, you know, she's driving the car and two of them are, you know, kind of, she's responsible for them.
You need to sort out the whole logistics, dynamics, you know, figure out how you're going to isolate that girl from her group.
And there are tricks and techniques for that.
What about three-way?
Whew, three-way, that's kind of another one of my really, really good way what I like to do, like, you know, these days, and especially in relationships.
There are, you know, basically, there's more and more bisexual girls, but actually by curious, you know.
I would say especially this generation, like, you know, X and Z, they are totally open up to things.
Like, you know, you can have this kind of more and more, they have experiences with other girls.
So, you can definitely play with it.
There's a whole game plan, actually, like, approach two girls and how to end up home with them, like, you know, or find yourself, like, you know.
Actually, if you're into the threesomes and the whole thing, like, the best thing is to find yourself a girl who is bisexual, by curious bisexual.
And then use her as a wingman, go out there, pick up other girls, bring them home and all that.
Actually, that's really easy way how to do it, like, and you can, like, you know, Bob.
That's a good strategy.
You can have amazing, and there's a whole game plan how to do, you know, basically, like, you know, we call this kind of, you know, kind of more private game, like, you know, what she needs to do in that segment, what you are doing in that segment.
Like, for example, like, you know, you can, you know, let's say you choose some girl, you are the one who is going to approach, you know, talk, talk, then she comes and you introduce, oh, this is my friend, you know, kind of Christina.
Then you eject, you go drinks, you leave them some time alone, somebody, and all.
So after, let's say, like, you know, couple of hours, couple of drinks, it's not you saying, hey, let's go back to my place or somewhere else.
It's your girl saying, hey, let's go to his amazing apartment, because there's a less resistance from her.
So, some elements, you know, as we say, like, you know, attraction, sexual rapport, some elements she's doing, and some elements, some parts of the game, you still have to do, you know.
So with the proper communication, you can develop really good, you know, wingman skills with your girl, where you can kind of go out and really kind of have fun, even in a relationship, even like, you know, with five, six years later, like, you know what?
So that's, that's one way how you can keep the spark in the relationship.
Oh, yeah, yeah, and one of my favorite ways, you know, one of my favorite ways, and I love to do that, like, you know, in relationships and like, you know, it's, you know, kind of, it's amazing when you have your girl, like, you know, next morning, you sit down for coffee or debriefing, oh, you know, when you said this, like, you know, kind of this, you know, kind of, so it's really amazing, because you become like a partners in crime, in a relationship, which is so much fun, you know.
Yeah, can you give guys, or maybe even girls, some tips on how to keep that spark in the relationship, this sexual spark, we covered one part, okay, it's a threesome, maybe, even in a relationship, if you can do it with your girl. What's what other things you think that people can can do to keep this spark?
I mean, like, you know, breaking the pattern of routine, you know, you know, the spark gets killed with a routine, like, you know, can I, you do every weekend the same, every day in the same, so, like, you know, the moment you break that, you kind of, you push.
Or maybe you have, both of you are very disciplined, hardworking.
Yeah, like, you know, then you give yourself a little bit of a break, you know, you go to sex shops, you experiment, you know, with different toys, different people, fantasies, you sit down, again, like, you know, play with her unfulfilled fantasies, you put your list of unfulfilled fantasies, like, okay, what are we going to do next weekend, you know, kind of, you know.
If you invest intelligence, and that's kind of what I'm teaching, this game is one here, with the brain.
Okay, if you, if you kind of have capacity to think and to analyze, you can be a good player, playboy, if you, you know, kind of, actually, using that IQ, not just to analyze things, but like, you know, to, like, you know, to do it properly.
So, you can really achieve a lot, like, you know, in your, in your, basically, usually, they say geeks are not, not good, like, you know, can I, with the girls, actually, I love working with geeks, with, with IT people, with high, you know, like, whole, you know, STEM field, intellectual guys, because I can really use their intelligence capacity into this field and put them into, kind of, give them the schemes, you know, formulas and everything.
They can kind of plug and play and create, use that intelligence and to create amazing dating life.
How do you put them more into the body?
How do you move this energy, this focus from the prefrontal cortex?
Yes, exactly.
But there are exercises, there are exercises, usually, like, you know, all my approaches are very physical, you know, approaching, turning them around, street stops, like, you know, doing that.
But as well, like, you know, in a long run, you sign them up for sports, it's excellent to do some sports, you know, gym, boxing, dancing, playing guitar, anything to get more in the body to get out from the brain into the body, like, you know, because I would say game is 60% brain, 40% body, you need both.
Just like, you know, you need to seduce not only her brain, it's two layers, seducing her brain, and giving everything what her brain needs to sleep with you, and then seducing her body, it's a body to body level.
I think, for example, if I'm thinking about myself, I think that I'm more here, and I'm more here, and I had some period, I don't know how many years before, that I had some period that I was single, and I went on dance classes, and I went almost for a year, and I got much more relaxed, much more playful, and I think that it helped.
The center of man energy is here, okay, center of man energy is here, like, you know, chill, like, you know, main chakra here, and center of female is lower, hips, that's why they kind of move everything, it's there, like, you know, male is here, so you just have to move it, exactly, from here, heart, yeah, like, you know, okay, yeah, so, like, there are ways.
So it's not balls, but heart.
Yeah, there are ways how to, um, how to move that energy, like, you know, sports, you know, any physical activity is one of the best, the different ways, you know, you can, but it's, it's teachable something that you can, we usually take guys on a coaching after how to move from here to there.
And it's also good when you go dancing, you're dancing with the girls, you're touching, no, no, that's amazing, any, any, anything, like, you know, go do anything, go work as a bartender, whole summer, summer, like, it will be just, you will be in your body whole summer, you know, like, anything that's physical, like, you know, any sports, gym.
Anything what you can do, like, you know, kind of just kind of get out from the mental zone, you know.
So, okay, let's go like this.
Uh, the core, the core value of this, of this brand, uh, is self-improvement, growth, working on yourself.
Uh, so what can guys do, um, by, by themselves, to start working, from my opinion, I, I always see in my mind, this two pillars, I see the first pillar being called mindset, which is beliefs, attitudes, uh, self-image, identity, things like that.
And the second pillar is skills, skills like communication skills, uh, like maybe self-awareness, which is very important skill.
I know several ways how to do, do, how to improve this, uh, skill.
And, of course, several other important skills that you can, that you can improve.
You know, what's beautiful here.
Two pillars.
The moment you approach a woman, they give you full honest feedback.
And I love them for that.
You know, my, my main coach, who I learned from, are the girls.
So, all my knowledge, skills, it comes down to them.
Because the moment you approach them, they will trigger, they will tell you everything what's wrong with you.
Everything what you didn't work on, on yourself, will come out.
You are, you know, dressed bad, you know, you didn't sleep well, you didn't eat.
Well, you don't work out, you're fat, you're, you know, you know, your bread smells bad.
You know, everything you didn't work on yourself.
You didn't fix.
You're shy.
You don't know what to talk.
You don't have a job.
You know, you don't have interesting life.
It will come out.
It can hit your ego.
And that's basically why, that's why there's a whole resistance to approach, why guys are feeling bad and, you know, because you know all that shit will come out.
And you cannot hide under the carpet.
If you work on yourself, as you said, on your skills and your kind of beliefs, I come there with a pride.
Look at me.
I can talk about anything.
I can have the most interesting conversation.
Actually, I was so crazy.
Like, my, my, like, in my first four or five years, I was like, like, man scientist.
Like, I, you know, kind of Tesla, like Einstein, like, you know, I was, I was really going beyond and above.
Like, I was subscribed.
I was the only male yearly subscriber to Cosmopolitan.
You know, know your enemy.
I knew all their trends, when the shoes are coming out, which is now in trend.
I knew everything.
Because, you know, look at her.
You were just too dangerous.
I was like, you know, you know how crazy I was.
Like, I would, I, my first, I think, like, you know, I bought, like, you know, voice recorder, this kind of voice recorder for the basic one for the seminars conference.
With the microphone.
Because I was like, okay, why the fuck?
I go out and some conversations, they go amazing.
We start making out and then nothing, nothing, nothing.
You know, like a 10X approach is nothing.
Like, you know, like, or street or cafes, like, you know.
So, I'm like, you know what?
Let me record one week of conversations.
So, I was, like, doing full week talking with 20 to 50 girls per day.
Very good idea.
Okay?
For a week.
On Friday night, I sat down.
I didn't go out.
I opened the Word document and transcribed all that conversations.
I said, she said, I said, she said.
That is a professional.
I said, she said.
Like, 500, I think, 400 or 500 conversations.
I print them out.
I print them and put them on the floor, on the living room.
I spent whole Saturday and Sunday analyzing.
Here I said this, here, there I said that.
Aha, look, when I said this, it got with a phone number.
So, I started, you know, seeing, like, the patterns, and, like, this is how crazy, and this is, like, how scientific I was.
Okay?
Like, you know.
So, yes, I agree, really comes down to two things on the end of the day, like, you know, your inner world, skills also.
You know, kind of, how do you see yourself, you know, because you can approach a girl.
You can go to nightclub and think you are the ugliest guy there, and nobody wants you.
You can, or you can go up to the club and be in your mind, I am the hottest shit here, like, you know, you know, kind of, you want me.
You know, all the girls want me here.
Both these beliefs are equally true and false.
Which one is more useful to believe.
And actually, I came to the point, when I was playing with the beliefs, like, I don't know, six months, like, you know, I really, like, you know, kind of, with every, like, molecule of my muscle, I knew, basically, I was like, you want me.
I would come, I would approach a girl with a mindset, you want me.
And what I usually do, when I bring a girl back home next morning, I'm like, okay, like, you know, I usually debrief.
My sweetest part is, like, our next morning, we have breakfast.
Tell me, when I approach you, what do you think about me?
You know, because then you learn what was good, what was bad, when I said this, what did you feel when I bought you a drink?
You know, her point of view, because then you start connecting things.
And she's like, I don't know why, you know, but the moment you approach me, I want to be with you.
Like, you know, I want to do.
Next week, another one, she's like, same thing, like, you know, because I came to the point where I, you know, basically, my game was not techniques at one point.
It was, I was just testing beliefs.
Can I do it with beliefs only?
And then I had, I had, I had, like, a real crazy research.
At one point, I hired, because I wanted, like, I wanted to learn from others, okay, okay, because, you know, I was, like, pretty much alone.
There was nothing, like, just, that was, like, 1999, 2000.
early, like, you know.
So, I took, I, like, this kind of Sennheiser wireless microphones, so I paid two models from model agency, hired them for a night.
Put them in a nightclub.
Put microphone on them.
It was on Shalata, like, you know, and I still remember, like, it was yesterday, like, you know.
I sat in a car, and I was listening all night how the other guys will approach them, and taking notes, and, like, actually recording, and I was, like, you know, so I was, like, you know, like, I mean, that's how crazy I was, like, you know, but to learn to master this.
I went beyond and above what normal people do to master this area, and that's why I'm today, like, you know, on the top of the game.
And I remember, like, you know, at one point, like, you know, majority of our approach is, like, you know, hey, like, you know, what you're drinking, what such a nice girl is doing by herself, or two girls, you know, like, lame, lame, like, nothing, okay, like, you know.
And one girl, I saw conversation was good, like, you know, but the guy left, you know, okay, actually, no, she rejected him, like, you know.
And I was, like, you know, later debriefing, like, why did you reject this guy, like, you know, kind of, you know, kind of, he liked you, and you liked her.
She's, like, yeah, I liked him, but I felt that he doesn't believe that he deserves me, because, you know, he was, like, thinking, oh, she's too pretty for me.
Beliefs.
She's, like, I felt he believes that I'm way too, I'm out of his league.
If you believe you're out of my league, you're probably true.
If you believe you don't deserve me, why should I think otherwise?
And that's the problem with beliefs.
So, what can, what can a regular guy do, because I suppose that regular guy, you are, you went so deep inside of this, fanatically, with obsession.
We will, we will talk about it, why, maybe if you, if you try to analyze yourself, why did you go so deep inside of this topic, this part of the life.
But, uh, what regular guy is not going to do all of this and he doesn't have to, he doesn't have to.
So what can you, uh, give to, to the guy watching this and listening to, to this, what can he do by himself to uplift his mindset and uplift his skills?
What he can do on a regular basis, because we are the creatures of habits and what we do every day is what, what counts.
What, what can he do?
Okay.
Every single day to uplift his mindset and his skills.
I'll give you a couple of really simple exercises.
And maybe the most important skills.
Okay, sorry.
I'll give you a couple of like, you know, kind of simple.
Okay.
First thing is like, you know, mind map your inner game, your thought process.
Be aware of what triggers what, you know, like it's, it's really like, you know, now we can go, but we know into the science, but like, you know, when you see a hot girl, you know, sit down and write down what goes to your mind.
What's stopping you when you want to.
She's out of my league.
Exactly.
And these are the bullet points.
This is like, you know, gold pit.
The mind will give you, let's feedback.
Mind will give you what's bothering him.
It can be your mother.
It can be like, you know, I remember like, you know, like I want at one point.
Like, you know, 10 years ago, I can start doing some, like, you know, path, you know, create a business that brings the money by itself, passive, you know, passive income.
Every, my project failed.
I tried five, seven, 10 of them.
All my passive profile failed.
And then I went into really deep inside.
Why, why, why?
And in one sessions, I remember my father telling me when I was like a 10 years old, my son, if you want to make money, you have to, you have to work to make money, work hard to make money, work hard to make money.
Money doesn't grow on trees.
Exactly.
And that, until I didn't solve this belief.
But people don't, don't, don't understand how this is important.
How important this is.
Exactly.
Because it blocks everything.
It blocks, you know, it blocks you.
It blocks you, like, you know, and then, so every new, let's go like this.
So mind map, the negative, negative beliefs.
And that level of life will require the new you.
Okay.
When you are, I had a problem with charging premium money for my coaching program, like, you know, for 101.
Like, I think I saw that with myself, these clients didn't come.
The moment I said, okay, like, you know, you know, my price is this, and it's okay to pay this, people start, I started attracting them.
And it was okay for them to pay that price, whatever it is, like, you know.
So it really is, like, really good way to kill it, okay, is to ask yourself contra questions, opposite.
For example, like, you know, the brain is the most moldable, easiest to change, first half an hour in the morning when you wake up, and last half an hour before you sleep.
Because of the mind waves, you know, brain waves.
Reading news or in this kind of, you know, opening phone, reading news portals is the worst, because it all goes into your unconscious, okay.
So if you take these two moments, these segments of the day.
When you wake up before you go to sleep.
First half an hour, last half an hour, like, you know, you can actually mold the brain, okay.
What do you do?
Let's say you have belief, girls don't like me.
You ask yourself, and, you know, and it's a funny thing.
If you ask yourself, okay, why I have no luck with girls, why, your uncles will tell you, because you're fed, because of this, because, like, you know, you don't make enough money.
Because of me, the brain will tell you, if you ask yourself these questions.
If you ask the positive questions, why every girl loves me?
That's very good.
Why every girl, as soon as I approach you, she wants to talk with me.
If I can, if I can get in for a second.
Sure.
So, usually people talk about these affirmations.
And what I heard from Vishen Lakhiani, he is the founder of Mindvalley.
I don't know if you're aware of this company.
They're number one.
Yeah, I know.
I'm not honored.
And he said, affirmations doesn't work, because if you say, I'm, I'm, I'm, I have a big dick, I have a big dick, and then you look down and it's so big.
But if you, he calls this lofty questions.
If you ask yourself, why do girls love me?
Exactly.
Yeah.
Then you try to find reasons why.
Reasons why it's possible.
I'm a guy who works on himself.
I'm the guy who, I'm funny, I'm this.
Exactly.
This is, this is the truth.
And that's how I changed, that's how I changed my whole map.
So, I wrote down everything what was fucking me up, what was blocking me on a piece of paper.
And I wrote opposite questions from, to attack each one of that.
Why I don't feel anything when I, why when I see a hot girl, I feel amazing.
Because, you know, that, that, that's a signal.
It's your girl.
You know, every, you know, why I always have something to say.
You know, I was like running after things to say, like, why I always have something, because like, you know, blah, blah, blah, blah, you know, and your brain will give you, you know, it's such an amazing machine.
We have the best computer attached to our body.
That was ever designed, like, you know, there is a saying, there is a saying, your, your brain is like a supercomputer.
It is.
No, no, no, I'm not saying it, it is.
And your self-talk is the program it will run.
And.
Your self-talk.
It's, it's, it's.
So, what do you say to yourself?
It's one of the programs.
It becomes your, your beliefs.
And your beliefs are the.
So, you can, so I would say what I'm doing now, speaking of seduction dating.
You can use techniques and you can run game based on techniques.
You can go there and make a approach, make a girl's horny and, you know, do the true techniques.
Perfect.
It works.
And that's level one.
You, that will get your results.
Then.
You take those things, techniques, and you create a autopilot game based on beliefs.
That's a true game.
Now, you don't need to think about and analyze everything.
It's kind of autopilot.
It's already in your conscience.
And it just executes.
Why, as soon as I see a hot girl, I go, I start walking towards them.
Because they need me.
That's my mind.
Because, like, you know, you're going to make their day.
You're going to make their night.
You know, you know, they want you.
They need you.
Save them from boring guys.
You know, that's my mind.
You know, how I train my mind.
But what is, with, with all that, sorry.
Like, you know, so it really, it really is about training your mind.
So, this is the first part.
Mind map.
Your thoughts, your beliefs, and try to use this first half an hour and the last half an hour of the day.
And that works.
Try to think about it and try to use these lofty questions.
Why am I good?
Now, there's a problem.
There's a problem.
Truthful reasons.
Some of the guys, it will work for some guys, for sure.
Okay.
Some of the guys, you need.
What can they still do?
Wait, wait, wait.
Some, you know, it will work for some of them.
Some of them, it's not going because they don't have authority.
to, you don't have authority to rewrite your own beliefs.
So, like, you know, there's a whole ego complex.
And I was like, you know, kind of, like, you know, you're not going to allow to, you know,
your brain is not going to allow you to, you know, to change yourself.
Like, you know, this is one of the ways to go around.
Okay.
Like, you know, other way, like, you know, is really like, you know, exposing yourself,
exposing yourself to the certain environments where you can prove it wrong.
You know, kind of go into discussions, you know, kind of, like, you know, prove your brain
wrong.
That everything is okay.
Like, for example, you're afraid to approach girls, you know, you go there, like, and you
do it, you know, kind of fake it till you make it, you know, like, brute force changing
beliefs.
That's, that's how I did it, like, as well, like, you know, kind of, but there's a, you
know, on coaching, that's kind of what, you know, it's hard.
Like, you know, I have more coaching things that I do as a coach to the client, you know,
but it really requires two people, you know, to work, like, you know, fixing yourself.
Some guys can do it.
Some guys have problems doing it.
Like, you know, can you be your own coach?
So, what, what else can they do regularly, day by day, to improve their skills that is,
that are going to help them with women?
Reading, meditation, dance classes, what can they do?
Going to the gym.
Okay, hang out with girls, you know, kind of, okay, like, hang out with females.
Create yourself a social circle.
Surround yourself with girls.
Don't try to sleep with every beautiful girl.
Try to kind of, you know, be their amazing guy.
See, like, you know, learn about them, the habits, the needs.
Be the guy who, you know, who understands, you know, who is, like, who takes care of them,
who takes care of people, be the leader type.
Like, you know, work on yourself, you know.
From meditation to sports, testosterone is really important in this game, okay?
That's kind of something we forgot about.
On the end of the day, it's estrogen needs testosterone.
And testosterone needs estrogen to be happy.
How do you do?
How do you work on your testosterone?
Like, certain foods.
You can Google it, like, you know, which foods boost testosterone.
Enough sleep, workout, heavy weights, like, you know, hang out, you know, kind of being a leader.
Like, and there's a whole thing, like, for example, the way you are sitting, it's lowering testosterone.
Because my balls are hot.
Put ice on them.
Here, like, you know, you're like, you're, you're, you're, you're sitting there, like, you know, bring some ice, like, you know, uh, no, like, you know, like, you know, like, you know, it's really low.
Like, you know, when you kind of closing yourself, they actually, they did measures, like, you know, kind of, you take, like, you know, this kind of beta positions.
You close yourself, they take blood, blood out, your testosterone lowers, like, you, you open up, you use the space, you know, kind of testosterone goes up, you know.
So there is a way, like, you know, to do, you know, kind of, there's a way, like, you better, but workout, hang out with men, do men's stuff, do physical stuff, compete, challenges, gym, red meat, you know, like, you know, old school stuff.
They will produce, that's better, like, you know, you know, that will produce testosterone, you know, and you'll feel better, you'll feel more sexual and, you know, it's, it's a very easy way to project, you know, and to attract as well, like, you know, so, like, I would say, take care of your testosterone, especially today, like, you know, with, you know, with all that kind of food, like, for example, chicken is full of estrogen.
Like, you know, um, so avoiding some of the foods, like, you know, that you eat, like, but there's a whole, like, you know, meal plan to, for having a kind of balanced life and your testosterone, like, you know, there, there are ways, there are ways, like, you know, and it's like, so that's gonna, one thing you can do, like, you know, I would say another thing, what you can do is really, like, you know, self-development.
Work in any areas of your life that you think that you know, like, you know, step out for your body.
One of the good ways is to watch this podcast.
Exactly. Continue watching, subscribe to the podcast, wherever you're watching it now, subscribe and keep watching, develop, keep learning, you know, knowledge, like, you know, skills.
Become a learning machine.
Exactly. Know each skills, like, you know, I mean, have some balance. You don't want to learn, learn, like, you know, use those skills as well somewhere, like, you know, I'm just gonna, you know.
Execute. Exactly. Don't just accumulate, like, you know, experience.
So use them wisely, like, you know, really, like, you know, everything what I did, like, you know, from, you know, martial arts training, to playing ping pong, to yoga, meditation, brain things, I incorporate everything, I use them, all those things on daily basis, you know, in some kind of routine also for seduction, for dating, whatever it is, like, you know, so try to,
Try to, you know, acquire the knowledge, but it's like, you know, can I use the knowledge.
One question is still waiting to be answered, but it's not going to be answered still. The question is, why did you go so deep? And why are you so obsessed about this part of the life? You're going to answer it later.
But first, let's, let us say to the audience, how does your, your regular day looks like? Do you have, because you are working on yourself for decades at the moment, and I suppose that you structured your day or structured your week in some way that is benefiting you to become better every single day.
How does your regular day look?
I'm actually, today, more enjoying the work of my last, of my last, the last 20 years, past 20 years, like, you know, so, because it's not only like, you know, push, push, push, next project this day, like, you know, like, you know, sometimes you can just kind of, you know, take some, you know.
Smell the flowers.
Exactly.
Like, you know, kind of relax your brain.
But yeah, like, you know, discipline, you know, kind of, I would say every morning I try to like, you know, a little bit, you know, kind of be productive, you know, kind of record something, shoot something, you know, learn, develop, like, you know, extend my skills.
Like, I always, like, kind of list things of, like, you know, I'm working on a couple of projects I'm running, you know, kind of couple of things that's making me money.
And always like a two, three projects in a pipeline that, you know, kind of, that will probably, like, you know, make money in the future, need to invest.
So that, like, you know, a little bit of meditation, good food, hang out with good people, girlfriend, like, you know, we do lots of stuff together as well, like, you know, evening gym, maybe some dates with some girls, two of us.
We go, like, you know, friends or something, like, you know, we go with girls, kind of movies, dinner, something, like, you know, always, like, try to kind of push a little bit, like, you know, the comfort zone, do something new, like, you know, nature, you know, balanced life.
I can try to kind of like, you know, build best life.
So what is the balance for you at the moment, work life and relaxing?
I do, I do like, you know, I'd like, you know, four or five hours a day, we're productive, I found busy, I'm morning person.
So I would say like, you know, from 10 till two to lunch.
That's my productive hours.
And, uh, yeah, like, you know, if, you know, if it's needed, like a project, sometimes something big, I'll say like, you know, all night, all day up doing stuff.
But I would say just kind of regular day, like, you know, that's kind of making like, you know, kind of three, four hours of work.
What, what habit would you pick that is the most important to you that you like doing it?
Is it meditation or something else?
Maybe reading?
Do you read?
What habit do you like to do at the moment?
I would say gym.
Gym.
Yeah.
I don't like, you know, kind of last, last few years, like find like myself like really good, like, you know, all that kind of moving from brain to the body, like, you know, pushing it like, you know, actually, what I didn't like, you know, since I'm now back from Brazil, I didn't do much gym.
So now I'm really back into the, into the body thing, I was just kind of being too much capirinias, cocktails, hanging out on a beach.
So these days, it's all about like, you know, kind of going back into that.
And, and I love actually, I love this, I love shooting new content, like, you know, creating, solving solutions, dating solutions that people couldn't solve, like, you know, kind of like I sit down, I always say like, you know, kind of my guys are actually giving me what's new on the market, or I go out there, I still do a couple of approaches per month, just to kind of stay in touch with what's happening, you know, different trends now different, like, you know, kind of, you know, girls are into different things.
So like, you know, it's like trying to kind of use my brain and my scientific craziness, like, you know, to kind of crack what's new and coming for the future generations.
So let's go even deeper.
Okay.
Try me.
The question that, that is waiting to be answered.
I know that you've been, you're also very spiritual guy.
You were experimenting with some alternative states of the mind, for example, let me call them like that transcendence, transcendence practices like ayahuasca, or something like that.
Let's try to combine this ayahuasca ceremony or ceremonies, I don't know how much you, you did of those with the, with this question.
Why do you pursue this calling?
Why, why did you spend last two decades, decades of your life becoming the Michael Jordan of, of dating and seduction?
Do you know, do you have this answer for yourself?
Do you ask this question to yourself?
Yes, like, you know, okay, like, you know, yes and no, I don't know, it's just a calling, as you said, like, you know, it's, you know, actually ayahuasca, ayahuasca opened up my eyes on that, because it was one of my questions to be answered there, like, you know, because it's whole different spiritual where you can connect with your past lives, with your mission, what's my mission?
And basically, it all, it all, it was always the same answer. You are the candle, you are the light, lead them, show them the way, help them.
So, yes, I think that's my mission on this life. And I just felt, you know, when I, when I'm coaching, I feel on fire, I feel like, you know, it's my, it's my thing, I'm, you know, I need to help people, come up with solutions, you know, kind of do what other, you know, what other brains cannot invent, you know,
I would say, like, you know, I don't want to compare myself with Tesla, with all, with all those, you know, kind of geniuses, but like, you know, I can see why they went or like, why, like, you know, Elon Musk wants to get us on different planets.
And like, you know, it's that kind of determination and fire, yeah, like, you know, it's really like, it's beyond logic, it's beyond, it's just something that, that keeps you awake and alert, you have to do it, it's a mission.
You know, it's, if you didn't experience it, it's hard to kind of, to explain it, like, you really, you really feel like, like, you know, I have to do this.
I was doing illogical stuff, like, you know, I'm not, like, you know, kind of, one friend of mine, he was like, you know, I have a group here of the guys in Amsterdam, like, you know, they have problems with girls, like, you know, he was running some group there, like, you know, but, you know, they don't have money,
and we can come up for, like, flight tickets, we can connect, we can collect two, three hundred euros, can you come and close them for a weekend for, like, I'm not sure, like, you know.
Like, it was no problem for me to sit in a plane, just kind of, there was no money, like, you know, I was, like, you know, paying my food, my hotel, everything, they just covered my flight ticket.
And I was, like, you know, taking these 10 guys and turning them into, you know, really amazing men.
So, uh, to answer, yes, like, you know, it's my mission, it's my calling, it's my, it's, it's beyond, like, you know, I love doing it.
And probably that's kind of reason why I still stay even though, so after all those girls, it's not, it's not all the girls.
It's not about the girls.
Okay.
Uh, so, you are, you are one of the avatars of this, of this brand, which is few values, the value of constantly improving yourself, uh, having this growth mindset, uh, doing something that, that puts fire under, under your ass, that, that is a mission for you.
And through that, you, uh, develop this sense of fulfillment, of freedom, and maybe even peace of mind because you are, you are doing it.
So, thank you for that.
Thank you for being an example of how you can really live the life of, of your dreams.
How can you achieve very great, great things?
I would say, like, you know, I'm doing what I love, like, you know, somebody, it's not the money.
The payoff is into the feeling, you know, that I'm getting, like, you know, sort of like, you know, I have no problem flying to another part of the world just to do this, you know, to continue working on that and continue helping people.
So, it really is, like, above that.
Especially when you can, you know, kind of monetize that and live with that, it's kind of like, you know, beyond and above what one can wish.
Do you have some other needs that you can fulfill?
Do you see some other things in life that is maybe that you are curious about, that you can go more into at the moment, or this is the life that you want to continue living?
I came to the point where, like, you know, okay, before maybe, like, whole business, you know, when I was saying I was struggling with the money, but now I would say, you know, your brand and your company comes to the point where, like, you know, it's kind of maintaining and making money.
So, I can now basically, I just, I spent, like, you know, two and a half months in Brazil, you know, on a beach and a nice house, like, you know, so I can be anywhere in the world and live the life I always dreamed of, you know, I was, like, a little boy, like, you know, kind of having a nice car, nice house, if you're bored, pack your luggage and fly to another continent and spend couple of months there.
So, like, you know, it's, you know, living my dreams at the moment.
So, when Rolling Stones or Mick Jagger says, I can get no satisfaction, is this how you can feel sometimes, or does this give you satisfaction?
I mean, it's, like, I would say satisfaction is about really understanding, you know, kind of understanding your needs and fulfilling them, like, you know, kind of, so, like, you know,
If you oversaturate them with stuff, of course, you're not going to feel any, if you're consuming them non-stop, you know, kind of, if you just have, like, a threesomes every day, of course, they're going to be, you know, they'll stop being fun.
And it's not going to give you satisfaction.
But if you're smart about it and you do it, like, once a month or, like, every so and then, it's going to be something you crave for and something that's going to give you amazing satisfaction.
So, it's all about, you know, if you eat your favorite spaghetti or dish every day, you will get, you know, after 10 days, okay, like, you know, fuck this.
Okay.
But if you eat it, like, once a week, it will still be for your favorite dish for a very, very long time.
So, it's, again, it's the brain, it's discipline, you know, know what the fuck you're doing.
So, what is the last advice, maybe, that you can give to the guys, to the camera of yours, before we go apart?
Last advice, like, you know, how much better do you guys have?
Okay, let's see.
Like, don't give up.
You know, kind of, okay, if you're in a problem for dark space, you know, kind of, like, you know, you don't have success with whatever area of your life it is, work on it.
Use, use intelligence.
I really love the movie, Men on the Moon, you know, when they, when the guy started growing, what was the movie name?
Like, you know, when they left him on the moon and, or Mars, and he started growing, you know, stuff.
He, I think that it was called Mars.
The Mars.
That's, you know, that's the mindset.
You figure the shit out.
You do matter.
You use your brain, whatever it is.
Is it the money?
Is it, like, you know, the love life?
You know, use intelligence and your analytical brain to sort it out.
Like, you know, is it your emotions, your traumas?
There are people who can help you, who can lead you.
It's easier with the coaches, of course.
Try everything what you can to fix by yourself.
And then, if you really can figure out something, find a coach, find a mentor who will get to the next level where you want to be, okay?
Yes, but first, you know, try doing it by yourself.
It's much more satisfaction than paying someone to do it for you.
But if you're really stuck, if you, you know, you tried everything, you know, nothing works, then find yourself a mentor, like a coach, you know, kind of who will help you reach your goals.
So, where can people find you?
You can find me on internet.
What's the, what's the best platform?
Okay, like, you know, Instagram, actually, like, you know, it's on a website, badboylifestyle.com.
And, like, yeah, like, you know, that's a starting point.
And, like, you have Instagram and everything there, like, you know.
So, I would say, because I'm on TikTok and Instagram, all social media, Facebook, like, different logins, usernames, so, like, you know, but, yeah, like, you know, badboylifestyle.com, all information is there.
Contact me, let me know.
We have, like, you know, kind of trainings all around the year and, like, you know, kind of some online stuff.
Do you have some next seminar, maybe?
Yes, next one is going to be in Croatia, Split, summer camp, our regular, like, you know, most fun that I'm actually preparing the whole year.
Okay.
Where all my coaches come and we do, you know, hardcore, like, you know.
When is that in Split?
It's mid-August, August 11th until 25th.
Is that Ultra Europe this year also?
Yeah, but I think it's before, like, it's before.
In June, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, that and, like, you know, it's, you know, we do stuff, basically, you know, on other continents.
It's, like, in Brazil.
It's one of my favorite destinations, like, you know, to relax and it's, like, you know, it's an amazing place to, kind of, enjoy life and learn how life can be beautiful and then, actually, you use that, kind of, and then you make it happen in your home as well, like, you know, wants to understand, yeah.
So, bad boy, Daniel, is this the best pronunciation of your, your name, Daniel?
Yeah, Dan, for America.
Dan is easier, like, you know, most people call me Dan.
Thank you, thank you for your time.
Thank you for doing what you do, for being example of, that you can create a life that you want and enjoy it to the fullest.
Guys and girls, I hope that you enjoy it.
Let's see each other again in two weeks and maybe in some near future, even more, more frequent.
Enjoy.
Thank you as well.
I can think for inviting me.
Pleasure.
Hvala.