One example is the famous story of Nestorius, who was declared a heretic at one of the early councils of the churches, because he couldn't make it, he couldn't get there in time, his church couldn't send representatives, they're dealing in three different languages, he said something, wrote something in one document that was a bit ambiguous about the nature of Christ, but all of his other writing is so classical, so orthodox, and shows that what he said here might have been, you know, a twist of words or something like that.
Well, the council having only one sentence said, heretic, gone, done. Having now resource to all of his stuff, the churches, as it were, reintegrated in the stories into the orthodox community, the warm relations between the churches that were, that considered themselves a story of churches and all that. Well, that's the research that you can do quickly, go through all of his literature, arrive at something. We had another girl here from Syria. She was studying manuscripts.
And she discovered that one manuscript that had been attributed to a certain author, was not, could not have been his, it had to be someone else. And she could tell by the quality of the language, and then even date things within the text.
Well, again, it was the digitized process that allowed her to see that quickly, rather than having to read through 400 books and go to Paris and go to different countries and compare the volumes.
Fr. David, Matthew, it's a real pleasure to be with you this morning. We're here in Rome as we get ready to launch the Alexandria Digitization Hub, which is a huge project that you guys have been working on for a very long time.
Fr. David, if I may begin with you, can you share the genesis of that project and your collaboration with Matthew?
Sure. It's a series of births, in a certain sense. It didn't start out as one idea, and then we were moving the train out of the station to arrive at another location.
For us, the library of the Orientalia, the Pontifical Oriental Institute, is unique in the world. There's no library anywhere that covers all of the Eastern churches.
So, the Eastern churches, which come out of Constantinople, the first church in Jerusalem is an Eastern church, and so on.
So, our library covers all of the churches, and when you say it covers all of the churches, it means it covers languages, it covers history, it covers politics.
Very often, the first thing that was written down was the Bible in another language, or translated.
When missionaries went from one country to another, they had to translate the Bible, they had to structure even the alphabet in different languages.
So, the Bible's become great sources of language, language development and structure and all.
So, we have quite a number of academics, researchers that come to the Orientali to use the library, the resources of the library.
We have students, it's basically a graduate school, but the concern was not many can come to Rome for a week or a month and use the resources.
Isn't there a way to make these resources more available?
And we're talking about a geographical area from Russia to Ethiopia, from southern Italy to southern India.
That's where the Eastern churches are, but even Western churches, bishops, scholars are interested in these resources.
So, my first interest was to digitize the books, get the books online for our students, our past students, for researchers, for scholars.
We could even have a combined thing online of several scholars studying a manuscript, that would be an excellent thing.
We have perhaps 500 manuscripts in the library.
So, that's how it began.
And we found some friends and benefactors, much of it through Matthew's help and inspiration.
People came here, sent big scanners.
People came from New York, experts in digitizing, and began the process of digitizing our own publications.
And it was kind of magical.
Like, in a certain sense, it was simple what they were doing.
High-density photographs of everything they were digitizing, 600 dpi, we could reduce to PDFs and make them available.
But immediately, there was the question, it would be nice if these could be researched by Word and not just pulling down a book or pulling down an article.
So, as we went on digitizing, we bought a scanner, we got another scanner, and we had two people hired to scan more and more books.
And then, we were looking initially at one set of software that was being developed that would allow researchers to do research on a manuscript.
But it was really with the arrival of AI that transformed our possibilities.
So, first, getting the text off of a PDF onto a computer language that could be easily researched by Word without errors.
But then, our library has, I don't know if it has 20 or 30 languages in it, ancient languages, modern languages.
And so, if you want to research something, you want to cross the languages.
So, we might have the works of John Chrysostom in four different languages.
And even that has a value for scholars.
How do they translate this word into another language?
Again, when you look at history, the arguments over the interpretations of the nature of Jesus, of the creeds,
A word like person in English, in Italian, sounds pretty straightforward.
But the word persona in Greek means, it can mean the mask that you wear in a play.
So, is that the best translation to make?
So, you see the debates of scholars from 1,000, 1,500 years ago trying to deal with these changes.
Well, again, to be able to put these things online, to use AI technology so that you're vectorized,
you're looking for concepts rather than words in one language.
So, you take the word nature or person and conceptually you translate that into all of the languages that are available to the AI program and you search through the entire library.
So, the richness for research and for analysis is really quite extraordinary.
Wow.
That's so inspiring.
And then, Matthew, when Father David came in with this goal of digitizing the patrimony of the church
and making the content and the books available from the Orient High to the students around the world,
what were some of the technical challenges that you faced?
Well, I mean, I think when we started the project, we weren't thinking so big as like the patrimony of the church.
I mean, that's something that we now are focused more on.
But, yeah, initially it was just, let's just try and make sure that these resources in the Eastern church are made more available.
And then, you know, there was always the idea that if it worked, then we could expand it.
There were a bunch of technical challenges.
I mean, you know, one is the books themselves and, you know, Father David can speak more to this than I can.
But, you know, many of these books were very different from each other, right?
Some had very delicate bindings, you know, some of the more modern books, not so much.
Some of them are very large books, some of them are very small.
And so, you know, as much as possible, you want the robot to do most of the work here, right?
With the arm, which, you know, the robot arm, which turns the pages and does the scanning for you.
So, we're trying to automate the process as much as possible, kind of reduce the human in the loop
and just to allow us to increase the rate at which we're scanning.
But obviously, you know, every time you change the book out, you have to kind of redial in, you know, the robot
so it understands what kind of text it's working with so it can effectively turn the pages.
So, I know that was a challenge.
And I know that the two lovely women who work in there have become something of experts at kind of sizing up books
and learning how to dial in the robot.
So, there's still very much like a collaboration between, you know, the robots and the human beings at this stage.
But, you know, the hope is that we'll be able to figure out new ways and deliver kind of new technologies into the hub,
which will allow for further and further automation.
So, we're less dependent upon people, you know, in this process and that will allow us to scan more.
So, I would say that would be one technical challenge that continues to this day.
I will just say that we're starting to look at some interesting approaches.
I'm sure some people may have seen some articles about how laser technologies and, you know,
kind of like CT scanning are being used to kind of see through books and especially like manuscripts,
which are very delicate, right, which they're afraid to kind of open up for the purposes of scanning.
And so, there's new technologies on the scene, I think, that show a lot of promise,
which would allow us to scan the books without actually having to necessarily open them up and turn the pages,
which in some cases could damage them.
So, I think the future is very bright for digitization.
I'd say that the second kind of biggest challenge was, and fellow David kind of spoke to it,
is how do we extract the information from the pages and then make sure that,
because, you know, OCR, optical character recognition, which is something anyone uses Adobe PDF,
yeah, is familiar with because it's what allows you to take an image and then allow it to select the text, right?
That's because Adobe programs, you know, run this optical character recognition on it, but it's a bit flaky, right?
So, if you were to go in and, like, copy all the text from my PDF document, typically, and paste it into a text,
it's a bit of a mess, right?
There can be all kinds of weird characters in there.
There's no formatting.
And I'm talking about, like, kind of, you know, these are kind of more simpler problems.
For more complex text, there can be all kinds of artifacts and things.
And so, one of the human-in-the-loop challenges was that somebody had to go,
as they were trying to extract information from the PDF, and clean it up.
You had to kind of clean up all the noise.
And in many cases, you had to kind of label the text, you know, what's a header, like, what's a footnote.
You kind of had to put that information in.
And you had to do all this labeling before you kind of would go through this process of then, like, digitizing it.
And I say digitizing kind of in a classical sense, not in the AI sense.
And so, what we were trying to figure out is, is there a way that we could run this extraction
and basically bring AI into the game so it could actually handle all the cleanup, all the labeling of, you know, the text,
and then also handle automatically this process of converting it from first to kind of vector embeddings,
which kind of makes this text language agnostic for people to query.
And then finally, to a format called TEI, which is like an archiving standard, which is kind of a rich metadata format.
This is all to say that this whole process of figuring this out was something that we felt if we could crack this
and have AI do this part of the job, this would allow us to significantly speed up digitization,
mainly because there's a lot of scanned content around the world, scanned for archival purposes,
but there's never been extraction run on it, which means you couldn't really effectively query it.
So, if we figured if we could be focused here on this particular problem, this could allow us to unlock all those PDFs,
which is just kind of sitting around for storage purposes.
And today, we've been able to pretty much automate that process.
That's extraordinary.
And, Father David, of course, the library is at the center of the university and the educational programs
that your students from around the world are coming.
How has this project impacted their studies, like making these texts available for students who, for whatever reason,
might not be able to attend class or come to Rome physically?
How has this digital documentation interacted with them?
And also, where do you see this going?
How do you see this impacting their studies in the future?
Well, one of the things that we had to consider quickly was pedagogy,
because obviously a concern would be plagiarizing, which is always a concern anyway.
But now, you can cover your plagiarizing pretty quickly.
So, one of the concerns of the Vatican, which heads all universities that have a Catholic name on them,
are under the general auspices of the Dicastery for Education at the Vatican.
And it tries to oversee and promote certain aspects of education.
And one that it likes to guarantee is interpersonal stuff, so that not everything is online,
not everything is at distance, not everything is through your computer screen,
because there is something that a mother communicates to a child that a book on mothering doesn't communicate to a child.
So, and questions and answers, that kind of interaction.
Well, what this process did was it made it more important to have more meetings between professors and students.
So, a student would present their doctoral project, their doctoral proposal.
And that's a fairly articulate process.
They have to have a bibliography and a direction to go.
A board of professors sit with the student.
They work it out, approve it, or change it, whatever.
Then the student has to return after the first piece of research and say,
if the student is writing in Italian and you know the quality of the person's Italian,
and now the student is writing like Dante.
Knowing the student, you know what's happened.
So, when you have regular meetings, instead of waiting until the dissertation is finished,
you can challenge the student with the content that the student has written.
Do you understand what you've written?
What are the implications of this?
And so, you have a more interpersonal focus in the educational process,
and the student has to defend.
Even if they've used whatever AI tools, the student has to defend what he or she has written.
So, oddly, the technology has improved human communication,
which is the last thing we always expect with AI and digitization.
Another benefit that it offers is there have been mistakes made academically in the past
for clear reasons that can now be researched in a more clear, concise, and quick way.
One example is the famous story of Nestorius,
who was declared a heretic at one of the early councils of the churches
because he couldn't make it.
He couldn't get there in time.
His church couldn't send representatives.
They're dealing in three different languages.
He said something, wrote something in one document
that was a bit ambiguous about the nature of Christ.
But all of his other writing is so classical, so orthodox,
and shows that what he said here might have been, you know,
a twist of words or something like that.
Well, the council having only one sentence said,
heretic, gone, done.
Having now resourced to all of this stuff,
the churches, as it were, reintegrated in Nestorius
into the orthodox community,
the warm relations between the churches
that considered themselves Nestorian churches and all that.
Well, that's a research that you can do quickly,
both through all of his literature,
arrive at something.
We had another girl here from Syria.
She was studying manuscripts,
and she discovered that one manuscript
that had been attributed to a certain author
could not have been his.
It had to be someone else.
and she could tell by the quality of the language
and then even date things within the text.
Well, again, it was the digitized process
that allowed her to see that quickly
rather than having to read through 400 books
and go to Paris and go to different countries
and compare the volumes.
That's extraordinary.
And then, Matthew, as we get ready to, you know,
start to really maximize the hub
as the scanners come in
and as they start to really,
the work comes underway,
what is that going to look like?
Can you break it down
and kind of walk us through those steps?
Sure.
I mean, so we embarked on this kind of proof of concept,
you know, I think it's almost a couple of years now.
So we had this kind of robot scanner.
We had this kind of high-end manual scanner
for more delicate manuscripts.
And we really just want to kind of push the technology
to see how far we could get with it.
And so, I mean,
we still think there's a long way for the hardware to go,
but certainly the robo scanner is helpful.
So we said, okay, so it's working.
We need to figure out this whole digitization process.
And that's kind of the last year
what we've been really working on
is how far can we push AI
in this whole automated ingestion process.
And I think we've got close to cracking it.
There's still some work to do, obviously.
You know, Father David mentioned to it.
I mean, one of the unique challenges
in this ingestion work is, you know,
some of these books have languages
which are ancient, right?
And so what this means effectively for AI
is the AIs are not able to embed them,
which is basically kind of convert
to map the text semantically effectively, right?
and basically convert it into math
that the AIs can read and understand numbers.
And that's mainly because embedding models
are trained on large corpuses of data
like large language models.
And if their training data,
the distribution of the training data
doesn't consist of large swaths of that,
of let's say a particular language,
it's just not capable of effectively embedding it.
So that's not to say that the AIs are useless at it,
that they may still get it 50% or 60% correct
because they can look at, you know,
the relationship between other languages
and they kind of make inferences.
But there's still a long way to go there.
So I think for most of the conventional languages
that are spoken today
and some of the ancient languages like Latin and Greek,
you know, the AI process
is still working very effectively.
So, and I think that in and of itself
is going to be enormously beneficial
is considering specifically
because the church's historical language
has been Latin,
so there's a lot written in it.
But I think there is an opportunity here
to kind of tap into these experts
in these ancient languages
and help them to kind of develop training data sets
so we can kind of trade into basic,
trade a better embedding model,
which is more capable of understanding these languages
and therefore mapping them more effectively.
So that's a research project
that I'm looking forward to embarking,
you know, with the Pontifical Universities in Rome.
But so the immediate next step is
let's get more scanners.
Let's just speed this up, right?
There's a lot of books here
amongst the Pontifical Universities.
I mean, the Gregorian and the Orientality
and the Biblical Libraries alone
are absolutely massive.
So we knew we needed, you know,
two scanners would not be near enough.
So we bought another five scanners.
So we'll have a bunch of robots in there
and working away.
And I still consider this
a kind of a proof of concept.
And the idea is that
we're going to have a webcam on the studio
so people can actually watch the books being scanned
and hopefully we'll have it in inventory
so people can kind of check
where their book is in the scanning queue
and see when it's going to be scanned.
And we think that'll be kind of fun.
But the idea is we want to show people
what this process consists of
and get them excited about it.
And I think it's especially like exciting
because when a book is on the scanner that day,
as soon as a scanning job is done,
it takes sometimes an hour or two
to process all the information.
And then it's immediately available
to, you know,
any of the users within Vulgate
or if the book is,
if the university has decided
they want to open source that information,
it can be made available to,
you know, millions of the users
through Magisterium AI.
So this is quite extraordinary
to think that, you know,
a book that was just literally scanned
by a robot within a few hours
is then able to anyone in the world
to scan it and drive insights from.
So, and I think once people realize,
you know, ultimately what this will mean
for scholarship,
and I think just generally,
you know, generally,
just for even, you know,
for us ordinary folk, right,
who are just looking for some insight
from the church to help us
in our day-to-day lives,
I think it will garner
a lot of attention.
And then what we're hoping is
we can do is we can then raise
potentially some funds philanthropically,
you know, maybe from the grassroots,
from some donors and foundations
to expand the scanner fleet
and hopefully invest in development
of even better hardware.
The final phase that I'm looking forward to,
and I say final in quotation marks
because I don't really know
where this project will ultimately go,
but obviously having the hub
in Rome is exciting.
There's a lot of libraries,
a lot of content here,
and we will be scanning for years,
but there's obviously,
there's great repositories
of information,
materials that should be scanned,
documents, books,
all over the place.
So the question is,
how do we get the scanners to them?
And so one of the things
we're looking at now
is kind of the development
of a flying hub
where we kind of build some scanners
which are a little bit easier
to kind of take apart
and reassemble,
and that way the scanners
can go to the works,
and that will allow us
to get our hands on more and more.
It's extraordinary.
And then Father David,
I mean, we know that
there's so many resources,
there's so many important books
and documentation here in Rome
working, you know,
within the pontifical university system.
This is something that,
you know, from my eyes
seems like it's very much
at the forefront.
It's an innovation.
It's something that I don't know
of any other university doing this.
What has it been like for you
bringing this mission,
bringing this, you know,
this really unique and new idea
to the pontifical universities
and to the Eternal City,
which does not have the reputation
for always being
the quickest adapter?
Well, it is true.
When we were conceiving
some aspect of this project,
the first books
that we were digitizing
and how can we access them,
I looked around the world,
Europe and North America,
at big universities
that had resources,
and nobody had a program
that could do anything better
than OCR reading
of a PDF file,
which shocked me.
I mean, we're not heavily funded.
we don't have
$15 billion in reserve
as a lot of universities,
bigger universities would have.
So, but at the same time,
I was concerned that
the church should be
on the cutting edge
of this stuff.
So, again,
it's just,
it's providential,
it's serendipitous.
Matthew and I knew each other.
Here we had other people
who were interested,
people offering their scanners
for this trial experiment
sort of thing.
So, even though
the AI technology
is changing rapidly,
digitizing technology
is changing,
it could be more rapid,
but it's changing.
It's important
for the church
to be on the forefront
of this kind of thing,
even to give direction
about where it should
or shouldn't go
is one thing.
To be making
its resources available,
I mean,
the church is about
the gospel,
which is the word
and communication
and creating community.
So, the more broadly
that we can do that,
the better it is.
I wouldn't say
it's a risk,
but it's a kind of
a nervous excitement
that the technology
is changing so quickly.
We would not have imagined
where we are today,
say, two years ago.
That's for sure.
And the rapid changes
in AI,
the first AI program
was magical.
Wow, it can do this.
The second iteration
was, wow,
now it can do this.
And then the third,
duration.
So, we're chasing something,
but we're chasing something
that makes sense,
that already has a fruit,
you know.
So, and who knows
where it'll go
and Matthew was mentioning
that languages.
We study here some,
let's call them
weird languages,
dead languages,
Nimidian,
Skobodian,
that you could,
all of the people
that can read these languages,
you could put into
one small classroom,
you know,
and yet important documents
are written
in these languages.
Now, they have languages today
that share the same root,
but how do you understand
that language
in its context
only through other literature
that are certain,
which is again,
the importance of having
not just scripture
in that language,
but all the other books
of politics
or whatever,
geography, science,
from that language
understand the connotations
that are in the word
at the time.
and the latest programs,
Google is very big in this,
but not only Google,
is analyzing a language
that nobody really knows
with the benefit
of languages
that have already been studied,
ancient languages,
and giving indications
how to break down
this language
and how to understand it.
So again,
even that sort of thing
is very informative
for the kind of research
that we're doing here.
So,
being at the forefront,
kind of being
at the cutting edge,
introducing these new technologies
in a way that is having
absolute good,
absolutely good results
and not worrying about
are they going to clone babies,
are they going to scan dogs,
you know,
or something like that,
but showing that good examples
of how the technology
can be used.
That's extraordinary.
And then, Father,
speaking on that potential for good,
we know that, of course,
you know,
if you just turn on the news today,
there's obviously lots of conflict,
lots of tension,
and of course,
in the oriental,
you know,
kind of sphere,
there is tension,
and violence and stuff.
With the AI being able
to help with documentation,
communication,
clearing up
and making,
you know,
evident aspects
of translations,
traditions,
and just making that scholarship
available on a global stage,
it seems like the potential
for ecumenical dialogue,
interreligious dialogue,
you know,
true scholarship across bound
is,
it seems like the potential
is immense for that.
Can you speak a little bit
on that importance
and how this technology,
the scanners,
the hub,
Magisterium AI,
you know,
is going to be able
to contribute to that?
Yeah.
It's strong and it's weak
at the same time
because a lot of it depends
on human beings.
So if human beings
don't want to,
they won't.
If human beings
are presented
with the truth
they don't want to hear,
they won't listen.
So that's there.
But on the other hand,
the other aspect
is absolutely true.
once it's there
in reliable documentation,
in demonstrable fact,
once it's there
historically
and anybody can look
at it and research it,
it is harder
to get away with a lie.
You still can,
but it's harder
to get away with a lie.
And people of goodwill
on both sides
of an argument
will find that.
And the example
I gave of the churches
having come together,
that this happens,
you know,
once the ground is clear.
But the, you know,
the problem
is always human beings,
you know.
And, but again,
the opening up the truth,
opening up the facts,
they become harder
and harder to resist
when they're broadly available
and not just locked
in the library.
And Father,
can you share a little bit
on how your students
are interacting
with these digitized documents,
how, you know,
maybe in the classroom
or if they're going abroad
for a visit
or for, you know,
an exchange program,
how is,
how is this digital,
you know,
technology coming
into the classroom
in a practical sense
and helping them,
you know,
on their everyday studies?
Yeah.
I would say we're still
early in that.
And obviously,
the younger generation
is much more adept
at the technology
than the professors
who are in the classroom.
So the,
I would say right
from the beginning,
three professors
were gung-ho about it.
The other 50,
well, you know,
and then ironically,
COVID came
and then there were
major conversions
among the other professors
when they saw
what the technology
could do,
both the visual technology
in the classroom
and then the access
to books.
So I would say
as it's still
in a kind of
experimental stage,
not in the sense
that it's an experiment
that we'll reject,
but we're learning
as we go
and for the professors
to learn
how to integrate
digitized resources
into study processes,
into textual research
and all of that
and affirming
or having cautions
or challenging students
in this or that direction.
And again,
more and more students
wanting to come here
to have access
to the resources.
But we're still
at a learning stage
of how better
to make these things available.
For example,
one thing that we couldn't
do so easily before,
we would have to have
a conference
and bring in
a bunch of professors
from around the world
to study a manuscript.
and now they can
do that online.
They can make a copy
of a certain text.
All of them can annotate it
in their various languages
and have this kind
of visual discussion
over a text online.
We'll back and forth
with it.
The document is saved
with all the annotations,
come back to it
in a week.
So the possibility,
that's already there,
but the possibilities
for enhanced,
high-end academic research
on documents
is really,
really quite rich.
And Father David,
can you share
a little bit
about how you've transformed
the Pontifical Oriental Institute,
brought, you know,
new technologies,
made, you know,
recording,
digital access
to the classrooms,
if you could share
that for our audience.
There are funny things
with technology.
When I was in Canada
and I worked
with native people
on a reserve
in northern Ontario,
and all of a sudden
mobile telephones
came out.
And I grew up
in Toronto,
and here with the irony
was that everyone
in Toronto
had a mobile phone,
had a phone,
stationary phone at home,
and a network of phones
in their office,
and we were up
in the bush
and have no way
of communicating
with one another.
You have to drive
two hours
to give a message
to someone.
And that's where
the technology was needed,
not in the city,
but so it's now everywhere.
But there was something
similar here
is that at universities,
I would say generally,
but maybe more specifically
in Rome,
come to us
and you can enjoy
our resources,
which is easier said
than done
for like 99%
of the world.
So again,
the whole thing
of when I came here,
there was not much
technology in the building.
Just in principle,
I wanted to have
technology,
modern technology
in all of the classrooms.
And again,
I could find
some resources
to get this done.
Again,
I would say
most of the professors
here said,
well,
if he can do it,
okay,
we're not going
to stand in the way,
let him go ahead
and do this.
And again,
two or three
loved it,
saw the advantage
of using it.
And we were using
Google and Google
for education.
And the professors
who could understand
the technology quickly,
they enhanced
learning for the students
right away
in the classroom.
So we put in
television screens.
We don't have
any overhead projectors
anymore,
but it's all
large screens
in the classrooms.
We brought in
Google technology,
microphones,
and speakers.
And if it was
a big classroom,
we might have
six sets
throughout the classroom.
If it was a smaller
classroom,
there might be
two sets
of speakers
and microphones.
And again,
there was high quality
stuff that Google
was producing.
And then you run
into other things
that some classrooms
had an echo
in them.
Again,
these buildings
are of a certain age.
One part of the building
that we're in
was built
in the 15th century.
So you have
to think of
how can we
retain the architecture
and yet update
the whole stuff.
So there are
people around
who know
this kind of thing.
We had two classrooms
which professors
refused in principle
ever to use
because there was
an echo.
And we had experts
come in
and they said
in these two classrooms
there's a reverberation
of more than
three seconds.
Now you think about it.
The students come
from around the world.
They're studying
in Italian.
For a lot of the students
it might be
their fifth language.
The professors
come from around
the world.
The language
that they're instructing
in is Italian
and it might be
their third
or fourth language.
So the professor
is speaking
with an accent.
The students
are listening
with an accent
and there's
an echo
in the room.
So again
we brought in
these experts
and it's
incredibly inexpensive
to do this
and even aesthetically
you can do it
well.
So we put in
sound absorption
panels
aesthetically
on the walls
and in the ceiling
and changed
the lighting a bit
and one professor
who said
he would never
teach in that classroom
said
now this is
my favorite classroom.
I spent half
of my life
in classrooms.
I never said
I had a favorite
classroom
but now
even students
were reacting
to that.
So we studied
color.
We studied
light intensity
and so they say
500 lumens
per square meter
is ideal
for study
and research.
The colors
that aid
conversation
life
energy
are yellows
and oranges
and reds.
So we repainted
everything
without toxic
chemicals
in the colors
and again
you could see
the difference.
So even
business technology
will talk about
creating a space
of joy.
So I don't know
how many students
get up and say
oh boy
I'm going to class
today
but you do
create an environment
that is enjoyable
to be in
and the chairs
are comfortable
to sit in
the colors
keep you awake
you can hear
everything that's
being said.
Another funny thing
that we put
into the main
conference room
was this is
when Matthew
first came
was we teched
up the main
conference room
so with all
the standard
technology
and all
but we put
in five
rotating cameras
and one of
the curious
things with
this was
just interesting
to see
on the big
screen
and of course
we're connecting
with the world
those who wanted
to see the thing
online
but the cameras
would then rotate
around the
conference hall
so students
and professors
who were sitting
and listening
would have the camera
on them
all of a sudden
so what was
one of the effects
less sleeping
during conferences
and all that stuff
so there was
a fun aspect
there was an
academic aspect
energy aspect
to the study
and all
and then
when as I say
when COVID
came along
Google again
did as many
companies did
a generous
thing
they allowed
the full
extent of
Google Plus
Education Plus
for all
Google Education
users
which means
that you can
record the
sessions
without having
to pay extra
for our students
that was really
quite rich
because they
could listen
to the lecture
a second time
in Italian
and pick it up
whatever they
were missing
and what we
found was
they came back
to the next
lesson
full of clear
questions
and the professors
themselves were
shocked
all of a sudden
the students
are intelligent
but they had
the chance
to listen to it
a second time
so again
you're going
to say
this is
technology
pretty basic
pretty simple
but it transformed
the quality
in the classroom
and professors
commented on that
the work
the students
are doing
is better
the papers
they're writing
are better
the instruction
is better
they're coming
back with
better questions
so again
you saw
the intelligent
use of technology
had great
human effect
it's about
the human being
the human context
if it serves
that
it can do
a great job
and then it was
just step by step
from that level
of technology
kind of very
human quality
of technology
to the next step
that we're
talking about here
so you just see
this multiplier effect
and again
as I would say
the church
is the group
that the church
is created
for good
it should be
on the cutting
edge of using
this stuff
for good
showing others
the possibilities
that's in the
technology
that's so extraordinary
and Matthew
working in the
tech sphere
and kind of
seeing also
how quickly
this is evolving
and hearing
from Father David
that these
changes are
radically transforming
in such a positive
way
the learning environment
and the educational
format for students
from around the world
where do you see
this technology going
I mean we see
so you guys
are digitizing
books
and bringing that
and vectorizing
and making that
knowledge base
available to the world
what other plans
do you have
where do you see
this going
in the coming years
well I mean
I think ultimately
I mean Father David
said it
I mean what we're
really trying to
figure out
is what is the
kind of most optimal
way
one to kind of
disseminate this
information
and make sure
it's practically
useful to as many
people as possible
I mean this is
this is kind of
what really drives
the company
the quest to build
and scale
Catholic AI
which is our
primary mission
and us we had
a secondary mission
to digitize
the patch
with the church
because that
serves the primary
mission
this is really
just about making
sure that
all of this
great insight
right
that you know
very few of us
got a chance
to go to seminary
or get a you know
master study
study theology
and philosophy
right
and so we know
the enormous
benefit
that comes
from taking
that time away
to study
these things
and for a lot
of people
never had that
opportunity
it's very
unfortunate
and in some ways
this has been
kind of a very
clerical lay
divide
right
and so
what I see
is a real
kind of exciting
opportunity here
is by making
all this information
available
distilling it
for people
is that
we can kind
of close
that gap
a little bit
right
so anybody
who's got
you know
questions
existential
wants to
probe
church teaching
more deeply
well now
they have a place
they can go
and they can
do that
right
and the AI
can patiently
work with them
right
and they can
move at
their own pace
and this is
something
when we talk
about like
the future
next steps
one thing
I'm really
excited about
is the
opportunities
for AI
to actually
be able
to kind
of adapt
its pedagogical
approach
for each
student
right
to help
them learn
more effectively
and I think
you know
if you think
of the old
traditional
paradigm
I think
we actually
go way
back to
University
of Paris
I think
when Thomas
teaching
is very
different
but in
modern
paradigms
you maybe
have
you know
in maybe
a high
school
you got
50 students
one teacher
they have
a curriculum
they need
to teach
and they
do their
thing
right
they teach
that
curriculum
and of course
those 50
students are
really pretty
unique
they're all
different
places
so sometimes
that particular
way of teaching
is not overly
effective
maybe for some
but not for
everyone
and that's
just
unfortunately
that's just
the best
way to be
able to do
you know
ideally I think
everyone would
prefer that
there was a
much smaller
you know
teacher
to student
ratio
right
so they
get more
personalized
education
but how
do we do
this
it just
seems
practically
ineffective
well
now with
something
like AI
we can do
one to one
right
in principle
if you have
a curriculum
and you provide
the AI access
to it
and you use
something like
voice mode
because a student
can actually
talk to and
interact
you know
with the AI
and the AI
can actually
kind of teach
and based
on how the
students
receiving
and being able
to you know
explain
the concepts
back to the AI
can say
is this working
or isn't it
my pedagogical
approach
until it
finds one
that works
really well
so like
there are
leaders like
Khan Academy
like Sal Khan
who've been
demonstrating
how this
technology
can be used
to kind of
really lift
people out
of poverty
Khan Academy
is an
incredible
example
and it's
very very
it started
you know
it's very
very big
in India
and I
think
the Catholic
Church
which has
been a
pioneer
in education
right
since
its very
beginning
there's a
real opportunity
for us
to kind
of establish
ourselves
as a leader
again
by
because
primarily
because we
don't look
at education
as a
business
right
I mean
this is
something
we're doing
is something
to advance
the common
good
we care
about
the human
person
and so
we can
afford
to kind
of
move
those
business
incentives
aside
the economic
incentive
aside
even
the political
and ideological
things aside
and say
listen
ultimately
what we
want
is for
every
person
to
flourish
so
what
tools
and
technologies
what
approaches
can we
use
to most
effectively
ensure
that
that's
the outcome
and so
because of
that open
mindedness
first approach
to education
I think
that there's
a real
opportunity
for the
church
to be
an early
adoption
of this
technology
and to
demonstrate
its
effectiveness
one of the
great
advantages
of what
we're
talking
about
in terms
of the
AI
technology
is that
it's
we're
talking
about
a closed
system
of research
so
what do I
mean by
that
if you're
the
magisterium
site
or the
Vulgate
site
you're
not
getting
what is
Uncle
Bob
thinking
about
Jesus
now
you know
you're
getting
the classic
texts
the teaching
of the
church
and so
it's a
reliable
source
of
research
and the
second
thing
is
people
would
worry
about
well
if AI
is
teaching
me
am I
going
to go
astray
well again
this is a bit
the challenge
putting together
a thing
but on
the other
hand
you say
do all
of us
believe
everything
that every
teacher
has told
us
from the
beginning
to the
end
that no
teacher
has ever
made
a mistake
well
welcome
to life
you're
going to
hear
different
sides
and different
opinions
but it's
the human
being
that has
to put
the pieces
together
you know
so
there's
a challenge
for these
technologies
that we're
talking about
to make
them as
reliable
intelligent
as possible
to serve
human
human beings
but not
to be
too
preoccupied
about
is there
going to
be a
mistake
here
or a
mistake
there
if I
decide
to do
some
weird
thing
because
of
something
I
saw
on
YouTube
there's
something
wrong
with
me
there's
not
something
wrong
with
the
technology
you know
and
father
David
how do
you
see
education
changing
as
we
continue
to
progress
into
the
AI
era
there's
a lot
of
students
who are
in high
school
now
they're
working
on
things
they're
trying
to
secure
their
future
work
towards
getting
a
job
and
of
course
that
landscape
is
changing
how do
you see
the role
of
education
the role
of
universities
changing
to
guide
form
students
but also
to prepare
them
for
what
could
be
an
uncertain
and
somewhat
daunting
future
but also
one that
has
the
potential
for
more
time
to
study
form
to
all
the
upside
as
well
I
don't
know
how
well
universities
can
do
that
there
is a
certain
aspect
where
universities
are
reactionary
something
is going
on
now
we'll
study
it
then
maybe
we
can
work
on
a
solution
but
to
prepare
in
advance
for
it
we
don't
know
I
don't
think
universities
and
schools
are
best
adapted
to
that
again
and
we
don't
know
what
the
next
five
years
of
this
technology
will
bring
certainly
a
preoccupation
is
the
job
market
what's
going
to
happen
with
so
many
jobs
with
advances
in
AI
and
all
this
stuff
and
one
of
the
classic
principles
of
Catholic
education
has
always
been
the
development
of
the
human
being
so
it's
the
full
development
of
the
human
being
so
it's
being
abreast
of
what's
going
on
is
my
identity
attached
to
technology
or
am
I
getting
too
depressed
about
something
that's
going
on
the
creativity
of
the
human
being
entering
this
world
with
creativity
energy
looking
for
new
possibilities
it
isn't
the
first
time
that
we're
going
through
kind
of
a
social
upheaval
and
so
it's
going
to
ask
for
mature
people
to
face
this
with
honesty
to
walk
through
the
fears
and
the
preoccupations
and
the
concerns
to
maintain
a
level
of
justice
and
the
classic
example
that
where
there
were
no
labor
laws
you
could
be
forced
to
work
hours
a
day
at
years
of
age
and
all
this
so
it
took
a bit
of
time
to
catch
up
with
that
to
create
the
laws
systems
ages
age
limits
for
work
and
retirement
ages
and
all
that
took
most
of
the
20th
century
to
refine
pension
laws
came
in
the
mid
20th
century
health
care
universal
health
care
came
in
after
the
second
world
war
in
many
countries
so
this
stuff
you're
reacting
to
so
as
best
we
can
prepare
the
human
being
for
facing
the
current
day
without
fears
over
concerns
or
preoccupations
of what
or
might
not
be
but
to
enter
it
with
courage
and
imagination
I
think
that's
the
best
that
we
can
hope
for
from
education
and
I
think
this
might
be
an
opportunity
universities
right
I
think
too
much
even
Catholic
universities
have
given
way
to
this
pressure
right
that
you know
the
purpose
of
a
university
today
is
for
you
to
achieve
a
degree
right
to
get
a
piece
of
paper
so
that
you
can
qualify
for
a
job
right
and
then
so
you
need
a
job
because
you
need
to
get
a
mortgage
right
and
then
you
need
to
be
able
to
have
money
in
education
supposed
to
be
about
right
and
I
think
for
if
you
look
at
like
when
I
was
going
through
high
school
I
think
probably
a lot
of
people
can
share
this
experience
I
you
have
to
be
reasonable
in
your
expectations
so
I
feel
like
that
universities
can
get
back
to
what
they
are
supposed
to
be
doing
which
is
basically
focus
on
helping
people
develop
and
so
in
some
ways
I
think
this
requires
some
pedagogical
changes
I
mean
in
one
regard
I
think
a
lot
of
the
teaching
will
probably
happen
between
the
AI
and
the
individual
mainly
because
the
AI
is
probably
more
effective
at
it
but
that
doesn't
mean
that
the
classroom
is
no
longer
useful
I
think
absolutely
it
still
will
be
it's
just
that
the
nature
of
the
classroom
I
think
will
probably
change
right
and
instead
of
that
being
a
place
where
information
is
basically
downloaded
to me
and we
all sit
there
quietly
and make
notes
in our
books
it'll
be
a
place
where
I
can
having
digested
all
of
these
insights
and now
having
effectively
understood
them
better
because
I've
worked
with
AI
to
make
sure
I
can
go
into
a
classroom
environment
and share
them
with
others
and we
can
actually
look at
problems
together
and I
can hear
other
people's
opinions
and
insights
and I
can
actually
learn
how that
process
should
be
done
how do
I
respectfully
ensure
my
ideas
are made
known
and how
I
respectfully
listen
to
others
ideas
how do
we
effectively
work
together
constructively
on
problems
so I
think
if
the
classroom
starts
to
resemble
that
more
I
ultimately
think
that
will
help
a lot
with
the
socialization
skills
which I
think
are becoming
increasingly
more difficult
to instill
especially as
people are
most of
young people's
lives are
mediated
through
devices
and actually
I think
practically
that will
help
prepare them
for the
job
market
whether
someone
has a
degree
or not
matters
to me
less
and less
as time
goes on
what I
care more
about
is
is the
person
a good
and honest
person
are they
a hard
worker
and when
they're
working
as part
of our
team
how effectively
do they
work with
others
and so I
think if the
classroom
environment
focus on
honing more
of those
skills
that actually
will
effectively
prepare them
better
for the
job
market
well that's
very exciting
and also
kind of
wild to
think about
you know
students
gene
and being
able to
really focus
on those
core values
and those
core skills
Matthew
as you know
we prepare
to launch
the
Alexandria
digitization
hub
and we
you know
two scanners
coming in
we have a bunch
more coming
in
it seems
as we're
scanning more
it does seem
still that we're
at the tip
of the iceberg
how much
more work
do we have
to do
to digitize
the patrimony
of the church
I mean
how many
books are
we talking
about
you know
hopefully
in the
next few
years
how does
that look
like
for our
audience
who you
know
wants to
keep up
to date
with that
progress
well I
mean
you know
I think
it's
hundreds of
thousands of
millions of
books
I mean
so the
patrimony of the
church is
not small
so in that
respect it's
daunting
it'll take
a lot of
time
but I think
it's worth it
I mean
so and again
we have to
like
it's important
to approach
this
there's
kind of
critical
doctrine
and dogma
right
there's
the works
of the
fathers
church
and so
that's been
our primary
focus
and we're
getting deeper
and deeper
into that
I feel like
by the end
of the summer
we'll probably
have the
collective works
of all the
fathers and
doctrines of
the church
made available
to anyone
in the world
in their
own language
for free
which is
pretty exciting
we already
have kind
of core
metasterial
teaching
is in there
now we're
going back
to the more
ancient
popes
and trying
to digitize
their kind
of ancient
writings
and their
ancient
encyclicals
and things
to ensure
that their
voices are
added to
the modern
magisterium
so I think
in the next
year
we'll get
a lot
done
but one
thing that
kind of
excites me
about this
project
and you
get this
experience
like when
you walk
into one
of these
libraries
is you
know
that a
bunch
of those
books
haven't
been
open
in 100
years
and if
you
were
to ask
the librarian
what's
in that
book
I mean
they could
tell you
what the
title is
right
who have
a lot
to say
even to
our
contemporary
world
but because
nobody knows
what they
have to say
because those
books haven't
been opened
unfortunately
their insights
are just
kind of
lost to
us
and so
what I'm
excited about
is this
process of
digitizing
these books
and then
of course
making them
available
through tools
like
what's
kind of
really
exciting
to me
about it
is that
somebody
may be
asking
a pretty
typical
theological
question
and because
we've
now
digitized
these books
these people's
insights
those insights
can now be
brought to
bear
they may
start
popping up
in unusual
places
and so
it almost
increases the
surface area
for research
which is
exciting
I think
for academia
but it also
ensures that
those insights
may be
particularly
useful to
someone
right
and so
that could
help them
hopefully
constructively
in their
life
and it
may lead
to devotions
you know
to some
of these
scholars
and we
may have
to
revalue
the work
and say
actually
that their
contributions
are much
more
significant
than we
thought
and maybe
we spend
more time
thinking about
it
right
and so
there
could be
more
spiritual
devotions
and more
research
that happens
as a result
and Father
David
how do you
see
you know
bringing
to the
modern era
all these
writers
that have
you know
have
kind of
been
falling asleep
for the
last couple
centuries
if you know
if these
books
haven't been
opened
or if
you know
scholarship
focuses on
a specific
niche topic
at this
moment
how do you
think it's
going to
inform
the dialogue
within the
church
and the
dialogue
with the
wider
society
having
all these
voices
kind of
coming up
to air
now
well
I think
you can
only help
because
there's
to make
an analogous
comment
a country
that has
only two
or three
political
parties
only represents
the people
that have
those kinds
of opinions
but if
you're in a
country
with a hundred
million people
you probably
need more
opinions
than two
or three
to cover
what the
people are
about
so same
thing here
there's
a democratic
factor
in this
the more
people that
have more
access
to more
resources
letting people
develop along
the spirit
of their own
genius
their own
interests
and all
it enhances
social
conversation
it enhances
the possibilities
for broader
justice
broader
human
understanding
whether it's
ecumenism
among
Christian religions
or other
religions
or even
just other
ideological
groups
other nations
other
countries
it just
enhances
those
possibilities
because it
doesn't limit
the people
this is always
a criticism
of a
classroom
is that
classroom has
bright students
not so bright
students
and a bunch
in the middle
people interested
in physical
labor
people interested
in that
well the
classroom
one teacher
and 50
students
can only
represent
kind of
one basic
position
this kind
of structure
allows for
many
kind of
geniuses
minds
interest
to be
expressed
and
developed
so
it
enhances
social
conversation
that's
fantastic
and I guess
my last
question is
how do we
think
for the
wider
church
as this
technology
continues
to bring
more and more
of these
arguments
to light
and shares
them around
the world
what are
your hopes
for the church
adopting this
more widely
more broadly
there's many
many
pontifical
universities
around the
world
there's
universities
around the
world
who might
not have
access
to this
yet
what are
your hopes
and dreams
as we
look towards
the future
well I
mean
the last
number of
years has
given indication
that it's
foolish to
make long-term
plans
you know
beyond three
months we
just don't
know what's
going to
happen out
there
so in
one sense
it's
running
with this
you know
there's a
title of
a book
I think
in the
1960s
are you
running
with me
Jesus
you know
and it's
with devotion
with faith
with all
goodwill
to run
forward with
this stuff
to use
as best
we can
but for
me to
predict
we wouldn't
have predicted
three years
ago that
we would be
where we
are now
with the
digitizing
project
so to
imagine
in the
future
I'm not
sure if
that's the
best question
to ask
it's a
logical
question
to ask
but how
do we
live fully
in the
moment
that we're
in
you know
it's
kind of
that for
me
I have
to agree
I think
that what
we should
be doing
now
is
thinking
about
I think
I'm hoping
that with
this new
pontificate
this is
becoming
more central
focus
is
constituently
what needs
to be in
place
in order
to ensure
that people
flourish
and then
we kind
of work
backwards
and say
how can
this new
technology
now
and possibly
in the
future
help
contribute
to that
flourishing
and I
think
if we
think of
it more
like that
given the
power of
this technology
and the
import
now that
it's going
beyond these
AI systems
disembodied AI
systems which
live in large
computing clusters
to now being
embodied in
robots
meaning they're
actually able to
physically interact
in our world
we start thinking
about the import
of that
it's going to
touch every
facet of society
right
so if we have a
clear understanding
of where
human beings
should be headed
how this technology
can help enhance
flourishing
that we can make
sure that we're
basically focusing
our society's resources
and developing
the technology
in a way
that will
optimize
flourishing
right
as opposed
to
impede it
right
by you know
like one
thing I get
concerned about
is you know
as AI robots
get deployed
more and more
it's likely to be
the case people
have more time
on their hands
and I think
that's a good
thing but for
many people
it could actually
not be a good
thing it could
end up impeding
the flourishing
because they
may choose
to use that
time to do
nothing but
game right
or spend time
in VR worlds
spend more time
on their devices
or God
willing God
forbid looking at
porn or something
like that I mean
so so I think
you know given
that that's likely
to be the outcome
for a lot of
people I think
it's really it's
critical for us
in the church
to remember
you know the
it's a you know
flourishing but
also the importance
of evangelization
right we have to
make sure that
we're the gospel
we're finding new
ways to deliver
the gospel in
ways that are
effective
we have to
find ways to
reach those
people who
maybe who
don't know
about the
gospel and
and the
benefits of
a Christian
way of life
how enriching
it is because
maybe they've
never seen it
or it's never
explained to
them if we
do that more
effectively then
people won't
just kind of
like by
default end
up disappearing
into these
virtual gaming
worlds simply
because they
don't know
what they're
supposed to be
doing with
their lives
right because
they haven't
had a chance
to discern
what their
gifts are and
figure out how
to put those
gifts in the
service of others
and of God
and so this is
why I think
is being
someone who
was working
technology now
for a good
period of time
I get very
hopeful about
the future
of it but
one of the
things I get
concerned about
is just how
do I
effectively
deploy the
technology
and how do
I even make
a case for
it and so
when you meet
people like
Father David
who are very
open-minded
who understand
the problems
and are willing
to try new
things out
it's exciting
because then
you get a
chance to
show people
to demonstrate
that that can
work and
ironically
maybe this is
not entirely
fair to say
but I have
found in
Rome in
particular
seeing is
believing
at least when
it comes to
technology and
things and I
think so the
more that we
can demonstrate
the benefits
of the
technology
people can
come and
they can
see it for
themselves
they can
interact with
touch with
it I
think the
more likely
it's likely
to scale
and be
adopted
elsewhere
and that's
one of the
reasons why
I'm so proud
of what
Father David
has done
at the
Pontific
Orientals
to do
because it
stands in
Rome
as probably
one of the
most advanced
universities
probably in
Italy
and that was
in large part
because Father
David just
looked at
the problems
and saying
how do we
do this
and anyway
I'm very
encouraged that
he's now
in a position
that he can
influence more
institutions now
and I'm seeing
a lot more
other Pontific
Universities
get excited
and be more
willing to
adopt the
technology
I think we're
going to be
seeing great
things
Matthew
Father David
thank you so
much for this
very inspiring
conversation
Thank you, Ben.
Thank you.