[SPEAKER_02] Pope Francis used that term. He says this is an exciting technology,but also a fearsome technology.So it's okay to have that fear,but that fear sometimes comes from ignorance.So if we can defeat ignorance,then we have a chance to move from something that could be potentially harmful to something that could be really harnessed for good.
[SPEAKER_01] Edmundo and Edmund,it's a real pleasure to have the opportunity to speak with both of you today.Just kind of starting out,I know that both of you come from strong ministry backgrounds.Edmund,I know that you worked in parish ministry for quite a while.Edmundo,I know on the diocesan level in Detroit,you worked in communications.If you guys could share for our audience who might not know so much about you guys,how did those experiences shape how you see technology's role in the church today?And maybe Edmundo,we can start with you.
[SPEAKER_02] Edmundo, Well thank you so much Benjamin,I'm so happy to be here and with Edmund as well.He's a close collaborator and a friend and yeah we're happy to be here.Yeah,that's a great question.So I was in college during the digital revolution,the first one.So I got to witness firsthand the excitement around technologies.We would call them emerging technologies at that time.And in fact,I said that's a great question,I said that's a great question.
[SPEAKER_02] I was studying economics and I switched to communications because of the excitement that I had with these new technologies and it just sounds funny now when you say new technologies emerging technologies and you're referring to the internet and email.But it was like mind blowing.It was the time where,yeah,just things were changing and very,very quickly.So at that time I was 17 years old.I switched.I had a powerful encounter with the
[SPEAKER_02] Lord. I went to this retreat and had a very, very powerful encounter with the Lord. And I felt
[SPEAKER_02] called to be at the intersection of technology and media and evangelization from the very, very
[SPEAKER_02] beginning. So that's been always part of who I am and what I do with my career. And I've been
[SPEAKER_02] very blessed to be able to serve the Lord in that intersection. So at that time, again, I was
[SPEAKER_02] young. I was looking at all these technologies. And one of the things that I was always so, it was
[SPEAKER_02] always so encouraging to me was the approach of the church, that it was never, it was always
[SPEAKER_02] providing wisdom on how to navigate this changing world. But it was always very hopeful. It was about
[SPEAKER_02] how can we use these technologies to advance the mission of Christ in the world? And that was a
[SPEAKER_02] type of framework that was reinforced in me at a very early age of always thinking about technologies
[SPEAKER_02] and emerging technologies and media as a tool that we can harness for good and for the mission of
[SPEAKER_02] of the church. There are obviously things that we need to be careful about and we need to use our
[SPEAKER_02] discernment. But that was always the voice of the church from the very, very beginning. We're talking
[SPEAKER_02] about mid-90s and it continued until now with different things that the popes and the magisterium
[SPEAKER_02] are, you know, the church magisterium is teaching us on how to navigate these and how to be careful
[SPEAKER_02] about it. So, but it's always been like that. It's always been in my heart, the desire to leverage
[SPEAKER_02] technology and media to evangelize. At the heart of it is, you know, the gospel is a story. That's the
[SPEAKER_02] best story that can be told. The best story that has ever been told and can be told. And I always wanted
[SPEAKER_02] to use media and leverage media to tell that story to the world.
[SPEAKER_01] Edmund, if you could share a little bit about about your background and how your experience working in parish
[SPEAKER_01] ministry has has informed how you see technology being utilized and harnessed by the church.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, I had 10 years in parish ministry experience and I started out as a youth minister. So,
[SPEAKER_00] for me that meant having a pretty tight budget and having to do a lot of, to wear a lot of different
[SPEAKER_00] hats. So, when you're in that situation and you're kind of brave enough to experiment with different
[SPEAKER_00] tech or software tools and things like that, that was definitely something I did. And so I think it
[SPEAKER_00] shaped me by, on the one hand, like teaching me how to be, yeah, I guess scrappy and test things. But I
[SPEAKER_00] I think it also showed me that, you know, the technology is like, if I'm working on something
[SPEAKER_00] the night before and then I'm in front of people the next day, it's very quick to figure out like
[SPEAKER_00] what works and what doesn't with, with people, you know? And so I think it helped me always place
[SPEAKER_00] like the person at the center of any technology or thing, you know, software app that we were using.
[SPEAKER_00] If it's not going to be helpful for ministry to other people, then yeah, it just gets thrown out really
[SPEAKER_00] quickly. So I think those two things, there was a lot of testing, experimenting and
[SPEAKER_00] um, just seeing what worked and what didn't. And I think I still kind of have that mentality
[SPEAKER_00] with the different tech and tools that I use today.
[SPEAKER_01] What can, what can you share about your experience, you know, in parish ministry and working, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] with, with young adults, with, with, with adults. And of course, you know, with younger people, like
[SPEAKER_01] has technology become something central to almost every interaction or are there certain
[SPEAKER_01] core interactions, core aspects of that ministry that, that even if we'd like to offload it to
[SPEAKER_01] technological, you know, efficiency or whatever, like it is centered around the people and that community.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. I mean the, the technology, I mean, it's, it's, uh, what is it? There's the Marshall McClellan
[SPEAKER_00] quote, quote about, you know, fish didn't discover water. Like, like it, it's just such a part of our
[SPEAKER_00] culture that even if you have teens or parishioners who aren't actively power users of technology,
[SPEAKER_00] the whole culture is, is, or has been impacted by technology and these tools and these, these
[SPEAKER_00] inventions. So, um, yeah, it was a part of everything. And I'm, I'm sure both of you have
[SPEAKER_00] heard so many stories of different parishes or ministries or even ministers who, um, kind of,
[SPEAKER_00] you know, looked back lovingly on the days before all of these technological inventions.
[SPEAKER_00] And then they kind of got left behind in the sense that it was really hard to communicate.
[SPEAKER_00] It was hard to relate to people who this is part of their whole world. Um, you know,
[SPEAKER_00] they might be with the church one or two hours a week and then all the other hours are spent
[SPEAKER_00] in a, in a culture and in society. Just, I mean, technology isn't just a part of that society.
[SPEAKER_00] It, it like is society. Like it's, it's such a, a core part of the fabric of what we experience day
[SPEAKER_01] to day. Um, and then Ed Mundo, maybe to, to, to jump to you. Um, you know, the late Pope Benedict
[SPEAKER_01] the 16th spoke about the digital continent and the need to evangelize that, that continent. And Pope
[SPEAKER_01] Francis of course spoke a lot about, um, about evangelizing online, you know, using even the word,
[SPEAKER_01] the term digital continent. Um, where do you think we are as a church? Are we, are we pioneers
[SPEAKER_01] on the digital continent? Are we settlers? Are we still tourists? Um, what, what's your gauge on that?
[SPEAKER_02] Yeah, that's a great question. Um, I love that, um, phrase from Pope Benedict because it helps us
[SPEAKER_02] think in missionary terms, right? Uh, in our duty to carry a message, a message of hope,
[SPEAKER_02] a message of, of, of life, right? Into a place. Um, interestingly, the, the, the church has evolved
[SPEAKER_02] in the way that they talk about, uh, digital in general. Um, with, with Pope Benedict, um,
[SPEAKER_02] we got that, that phrase to the digital continent. Again, I think it's very helpful in, in, in many
[SPEAKER_02] ways and I love it so much. Um, but you see a change with, uh, from then to Pope Francis and now with,
[SPEAKER_02] with Pope Leo where the church understands it a little bit different and more along the lines of
[SPEAKER_02] what Edmund was saying. Uh, they use the digital culture instead of digital content more, uh, now,
[SPEAKER_02] um, in, in church documents. Um, so it, it kind of makes sense if you think of it.
[SPEAKER_02] Um, Pope Benedict, um, and, and that generation and I'm part of that generation too, even JP too,
[SPEAKER_02] we were immigrants, right? Coming into these digital continents, right? We were, we were,
[SPEAKER_02] it wasn't something that we grew up with, but we had to learn how to be in it. Um, and then you have
[SPEAKER_02] millennials and younger, right? Who are digital natives. And the church speaks about these two
[SPEAKER_02] groups of digital migrants and digital natives. Um, but for digital native natives, as Edmund was saying,
[SPEAKER_02] this is, this is everything they know. Um, and it's not like you can opt in or opt out. It's just part
[SPEAKER_02] of the culture. It's part of where we are. Um, so good things about the concept of a digital continent is
[SPEAKER_02] the idea of being missionaries, of knowing that we are going into a foreign place to bring a gospel,
[SPEAKER_02] the gospel message, a message of hope and in life that people need to hear. Um, so that's super
[SPEAKER_02] helpful. The digital culture, um, language helps us understand that that is not something that we can
[SPEAKER_02] avoid, but this is where we're immersed. And this is what people are experiencing. It's part of their
[SPEAKER_02] ecosystem, their ecology, uh, that they are a part of. So, so that's, that's, that's a more nuanced, uh,
[SPEAKER_02] concept where regardless on your use of technology, you could be a heavy user or not. Um, in terms of
[SPEAKER_02] digital tools, you're still part of these new digital culture. Um, you know, good news is that the,
[SPEAKER_02] the gospel, the good news are truly good news. And, and this is what people desire and, and crave. Um,
[SPEAKER_02] I find it very interesting. You know, you see all the, all the data, uh, from this year in terms
[SPEAKER_02] of the interest in the Catholic faith, you know, that, that has been registered in Google searches
[SPEAKER_02] and so forth. Um, it coincides with these new digital revolution connected to artificial intelligence.
[SPEAKER_02] So, so we see, we see two things happening here. We see the increasing in curiosity for, for the
[SPEAKER_02] faith. Uh, and then we see a world that is becoming more and more technologically complex
[SPEAKER_02] in advance. So, so we see the two things happening. I don't think it's a, uh, coincidence. I think it's,
[SPEAKER_02] it's connected. I, I think as people are more and more part of this digital culture, um, there is a
[SPEAKER_02] desire for true encounter with, with God and, and, and, and true understanding of what human, human, um,
[SPEAKER_02] um, what we are as humans. So I see the two of them very much connected. So for me, this is a springtime
[SPEAKER_02] of evangelization. This is the continuation of second Vatican council and all those promises,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, so 50 plus years after, you know, I think this is a time where we're going to see a lot
[SPEAKER_02] of opportunity, um, in the church because of these technological changes and what they bring to our
[SPEAKER_01] culture and the questions that they pose. Um, how do you see AI helping parishes, um, serve people better?
[SPEAKER_00] Well, I mean, I think part of the problem right now is that we're not seeing a lot of parishes using AI,
[SPEAKER_00] but I think, um, you know, one of the really, uh, one of the strengths of AI is its ability to take
[SPEAKER_00] lots of information and, um, synthesize it, organize it, things like that. So, um, I think the first thing
[SPEAKER_00] I come to, um, when I'm talking to someone who's not super familiar with AI, but is in ministry
[SPEAKER_00] is, uh, not what they would expect. They would expect often people go and try to use AI and they
[SPEAKER_00] just type in like, write my email for me or something like that. There's so many other tools
[SPEAKER_00] that can take information. For example, notebook LM is one that I refer to a lot because you're able to
[SPEAKER_00] upload lots of information. You could, you know, 10 church documents or a bunch of, um,
[SPEAKER_00] catechetical resources and then organize that information in interesting ways. So, um, and
[SPEAKER_00] especially moving into the, the age of AI, um, information is not, uh, the, the end all be all
[SPEAKER_00] anymore. The, the valuable thing. It's more like the medieval times, right? It's how you combine
[SPEAKER_00] information. Like we said at the beginning, like to be useful to other people. So there's lots of ways
[SPEAKER_00] that, um, yeah, AI makes quick organization and accuracy and things like that really useful. Um,
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, Mundo talks a lot about this really shifted my entire worldview on, on just ministry
[SPEAKER_00] in general talks a lot about the difference between like mission support and mission direct.
[SPEAKER_00] And so I think there's a lot of opportunities in the mission support category for behind the scenes,
[SPEAKER_00] analyzing data, getting more accurate information, and then also like personalizing
[SPEAKER_00] how someone like the minister or, um, someone being ministered to like accesses that information
[SPEAKER_00] and data. So that's often the first thing, um, I turn to because it's a lot easier to kind of wrap
[SPEAKER_00] your head around is this like organizing processing information in more useful ways.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, Edmundo and Edmund, could you guys break down what is, what is mission support and mission
[SPEAKER_01] direct? Edmundo, go for it.
[SPEAKER_02] Edmundo: Yep. Um, happy to do that. Um, when, when I was working at the Archdiocese of Detroit,
[SPEAKER_02] we came up with this system or the Archbishop came up with this system of, or framework to think about
[SPEAKER_02] the work that we do, um, as a diocese, you know, as a local church. And, and, and we had these, uh,
[SPEAKER_02] kind of division of labor, right? We have the mission support area, and then we had the mission
[SPEAKER_02] direct area. Um, but mission support are all those, um, um, you know, for us, we're departments,
[SPEAKER_02] but functions, that's probably the best way to think about that, that are not doing mission directly.
[SPEAKER_02] They're not impacting mission, but they are supporting mission or there is slowing down
[SPEAKER_02] mission or making mission less, less, less effective. So that would be, uh, areas like
[SPEAKER_02] finance, HR, technology, um, that in, in, uh, you know, they are not necessarily ministry,
[SPEAKER_02] but if done well, um, you can really enhance ministry. So for mission support areas, would you
[SPEAKER_02] want to look our, for our efficiencies, right? How do, how can we do these in a better way,
[SPEAKER_02] faster way? Um, so that we can free up resources, both monetary resources, but also time to do more
[SPEAKER_02] mission. And the mission direct area is, is, is everything that we do as a church that, that is,
[SPEAKER_02] that is the mission. So that would be Catholic schools and the ministry that we have and teaching
[SPEAKER_02] children and teaching adults to, um, the, the work that we do, you know, evangelization in the
[SPEAKER_02] parishes, all the sacramental, uh, component of a parish. So that would be the, the, the mission
[SPEAKER_02] direct. And in, in, in those, uh, you really don't, you're not looking for, for efficiencies
[SPEAKER_02] as much as, as effectiveness. Are we, are we, um, doing mission in a way that is, is accomplishing
[SPEAKER_02] our, our goal that people know and love the Lord that they can encounter Jesus. So, so, you know,
[SPEAKER_02] when we have this division, you know, there's efficiencies in one side, which is the most important
[SPEAKER_02] part of it and effectiveness on the other side of things. Um, and both are connected. You need
[SPEAKER_02] efficiency and effectiveness in both areas, but, but it just allows you to think differently
[SPEAKER_02] about ministry. So when I think about artificial intelligence, it's like a no brainer to incorporate
[SPEAKER_02] artificial intelligence in, in all of the mission support, um, areas in a parish or in a diocese,
[SPEAKER_02] because, you know, you want to free up resources. You want to have, uh, the ability to invest those
[SPEAKER_02] resources, other things that, that are mission direct, uh, time and, and, and people, personnel,
[SPEAKER_02] and also, um, um, um, you know, uh, monetary resources. So that's a no brainer when it becomes
[SPEAKER_02] more of a, where the, where people need a lot of more wisdom and discernment is on the mission
[SPEAKER_02] direct. How do you incorporate AI on the mission direct? And I think people that that's where,
[SPEAKER_02] where there's a lot of, um, uh, concerns, I would say from, from the local churches and,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, priest pastors a lake, so ministers and lay leaders, um, that's where, where we're trying
[SPEAKER_02] to figure out how to do it. Um, there are, there are frameworks to think about that. And we can talk
[SPEAKER_02] about it here, um, that can move you from fear to confidence and from fear to, um, hope in, in this
[SPEAKER_02] age. Um, but that's, I think where, where the big conversation is happening right now and where people
[SPEAKER_02] are, are concerned about it. Um, and, and, and I think sadly, part of the problem is that people are not
[SPEAKER_02] talking about it openly. Um, because I think that it's more like, you know, you're a AI user,
[SPEAKER_02] but, but you don't want to tell people because you're going to be seen as, as not, not putting
[SPEAKER_02] people at the center and not having the human flourishing and the human person at the center.
[SPEAKER_02] So you're kind of doing it, but, but isolated instead of having learning communities, uh, where
[SPEAKER_02] we're talking about how to do these in a way that advances the mission of the church. So I think that
[SPEAKER_02] that there's a need for a greater conversation and openness about how do we use this technology
[SPEAKER_02] for good. And, um, and that's, you know, I need to, I need to find the exact quote, but,
[SPEAKER_02] but what stuck with me is that these aren't like talents, you know, when we talk about the parallel
[SPEAKER_02] of talents that have been, uh, provided, you know, in God's providence have been available to us.
[SPEAKER_02] And then we need to think about how to use information. So I, I encourage a greater
[SPEAKER_02] conversation in pair settings and dial settings for, for how do you incorporate AI on this mission
[SPEAKER_02] direct and mission support. It should be all about implementation, like best practices. I mean,
[SPEAKER_02] companies are doing that, like that's an, that's, that's an easy win for a lot of, a lot of parishes.
[SPEAKER_02] And if you think of parishes, you're thinking about entities that have limited resources. Um,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, I love the definition of a pastor is someone who is overwhelmed, uh, understaffed, um,
[SPEAKER_02] um, and on, uh, underfunded, you know, and, and, and that's a reality for most of the pastors. So
[SPEAKER_02] incorporating AI and mission support should be a given. Now that the fun conversation,
[SPEAKER_02] the interesting conversation is how do we incorporate it into mission?
[SPEAKER_01] I have sensed that feeling that, um, that a lot of people are using it, but they just,
[SPEAKER_01] they don't want to say it. And I think that with more honesty, that would be a beautiful thing,
[SPEAKER_01] which is obviously what we want to do with Catholic futurist. Um, but Edmund, um, I think for, for a lot of,
[SPEAKER_01] of, uh, of our viewers and myself included, I don't, I don't know that much about what goes into
[SPEAKER_01] organizing a parish.
[SPEAKER_00] Everyone in the parish boundary is a member of that Catholic parish, meaning that everyone Catholic
[SPEAKER_00] or non-Catholic is, is part of that parish boundary, which means that that's, that pastor's
[SPEAKER_00] responsibility on behalf of the Bishop and Jesus to, to evangelize, to, to make disciples, to, to give the
[SPEAKER_00] the sacraments. Um, so then the pastor goes, man, there are tons and tons of people in this parish
[SPEAKER_00] boundary. Well, um, there are Catholics that show up for worship and they're part of the Christian
[SPEAKER_00] community. And hopefully they are also involved in this task of evangelization, the parish boundary.
[SPEAKER_00] But again, like, um, in today's day and age, these parishes are, are rather large. Even the smallest
[SPEAKER_00] parishes that you could think of is hard for the pastor to be available for all of his people at all
[SPEAKER_00] times. And so, um, you know, decades ago, there was this, you know, more formalized, uh, movement of
[SPEAKER_00] formalizing positions of volunteers who volunteer voluntarily get involved in the mission of that
[SPEAKER_00] local church. And then we started seeing them like professionalizing of these roles as, you know, this
[SPEAKER_00] lady got more and more, um, educated as like, they get, they get more training, they get more
[SPEAKER_00] formalization around that, which is a great thing. So, um, you have in lots of dioceses parishes that
[SPEAKER_00] have some level of paid staff, although, um, admittedly a lot of, I mean, it varies widely. Like
[SPEAKER_00] there are parishes that have very few paid staff. So, um, you know, to avoid getting too much into like
[SPEAKER_00] the canonical and theological aspects of it, like what goes into the parish is the pastor and either,
[SPEAKER_00] you know, paid staff or a combination of paid staff and volunteers, like cooperating with
[SPEAKER_00] the laity, um, to, to accomplish God's plan for, for our salvation in this local area. So there's
[SPEAKER_00] kind of those three areas. You have the pastor, the lady, and then the geographic location, the mission
[SPEAKER_00] territory. Um, there, there, there's other things involved as well, but like focusing on that for
[SPEAKER_00] our conversation here, like that's really the basic elements that we're talking about when we talk about
[SPEAKER_00] this parish community. Um, and, and I think most parishes don't, don't spend enough time thinking
[SPEAKER_00] about the people that don't show up, especially in the U S church. If we're talking in particular about
[SPEAKER_00] that, um, because for so many years we had this, um, assumed cultural religiousness or assumed cultural
[SPEAKER_00] Catholicness. Um, and so lots of people talk about, you know, people leaving the church and the Catholic
[SPEAKER_00] church, um, in, in droves. And so there really is this, uh, we've, we've gone from, there's a book, um,
[SPEAKER_00] from Chrysostom to apostolic mission. And I believe is the name of the book, but it's this
[SPEAKER_00] idea that like, we no longer live in the, in a civil, we live in a post-Christian civilization and
[SPEAKER_00] culture. So there really is this pressing need. Um, you know, as the popes recently have talked
[SPEAKER_00] about this, the past couple of popes, like this need for this new evangelization, this re-evangelization
[SPEAKER_00] of our parish boundaries. And so like Amunas, I love Amunas said, you know, like we would,
[SPEAKER_00] we would be disappointed. We'd be embarrassed if we don't use the tools that we need in youth
[SPEAKER_00] ministry circles. This came up a lot, you know, there'd be this kind of shame of like,
[SPEAKER_00] well, Jesus didn't use PowerPoint or Jesus didn't have to use slick t-shirts or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00] And I remember sometimes I would just quip like, yeah, Jesus didn't have PowerPoint graphic design
[SPEAKER_00] or toilet paper. I would like to use toilet paper. Who among us would give up toilet paper? Like,
[SPEAKER_00] like, like it doesn't, it doesn't mean that, um, the things he did not use is a normative rule that
[SPEAKER_00] he's imposing on us. Um, so anyway, so that, that's kind of what, what actually was really exciting for
[SPEAKER_00] me was being in these places that Pope Francis and Evangelii Gaudium talked about. These can be like
[SPEAKER_00] places of great creativity precisely because of their flexibility and their localness and, um,
[SPEAKER_00] Um, the way that the people there can be plugged into the local culture and community.
[SPEAKER_01] What opportunities do you see that aren't being, that aren't being taken on a practical level where
[SPEAKER_01] you, where you look at a diocese or a parish and be like, okay, I see the opportunities, but the staff
[SPEAKER_01] is not using this tech or they're not seeing how they could make their life easier in this way.
[SPEAKER_01] And technology is really built for that. We need to create a, a framework where people can have,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, in a safe and productive way, these conversations. So the leadership needs to provide
[SPEAKER_02] that framework or that sandbox for people to feel comfortable and safe, to be able to experiment and,
[SPEAKER_02] and be creative and, and, and use these, these technologies for good. So, so the question shouldn't be,
[SPEAKER_02] how can we protect ourselves from this technology, but how do we use this technology
[SPEAKER_02] to facilitate human lives? Um, so that we can spread the gospel, to build community, to witness for
[SPEAKER_02] Christ. So, so that's, that's the type of spirit that we should have, not one about defending ourselves
[SPEAKER_02] from these, uh, fearsome technology. Um, Pope Francis used that term. He says, this is an exciting
[SPEAKER_02] technology, but also a fearsome technology. So it's okay to have that fear, but that, that fear sometimes
[SPEAKER_02] comes from ignorance. So if we can defeat ignorance, then we have a chance to move from,
[SPEAKER_02] from something that could be potentially harmful to something that could be really harnessed for
[SPEAKER_02] good. So, so providing a framework, I think should be the most important thing. And I think the Vatican
[SPEAKER_02] is going to come with, with a document. I think what Lee is working on something that's going to help
[SPEAKER_02] us, but, but even if you look at, at the things that are out there already, you can come up with that
[SPEAKER_02] framework. So, so using, um, so Pope Leo already wrote, um, the, the World Day Communications message
[SPEAKER_02] that is going to be published next year in 2026, in February 24th, in the Feast of St. Francis and
[SPEAKER_02] Sales, I believe. Um, but, but it's always published before where it's, it's made public now. So even if
[SPEAKER_02] you take some of that, um, uh, message about preserving human voices and faces and other documents,
[SPEAKER_02] you can start putting together a framework that creates these safe, safe sandbox for us to
[SPEAKER_02] creatively, um, advance the mission of the church. So, so just things that come to mind that could be
[SPEAKER_02] part of that framework, you know, um, human dignity needs to be at the center and it's not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_02] So we can evaluate a technology with simple questions. Does this uplift human dignity or is
[SPEAKER_02] it diminishing it? Right? So there's a way for us to create that safe sandbox by asking the,
[SPEAKER_02] these type of questions. Um, you know, the, the tools that we're talking about with AI,
[SPEAKER_02] they, they provide efficiency and reach, but they cannot and can never replace, um,
[SPEAKER_02] the things that are uniquely human. That's what, uh, Pope, um, Leo was saying, right? Empathy,
[SPEAKER_02] ethics, moral responsibility, uh, pastoral care, discernment, those are the things that need
[SPEAKER_02] to remain human. You know, another thing could be, you know, that technology is not an idol,
[SPEAKER_02] right? Like that's the, the, the other part that we see in the, in the documents that the church has
[SPEAKER_02] published, right? And then Tico Enova, the technology can become this false god for humanity that we can
[SPEAKER_02] see technology as saving everything that is, that needs to be saved in a parish or in a diocesan
[SPEAKER_02] setting. Well, we shouldn't have that approach. Um, but we can see it as a tool that can serve
[SPEAKER_02] us and, and it's always serving us. We're never, technology is never the master. And then, and then
[SPEAKER_02] the goal is to facilitate, uh, pastoral encounters. Um, so those are just a few things. I think maybe
[SPEAKER_02] another, another thing that comes to mind in terms of creating a sandbox or a framework is, is, is, is
[SPEAKER_02] what Pope Francis would call the wisdom of the heart, right? And machines can process data, but it takes
[SPEAKER_02] the human heart to, to process meaning and to discern. So discernment is something that needs to be kept
[SPEAKER_02] there. So if you create that sandbox in a diocesan setting, in a, you know, in a conference, you know,
[SPEAKER_02] setting in a, in a parish setting, then people can be encouraged to, to creatively use these technologies
[SPEAKER_02] for good. Um, here are some things that I, the other day, Edmund and I were talking about these,
[SPEAKER_02] and then we, we came up with some use cases that, that could be something that parishes could consider.
[SPEAKER_02] You know, I'm going to share three that come to mind, um, that, that I, I would think are pretty
[SPEAKER_02] safe for, for, for parishes to implement and consider in these learning communities. So one would be,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, catechists, like, you know, Edmund and I have a project around the catechism and, and, and,
[SPEAKER_02] and, and the project, project's goal is to, to unlock the wisdom and the beauty, you know,
[SPEAKER_02] that, that we have in the catechism of the Catholic church. Um, so, but, but the reality is that a lot
[SPEAKER_02] of the catechists in a parish, they don't have the formation, um, um, that sometimes they require,
[SPEAKER_02] um, they have some formation, but sometimes it's not sufficient. Um, these are volunteers who have
[SPEAKER_02] busy lives and are, are serving out of love for the parish. So we can equip them with, with,
[SPEAKER_02] with ways that they can leverage AI to prepare their lessons. That would be a super helpful
[SPEAKER_02] thing. So teaching them how to use AI, not to write the lesson, but to make it better,
[SPEAKER_02] to adapt some of the materials for the age group that they were teaching, that would be super,
[SPEAKER_02] super helpful. So, so, so a simple thing that they could do is just write your lesson,
[SPEAKER_02] right? Like usually parishes provide, um, guides or curriculum for every lesson, write your lesson,
[SPEAKER_02] and then, and then ask chat GPT or, or, or, um, other, um, AI tools, you know, to, to, with some
[SPEAKER_02] framework and with some context, and that's what the parish should provide, you know, how, how do I adapt
[SPEAKER_02] these in a, in the best way possible for an audience of, of, of boys, of sixth grade boys? How do I adapt
[SPEAKER_02] that here? Um, uh, you know, using this framework, can you tell me what things I can, I can do better
[SPEAKER_02] in my lesson? So those are just, just things that, you know, uh, parishes cannot provide that, that
[SPEAKER_02] personalized coaching for every catechist in the parish, uh, but they can provide that framework and
[SPEAKER_02] and they can provide that way of using AI to help the catechist become a better catechist. That
[SPEAKER_02] doesn't substitute, uh, the, the prayerful spirit of a catechist of seeking the Lord first. It doesn't
[SPEAKER_02] substitute the discernment that person still needs to discern and to make the decisions. And it doesn't
[SPEAKER_02] replace the catechist because we need the catechist teaching, uh, children or teaching, uh, adults and
[SPEAKER_02] passing down the faith person to person. So, so we're not replacing anything. We're just elevating
[SPEAKER_02] and make, make, um, ministry better. So that's just one example. I can, I can share others. Edmund
[SPEAKER_02] has a lot of good examples that he can share as well. Edmund, before I go to the next question is,
[SPEAKER_01] is there anything you'd like to add on that? I mean, those, those frameworks and those examples,
[SPEAKER_01] I think, um, really illustrate well, kind of the opportunities. Yeah. I mean, uh, the only thing I
[SPEAKER_00] can think to add, you know, I'm going to share a lot of these really practical things. I think,
[SPEAKER_00] I think, um, the biggest thing I am most excited about is that what we're seeing in AI,
[SPEAKER_00] not just the technology and what it's doing, but what we're seeing is a whole shift. I think in,
[SPEAKER_00] in my view, in our, in our collective view of the world. So for hundreds of years now, since, um,
[SPEAKER_00] really the enlightenment, we've been viewing the world across all different subjects and domains,
[SPEAKER_00] um, science, religion, philosophy in, in the West, there's been this predominant view of the world,
[SPEAKER_00] which is, um, that the world is like a machine. It's mechanistic, it's linear, it's cause and effect.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's interesting that in the church, um, as well as in the sciences over the last couple of
[SPEAKER_00] decades, we've started to see the breakdown of that. And I think, you know, the like Western civilization
[SPEAKER_00] saw at the height of the fruit of this kind of like materialistic, reductionistic,
[SPEAKER_00] linear view that you can just understand things as parts and you put in this and you get out this
[SPEAKER_00] output. And it just isn't, it just isn't sustainable. It's not, it's not, um, it doesn't match with reality.
[SPEAKER_00] And so like World War II and all of these like fruits of this view of the world. And so we're seeing
[SPEAKER_00] like this move towards more ecological ecology systems view of the world, which actually is very
[SPEAKER_00] Catholic. Like the human person is only understood in relation to others. So the thing I'm like really
[SPEAKER_00] excited about is this deeper, um, worldview shift that AI forces us to have because, um,
[SPEAKER_00] there's this thing called the realization gap. Jeremy from, uh, Jeremy Utley from Stanford
[SPEAKER_00] university did this research where he found that lots of people that use AI, there was a big majority
[SPEAKER_00] of people that were, they considered underperformers. So they didn't get anything out of AI. And then
[SPEAKER_00] they examined and surveyed the people that were over performers who, who tended to get more results.
[SPEAKER_00] And the difference between the two groups was that the people who were underperformers viewed AI
[SPEAKER_00] as a tool, whereas the people who were over performers viewed AI as a thinking partner.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is, this really highlights like this difference in worldview of how you interact with
[SPEAKER_00] things. So for example, a parish, someone as a parish leader or pastor, who's very linear,
[SPEAKER_00] top down type of approach to leadership is like, if I do X, then Y happens. But we know
[SPEAKER_00] that that just isn't the case. These are complex organizations. These are complex systems.
[SPEAKER_00] And so a system you can't control, you can only cultivate. So I think what's really exciting,
[SPEAKER_00] what people are going to be forced to do more and more is to think of the parish and evangelization,
[SPEAKER_00] um, much less like a S a machine to control. Like you put in these inputs and you should get out this
[SPEAKER_00] thing. And much more like, like in a sense, a garden, like you, you cultivate a garden, you have
[SPEAKER_00] to work with a garden. It's interesting too, that with the rise of this idea, which is called complexity
[SPEAKER_00] science, with the rise of this idea in the sciences, we have the rise of synodality in the church.
[SPEAKER_00] And one of the big tenants of complexity theory is that you have to be sensing what's going on,
[SPEAKER_00] discerning, responding and, and facilitating. And that sounds much more like a synodal church.
[SPEAKER_00] It sounds much more like accompaniment. And so, um, Catholic leaders have to think of themselves less
[SPEAKER_00] as, uh, someone who transfers the data or the content, and much more as a thinking partner with
[SPEAKER_00] those that we're ministering to as someone who mentors and accompanies and is alongside.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's interesting to know that like Pope Leo is, um, address the Catholic digital missionaries
[SPEAKER_00] said this, um, uh, specifically, like, it's not simply a matter of generating content, but of creating
[SPEAKER_00] an encounter of hearts. And so we have to do away with this, this old model that we've been given,
[SPEAKER_00] even in our, in our schooling and our education systems, this industrial view of man and of society,
[SPEAKER_00] that's a machine, it's linear, and it's much more systems. It's people interacting,
[SPEAKER_00] listening and cultivating and looking at the fruits of that. Um, so that, that's like a little bit
[SPEAKER_00] deeper and more nerdy answer, but I think AI forces people to have to think in this more holistic way
[SPEAKER_00] about the outcomes that they're trying to achieve.
[SPEAKER_01] What, how do you guys see parishes kind of adapting their approach to welcome kind of these,
[SPEAKER_01] these people who are digitally converted, you know, intellectually converted through,
[SPEAKER_01] through the new media?
[SPEAKER_02] I find it super interesting that, um, people open up with ChatGPT and other chatbots so much more than
[SPEAKER_02] with people. Um, so that's, so, so, so for some people that would be super scary and like, oh man,
[SPEAKER_02] like the world is ending because someone opens up so much to a machine instead of a person. Like,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, you guys may have seen that, that graphic, that meme where it's like an iceberg. And here's
[SPEAKER_02] what I tell, um, my friends. Here's what I tell my spouse. Here's what I tell my therapist. And here
[SPEAKER_02] is all that I tell, uh, uh, chat GPT. Um, yeah, there, there, there, there, there's something there that,
[SPEAKER_02] that, that, that I think we should all be reflecting. So if I would be a priest and if I'm even an older
[SPEAKER_02] priest, priest that doesn't quite understand everything about AI, I should be very curious about that. I should be
[SPEAKER_02] thinking deeply about that, that, that reality that, that, that, that, that we have right now where,
[SPEAKER_02] where especially young people are opening up, um, so much with, with, with ChatGPT, right? We've seen
[SPEAKER_02] that the number one use is not search. He's, he's, um, it's, it's therapy, right? That people are going
[SPEAKER_02] to a chatbot to, to get therapy and, and, and therapy is, is a search for, for what? For understanding
[SPEAKER_02] ourselves and understanding relationships. Um, so, so that should be something to reflect on,
[SPEAKER_02] regardless if you touch or not AI, that should, that should, that should really drive your curiosity
[SPEAKER_02] and start asking very, very important questions. Why someone is so much more open to share deeply,
[SPEAKER_02] um, there than, than in, in a, in a context, uh, where, where there's human encounter and divine
[SPEAKER_02] encounter, right? And, and then what can we learn or what is, are these technologies providing that
[SPEAKER_02] we're not providing in the church? And, and what comes to mind is the whole idea of listening,
[SPEAKER_02] right? I mean, the, the reason why people share in ChatGPT, yes, there is the, the unembarrassed to
[SPEAKER_02] talk to someone about others, these things with someone else, but it's this, this idea that,
[SPEAKER_02] that ChatGPT is trained and other chatbots to, to be very empathetic and very affirming and, and, and,
[SPEAKER_02] and very welcoming to your inquiries. And, and, and they provide always positive feedback when you ask
[SPEAKER_02] a question, you're trained to do that. And then they suggest things and paths. So, so for someone
[SPEAKER_02] that, that may not have a pastoral, you know, you know, um, training, uh, you can start thinking
[SPEAKER_02] about why this is happening there. Why are young people, especially doing, using, using the technology
[SPEAKER_02] in this way and what can we learn in the church and where can we step up? Um, and also it's not
[SPEAKER_02] terrible, right? If someone has a very, very, a question that they don't feel comfortable sharing
[SPEAKER_02] with anyone else, and we can point them to a technology where they can ask those questions
[SPEAKER_02] like Magisterium or, or Truthly, or some of these, um, you know, tools that are trained in church,
[SPEAKER_02] churches teaching, and they're getting some answers. That's not the end of the world. It's actually a
[SPEAKER_02] positive thing that people are, are finding a way to look for those things. And, and honestly,
[SPEAKER_02] that's not that different from what people were doing before, which is just asking Google,
[SPEAKER_02] right for the same type of questions. So, but, but, but, but the difference between Google and, and, and
[SPEAKER_02] AI is that, that the way that the machine responds is so empathetically and is listening to you that
[SPEAKER_02] you open up, right? Um, so I would be, if I would be a pastor, it's like I would be praying and discerning,
[SPEAKER_02] and how can we become a more listening community? How can we create a space that's where people can
[SPEAKER_02] ask questions and not feel judged by them, but that we can welcome them and guide them? How can we
[SPEAKER_02] provide those opportunities for that personal encounter that leads to the divine encounter?
[SPEAKER_02] So for me, that's a really, really important conversation to have, um, in, in a, in a church
[SPEAKER_02] setting. Um, you know, here's another thing that comes to mind and, um, you know, none of us wants a
[SPEAKER_02] priest to write their homilies, you know, have Chachipty write their homilies, right? That doesn't
[SPEAKER_02] make sense, right? And maybe there are some priests that are doing it, but, but, but that doesn't mean
[SPEAKER_02] that you cannot use these tools to, to become a very better homilist, right? If I would be a priest
[SPEAKER_02] or a deacon, I would be recording all my homilies and I would be loading them to, to an AI tool. And I
[SPEAKER_02] would be asking critical questions about my, my preaching. I would be asking questions, you know,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, feedback with, with some constraints and context, I would be asking the AI
[SPEAKER_02] tool. I would be providing the AI tool, certain, certain frameworks to use. Okay.
[SPEAKER_02] Use these homiletic framework, right? That is the one that I was trained when I was a seminary,
[SPEAKER_02] use these homiletic resources. And now I provide feedback to my, my preaching. And I want to tell
[SPEAKER_02] you also that, that the, the constraints on the context involve my community. So I am in a suburban
[SPEAKER_02] parish or I'm in a rural parish and the average speech is these and the, the, you know, the educational
[SPEAKER_02] level is these and primarily, you know, this is a type of, this is, this is my, my, my community,
[SPEAKER_02] my parish community. And then allow the tool to, to, to using these, these things and analyzing,
[SPEAKER_02] as Edmund was saying at the very early, very early in the podcast, the, the power to, to do those
[SPEAKER_02] things as a, as a pocket data scientist, and then provide feedback to you that, you know,
[SPEAKER_02] you're not, you're not going to do everything that AI tells you, but it's going to, it's going to make
[SPEAKER_02] you think deeply about your ministry with the hope that in your 40s to grow as a better homilist,
[SPEAKER_02] so that the word of God that you're preaching could be done in a more effective way.
[SPEAKER_01] And I just wonder how we as Catholics can effectively be preserving and a more that Christian moral
[SPEAKER_01] formation for these young people as the technology is allowing inputs from outside.
[SPEAKER_00] We often revert back to this thing that we learned that's baked into our culture, which is this,
[SPEAKER_00] this kind of Protestant Reformation era view of what evangelization and even the faith really is,
[SPEAKER_00] that, that it's an intellectual pursuit and it's not an intellectual pursuit. And you,
[SPEAKER_00] this is why Cardinal Ratzinger, then Pope Benedict and JP II and all of these influential thinkers were
[SPEAKER_00] moving towards this, this resource mawn to the sources, not just because they needed to reclaim
[SPEAKER_00] tradition, but because they needed to reclaim a more complete view of the human person. And so we,
[SPEAKER_00] like, I love Aquinas and my, my, um, yeah, my Thomistic brothers and sisters in Christ, like I,
[SPEAKER_00] I love them. And as someone who's a recovering, um, Catholic intellectual, like I had to unlearn some of
[SPEAKER_00] those habits of treating the faith as intellectual pursuit. And I think in a lot of public discourse,
[SPEAKER_00] we sometimes, because it's, it's exciting, it can be exciting, exhilarating, um, fun to show someone
[SPEAKER_00] their flawed thinking. But if, if all of us were rational, logical beings, like we wouldn't have
[SPEAKER_00] all the problems we have. And it's not enough to just say, well, people just refuse to accept the truth.
[SPEAKER_00] Like, like it is the case that a purely intellectual presentation of the faith, um, is not sufficient,
[SPEAKER_00] right? And CF all the saints and theologians that write on this. And so, um, I think it's very
[SPEAKER_00] encouraging that, um, Pope Leo as an Augustinian is, is hopefully going to continue to reclaim this.
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, I think it's not a coincidence that Pope Francis wrote on the human heart and this,
[SPEAKER_00] and the divine heart, like we reclaiming the heart is really the antidote to that. And so what that
[SPEAKER_00] means is, um, being more self-aware and being more transparent about what, um, because that's how you
[SPEAKER_00] have authentic communion with another person. Like that's how you have authentic relationship with
[SPEAKER_00] another person is not, um, you, you sit down there and let me just explain it to you, but it's two
[SPEAKER_00] people side by side who are looking out at the world and making sense of it and are not afraid to admit
[SPEAKER_00] the doubts and challenges and the struggles and, and to be more of a, um, uh, uh, mentor might be the
[SPEAKER_00] wrong word for us in the English world, but like to be more of a guide and a friend who's looking out
[SPEAKER_00] at all of these mountainous areas and these muddy areas and saying, Hey, I've tried traversing those
[SPEAKER_00] areas. I've, I, here are some paths that have helped for me. And like, what do you need to, to also find
[SPEAKER_00] Jesus Christ, um, today?
[SPEAKER_01] My final question to both of you is, uh, if we look at ahead at, uh, 2035, what are healthy parishes
[SPEAKER_01] doing? What, how do you guys hope, you know, they've integrated AI and some of these emerging
[SPEAKER_01] technologies that we're, we're starting to see the fruits of now?
[SPEAKER_02] Maybe something that I would love for parishes to, to start doing not in 2030, 2035, but 2026
[SPEAKER_02] would be providing more resources for parents. You know, we're talking about parenting, uh,
[SPEAKER_02] but also just for the whole parish on, on how, how do we, how do we use technology without abusing
[SPEAKER_02] technology, right? So, you know, the, the technical term would be media and artificial, um,
[SPEAKER_02] literacy, but, um, being able to provide real practical resources for parents and for parishioners
[SPEAKER_02] on, on how to use and not abuse artificial intelligence. So that would be something super,
[SPEAKER_02] super helpful that, that parishes should be thinking about it. I think that would be more,
[SPEAKER_02] one of the most, um, welcomed, um, resources that, that a parish could, could offer now. Like
[SPEAKER_02] not, not in five years, but now, um, you know, sometimes, you know, if you, if you go to an average
[SPEAKER_02] parish, you know, you look at here in the United States, you know, you look at the, the events that
[SPEAKER_02] sometimes parishes is sponsored and, you know, you look at the parish events calendar, and then a lot of
[SPEAKER_02] things, you know, are poorly attended because they're not, they're not touching the things that people
[SPEAKER_02] really care about. Um, there are the things that the parish is pushing to others. So just, there's
[SPEAKER_02] sort of a match of interest and need with offerings. So I would say, yeah, like if I'm a pastor and I'm,
[SPEAKER_02] you know, watching this podcast, if I'm a lay leader, lay minister, I wouldn't start to think
[SPEAKER_02] about how could we create these media and artificial intelligence literacy resources, courses, uh,
[SPEAKER_02] conversations for the parish now, so that we're using non-abusing technology. Now, the question about
[SPEAKER_02] the future, you know, in, in, in, in five, 10 years, where do we want, um, where, where do we want to be?
[SPEAKER_02] So for me, I'm going to start with the most hopeful perspective because I, that's how I think about
[SPEAKER_02] these things. Um, maybe this is my, you know, it was sharing that I started in, in 1994 when I was
[SPEAKER_02] in school and that was my conversion and emerging technologies were happening. And I could see from
[SPEAKER_02] there to now, how we're able to share the gospel in, in such creative ways around the world where,
[SPEAKER_02] where back in the day, you need to, you needed to own a media company or work for a media company to
[SPEAKER_02] put a message to, to, to the people. And now you can't, you can do it without that. You know,
[SPEAKER_02] anybody can, can publish a message. So, so I've seen that revolution from 1994, um, to now. And,
[SPEAKER_02] and, and, you know, what I see ahead is, is maybe three things. One is, um, AI is going to bring the
[SPEAKER_02] cost, uh, down for a lot of the things that, that right now there are very expensive to do. And that's
[SPEAKER_02] that's going to promote, I think the leveraging media, um, and, and creative tools to do beautiful
[SPEAKER_02] things that communicate the gospel message in other effective ways. So I could see that being very
[SPEAKER_02] important on how AI is going to change media production and communications for good. Um, I would
[SPEAKER_02] love in, in five years to see all the parishes leveraging AI for all the mission support things
[SPEAKER_02] from translations, active translations for all their, you know, parishes that are multicultural to,
[SPEAKER_02] to data analysis of the parish territories that we were saying and understanding trends and
[SPEAKER_02] understanding opportunities to, uh, parish ministers that every year, you know, the priests,
[SPEAKER_02] the deacons, the late peaceful ministers are getting better because they're using AI as a thought
[SPEAKER_02] partner and a critical partner and the, and they're getting better at their homilies and their preaching
[SPEAKER_02] and the catechesis and being better teachers. So, so I would love to see, uh, these AI tools agents
[SPEAKER_02] helping, helping the parish do things better, but never substituting, um, the, the human interaction
[SPEAKER_02] and what's uniquely human. Um, so, so, so I would love in five years to, to be a church that is confident,
[SPEAKER_02] a church that is not afraid, uh, a church that understands what AI is and is not, and is able
[SPEAKER_02] to leverage and harden his AI for good in a way that the Lord would be proud of us of using these
[SPEAKER_02] resources that he's allowed us to have at this time and this age, and that we're using it so that more
[SPEAKER_00] people would come to know and love him. And Edmund, what about for you? Yeah, I, I, man, I love doing
[SPEAKER_00] this with, you know, because it's nice. I can, I can kind of give, uh, maybe a, a different, like a
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know, maybe like a different take that I wouldn't, I wouldn't have given like, because I,
[SPEAKER_00] I believe what Edmund is saying, but I think the only thing I would add, I think I have like a holy,
[SPEAKER_00] well, I hope it's holy, but I think I have a particular type of, um, kind of frustration with the church.
[SPEAKER_00] So I think I want to paint a little bit more of a cautionary, like, like a picture that, you know,
[SPEAKER_00] the internet, like, I think we're going to see something very similar to what happened with
[SPEAKER_00] the internet where we're going to have similar patterns, but just heightened, like intensified,
[SPEAKER_00] and it's going to happen much quicker and it's going to be more intense. So, um, the internet
[SPEAKER_00] democratized information, the internet in some ways started decentralizing leadership and authority.
[SPEAKER_00] And these things happen really fast. You see this like boom in, you know, moms and, you know,
[SPEAKER_00] stay, you know, stay at home parents and like college kids starting ministries and apostolates
[SPEAKER_00] and these things. And the parishes, like the hearing of parishes during COVID that didn't have
[SPEAKER_00] a list of any of their parishioners email addresses was really disheartening. And, and, and things like
[SPEAKER_00] that, parishes like that, it was, it was a very negative, you know, effect. Like it, it wasn't great. Um,
[SPEAKER_00] but I think what's really concerning is that as we move into this AI world, those types of mistakes are,
[SPEAKER_00] are going to be have more dire consequences and it's going to be quicker. So there's, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] two, two ideas, like we're used to this idea of bell curves that, you know, more or less,
[SPEAKER_00] there's going to be a big group of people that have about average experience of things, whether it's
[SPEAKER_00] resources or experiences, time or information. But with AI, we're having more of what's called these
[SPEAKER_00] like power laws where you have lots and lots of people that don't have much, and then a small,
[SPEAKER_00] small percentage that have a lot. So if you think back to like feudal society, where you had a small,
[SPEAKER_00] small 1% of the population had access to resources and riches and all of this, and then everyone else
[SPEAKER_00] had a much, much different experience. Like I think in, in, in my hopeful view of the future is that
[SPEAKER_00] Catholic leaders, parish ministers, pastors, don't see this as just a gimmicky tech fad, but see this as
[SPEAKER_00] as what it is, which is a revolution of society and the way we think and act and talk that forces us
[SPEAKER_00] to be on the cutting edge of this. Like we have to be using these things, or at least like thinking
[SPEAKER_00] about how to use this, these technologies. And, um, you know, as Pope Leo said in that same address,
[SPEAKER_00] he said, um, today we find ourselves in a new culture, deeply characterized and formed by technology.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's up to us to ensure that this culture remains human. So I think, um, what I hope to see
[SPEAKER_00] is that we understand that this is a really, really pressing time for the church to get involved in
[SPEAKER_00] this technological revolution. Um, like we can't sit on the sidelines and all the things Ed Muno said is
[SPEAKER_00] like, I believe a hundred percent that we are, are given this huge opportunity to bring the church's
[SPEAKER_00] wisdom, hope and confidence into these spaces, but we have to be involved in it. And we, it,
[SPEAKER_00] we have to be involved in it yesterday and it's exciting to be involved in it. And there is hope
[SPEAKER_00] there. Um, but I just really hope by 2030, um, we're seeing a new shift. Like we're seeing something
[SPEAKER_00] we didn't see at the dawn of the internet age. Like we're seeing a different response and reaction from
[SPEAKER_01] Catholics everywhere. Edmund, thank you so much from so much for that. Um, Ed Mundo and Edmund,
[SPEAKER_01] I'm very grateful for your time this morning. It has been a fascinating and, you know, just incredible
[SPEAKER_01] conversation. I'm very grateful for, for, for you joining me on this. And, um, um, I hope to do it
[SPEAKER_01] again soon sometime. Oh, thank you, Ben. Maybe next time in Rome, we should just go out and
[SPEAKER_02] Hvala što pratite kanal.