[SPEAKER_00] Ok, so the most dramatic thing during the presentation is to share the PowerPoint.
[SPEAKER_00] If I see this correctly, I was successful in it.
[SPEAKER_00] So I'm very grateful to my friend Stjepan Štivić and also to all organizers for this invitation.
[SPEAKER_00] I indeed think this kind of confidence is very important and I'm very sorry that I can't be with you today in person,
[SPEAKER_00] but I will try to make this better on some other occasion.
[SPEAKER_00] So the notion that the relationships between the church and secular authorities is different
[SPEAKER_00] in Western and Eastern Christianity is much widespread.
[SPEAKER_00] And it was probably only corroborated by a relatively fresh experience
[SPEAKER_00] when many Orthodox and Catholic believers in Central and Eastern Europe lived under communism quite recently.
[SPEAKER_00] And there it was a notion that the Catholic Church, despite of all difficulties,
[SPEAKER_00] showed greater resilience in her relationship to secular authorities.
[SPEAKER_00] But the point of my paper will be that this difference was not caused by ideal foundations,
[SPEAKER_00] because both Eastern and Western Christianity shared, in fact, main foundations of formation of these relationships between throne and altar.
[SPEAKER_00] The first experience of Christians in the very beginnings of Christianity was twofold.
[SPEAKER_00] On one hand, for the first 300 years, Christians used to live in an environment where both secular authorities
[SPEAKER_00] and the majority pagan environment mainly chose to simply ignore them as if Christian communities didn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00] That's very important, because it formed ever since a part of Christian DNA,
[SPEAKER_00] because Christians instinctively knew that there would be situations
[SPEAKER_00] where they absolutely couldn't rely on secular authorities.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, this basic situation from the antiquity was later changed in both West and the East,
[SPEAKER_00] but nevertheless, it still remained an important early experience.
[SPEAKER_00] On the other hand, Christians were faced from the very beginning with a great problem
[SPEAKER_00] in their relationships to secular power, to secular or political authorities.
[SPEAKER_00] If they took their Christianity seriously,
[SPEAKER_00] They couldn't take part in the worship of the emperor,
[SPEAKER_00] which became the link between all subjects of the Roman Empire very early in the history of Christianity.
[SPEAKER_00] So, they tried to compensate for this great handicap
[SPEAKER_00] by affirming their steadfast loyalty to secular power and to the person of emperor himself.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is already visible in early scriptural foundations in the early New Testament texts,
[SPEAKER_00] particularly in the famous passage from the letter of the Apostle St. Paul to the Romans in 13th chapter,
[SPEAKER_00] where there are almost no limitations put on secular authority,
[SPEAKER_00] because it is divine in origin in St. Paul's view.
[SPEAKER_00] And I even have the impression that this secular authority didn't have any real obligations towards its subjects.
[SPEAKER_00] Why St. Paul put the things so radically and drastically,
[SPEAKER_00] particularly in view of the later development?
[SPEAKER_00] I think he did so because he expected the second coming of Christ very soon,
[SPEAKER_00] so he assumed that this question of the relationship between church and state wouldn't be of much importance.
[SPEAKER_00] His view was later echoed
[SPEAKER_00] also by some other New Testament texts, particularly by the first epistle of St. Peter in the second chapter,
[SPEAKER_00] where the main tone is the same as in the Romans.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, there is also another current present in the New Testament,
[SPEAKER_00] particularly in the last book of the New Testament, in the Revelation of St. John,
[SPEAKER_00] where Rome is clearly identified as Babylon
[SPEAKER_00] and seen in a much degradating view.
[SPEAKER_00] But this current was clearly a minority view among Christians in antiquity and
[SPEAKER_00] also during the later periods, although this current existed.
[SPEAKER_00] It must also be said that another very important passage for the formation of relationship between church and state,
[SPEAKER_00] the scene of Caesar's coin in Synoptic Gospels,
[SPEAKER_00] is much more ambiguous than the passage by St. Paul.
[SPEAKER_00] Although there was a tendency among Christian writers to interpret
[SPEAKER_00] this passage also in a way more favorable to the emperor.
[SPEAKER_00] Although, in my view, it is clear from the words of Jesus
[SPEAKER_00] that the real emphasis is on the notion that there are spheres where the emperor had no end.
[SPEAKER_00] These scriptural foundations and this basic experience of the relation to void secular power
[SPEAKER_00] is clearly shared by Western and Eastern Christianity.
[SPEAKER_00] And it was also repeated by many early Christian authors, particularly by apologists, even by Tertullian.
[SPEAKER_00] Although in his writings, we also can see some ironic passages,
[SPEAKER_00] but he remains true to the basic concept of
[SPEAKER_00] explicit loyalty of the Christians to the emperor and to the secular power.
[SPEAKER_00] Now, the situation changed dramatically and also somehow rapidly
[SPEAKER_00] with the unexpected conversion of Constantine the Great at the beginning of the 4th century.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is important to quote the famous German church historian Hartmut Lepin who once wrote
[SPEAKER_00] that it was completely unimaginable even at the end of the 3rd century for the Christians
[SPEAKER_00] that emperor could be Christian because his functions were at the time so much connected to various forms of pagan worship.
[SPEAKER_00] So this change at the beginning of the 4th century was dramatic in more than one way.
[SPEAKER_00] And it also calls for the new definition of the relationship between
[SPEAKER_00] church and political authority, of course,
[SPEAKER_00] building on scriptural basis and on the basis of early apologists.
[SPEAKER_00] And there are two main starting points for the new definition of the relationship
[SPEAKER_00] between church and state, between bishops and emperor, between bishops and kings later on.
[SPEAKER_00] And this starting point in the west is a definition from the letter which the bishop of Rome,
[SPEAKER_00] Gelesius I, wrote to the Eastern Roman emperor, Anastasius I,
[SPEAKER_00] at the time of one of minor chisums in the history of the church at the end of the 5th century.
[SPEAKER_00] The other one is a similar definition written by the emperor Justinian I the Great somehow
[SPEAKER_00] some decades later at the beginning of the 6th century in the preface to his 6th novel.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is often assumed that this preface by the emperor Justinian forms the base
[SPEAKER_00] of the notion of the so-called symphony between church and state in Eastern Christian traditions,
[SPEAKER_00] which is supposed to be different to the somehow more conflict relationship between imperium and
[SPEAKER_00] sacerdotium in the west.
[SPEAKER_00] But if we read these ideological foundations or these ideal foundations
[SPEAKER_00] in Pope Gelesius and in the emperor Justinian, then we can say that all the basic ideas are the same.
[SPEAKER_00] They are two separate powers in the world according to both texts.
[SPEAKER_00] And one power is secular power represented by emperor or by political authority.
[SPEAKER_00] And the second power is spiritual power represented by priests and bishops.
[SPEAKER_00] And basically in both cases, these powers are equal also in Justinian and even more.
[SPEAKER_00] Both authors, Gelesius I and Justinian I emphasized that since holders of spiritual power, bishops and priests
[SPEAKER_00] perform their duties not only for themselves or for other people,
[SPEAKER_00] but also for holders of spiritual powers, they should enjoy particular respect.
[SPEAKER_00] And in this case, or from this origin, the highest worth of spiritual power could be deduced.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is not only limited to the Western view, to the ideas formulated by Pope Gelesius,
[SPEAKER_00] but the same notion is also present in this so-called Magna Carta of the idea of symphony by
[SPEAKER_00] and the emperor Justinian, the only difference is perhaps the person of both waters.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is, of course, significant that the definition of the proper relationship between
[SPEAKER_00] spiritual and secular power was defined by the Pope in the West,
[SPEAKER_00] by the bishop, by a bishop in the West, and by an emperor in the West, in the East.
[SPEAKER_00] And this by an emperor who was also an avid theologian, of course.
[SPEAKER_00] So we cannot assume that the foundations of the relationship between
[SPEAKER_00] church and political authorities is different in the East from that in the West.
[SPEAKER_00] What in fact was different was like Dr. Vedrish already
[SPEAKER_00] showed for another aspect of the building of these differences
[SPEAKER_00] between East and West was political development, which was in fact quite different
[SPEAKER_00] and was marked by a great and grave crisis of the secular authority in the West,
[SPEAKER_00] in the former Western part of the Roman Empire, and by the stability of the same secular power
[SPEAKER_00] and the secular authority in the Eastern part of the former Roman Empire.
[SPEAKER_00] Because even if the position of the emperor was held by a person who was personally weak,
[SPEAKER_00] like the famous Eastern Roman Empire, Theodosius II, in the first half of the fifth century,
[SPEAKER_00] the imperial authority in the East remained intact.
[SPEAKER_00] On the other hand, the case of Theodosius' relative, Valentinian III, in the West,
[SPEAKER_00] shows us that a weak emperor also weakened the idea of imperial authority itself.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, particularly because of the fact that the objective circumstances of Valentinian's rule
[SPEAKER_00] were much more difficult in the West than the objective circumstances of Theodosius' rule in the East.
[SPEAKER_00] And then this crisis of secular power in the West only deepened from the end of the fifth century
[SPEAKER_00] till the revival of this secular power with the Franks in the early Middle Ages.
[SPEAKER_00] And that was an opportunity, of course, not an opportunity which was intended for the church
[SPEAKER_00] to establish herself as a much more independent institution in the West during the early Middle Ages.
[SPEAKER_00] And she retained her self-worn strength only after the revival of the secular power,
[SPEAKER_00] particularly since the beginning of the ninth century.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's why the relationship between church and secular authorities remained strained,
[SPEAKER_00] much more strained in the West than in the East,
[SPEAKER_00] where the imperial authority was never weakened.
[SPEAKER_00] Nevertheless, the basic idea of the need for cooperation between church and secular authorities remained vivid also in the West and was never abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00] So the notion of the so-called Reichskirche, as in the later Holy Roman Empire, was an ideal
[SPEAKER_00] which was never really abolished also in the West and was much more common than the periods of protracted conflicts.
[SPEAKER_00] Although particularly in the Catholic history, the emphasis is almost always on these cases of conflict,
[SPEAKER_00] like the famous conflict of investiture during the high Middle Ages.
[SPEAKER_00] And to conclude, there was also another development limited only to the West,
[SPEAKER_00] which probably changed the relationship between church and state for good in the West, but not in the East.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is the experience of wars of religion during the 16th and 17th centuries,
[SPEAKER_00] which put to the fore calls for separation between church and state,
[SPEAKER_00] and even between religion in society.
[SPEAKER_00] And this concept is something which is completely alien to the Eastern Christianity,
[SPEAKER_00] where this experience of wars of religion during the early modern age, of course, never existed.
[SPEAKER_00] And if the areas of Eastern Christianity ever accepted the idea of separation
[SPEAKER_00] between church and state, then it was, of course, imported from the West.
[SPEAKER_00] But it is clear, I think, from this presentation that basic foundations for the formation of relationship
[SPEAKER_00] between church and state in both parts of European Christianity
[SPEAKER_00] were basically the same and were founded on the same early experiences of the first church or early Christianity,
[SPEAKER_00] even before Constantine.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you for your attention.