[SPEAKER_01] Hello. Hey, how are you? Can we hear each other? Yes, I can hear you. Can you hear me? Yeah. Great. Great, man. Perfect. Thanks for being on your podcast. No problem. It's my, it's my pleasure, man. Yeah. Yeah. So, uh, uh, for me, it's also exciting because I actually started, uh, last year, I tried to start my own podcast. Okay. And then I postponed it a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00] So now I'm still kind of like in developing stage and I'll hopefully resume it as well later. You know, I've been, I've been thinking about it for a long time and, uh, I, I had something in me, you know, I'm a perfectionist and the, I, I had a, a trouble troubles before to, to start, uh, something. And this time I just said to myself, okay, it's not going to be perfect. I just need to start. And, uh, I
[SPEAKER_01] I need to optimize after, after I just started, started something. Yeah. So that's the only way to go. Yeah, it is. So I'm, I'm super grateful that you accepted the, my invitation. No problem. No problem for me. It's pleasure. Yeah. So where are you right now? Are you in a St. Petersburg? Yes. Uh, yeah. I'm in St. Petersburg right now. Uh, we are, as you remember from a leap summit, uh, for as well joining.
[SPEAKER_01] And the leap summit, uh, we are in St. Petersburg, Russia. That's where we're mostly located. And, uh, here we're doing specializing in the social media marketing, uh, also in the video production, uh, as well. So kind of like trying to develop both things. And, uh, as I was starting pretty much like three years ago, I was, uh, at that time, I was like, I didn't know what to do. And, uh, then
[SPEAKER_01] I was, okay, maybe let's try to go freelancing. So I went on the platform, uh, like Fiverr and just started to look for other services for, uh, other things that I can maybe do. And, uh, eventually I found the, uh, I would say not really success, but I found what I liked through Instagram, a social media marketing.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay. And now we're also developing, uh, video production. And then in the future, hopefully we're gonna develop more and more stuff. So that's where based at the moment.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the same time, uh, I studied in the US in university, uh, and I graduated there. So I went to actually, that was like long, longer time ago.
[SPEAKER_01] I was, uh, playing tennis, uh, professionally traveling, uh, and then I was like, okay, maybe, uh, I should try and go for play for university in US because they have like a good programs to be on the scholarship.
[SPEAKER_01] You can play for university. And at the same time, you can get a really good degree. So this is why your English, English is so good.
[SPEAKER_01] Thanks. Yeah. I mean, that's, I guess, like you were saying, you just have to start doing the same English. I wasn't, I could say I was good at school in English, but I wasn't the best grammar, but I think the biggest advantage I had is I had a lot of practice.
[SPEAKER_01] I was traveling, speaking English to other players, speaking English to other players, speaking English to other players, and speaking English to other players, and speaking English to other players, and speaking English to other players.
[SPEAKER_01] I was good at school, but I wasn't the best in grammar, but I think the biggest advantage I had is I had a lot of practice.
[SPEAKER_01] I was traveling, speaking English to other players, coaches, and then when I went to university, just, I was basically just speaking English all the time.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm. Great, man.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. What about you?
[SPEAKER_00] What about me? Uh, I'm, uh, I'm, I was born in Osijek, uh, in Croatia and, uh, I moved two years ago. I moved to Zagreb to the capital. So you've been here, so you know, uh, how Zagreb is like.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. And, uh, I moved here because, uh, I wanna, uh, I wanna have, uh, better opportunities in my life and in my career.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, because I have this ambition inside of me and I wanna, I wanna grow. I wanna develop myself and do bigger things in life.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is why I moved here. And right now I'm, I'm working in a company that is called Seas. It is, uh, it is a company that, uh, that, uh, gives us services in, in the scrap, uh, recycling, metal, metal recycling.
[SPEAKER_00] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] And we are the biggest company here in, in the whole Balkans.
[SPEAKER_00] So we employ 2,000 people and I'm really, really close to the, to the, to the owners and to the, to the board members.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is a great opportunity for me to, to, to learn, uh, how, how, how, how, how, how can you really lead, uh, uh, a bunch of people and create a great organization.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is, this is, this is, this is where I'm, where I am right now.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, you know, recently I started this, or at least I'm trying to, to create a brand, uh, under the name of LUDE, as you've seen on Instagram, where I sent you the invite.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, the LUDE acronym stands for life of our dreams.
[SPEAKER_00] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] So I, I wanna, I wanna inspire, inspire, empower and educate people so they can become the best version of themselves.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so they can reach their full potential.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, so they can touch their dreams maybe someday.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] I, I think that, that living a life that way is much, much more interesting than, than just settling for the, for the average.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, I think inspiring others, helping others is, uh, I would say is the biggest thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's gonna, in the future pay off for you at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, what are you doing?
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's going to be great, especially you, I think you mentioned, are you planning to do some like courses, educational courses, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think, I mean, that's online education is, uh, developing, I would say, a pretty strong now.
[SPEAKER_01] Pretty strong.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, from my experience, when I was in university in us, I could say that, I mean, I learned a lot of stuff, but you know, some stuff didn't really help me, uh, to, you know, to implement where I'm today.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it's, uh, uh, it's good if someone can also, uh, I'm actually also recording, uh, some courses online courses, cause I've been asked to do that.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, a lot of, uh, clients, a lot of people that were all always asking me like, can you record a course?
[SPEAKER_01] Can you about that?
[SPEAKER_01] So I actually developed a course and, uh, I'm in the process of publishing it.
[SPEAKER_01] So I will actually.
[SPEAKER_01] So what, what is the topic of the course?
[SPEAKER_01] It's, it's about Instagram, like how basically brands can adapt to how they can grow their accounts, basically everything about that.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I actually decided, for example, now I'm planning to post that on Udemy platform.
[SPEAKER_01] And because I mean, my niche is kind of like building a brand, building my reputation on, uh, platforms like freelancing platforms.
[SPEAKER_01] Cause that's what my, uh, I would say journey started.
[SPEAKER_01] So I want to continue to try to scale my brand company on those freelancing platforms.
[SPEAKER_01] Fiverr is the main one for services, but I want to try to go for Udemy as well, because I think there is a lot of potential at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I like the platforms a lot because you get like really competitive because there's other people next to you.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it's good that you're in that competitive stage as well, and you can progress and you're looking to always, uh, grow your brand, get better reviews and all this stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's, I think, uh, what I'm trying to focus, uh, and I'll continue to focus.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think like Udemy, it's, it's great platform, especially like, uh, I mean, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01] What are your thoughts on the, on Udemy actually?
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I've been, uh, I've been using, uh, Udemy for, uh, I bought some, a few courses there and, uh, it is a great platform.
[SPEAKER_00] But what I was, uh, thinking about, I was thinking about, uh, self publishing the courses that I create, you know, uh, I, I, I got you.
[SPEAKER_00] You, I get your point that, uh, there is a, uh, a feeling of, uh, competition there on the, on those platforms.
[SPEAKER_00] And maybe it will drive more, uh, more, uh, more from you, more, more energy, more, more drive.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you do your, your, uh, business.
[SPEAKER_00] So you do your products even better, but, uh, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm, I'm thinking about self publishing.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's, it's also good.
[SPEAKER_01] Self published like platforms, like Thinkific, for example, uh, I actually, uh, we close, we work with them very closely.
[SPEAKER_01] So, uh, I'm going to go for, uh, self publishing as well, but a little bit later because I still want to, uh, you know, you know, if you go for self publishing, obviously you need to develop a website.
[SPEAKER_01] You need to develop more about this strategy.
[SPEAKER_01] How are you going to get, uh, the clients, how are you going to control all of that?
[SPEAKER_01] So it's also good.
[SPEAKER_01] I think there's a lot of potential from that.
[SPEAKER_01] Obviously you can just grow even bigger, I think, without the platform.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, but for me, as I'm trying to, in the niche as well, which I mean, I think, uh, I can get good start with the Udemy first and then I'll definitely look forward to, to jump and go for self publishing.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] It's great because, uh, uh, when you, when you, when you start on, on the, on the platform, like Udemy, you will get an instant feedback.
[SPEAKER_00] It is, it is, it is much more challenging to, to self published, uh, to self publish it because, uh, it involves so much more work than, than publishing it on, on other networks, on other platforms.
[SPEAKER_00] But, uh, when you, when you said, uh, that, that this is your strategy and, uh, my strategy right now is, uh, this is why I started with, with these podcasts, with these podcasts, with these interviews.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I just want to, I just want to, uh, uh, and, uh, communicate and network with a lot of people all around the world.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is, this is my fifth one.
[SPEAKER_00] My fifth podcast, your fifth guest.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, so I've been, I've been talking to, to the people.
[SPEAKER_00] The first guy was from Estonia.
[SPEAKER_00] He is an entrepreneur from Estonia.
[SPEAKER_00] And the second, uh, lady was from United States.
[SPEAKER_00] The third one was also, uh, architect from, from Los Angeles.
[SPEAKER_00] And I don't know, fourth was a guy entrepreneur from New Zealand.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, people from all around the world, from all, all around, all, all different backgrounds, different stories.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is very interesting to me, you know, uh, my strategy is to, to network, to, to meet a lot of people because, and especially in the future, I'm going to try, try to, to focus more on, on the people that, that are in the niche, in my niche.
[SPEAKER_00] And the, of personal growth and education.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, for me right now, I'm trying to find a teacher that I'm going to build a course around.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, so this is my first goal to find a teacher or teachers.
[SPEAKER_00] And the second goal is, is to find people who will help me, uh, promote the course.
[SPEAKER_00] so that I will do an affiliate marketing with, uh, when the course is created.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is, this is my strategy right now.
[SPEAKER_00] This is why I started with this podcast.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] To be, to be completely honest about it.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, uh, podcast is, is amazing.
[SPEAKER_01] I've seen, I actually listened to a lot of different podcasts, like Gary V.
[SPEAKER_01] Obviously he has a lot of content in his podcast, YouTube.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, and, uh, I like, I like podcasts a lot because it's just, you can, uh, you can, uh,
[SPEAKER_01] do other things like you can still work, do your stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, and at the same time you listen to the podcast.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think at the same time, like you're working out, you can listen to the podcast.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, those are great because you obviously it's, it's hard to get started.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm, I'm sure you're, you know, in that zone where you're trying to get more guests.
[SPEAKER_01] You're probably emailing them, like sending them messages.
[SPEAKER_01] And, but that's, that's the stage where everyone has to go through.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I think this is just, uh, the time matters of how long you're going to, you know, keep doing that.
[SPEAKER_01] And then in the future, you're going to have obviously structure and people going to be writing to you to be on, on the, on your podcast.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's, it's really good investment.
[SPEAKER_01] And especially for networking purposes for just building your brand, building your community.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, definitely that's going to really work out pretty well.
[SPEAKER_01] So, yeah, so I think, uh, uh, what, what else I wanted to say, what is your, uh, what type of course you want to like start building?
[SPEAKER_00] For example, the first one, you know, uh, I've been thinking a lot about it and, uh, the, your, your, uh, uh, your route is a little bit easier to, to, to produce.
[SPEAKER_00] Because you said that you were going to create courses on the topic of Instagram or something that is, I call it hard skills.
[SPEAKER_00] There are hard skills, but I, I think that I'm going to focus on soft skills.
[SPEAKER_00] So I don't know, skills like communication or productivity or things like that, where, you know, uh, you cannot measure them that easily.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, there, there is really this, uh, it is, it is hard to, to, uh, to, to educate people on, on things like that because, uh, those, those skills and those, uh, those things sound so abstract, you know, and, uh, I'm, I'm going to try to make them as practical as possible.
[SPEAKER_00] So people can really, really make action as soon as possible and, and improve their life, improve their lives, uh, really, really quickly.
[SPEAKER_00] So this, this is, this is something that I'm, that I'm trying to, uh, to do.
[SPEAKER_00] So I think that the, the first one, uh, would be about communication because I, because I think that communication is one of the most important tools, uh, that we have in our, in our arsenal as human beings, because we cannot do anything by ourselves.
[SPEAKER_00] We, we, we, we, we, all, all the things that we need to do, we need to do, uh, do them, uh, in teams, in, uh, in organizations.
[SPEAKER_00] So we, with other people, and if, if you want to motivate people, if you want to lead people, you, you, then you gotta be able to, to communicate more effectively.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is, it is a topic that a lot of people don't think about, but when, when you, when you go, go into it a little bit deeper, you will come to understand.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So humans are, uh, social, uh, beings and the only tool that we use is communication.
[SPEAKER_00] So, I don't know, bodily communication, uh, your face, facial expressions, your voice, deepness, pitch of your voice, things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Your eye contact, your, your movements, your, your, uh, and in the end, of course, it is the spoken word.
[SPEAKER_00] And you know all of this because I know that, that you are, uh, doing public talks.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you know what I'm saying?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, communication, I would say is one of the, it's probably the biggest, uh, in business as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Right.
[SPEAKER_01] If you're doing any sort of, if you're offering a service, communication comes, I would say as a bigger percentage than the actual service, because you need to be able to, uh, reply quickly.
[SPEAKER_01] You need to be able to explain, to make sure you can, you know, just talk as well properly, have the professional writing.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's just, I think it's, it's, there's a lot of things goes into communication and, uh, you can solve a lot of things as well through communication.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it's a really great topic.
[SPEAKER_01] And a lot of people, they actually don't, it's just, you know, you don't really learn this at school, at universities, like a lot of stuff that, uh, as well, I'm sure you're going to focus on.
[SPEAKER_01] It's just not taught by, to us.
[SPEAKER_01] So I never had any class.
[SPEAKER_01] I had a public speaking class, but the only, the only thing I did there was I was like memorizing my speech, presenting, and then I just got feedback on it.
[SPEAKER_01] So it was just really hard.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, it was very fast as you know, like when you're a student, you have so many things going on.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the same time, you start trying to start your hustle to your business.
[SPEAKER_01] You're just not like you're more in your business side rather than school.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's just sometimes when you get those, uh, subjects like public speaking, you just, the subject can cover all.
[SPEAKER_01] And they just teaching really basic stuff, which I I'm sure, you know, it's good, but at the same time, not for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01] So some people needs more, I would say in depth or more examples, more proofs, you know, personalization as well as I think is very important.
[SPEAKER_00] And you know, as a public speaker that we learned the best from examples, from symbols, from metaphors.
[SPEAKER_00] So as a public speaker, I don't know, I heard that Lisa Nichols, I don't know if you know who that person is.
[SPEAKER_00] Lisa Nichols says that you don't, you don't tell them, you show them.
[SPEAKER_00] So when you, when you are communicating, try to show people something, not, not tell them about something.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, when you show them, then they can create the picture in their minds and really connect with the, connect with the idea that you want to, want to give to them.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I, I just, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00] Go ahead. Go ahead. Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00] I, I just want to, I just want to, I just want to for, for the audience to know a little bit more about you.
[SPEAKER_00] I, I have so much questions to ask you. I don't know. I don't know. How, how long can you do it? How much time do you have?
[SPEAKER_00] Well, it's as long as you need.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So we're going to dive deep. Okay. So can you, can you, can you maybe tell the audience a little bit about yourself?
[SPEAKER_00] What is your background? What is your background story? Where have you been born? Raised? Can you tell, tell us something about your parents, maybe siblings and things like that?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, of course. So my name is Vasily and I've been born in St. Petersburg. That's where I live now. And we have, like I was saying, an office here. And I was basically born in that city. My parents from St. Petersburg as well. And my grandmothers, grandfathers, they all live here in St. Petersburg. So we're kind of like all in one city. And I also have two older sisters.
[SPEAKER_01] And they are obviously when we were very young, they were for me as like, like mentors. They were just like, kind of like helping a lot with, like, obviously communication with just, you know, in general, helping with other things. And later on, they became like, we started to be really close with each other. Like we always helped each other in anything. If it's at school or if it's, we'll go somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think we're just, you know, we were raised as a very, I would say friendly with each other. And later on, when we became older, I was playing tennis professionally.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's where, at the beginning, my parents, they wanted me to be in sports. So they tried, I tried many different. I tried tennis, I tried football, soccer, and hockey. And then eventually, it turned out to be the tennis because my, I liked it. I was always playing with like a racket, holding it, running with it.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's where I also started when I was around six, seven, I started playing tennis in the group. And later on, when I became like 10, when I was 10 years old, I started to play my first tournament in St. Petersburg.
[SPEAKER_01] And they were going really well. I would say I was, I really liked the sport. I was already like competitive. And my, also my father, he was, he wasn't professional athlete, but he was more as also very, I would say energetic, very athletic.
[SPEAKER_01] He liked sports as well. So that's kind of like the discipline I got from him. And then when I became around 12, 13 years old, I, I started to try to play my like international tournaments.
[SPEAKER_01] I went to, I remember Finland. That's the first, actually the St. Petersburg is really close to Finland. So a lot of people, they go there just for like shopping. And always, I just tried and went there to play a tournament.
[SPEAKER_01] And afterwards it became like, I would say routine. I was playing more consistently. And I was playing national tournaments. Eventually I was, I would say in the top 20, top, even, even I was like close to top 10 in Russia.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I went, when I was playing it. Top 10 in Russia. Yeah. In tennis. Really? Yeah. And then. Really good. Thanks. And then when I went to. That's not, that's not an easy task. I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, yeah, I, I, I mean, I wasn't like super amazing, but I was, I, a lot of kids at that age, they have, some of them have talent. And of course that's a huge advantage when you're in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01] If you have a talent, uh, you know, it's already gives you a lot of, uh, you have like the feeling on the ball. You're more kind of like coordinated and, uh, I didn't had a really talent.
[SPEAKER_01] I was more of the, like a hardworking. So when I was closer to like 15, 16, 17 years old, I started to play more international tournaments. And then I got to, uh, 350 in the world in juniors.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, that's, I would say when I became like 17, 18, that's where I started to get that, you know, through hard work started to pay off really. So when I turned 18 afterwards, I was like, my parents were like, you need to have also education, good, uh, degree as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And if you're in Russia, you can't really do both things. So like, like you can either go and play full time professionally and just forget about university or you just stop playing tennis professionally or any other sport and just go and study for different.
[SPEAKER_01] So you, so you stopped playing tennis at 18. So I basically, I didn't stop. So I went to, uh, I went to sports university in Russia, which is like all the athletes go there.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, that university helps you to still continue to play professionally. So I went there first for one year, just to see. And, uh, then I was still playing, uh, competitively.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I saw that, uh, in America, they have those like scholarships they have, uh, uh, you can also play for university. And at the same time you can, uh, later on build your professional career, or if it doesn't work out, you can still get a good degree.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was, uh, my parents, my dad, he also liked that idea because when I was like 20, I didn't really, uh, had the like amazing, uh, results.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I was, I would say I was above average, but I wasn't, I knew that it's going to be really, really hard to get to like top hundred in the world professionally because they just competition is, uh, you know, when you have that feeling, like when you need to make that decision, uh, it's not easy, but, uh, I decided to play for, to go to the university and play there for, for the team as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And I got a scholarship, which was very nice because all that, uh, financial side of my parents, which they helped me early in my career.
[SPEAKER_01] It's kind of like paid off a little bit because they didn't have to, uh, pay for university.
[SPEAKER_01] And then at that time I started to also with my freelancing hustle, because when I got to us, I saw a lot of.
[SPEAKER_01] When did you started it around 22, 23 freelancing career?
[SPEAKER_01] Freelancing career.
[SPEAKER_01] It was yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Around 21.
[SPEAKER_01] I would say somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01] 21.
[SPEAKER_01] So how old are you right now?
[SPEAKER_01] I'm 23.
[SPEAKER_01] 23.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So I started.
[SPEAKER_00] You're so young still.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Still pretty young.
[SPEAKER_01] A lot of, uh, year, years, uh, to go with business and experience.
[SPEAKER_01] But I started because I mean, when I got to university, I knew that I'm foreigner and, uh, to stay long in university is going to be harder.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I need to start doing something now.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was like, okay, maybe let's start with freelancing because when I was playing professionally tennis, I had my coach and he was, uh, basically he was running his own business and I actually helped him with social media.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, later on I did, I realized that this is something that I could be, uh, good at good.
[SPEAKER_01] Also, maybe this could help me in the future.
[SPEAKER_01] So when I was studying in university in us, I was at the same time doing a freelance freelancing.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, it's I basically during those times, uh, I didn't really had any fun time to be honest, because, uh, when I was, uh, doing on Fiverr, you have to always obviously keep up with the rating, keep up with the.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, all this orders, completion rates and, you know, delivery refunds, et cetera.
[SPEAKER_01] So my goal was to really get to the top of the freelancing on Fiverr to be like operate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] And I knew in order to become the top rate seller, I need to really put in the time and the work as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's what I was doing.
[SPEAKER_01] I was just, uh, going to my classes in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, then we had like a gym training with the team.
[SPEAKER_01] And then we had the lunch, then went to the training tennis.
[SPEAKER_01] And afterwards just coming back home, doing the homework and then doing the freelancing hustle.
[SPEAKER_01] So where have you, where have you been in United States?
[SPEAKER_01] I've been in which country city.
[SPEAKER_01] So I studied in South Carolina, uh, in Charleston city.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, we traveled a lot.
[SPEAKER_01] So I traveled on the, pretty much went to the New York, Florida, uh, into California, uh, Georgia, Virginia, like pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, not, of course not all the states, but I'll, I'll, I'll, I would say quite, quite a few to be honest.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so, so, so, uh, a big, a big portion of your childhood was, uh, about tennis, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, what, what, what can you tell the audience?
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe what did you learn, uh, in, in those years, uh, with this relationship with tennis and with everything that, that you needed to do to, to, to progress in one part, to be in the top 10 in, in whole Russia in your generation, which is really, really remarkable result.
[SPEAKER_00] result if you know how much Russians there is.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So what did, what did you learn during those, this period of your life and, and this relationship with tennis?
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, the first thing is that you have to put in the hours of work.
[SPEAKER_01] So no matter what you're doing is like, I had to train all the time because if I would not be training, preparing, you know, like waking up early in the morning, going for a run, then doing exercises.
[SPEAKER_01] Like if I won't be doing that, I wouldn't be able to achieve good results.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's, you know, you can really skip that.
[SPEAKER_01] There is no shortcuts.
[SPEAKER_01] Just have to literally, uh, sit and start, you know, doing, start, uh, your routine pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, the same transition to the business, to the freelancing first that, uh, I knew that I have to put in the hours at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] So I had to wake up early in the morning, go to Starbucks and start, you know, working on my freelancing.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, and then I, I, I have to do the same in the evening.
[SPEAKER_01] So just literally you have to, uh, time management.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's the biggest, uh, from, from, um, I would say from that experience that I had to manage my time.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I realized sometimes because I was like, okay, maybe I can postpone it later.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, you know, I just had no time to, when you're at that, when you're in university, you just don't have like free time.
[SPEAKER_01] To be honest, you just have to like go practice school.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I was kind of like behind a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01] And that feeling is not good at all.
[SPEAKER_01] You feel like you're behind, you need to catch up and you're just stressed, depressed as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So I learned the lesson that is better to be, uh, you know, it's better to suffer maybe some period of time, but then later on it's going to pay off and you're going to be much more, you're going to have better discipline because discipline is, uh, is very important.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00] So the lessons that you learned, uh, from tennis, you just applied to, to, to, to the, to, to your career right now and to the business.
[SPEAKER_00] And of course they, they are working in, in both, in, on, on both, uh, platforms, as I, I can say.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Really, really interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, can you tell me maybe, did you learn the, about discipline for your, from your father maybe, or is it something that, that you just developed, uh, by yourself?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I think, yeah, I think my father, he helped me definitely a lot because I, he was very, very, very good.
[SPEAKER_01] He was very strict, but at the same time, I, you know, he was, uh, disciplined and I was always watching what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, when he was waking up every morning, uh, going for exercising, jogging, you know, I, I just saw it.
[SPEAKER_01] And when I was young, I didn't realize it straight away, but he was always kind of like, uh, pushing me into the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, saying to me things that I was at the beginning, not, uh, I was basically disagree with him.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, but I was still doing because I was just, uh, you know, I wasn't that kid, which is like, no, I'm not going to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01] I was, I could be upset, but I still will do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I saw that it, uh, impacts me pretty well.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I saw the results.
[SPEAKER_01] I saw that it actually helped me.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think he, he helped a lot in that.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when I, uh, when I was in university, I just saw other, uh, students, what they're doing, what the, how they're spending their time.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was already, uh, realized some of them were just like having too much fun.
[SPEAKER_01] So I knew that at some point they will have to start doing that work.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was kind of like, uh, I tried not to waste the time.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the same time, I met some people who were very successful already at that stage who, uh, one of them actually, uh, his name is Will.
[SPEAKER_01] He, uh, was one of the founders of the app, uh, which brought, uh, basically, which was higher, uh, than the Snapchat for a few weeks.
[SPEAKER_01] And, and, uh, when I saw those like entrepreneurs, young hustlers, I was like, wow, this is, this is great.
[SPEAKER_01] This is, this is for me.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, this is, yeah, this is great.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the same time it opens, you know, a lot of doors because before when, like, when you, uh, grew up in Russia, like the mindset of people.
[SPEAKER_01] Here is a little bit different than us and many others.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, and I'm sure this could happen with any other country.
[SPEAKER_01] Like if you're born in another country, the mindset is everywhere is different.
[SPEAKER_01] And when I went to us, I just saw that at a younger stage, people could already develop some things and they think outside of the box and they can come up with something.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was like, you know, I shouldn't be wasting time.
[SPEAKER_01] I should be start and also working on something.
[SPEAKER_00] So let's talk, let's talk a little bit about mindset then.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you know, I, I learned so, so far that, uh, uh, mindset is created by few pillars.
[SPEAKER_00] I call, call it.
[SPEAKER_00] So the first, the first pillar is genetics.
[SPEAKER_00] It is something that you've got and you cannot change it.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is the first pillar.
[SPEAKER_00] The second pillar is your parenting.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, where have you been, uh, where you, where you have been born and around whom have you been born?
[SPEAKER_00] So who are your parents and what did they teach you?
[SPEAKER_00] I think that all of those soft skills that I'm, that I was talking about, uh, we really learned from our parents.
[SPEAKER_00] And then after it, uh, we learned some hard skills during our, the first, the third pillar, our educational system or formal educational system.
[SPEAKER_00] And the last pillar is, uh, for me, it is, it is media.
[SPEAKER_00] So when you combine, combine all those things, genetics, parenting, school system, and media, this is, this is something that creates a mindset and collective of mindset.
[SPEAKER_00] Mindsets, uh, is called culture.
[SPEAKER_00] So can you, can you maybe compare to, to, to me and to the audience, uh, the mindsets and the culture that you see?
[SPEAKER_00] That you've seen in United States and that you seen, uh, that you witness during your, uh, your younger days.
[SPEAKER_00] And right now in, in St. Petersburg, St. Petersburg and in, in Russia as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, uh, you know, in Russia, I would say, uh, we have, obviously we have, uh, some of the fields, which are like very well developed.
[SPEAKER_01] Some of the fields are not very well developed.
[SPEAKER_01] So when I was, uh, for example, playing tennis, uh, we still like in Russia, it was very limited, uh, courts.
[SPEAKER_01] We didn't have enough support as well from that.
[SPEAKER_01] So, uh, I would say in the summary to say the mindset people are, um, they're a little bit, I would say cold, you know, like they're a little bit closed.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, uh, I think that they just, uh, I would say like underestimating themselves, thinking that, uh, they won't, they won't be able to achieve it.
[SPEAKER_01] Or it's just too hard or it's not like, it's still maybe early.
[SPEAKER_01] So, because when I was at school or university for one year in, in, in Russia, I, you know, I was experiencing that.
[SPEAKER_01] Like a lot of students just, uh, they were saying, uh, okay, I'm gonna graduate.
[SPEAKER_01] Then I'm gonna work, uh, what I have degree on.
[SPEAKER_01] So they, they were just very kind of like, uh, one, uh, way go.
[SPEAKER_01] And when I went to us, I saw a lot of people there just like trying to create something, trying to, you know, just come up with something, always thinking outside of the box.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, and then I saw the results from them as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was like, if he's doing that, he, and then that person got really good results from it.
[SPEAKER_01] That means it's working.
[SPEAKER_01] So that means that pretty much, uh, anyone.
[SPEAKER_01] could try and start doing that.
[SPEAKER_01] Of course they need to have a mindset.
[SPEAKER_01] Like you mentioned that genetics.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I think it's very important.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, obviously it's not super important because a lot of, uh, stories, a lot of people, they maybe grew up from like, uh, uh, you know, not very good families, but then later on, they still were able to.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] I agree.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] To find the right path to fight with that.
[SPEAKER_01] And just, you know, building their career as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think, uh, very important from, from the first thing is you have to be able to work.
[SPEAKER_01] Like you just have to, uh, you know, sit there and work on your stuff for, I dunno, for 24 hours, maybe for even more, uh, don't sleep and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to have that feeling because if you don't have that, it's just not going to work out.
[SPEAKER_01] Like you, because when you're creating something, uh, especially that stage, you just have to give up a lot of, uh, other good stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] Which you have like your three time, your friends in the family, for example, you have to, because you have to keep working on your thing.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, then afterwards is the, I think very, was the discipline because when you're, if you're going to continue to work for like all the time, 20, you're just going to be exhausted.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, you're gonna, at one point you can just literally stop everything because you'll be thinking that you have too much and you're not going to the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think time management and discipline is, uh, very important.
[SPEAKER_01] And in Russia, people have, uh, people, people are very hardworking, like, uh, they have that feeling and they're big fighters as well.
[SPEAKER_01] But what maybe some of them don't have is that creative, uh, you know, creative thinking or be willing to take risks, for example.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, in us, of course, I mean, just, uh, like the education is also different.
[SPEAKER_01] Like the way people are taught in Russia and us is, is also different.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, but I think like from us, I just saw those people thinking more outside of the box, uh, than here in Russia.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, I can be free to, to say that, uh, United States really, really inspired your, your, uh, way of thinking.
[SPEAKER_00] It just, I think it just opened a lot of doors.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] It's so, uh, opened a lot of doors.
[SPEAKER_00] You said that, uh, for, for success in life, it is really, really important to, to be able to work hard.
[SPEAKER_00] And to have, uh, perseverance, to be disciplined, disciplined.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, and you, you gotta understand also.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, the audience gotta understand that working hard, only working hard is not enough.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course.
[SPEAKER_00] You need, uh, a lot of people are working their tails off each, each day, every day and every, uh, day in and day out.
[SPEAKER_00] And they are still struggling in life and they're not progressing.
[SPEAKER_00] They're not moving forward.
[SPEAKER_00] And for me, they are, they are just like a car that, that is stuck in the mud and cannot move forward because they need a little bit help.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, of someone who can, who can move them from that spot.
[SPEAKER_00] And for me, uh, for me, uh, this piece of, of a puzzle here is, uh, education.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] It is education, but particularly what kind of education?
[SPEAKER_00] I don't think that geography will help you, uh, change your mindset, uh, or, or some other, uh, studies.
[SPEAKER_00] But in particularly, I think that, uh, uh, personal growth.
[SPEAKER_00] So everything, everything starts with, with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00] Everything starts with, uh, with, with your own personal growth.
[SPEAKER_00] And when you progress, when you become better, then your business also can, can become more, can become better and can scale.
[SPEAKER_00] And you can lead more people and you can produce more results.
[SPEAKER_00] So can you tell me maybe what is, what is your relationship with, with, uh, with education?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, have you finished the college?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, are you, are you maybe, uh, educating yourself somehow and things like that?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I graduated from, um, the university in, uh, South Carolina.
[SPEAKER_01] And I would say like the last year for me was the hardest because my freelancing hustle was already.
[SPEAKER_01] kind of like moving.
[SPEAKER_01] I started to get results.
[SPEAKER_01] I was able to make money and, uh, it was really hard to manage those two things.
[SPEAKER_01] I would say three things because I was still also playing and I had to, had to play well to maintain my scholarship and to have good results.
[SPEAKER_01] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] So, uh, the lesson from that I learned is that you need to, uh, even if something that you don't like, for example, at that stage, I was not enjoying a lot of doing homework and school work, but I was still doing it.
[SPEAKER_01] I was still trying to manage it.
[SPEAKER_01] And if you can manage something that you are not, don't really like doing that, then that, uh, you know, feeling that, uh, skill is going to be very helpful in the business.
[SPEAKER_01] Why?
[SPEAKER_01] Because it's just, uh, if you're able to prioritize things and if you're able to manage them, because you know, that feeling when you are, for example, you found something in business that you like, and you just literally go full all in.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you spend all day creating maybe a website putting that everything because you're just love it so much.
[SPEAKER_01] And that is good, but you still need to prioritize.
[SPEAKER_01] You still need to, you know, uh, finish your other tasks or, you know, do other stuff, which you have.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's, it's very important.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I learned and, uh, education, I mean, uh, from university, like you were saying, like geography, some of the subject, a lot of subjects, which I took.
[SPEAKER_01] They literally just, I didn't really had, uh, much of, uh, effect from them.
[SPEAKER_01] Like they didn't really, uh, because, you know, if you take like a less, uh, subject and you pass it, then if you don't apply within maybe, uh, two months, three months, then, you know, you lose a lot of information from that.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was doing, uh, my agree with you 100%.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was doing my minor was in, in a computer information system.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was doing programming.
[SPEAKER_01] I was learning Python, Java.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, when I was, uh, when I passed the course and then I was like, okay, I have some skills, but then I didn't really apply them.
[SPEAKER_01] And then now, for example, it's just, you know, it's really hard now to remember what I did and it's going to take some time.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I still have that memory a little bit, but I need to still, uh, go through the course and be able to remember.
[SPEAKER_01] So I would say, you know, if you learn something, the best ways to, if you can implement it in something like, for example, even though if you learned the programming course, you can create a course yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] You can learn from your instructor, from everything, then you can try and potentially create a course.
[SPEAKER_01] So, you know, other students, this could find helpful because you pass the course, you have this information and to make sure that it doesn't go away, you can create your own course.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think this is a, this is a good, uh, as well investment of your time because other students might find it helpful and, uh, you can get good feedback on this.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, I agree. So, uh, can you tell me maybe, uh, are you doing something every day that, that's, uh, do you, do you use some chunk of time every day to, to be working on yourself?
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe to, to be reading, uh, watching some kind of, uh, educational videos, listening to some kind of a podcast or things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] So do, do you, uh, try to, uh, to work on yourself every single day?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. I mean, it starts from, uh, in my, in my, uh, from my experience, it starts from waking up early.
[SPEAKER_01] I think this is the, uh, I've seen it. I've seen it on your vlog.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes. Yes. So I, I do it. I would say, uh, you know, I had the, in September, I was, uh, also tried to put myself in a challenge where, you know, uh, because it, it, I think it's good to also experiment with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] Because obviously waking up early is not for everyone. Some people just cannot do that.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I found from myself, it helps me a lot. Because when I wake up earlier, uh, and I start working, uh, then I become much more productive.
[SPEAKER_01] So like my first three hours, uh, if I can start working, let's say at, uh, eight o'clock in the morning or even like 7:30.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, if I work until like 11:00 AM, I can, you know, get a lot of stuff done, uh, compare working like for four or five hours in the evening.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's what I learned from myself. And, uh, that's what I'm trying to consistently do because it helps me a lot.
[SPEAKER_01] Like it's, it's a good feeling as well. When you can do the, you know, your, like the most important tasks in the morning, and then you have the rest of the day for more of the creative side, more of the strategy development.
[SPEAKER_01] So for me, it works well if I can do that operational work in the morning and then just work with the team with developing other services and stuff in the afternoon.
[SPEAKER_01] Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. Also what I found, uh, when I, when I continue to work out, for example, exercising, uh, I think it's helps me.
[SPEAKER_01] It helps me a lot in the evening. Like when I go in the evening and go exercising, I try to listen like to the podcast.
[SPEAKER_01] to the Gary Vee podcast, to, uh, Team Ferris, to some of the others for like online courses, because I want to, I wanted to create the online course.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] And before I started creating online courses, I wanted to get more information. So I went for, uh, this guy, Phil Ebner.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. I've been, I've been listening to it. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. So I was listening to him because he, he has a good experience in Udemy. He pretty much made it on Udemy.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I was listening to his podcast, uh, and, uh, you know, I was just also learning so I can plan my course on how it will look and how I will promote it.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, that's how I would say I was doing that passive learning at the same time when I was doing working, when I was working out.
[SPEAKER_01] So, so you, so you call it, you call it passive, passive learning.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, passive learning because it's really interesting. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Because you go literally on the treadmill, you run for 20 minutes or whatever, or just working out, lifting weights.
[SPEAKER_01] And instead of listening music, you listen to the podcast because you can, obviously you're getting in better shape.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the same time, your mindset is thinking about something, uh, creative, something that you'll work on in the future.
[SPEAKER_01] And for me, it works well because, you know, those two things connects well.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I'm working out, I'm motivated. And the same time I get that, uh, new ideas, new strategies in my head.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when I go, uh, when I finished my workout, I just eat and then go sleep.
[SPEAKER_01] So I tried to not even open my laptop because I know that if I open it after in the evening, I could stay for all night and just find something, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it's, it's also important to shut down some of the things.
[SPEAKER_01] Like for example, you have your time in the morning, you have your time in the afternoon, and then I'll turn off everything.
[SPEAKER_01] Doesn't matter if it's, uh, even if, if some things are due, you know, you still need to, I would say, for example, let's say I have an order due, uh, that time.
[SPEAKER_01] And I had a lot of time to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And if I push it to the last minute and then I try to stay like until the last moment, obviously you need to finish that order, but you need to also punish yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] Like if you wait for so long, you need to give yourself a punishment.
[SPEAKER_01] So you can, in the future, you can, uh, start it early.
[SPEAKER_01] So I learned, I learned that lesson too.
[SPEAKER_01] And I try to, uh, you know, to work with myself because it's, it's the end of the day.
[SPEAKER_01] It's you, you're going to be driving your business.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to be, you know, leading your team.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to be, you're, you're the leader.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to at the same time test and train yourself very well.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] I see.
[SPEAKER_00] I see that you are very business minded person.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so let's, let's, let's dive in a little bit in this topic more.
[SPEAKER_00] I, I see that, that you've been waiting to, to speak more about this.
[SPEAKER_00] And I wanted, I wanted to, to have a little more background from, from, of your background story.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, let, uh, so let, let, uh, tell us a little bit about your, about the beginning
[SPEAKER_00] of, of the freelancing career about the Fiverr and, uh, things like that until this point where
[SPEAKER_00] you started traveling all around the world and, uh, giving public, uh, public talks on conferences,
[SPEAKER_00] uh, creating awesome videos, which are really, really like.
[SPEAKER_00] So thumbs up.
[SPEAKER_00] I really enjoyed them.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you are also very courageous to have your team besides you, uh, every single day and doing
[SPEAKER_00] these vlogs and really, really, really great production.
[SPEAKER_00] So thumbs up.
[SPEAKER_00] So can you tell, uh, tell the audience a little bit about the start of the freelancing and
[SPEAKER_00] move us through, through, through today?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I mean, when I started, like I was saying, I started it on the freelancing platform Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, you know, I tried also besides that, I tried to do it on my own through just literally
[SPEAKER_01] when I was in Russia, I was just sending maybe 50 to 150 text, uh, messages through WhatsApp,
[SPEAKER_01] through emails to different like companies, small businesses, uh, to promote their Instagram
[SPEAKER_01] account.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I was doing Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] So I created the Fiverr profile and Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_00] And how, how did you stumble upon the Instagram?
[SPEAKER_00] And how did, how did you, uh, thought about it that you could, that you could do something
[SPEAKER_00] like this?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So I, I tried before Instagram, I tried, uh, I tried to do graphic because I had a background
[SPEAKER_01] in Photoshop.
[SPEAKER_01] I had some video editing skills.
[SPEAKER_01] So I tried, uh, first doing graphic designs and I went as well on Fiverr and was just creating
[SPEAKER_01] some graphic designs for my friends.
[SPEAKER_01] And I realized that it's not that what I like to do.
[SPEAKER_01] It's not that, that I can do well.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I was not really passionate about it.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was just like, uh, I should not do it if I'm not passionate because at the end of
[SPEAKER_01] the day, uh, it's not obviously money matters, but if you don't have a passion, if you don't
[SPEAKER_01] like doing that, you're not gonna, you know, you're not gonna push, uh, 24 hours to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you're gonna be like always not enjoying it.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] You will not have energy to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] You will not have energy.
[SPEAKER_01] Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01] So then I was, uh, tried video as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Same thing happened.
[SPEAKER_01] I enjoyed it, but, uh, still I was not very, I would say I was slow and I, I knew that there
[SPEAKER_01] were people better than me that it's not very, uh, it's not the niche, which I could be
[SPEAKER_01] like an expert.
[SPEAKER_00] So then if I can say for, for a second, which is really important for the audience.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you have an idea of something, uh, that you want to do something, uh, for me, it is,
[SPEAKER_00] it is the best to do it right away and to really see if you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, you just have to, you know, do it.
[SPEAKER_01] It's not about, it's not about the money at the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01] You just have to, uh, tell yourself, can you do this for literally 15 hours straight?
[SPEAKER_01] Are you going to enjoy doing that or not?
[SPEAKER_01] And if you say no, then, you know, in the long term, it's not going to work out.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to be really passionate.
[SPEAKER_01] And when I was helping my coach with, uh, his fitness, uh, business and, uh, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] basically he was, uh, asking help in the social media.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was like, yeah, I'll, I'll, I'll be happy to help.
[SPEAKER_01] Although I didn't have amazing results with Instagram, et cetera, but Instagram, because
[SPEAKER_01] he wanted me to promote, know his Instagram.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was literally sitting there with, uh, his, uh, with my phone, with his Instagram account.
[SPEAKER_01] And I tried and I started to engage with other people.
[SPEAKER_01] I started to, you know, following them.
[SPEAKER_01] I started to sending messages to them.
[SPEAKER_01] I started to interact with them.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, I, I liked that process.
[SPEAKER_01] I liked, uh, I just, you know, I would say I was trying to get their attention at the same
[SPEAKER_01] time providing some value there and structuring the content of, uh, my fitness coach brand.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, I really enjoyed that process.
[SPEAKER_01] I was just literally spending, uh, pretty much the all majority of my free time and creating
[SPEAKER_01] posts, writing the description, you know, all researching all these hashtags and just trying
[SPEAKER_01] to find people, uh, through other like competitor accounts for others.
[SPEAKER_01] I just enjoyed that process.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, then I realized that let's maybe try and come up with some sort of a service
[SPEAKER_01] to help other people as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Because, uh, during that time when I was helping him, uh, I grew the account to 10,000 followers
[SPEAKER_01] in around three, four months.
[SPEAKER_01] And then we were able to, and at that time it was much easier to grow
[SPEAKER_01] because there were no limits pretty much on Instagram.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, then we got a feature.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you, you growed it, uh, without the promotions or paid promotion.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So I just grew it manual.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was just like following organically people.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I was posting a really good content where I was structuring.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, he was, uh, selling those like a fitness band, elastic bands and fitness mats.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was, uh, structuring and putting them into like the workouts.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was creating like workouts for people.
[SPEAKER_01] If they buy those products, they can go to Instagram and they will see different workouts,
[SPEAKER_01] which I was creating.
[SPEAKER_01] So I just, I liked, and I used some of my, uh, photo, uh, Photoshop skills, just, just to kind
[SPEAKER_01] of like make it nicer.
[SPEAKER_01] But in the end of the day, I was enjoying the process of growing the account, getting
[SPEAKER_01] the feedback from people, enjoying, and ultimately I were able to get more sales from that as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So when I was, uh, at the stage where like, if I go full time with him and continue doing
[SPEAKER_01] that, or if I can, you know, maybe potentially start this as my own service, I decided to choose
[SPEAKER_01] to go and start it as my own a service because I mean, I was, you know, more passionate.
[SPEAKER_01] And of course in his business, I would say, uh, you know, he was doing really well, but I
[SPEAKER_01] was also managing, you know, a lot of different styles.
[SPEAKER_01] I was managing the shipping, managing the, creating the website, creating the application as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So for me, I decided to take the route of sticking more to Instagram and, you know, trying
[SPEAKER_01] at least giving a try to develop and help maybe other people.
[SPEAKER_00] So is it, is it, is it much harder right now, uh, today to grow your Instagram account?
[SPEAKER_00] And then it was, I don't know, three or four years ago.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I mean, now obviously it's harder because you have like engagement drops, uh, like crazy
[SPEAKER_01] compared to a few years ago.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, you know, it's just, you have those limits, you have a lot of different tools, a lot of different
[SPEAKER_01] platforms, uh, and it's just, uh, you know, you have to, I would say you have to know those limits.
[SPEAKER_01] You have to be knowledgeable about all of that stuff, because if you do something wrong, Instagram
[SPEAKER_01] could restrict your account.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's basically the worst thing could happen.
[SPEAKER_01] So now it's much, I would say harder because Instagram is also encouraging you to use paid promotions.
[SPEAKER_01] So you need to put money into Facebook ads and Instagram ads, which is a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01] Like it's, it's not bad if you, if you're investing in, in, uh, in the ads, it's good.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to get the return back, but you have to be careful which type of content you're promoting.
[SPEAKER_01] Because if it's just picture of your friends and you're trying to run, uh, Instagram ads for that, it's not going to bring you any results.
[SPEAKER_01] If it's something valuable, like where you're maybe, you know, explaining something, providing value and you run ads on the video like that.
[SPEAKER_01] Then it's going to bring you a lot of value because people are going to be saving.
[SPEAKER_01] People are going to be probably sharing with their friends and ultimately it's going to lead to, uh, maybe some leads and maybe some sales or at least some conversions in the future.
[SPEAKER_00] So, I watched, I watched your video, uh, the one, uh, the other day about, uh, about using hashtags.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] And it really, really helped me.
[SPEAKER_00] So I I've been, I've been, uh, doing Instagram for about a year right now with this, uh, brand loot.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, I've been, I've been using hashtags that are really, really popular.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, in this video, you, you, you said to us that if you have a smaller account, so I, right now I have around three and a half thousand followers and I get around 100, 150 likes on average.
[SPEAKER_00] And you said, and you said, if you, if you, if you have, uh, this amount of likes, then you need to pick, uh, you need to pick, uh, hashtags that, that have around 10,000, maybe 15,000 or 20,000, uh, likes.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So I tried it and usually I get around 1000 people rich.
[SPEAKER_01] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, for this post, I think in the first day that I got 4,000, uh, 4,000 rich, which, which was really, really great.
[SPEAKER_00] Wow.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so thank you.
[SPEAKER_00] It, it felt it worked.
[SPEAKER_00] No.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, hashtags is, is, uh, it's a big talk as well about that because you have to also what, what it's good.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, let's say you want to target people who are in, um, for example, in, uh, Zagreb, Croatia.
[SPEAKER_01] Right.
[SPEAKER_01] You can use hashtags, like for example, you just write Zagreb hashtag and you will see a lot of different, uh, choices, like maybe Zagreb lifestyle, Zagreb city.
[SPEAKER_01] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] And if you use more of those of the city and you post something which is relevant, so you can, you know, you can use these hashtags to get the audience, which are in Zagreb or maybe visiting Zagreb or maybe travel to Zagreb.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's also good if you're, uh, testing those city hashtags because they can help you get a more relevant audience for you as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So, but yeah, I mean, it's, it's good strategy.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you started, uh, with Instagram, Instagram, uh, because of your coach and you really liked the process.
[SPEAKER_00] This is why, why you stick to it and you did not, uh, gave up.
[SPEAKER_00] You didn't, didn't give up.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, and after it, you started to, to give it as a service on Fiverr, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00] Yes, correct.
[SPEAKER_01] So I went, uh, on the freelancing platform.
[SPEAKER_01] I tried other ones.
[SPEAKER_01] So this wasn't only Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] It was Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] It was Upwork and, uh, and I tried another one.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it was a Russian one.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, then I was just, you know, getting, uh, I put myself out there.
[SPEAKER_01] I recorded the video of myself.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, it was, I would say now it's, it was terrible because I was just sitting in my room and, uh, I was very shy.
[SPEAKER_01] I was not used to public speaking and speaking at all.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I was just very shy, but I knew that it's going to help me because the video, they convert much better compared to photo or even nothing.
[SPEAKER_01] So I, I did it and I started to get, you know, some people writing me.
[SPEAKER_01] I remember my first client ever was, uh, actually a student and he paid me like $5 to help him with his account.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was literally, uh, working, uh, it was like one month work for $5.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I, I, I even wanted to work longer.
[SPEAKER_01] And I gave him another few weeks of free work because I liked the process of, uh, just him being happy of my work.
[SPEAKER_01] And I want, I wanted him to become even more happy.
[SPEAKER_01] So like I tried to over deliver him and he was in, he wrote amazing review.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was, and now for me, it was like a huge energy.
[SPEAKER_01] And so $5 in total for all your service.
[SPEAKER_01] It was, it was $5.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I was literally working for like a month.
[SPEAKER_01] Is it, is it $5 for an hour or $5 for a month?
[SPEAKER_01] It was before it used to be, uh, I used to charge like at the very beginning for $5, like for the whole month.
[SPEAKER_01] And then once, and then once I got like five clients, I, of course I raised the prices because, you know, I was like, I, it's just getting too much.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm not going to provide the same quality, which I want.
[SPEAKER_01] So obviously, uh, once you're at this stage where you're getting already customers, then you will be able to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_01] You'll be able to, uh, you know, like for example, increasing the prices is, is another topic, but like, you'll be able to figure out what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01] How much you're spending your time, how you can be more productive, you know, how you, maybe you can come up with an extra services.
[SPEAKER_01] So you're going to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's going to take some time, but for me, I will just enjoying the process.
[SPEAKER_01] Like it's not the point where I was earning, but I was just building my brand on the platform.
[SPEAKER_01] And I really liked it.
[SPEAKER_01] I liked the reviews, which I was getting and, you know, just the overall, the process of, uh, you know, getting that order, communicating, delivering the order.
[SPEAKER_00] And you became a top rated seller on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, I became top rated seller on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] It was, uh, last year in April.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, actually it was funny because I remember that day and I wanted to quit Fiverr before I wanted to quit and stop doing, uh, what I was doing on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] Because, uh, at some points I was, uh, you know, my services were not, uh, there were some problems or misunderstandings with the search and how my, uh, services were not.
[SPEAKER_01] My, uh, services were rated in the search.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was also not upset, but I just was confused with Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] But then I was telling myself, just keep going because my goal was to become a top rate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was like, just keep going.
[SPEAKER_01] It's going to be fine.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, eventually everything's going to be fine.
[SPEAKER_01] So last year I was literally, it was six o'clock in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] It was very hard day.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I was just, uh, uh, you know, not, uh, not in the mood of working, but I knew I had to do it because otherwise it's going to be a big mess.
[SPEAKER_01] So I opened my laptop, go on the Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] And then it says you're a top rate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] And at that point I was like, yeah, I was like, I couldn't believe it because they don't tell you when you're going to be a top rate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] Like it's just going to happen from maybe today or next year.
[SPEAKER_01] But in my head I was like thinking maybe I'll be top rate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] So it was April.
[SPEAKER_01] And I was thinking maybe I could be like in the end of the year, top rate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] So imagine like I was not even expecting it to be right now.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I get the message like that.
[SPEAKER_01] I love it.
[SPEAKER_01] So of course the result I got, it just pushed me so much.
[SPEAKER_01] So like I said to myself, okay, Fiverr is working.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, you're getting a good feedback.
[SPEAKER_01] You're getting customers.
[SPEAKER_01] And I met a lot of friends, uh, like partners, uh, potential like clients.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I met a lot of them, even lip summit.
[SPEAKER_01] They found me through Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] So the summit, they contact me.
[SPEAKER_01] They actually used some of my services.
[SPEAKER_01] They liked it.
[SPEAKER_01] And then we started talking about me being, uh, the speaker at the lip summit.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was like, okay, it's working.
[SPEAKER_01] So let's continue and push it even more.
[SPEAKER_01] And so, sorry, sorry.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, go, go, go, go.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So, and then, uh, I decided to go full in a push it even more.
[SPEAKER_01] And now we're at this stage where we're a company, but we have Fiverr as our, like a backend.
[SPEAKER_01] So basically, uh, before it was, it was like, and now it's also, it's my personal brand.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] But now we have created a company, uh, which called not media.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when people go on the website, they see all information about what we have services and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when they go and place the Fiverr, it's actually happening on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, uh, so at the beginning you are giving the services, uh, as yourself, as Vasily.
[SPEAKER_00] And right now you are giving the services on Fiverr as a company.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, uh, in, on Fiverr, it's still going to be me.
[SPEAKER_01] It's still going to be my picture, my, just, if, if they find on Fiverr, they're going to find my personal brand.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] But, you know, in order to obviously build a company and, you know, build your, as well, reputation, we have obviously created the brand.
[SPEAKER_01] We have created the website.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when people go on the website, they see all the information about the services, about the stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] And then if they want to contact us, they go and then it's redirected to Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's, it's very good, I would say, uh, synchronized together, but all the operations, all the communications, all the handling of orders happening on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] So I'm still building my freelancing reputation at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's what I want to go because, uh, in the future I want to, you know, develop, uh, um, maybe another business where I'll help freelancers, where I will inspire freelancers to start their own hustle.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, now I'm at the stage where I want to, you know, try to build my online courses, see how they're going to go.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I'll write a book as well about the freelancing.
[SPEAKER_01] Great.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm going to buy the book and the course.
[SPEAKER_00] I'll give it for free.
[SPEAKER_00] No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm going to buy it.
[SPEAKER_00] I just, I just insist.
[SPEAKER_00] I want to do it.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, so have you heard, uh, maybe about the, uh, the Robert Kiyosaki?
[SPEAKER_00] Do you know who he is?
[SPEAKER_00] No.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So he, he wrote the book, rich dad, poor dad.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is, it is a bestseller.
[SPEAKER_00] So in this book, you have, uh, a cash flow quadrant.
[SPEAKER_00] And so on the top left, it says there, there are employees.
[SPEAKER_00] So they change their time for money on, on the top, uh, on, on the bottom left.
[SPEAKER_00] There are, uh, there are freelancers.
[SPEAKER_00] So the, the, the people like, like, like you are, like you were a few, few months or a few years ago on the top, on the top right are entrepreneurs.
[SPEAKER_00] So when, when we, we talk firstly about freelancers, they change all their time for money.
[SPEAKER_00] And when they stop, everything stops.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, employees, they have this privilege.
[SPEAKER_00] If they stop, they can go on vacation.
[SPEAKER_00] They, they can go on a, I don't know if they're sick, they can, they can go on a sick leave.
[SPEAKER_00] But if you're a freelancer, when you are sick, everything stops when you go on a vacation, everything stops.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, on the top right corner, corner, there are entrepreneurs.
[SPEAKER_00] They exchange other people's time for money.
[SPEAKER_00] And on the bottom right, there are investors.
[SPEAKER_00] So what they do, they, they, they change, they exchange their money for more money.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, you know, a lot of, a lot of people, uh, that are right now in, in those top, in that top left corner.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, employees, and they want to become self-employed.
[SPEAKER_00] They want to become freelancers.
[SPEAKER_00] Do you think it is, it is a great way for them before they move to entrepreneurship to go and try to do something on only by themselves?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, just, just like, just like you did with freelancing.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. I mean, I think it's, uh, very important because there's need to, uh, it's kind of like transitioning from employers into freelancers.
[SPEAKER_01] It's that's where you put yourself in that environment where you're responsible for, uh, obviously the work you're doing at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] You're responsible for your growth, for your, uh, you know, planning of time, uh, and et cetera.
[SPEAKER_01] So like you're, you're starting to be more responsible and some people they're like, oh, I want to be an entrepreneur, but they're just, they don't, don't have any idea what it's going to be like.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's also going as a freelancer.
[SPEAKER_01] It's good because you can test yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] You can see it.
[SPEAKER_01] And then in order to jump into the next step, I would say it's start to hire, for example, an assistant who is gonna, uh, let's say, you know, okay, this part of the work you can outsource, you can maybe hire an employer and, you know, start teaching.
[SPEAKER_01] That's what I did.
[SPEAKER_01] That's how I started to, uh, develop my team.
[SPEAKER_01] I had, uh, my first, uh, it was actually a friend.
[SPEAKER_01] He started to helping me and I was obviously paying him certain amount of, uh, amount and, uh, he was doing that work.
[SPEAKER_01] And basically it was for me, it was good because, uh, I knew that, uh, I knew that you have to do this, this, this, and I just explained to him and he was doing that work.
[SPEAKER_01] And for me, it was easier because I was, you know, trying to do more and trying to develop, uh, in the future.
[SPEAKER_01] And then second employee, it happened the same.
[SPEAKER_01] I had that amount of work, which I knew how to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And I just explained it, showed it, you know, she taught, and then another person started doing that.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's how you start developing, you know, slowly and slowly your team.
[SPEAKER_01] So in the future you have, uh, basically, you know how to do this work, but you have your team members who you explain to them, show them, and they're responsible fully for that amount of work.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, like, like, like this, you can start, you know, growing and transitioning from entrepreneurship, but then you also have to be responsible for their quality.
[SPEAKER_01] You have to be, you know, check them.
[SPEAKER_01] You have, so it's, it's another, uh, I would say it's, it's another story and.
[SPEAKER_01] It's a different skill.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Different skill at that stage.
[SPEAKER_01] You also, you can be lucky.
[SPEAKER_01] You can have a, for example, person who can be, who will be also motivated, who will be like skilled and, you know, understanding straight away, or you can get a person who is just gonna realize that it's not for him.
[SPEAKER_01] And he's just gonna probably leave and you have to accept it.
[SPEAKER_01] And you have to, you know, continue to find another team member and, you know, uh, and work with him.
[SPEAKER_01] And then he will be able to make a decision to stay with you or not.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Very good.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so, uh, have you been, uh, have you ever been employed?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, actually never, never.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So you don't know what's, what's, what's, what is the feeling of, of being employed?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Never, never been.
[SPEAKER_00] Great.
[SPEAKER_00] So you just dived in, uh, freelancing and right now you're building your company and you're building.
[SPEAKER_00] your, your team, your organization.
[SPEAKER_00] Very, very good.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so, uh, can you tell maybe, uh, someone from the audience, let's try to help one person
[SPEAKER_00] today.
[SPEAKER_00] So if they're thinking maybe, maybe they're studying right now, they're, they're in a college
[SPEAKER_00] and they're thinking about making some money on a, on a side maybe, and they, they want
[SPEAKER_00] to do some kind of a freelancing thing.
[SPEAKER_00] So how can they start?
[SPEAKER_00] Do they need to, to, uh, analyze themselves and see what kind of a skills they have?
[SPEAKER_00] What kind of a passion they have and diving in this particular thing or what, what, what advice
[SPEAKER_00] do you have for them?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think, I mean, first is just, uh, like where is listening?
[SPEAKER_01] If you have, for example, a passion, like if you have a hobby, maybe in painting, right?
[SPEAKER_01] You can, you know, literally turn this into your freelancing hustle.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to just look at you, just realize what you enjoy doing.
[SPEAKER_01] Maybe it's, if it's just the hobby, you know, I dunno, even like sports, you need to develop
[SPEAKER_01] your hustle through, you know, with your hobby.
[SPEAKER_01] So for example, if you're at university, you have a lot of different courses, like sometimes,
[SPEAKER_01] you know, try and try to take different, like try to take programming course, try to take
[SPEAKER_01] design course, try to take, uh, uh, there's like creating your website, try to take finance,
[SPEAKER_01] you know, so it's good to try and, and, and try different things, or you can just go literally
[SPEAKER_01] take online courses.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, you go, you can go on Udemy and just try a few courses because then when
[SPEAKER_01] you, you know, finish them, you will be able to have the feeling if you are enjoyed it or.
[SPEAKER_01] And once you learn something, uh, go and try to apply straight away.
[SPEAKER_01] So you can go to the platforms, freelancing platforms, because platforms are great.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, since you don't need to create your own website, you don't need to create, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] you just literally going out there, looking at what other peoples do, you know, realizing,
[SPEAKER_01] coming up with this service and just, you know, offer it.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, you know, if you have any skills in Photoshop, go ahead and offer, I will edit your photo
[SPEAKER_01] in 12 hours, for example, because, uh, when you're, there's a lot of services like that,
[SPEAKER_01] like with the Photoshop.
[SPEAKER_01] So if you want to have some competitive advantage, you can offer a low price.
[SPEAKER_01] You can be like $5, for example, just to get started.
[SPEAKER_01] And you can do it quicker than any other.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, instead of 24 hours, do it for 12 hours.
[SPEAKER_01] And then it's just literally, if you, if you like it, it just go and approach.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, you have on fire, for example, you have the buyer request section where you
[SPEAKER_01] can go and message other people, other potential clients and just try to make, become more personalized.
[SPEAKER_01] So just like literally don't do copy paste messages every time, write a new message and
[SPEAKER_01] try to become more personalized.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's how you're going to realize like in the future, then you will see, okay,
[SPEAKER_01] I enjoy Photoshop or I enjoy creating website.
[SPEAKER_01] And then you can, you know, start pushing that.
[SPEAKER_01] Because it's literally like, if you don't enjoy something, you know, you should not be doing it
[SPEAKER_01] because it's going to not going to work out.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to be stressed that you're going to hate yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] And then eventually you want to come back to your old job or being corporate.
[SPEAKER_01] So you just have to find that passion.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, I, I, I love it.
[SPEAKER_00] So do you, do you advise to the people maybe that, that are employed right now that they can see
[SPEAKER_00] what their strengths are, what they love, love to do.
[SPEAKER_00] What are their hobbies, what, what they can, uh, expand on and do it.
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe, uh, like a side hustle, uh, in the, in the afternoon after their work.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know, use some, some chunk of time, three, four, five hours in the afternoon.
[SPEAKER_00] And just start the process, start the process.
[SPEAKER_00] And one day, one day they can maybe move to do, do it full time.
[SPEAKER_00] And then in the future, uh, create their, their own team and start creating their own, their, their own organization.
[SPEAKER_00] Just like you started right now.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, I would suggest like whoever's, for example, employed working in the company.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, the best way, if you want to work on your own stuff is if you do it in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] So literally go to bed early.
[SPEAKER_01] Like you finish your work at six or seven.
[SPEAKER_01] Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, five.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Because if you're going to do it after your work, you're going to be exhausted.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, you know, like, it's just exhausting feeling.
[SPEAKER_01] Like you don't have any energy because you already spent so many.
[SPEAKER_01] Very good advice.
[SPEAKER_01] Regular work.
[SPEAKER_01] So just go to bed at nine, 10 PM.
[SPEAKER_01] Wake up at, you know, five 36 and spend those two, three hours working on your own thing.
[SPEAKER_01] Because you will have a lot of energy.
[SPEAKER_01] You will be like, uh, you'll have that feeling like you're in your own business.
[SPEAKER_01] And then once you stop, you go to your normal, you know, job, you do your work there, et cetera.
[SPEAKER_01] And then after that work, you can maybe think about the strategy for next day or think how you can.
[SPEAKER_01] So don't do like any operational because you're going to be, uh, not productive at all.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, but go to bed early, uh, wake up again early and then do operational, you know, all that main stuff in the early morning before your day job.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think this is, this is what I learned from school as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Great advice.
[SPEAKER_01] I was doing that before school and I had a lot of energy.
[SPEAKER_01] I was like pushing and I was productive and just everything was great because at the end of the day, you just want to lay lay in the bed, watch some video or a movie.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's so hard to like, so hard to focus and you're not, and it's not good to push yourself at that point because you're not going to be productive.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's just the most important.
[SPEAKER_01] Just like Gary Vee says, play Madden and watch House of Cards.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, Gary, Gary Vee is interesting.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, Gary Vee is saying like always, obviously he's saying like what you're doing after six till nine.
[SPEAKER_01] Obviously if you can do it, it's amazing.
[SPEAKER_01] But I, from my experience, it's, it's much harder.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] It's a better strategy to do it in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Because you're fresh, you're just, you know, ready to go and do it.
[SPEAKER_01] So the same, same what Gary Vee says, but just do it in the morning and that's going to be more productive.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] I hope that we, that you inspire, that we inspire someone right now.
[SPEAKER_00] Great.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] I see that, that you, you have your emphasis also is largely on, on your personal brand.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you have a, you are really active on a lot of conferences.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] You, you, you want to connect with, with people in person.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you want to share your message.
[SPEAKER_00] You want to share the things that you are doing.
[SPEAKER_00] And you also are creating, uh, your vlog around your, uh, yourself.
[SPEAKER_00] So why is it that you are creating this personal brand?
[SPEAKER_00] Why do you think that this is important?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So a good question.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I decided to invest, uh, obviously it's money at the same time and time into that.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, into the personal brand because personal brand.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's especially as good for if you're a freelancer or looking to be a freelancer, you go as your personal brand, not just go as a company, which you want to create, but just go as a person.
[SPEAKER_01] Because in the future, uh, it's gonna, obviously your name always stays, right?
[SPEAKER_01] You're not going to change your name and obviously your face as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So, uh, in the longterm, hopefully, hopefully, I mean, a lot of people, they do different stuff, but, uh, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you're going to be in the future, like people are going to realize by your name, you know, they're going to be like, Oh, uh, for example, this guy did a good job.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, so it's just, it's just very important for, you know, uh, you know, building your obviously brand awareness, because then if you're going to go and start your company, uh, you're going to have already some sort of community.
[SPEAKER_01] or people are going to already, you know, kind of like could support you in that.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's why it's important to build your personal brand on social media, for example, building your community.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, you know, when you start something, when you go with some sort of projects, you can have that support of people.
[SPEAKER_01] And yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] And, and, uh, people buy from, from, from the people they trust and then that they know.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the end of the day, you know, you can offer the same service, but, uh, you know, for example, John, he enjoyed working, you know, with you rather than other person because he had that good vibes connection.
[SPEAKER_01] And then just, you know, he enjoyed the process.
[SPEAKER_01] So it even, it's good for your company.
[SPEAKER_01] Like for example, Gary Vee, he's building a huge personal brand and he's already, he has an incredible personal brand, but at the same time, that personal brand helps him, uh, you know, for getting, uh, bigger clients, corporate clients, uh, and for his agency, for his other companies.
[SPEAKER_01] So it helps him in the longterm for the companies as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And for the same time for you, it helps you in, uh, different skills as well in, you know, personal growth and et cetera.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's very important.
[SPEAKER_00] So if, if someone wants to start, uh, uh, improving and growing their personal brand, how can they start?
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I think, I mean, right now, for example, Instagram, right.
[SPEAKER_01] It's, it's a big, uh, one of the, uh, where people are right now on Instagram mostly.
[SPEAKER_01] And of course it's good to build your personal brand on social media.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, LinkedIn, it's also great if you can start and develop.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, myself, I haven't been really, uh, heavy on the LinkedIn yet, but my goal is to be also consistent there and see what this could bring me.
[SPEAKER_01] But I was really, I'm really pushing right now Instagram, uh, and YouTube, YouTube is the slowest platform, uh, for growth.
[SPEAKER_01] But at the same time, it's good for a longterm because you're building like your legacy, all those videos, all those information you put there.
[SPEAKER_01] It's gonna help in the future, in the longterm people can find more information.
[SPEAKER_01] They can, uh, look back and maybe be inspired by your journey.
[SPEAKER_01] And then eventually you can, you know, also build your channel.
[SPEAKER_01] So YouTube, you have to give maybe like three to five years to really build, uh, it's successful Instagram.
[SPEAKER_01] It's much faster.
[SPEAKER_01] You can just literally go and start putting the content, start, you know, uh, documenting your journey and it's hard.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, it's, it's very hard.
[SPEAKER_01] Like it's, it's just incredible how hard it is to go out there and just start talking from your phone and just, you know, because it's not what, um, the majority of people do.
[SPEAKER_01] But at the same time, you have to realize that if you want to be at the 1% of, uh, you know, earning and just be, you know, very successful.
[SPEAKER_01] You have to do the work, which, you know, like probably less, like 1% of the whole world are, are doing it.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, this is, uh, I think super important.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] You gotta do something that, that is uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00] Oftentimes.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So you gotta step outside of your comfort zone.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Comfort zone is, uh, is, is also, and you know, I also like, I talk about that and sometimes, for example, I could take some break.
[SPEAKER_01] Because we're humans.
[SPEAKER_01] Like it's, we're not all perfect.
[SPEAKER_01] So like we can do mistakes.
[SPEAKER_01] We can do things.
[SPEAKER_01] But of course, like, even though like I had a small break on Instagram, I was not very active in the last maybe two weeks as I was before.
[SPEAKER_01] And now for me, it's harder to get back because it's just like, I lost momentum.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I lost that feeling.
[SPEAKER_01] And now I'm thinking about too much of what I should say, what I should not say.
[SPEAKER_01] And that is not good.
[SPEAKER_01] So if you can go and slowly just doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01] Like if you think the content is, uh, like literally shit, just, you know, it's, it's your, it's your vision, but other people might find it super useful.
[SPEAKER_01] For example.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's just literally like, you know, don't hear what others say and just like, don't really pay attention to what they say or what they think.
[SPEAKER_01] Just put consistently content so people can.
[SPEAKER_01] So you're always consistently appearing at least on Instagram stories, always at the top.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have fresh new content and then more people, maybe in six months, they will say, oh, like Vasily, you helped me.
[SPEAKER_01] I liked your journey.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01] Blah, blah, blah.
[SPEAKER_01] People are always quiet.
[SPEAKER_01] They're going to be quiet.
[SPEAKER_01] They're not going to say any compliments or even negative feedback.
[SPEAKER_01] They'll be quiet.
[SPEAKER_01] But then at some point, some of them going to say that.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when you reach, when you hear that one person said you're doing good, this has to push you even more to continue to get, uh, you know, so you're doing is the same with the freelance.
[SPEAKER_01] If you get first client, first five star review, this pushes you for more the same on the social media.
[SPEAKER_01] You got one good feedback.
[SPEAKER_01] This has to push you.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Results push you forward.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So that's what I think.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you said that, uh, that maybe the, the best, uh, the best way to start creating your personal brand is documenting your journey.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you are, you can, you can start documenting your life and the things that you are passionate about, the things that you are moving towards your goals, your vision.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, what can you say to the, to the, to the, to the people that are really, really afraid to put themselves out there?
[SPEAKER_00] And because of the things that you said, because of the fear of the opinion of others, that someone is going to ridicule them, uh, fear of, I don't know, of the, of the bad feedback of the haters.
[SPEAKER_00] Have you, have you, have you been, uh, uh, familiar with something like this?
[SPEAKER_00] Have you, do you have any haters?
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe, uh, so, so, so that they said something bad to you in the beginning that, that, uh, got you discouraged a little bit or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I mean, when you were saying that, uh, what you can say to others, like I was at that stage where I was very shy.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I had like maybe 300, uh, followers I had, I was not even posting at all.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I have, uh, my friend in university, he was always kind of like, he was, because we were crazy about Gary Vee.
[SPEAKER_01] I was listening to him and my friend was also, and he was more confident.
[SPEAKER_01] He was more like as a public speaker as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And he also pushed me.
[SPEAKER_01] He's like, Vasily, you have to try it at least, you know, go out there, just, you know, put the.
[SPEAKER_01] Put the picture, put the video, like, don't worry about what other people say.
[SPEAKER_01] Just, you know, try and do it.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's how I, you know, started to try, started to be more comfortable.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, for example, when I was shy, uh, when I was offering my services on Fiverr, I tried to, uh, you know, do another service where it was consulting with the client.
[SPEAKER_01] And when I started doing consulting more like on Skype with the clients, I became also a bit more comfortable because when you're a freelancer, you're also very close in the very close environment.
[SPEAKER_01] You don't talk to anyone.
[SPEAKER_01] You just send messages.
[SPEAKER_01] You do your work.
[SPEAKER_01] That's it.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's good to, uh, be able to network, like going to the conferences, going like being a guest on the podcast or just going out there and talking with your university friends.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to practice those and then you can transition this into your social media and at least start doing because, uh, for example, like there's another top rate seller.
[SPEAKER_01] He's in graphic design and we're good friends as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And he was very shy with, uh, the social media.
[SPEAKER_01] And then he would send me messages like Vasily.
[SPEAKER_01] Thanks.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, you inspired me.
[SPEAKER_01] And now he started to put himself out there.
[SPEAKER_01] He started to record and, uh, he looks, I would say he looks perfect.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, I mean, he's just very natural.
[SPEAKER_01] He just started doing that.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, in, he has good results.
[SPEAKER_01] He has good feedback on his posts.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm sure people writing to his, to him direct messages, because it's at one point, you just have to realize that you have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] Give it a try.
[SPEAKER_01] And once you start doing it, please don't stop.
[SPEAKER_01] Because if you can take a break, like I took even for like two weeks, it feels so weird.
[SPEAKER_01] It's like, it's a feeling where you just, uh, the very beginning again.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you know, I'm, I'm also thinking about, uh, uh, doing something like this, uh, creating more.
[SPEAKER_00] of my personal brand.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, you know, I'm, I'm a human just like anyone else.
[SPEAKER_00] I, I have this, it's, it's, it's not, it's not fear.
[SPEAKER_00] It's, it's, it's really funny feeling that, uh, when I start to put myself out there, I don't know, someone will tease me or something like this.
[SPEAKER_00] And then in the end, I think to myself that nobody, in the end, nobody even cares about, about, about you.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, all the people are only, uh, considered, considering, considered about themselves.
[SPEAKER_00] And they, they, they don't think about you that much.
[UNKNOWN] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] That's absolutely true.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, I would love to have, like, if you go, you know, if you start showing your, even your life, your corporate life, giving some, you know, uh, talking about something there.
[SPEAKER_01] I would enjoy watching because, you know, it's, you're in, uh, Croatia, you know, you're working the company and, you know, I mean, I would love to, to follow it and see what's, what's it's out there.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think, so I think it's just, uh, for us, like when we're trying to put our content, we're thinking, oh, this might be boring.
[SPEAKER_01] This might be, uh, I did it every day and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01] But for other people who are in other countries, in other cities, you know, for them, it's also, they're, they enjoy it because they want to see the culture.
[SPEAKER_01] They want to see how it's out there.
[SPEAKER_01] If you can maybe share something, talk about something that's just going to be useful.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it's, it's very important.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I think that you inspired me to start.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, obviously, you know, building your brand, if you're going as your brand, it's good.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you're building your brand and you can develop your brand and then connect this to your personal at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] So people can know that you're a brand, but at the same time, you're the owner of the brand.
[SPEAKER_01] You're the leader, leader of the brand.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's also perfectly fine.
[SPEAKER_01] You can go as a brand, but you can, you know, you have to be comfortable putting out yourself all there.
[SPEAKER_01] So people can understand that those you're connected with the brand and you're the leader.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think, I mean, I know that doing separate, like if you're pushing your brand at the same time, you're pushing your personal brand and you have two different accounts.
[SPEAKER_01] Then you're just, you know, thinking too much about the content, which content should go there, which content should go there.
[SPEAKER_01] And you become, I would say slow.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's just better to put, if you go as a personal, just the person and you just develop your community.
[SPEAKER_01] Or if you're already as a brand, just, you know, it's fine to be, to post the brand stuff, but then also show yourself and that you're connected with the brand.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think just better have one account than have two and then you're, you're slower.
[SPEAKER_00] And so, so you think that the, the right strategy for me right now is then to, to show my face a little bit more on my, on my, on my brand loot.
[SPEAKER_01] Because yeah, of course, I mean, it's, it's obviously for you, it's going to be weird at the beginning, but then because you're at the start.
[SPEAKER_01] It, I mean, I'll, I mean, not really at the start because you already have good audience, but still you're at the beginning because of all this entire journey.
[SPEAKER_01] So you can, you know, it's fine to show if you're going to reach like, I don't know, 50,000 or 100,000 followers, or you're going to be already developed really high as a company.
[SPEAKER_01] And then suddenly you're going to start showing yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] That's going to look a little bit strange.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] You can do it now.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, you know, you can develop your personal brand together with the company.
[SPEAKER_01] And then if you want to do separate in the future, you can do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And people will come from your brand account.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Thanks.
[SPEAKER_01] Because I remember there was one account.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know if you maybe know, it's called ask a millionaire.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_01] I am a part of his.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Sean Thomas.
[SPEAKER_00] His name is Sean Thomas.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm, I'm part of his, of his group.
[SPEAKER_00] Me too.
[SPEAKER_00] Most, most want.
[SPEAKER_01] I will.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Me too.
[SPEAKER_00] Really?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] I was one of the first members.
[SPEAKER_00] Me also.
[SPEAKER_00] I have a lifetime subscription.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Me as well.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't see you there.
[SPEAKER_00] You're not the, maybe that active there.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm not active at all.
[SPEAKER_01] I was before I was active and I was talking to Sean and I got the t-shirt and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] But then I, then that was just not very, not really active there.
[SPEAKER_01] And I don't really go there, but it's, it's interesting for me how he branded himself
[SPEAKER_01] because he was ask a millionaire brand.
[SPEAKER_01] And then he was like, my name is Sean Thomas.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm the founder of Oscar millionaire.
[SPEAKER_01] And he was telling, so he was like connecting brand together with his personal brand.
[SPEAKER_01] And he was very active on Periscope.
[SPEAKER_01] I remember him a lot on Periscope.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Me also.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it, it was a, it was a good example to go.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] So I think that the people will learn a lot from you.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I think that, uh, sometimes or maybe more often it's, it's much better, uh, better to learn from someone who is at the base of the mountain than, than someone who is on the top of the mountain.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, because I think that, uh, that's young people right now can relate to you more than to someone who is on the top because they are so, so, so far away.
[SPEAKER_00] Right now.
[SPEAKER_00] It's true.
[SPEAKER_00] It's actually, you gave me a good, uh, as well, like, uh, motivation.
[SPEAKER_00] And at the same time, it's true.
[SPEAKER_00] Like what you're saying is true.
[SPEAKER_01] Like what you're saying is true.
[SPEAKER_00] You are really big on productivity, on the performance.
[SPEAKER_00] So for me, productivity starts with the vision.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you got to have this vision inside of yourself, in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00] And this vision is going to pull you, is going to, is going to give you the energy to do the things that you, that you got to do every single day to, to go, to grind, to be in the process and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] So can you tell me what is your vision for, for, for your company?
[SPEAKER_00] And what is your vision maybe for, for your life in general?
[SPEAKER_00] And do, do you have this, uh, habit of goals and setting of planning and things like that?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, my ultimate goal with the company is obviously building, uh, a big company with, you know, over 500,000 people working.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's like a big corporation.
[SPEAKER_01] This is my like ultimate goal.
[SPEAKER_01] And of course I know that it's going to take, uh, a lot more years.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, you know, that's where I have my smaller goals, which I, you know, set, for example, certain goals for like three months for six months.
[SPEAKER_01] And I try to achieve their personal goals, their company goals as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And this is very important because if you don't have any goals, uh, you're just gonna go, you're gonna be at, uh, one point, uh, you know, always.
[SPEAKER_01] So, you know, I would say the vision is of course, is to continue, uh, right now.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I'm, we're pretty set on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] So I want to continue to expand it because, uh, you know, it's also like when Gary V was saying scale the unscalable.
[SPEAKER_01] This is also interesting because I'm trying to scale freelancing platform, which is at the same time, super risky because, you know, there's a lot of rules.
[SPEAKER_01] There's a lot of stuff, but I find it interesting.
[SPEAKER_01] I find it, uh, you know, exciting at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] So I want to continue to scale it, but then at the same time I'm realizing that I can't put all my eggs in one basket.
[SPEAKER_01] So I have to still develop something, uh, you know, that could also potentially help you maybe in the future.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's where I'm thinking about online courses that developing, you know, good number of online courses and maybe, you know, going to the, like Udemy platform and trying to build my brand there.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's also like, my goal is to try to, you know, uh, develop something that is not only that is dependent on Fiverr, but something outside, because I think that's smart.
[SPEAKER_01] And at the same time, you know, this could open more doors for you.
[SPEAKER_01] So I would say, uh, for the vision as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Right.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's just, uh, for maybe like a personal, uh, I don't really have like, like I'm 23, I'm still super young, you know, uh, I know that like, I'm not.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably going to be married in the next, I don't know, two or three years.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, you know, I'm still at that stage where I have a lot of time, which I want to use as productive as possible.
[SPEAKER_01] Because when you're going to get like, uh, obviously I have a girlfriend and set, et cetera, but when you can get married, when you're going to have, you know, kids and stuff, you know, you're not going to have that much of time.
[SPEAKER_01] Compared to what you have if you're 22, 21, 23, 24 now.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's what I'm also thinking.
[SPEAKER_01] So I don't have any, uh, like plans for when I'm 30, 40, because it's still, for me, it's a long time.
[SPEAKER_01] But I know that now at this stage, I need to develop something that could be, uh, that I can put a lot of hours now and it still could pay off.
[SPEAKER_01] Maybe not like a hundred.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm not talking about like super passive income where you just sit and everything runs for you, but still you can build, uh, like a base, which is going to help you in the future as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And when you're 30, you have something with you and then you can still work on, you know, other things which you want.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's my goal.
[SPEAKER_01] My goal now is to continue to build, continue to expand the team, uh, expand the services.
[SPEAKER_01] So we can be more, I would say stable and growing as a company.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I want to also, obviously I want to be speaking more.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to continue to build my personal brand at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm more, I want to write books as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's what, you know, my personal, and I want to be focusing a lot when I'm like 30, that stage, I want to be also, you know, continue to expanding my personal brand there.
[SPEAKER_01] So now it's just all about putting us and doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01] Like if you're even now, if you're like 30 or 33, you know, you, you just have to like leave and you have to find time or the situation you have.
[SPEAKER_01] So if you're married kids and you're starting something, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01] You still will be successful.
[SPEAKER_01] You're still, you know, going to make a lot of money and you're going to have good life.
[SPEAKER_01] You just have to adapt to your time and prioritize things.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] This is why I liked, uh, this is why I like, uh, Gary V's mindset on this.
[SPEAKER_00] He's, uh, encouraging people that even if they're 50 or 60 years, years old, they still have plenty of time because they're going to live to be 100 years old.
[SPEAKER_00] You have, if you're 60, you have 40 more years to do a lot of things and you can do really, really big things in 40 years.
[SPEAKER_00] So I really, really love, love his, uh, attitude towards this, this, and you know, uh, this age thing is crippling a lot of people.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, someone who is maybe your age, you think, think to themselves, oh man, I'm too young.
[SPEAKER_00] There, there's a lot of time for me.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't need to do it right now.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm going to take it easy.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, if someone is, I don't know, 50 years old, they're going to say, oh, it's, it's over for me because I'm, I'm too old and I'm not going to amount to anything in life anymore.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's really, really great approach that he has and that's, that's he, he's really, um, uh, trying to tell people all over the social media.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] At the same time, you know, people should be, uh, you know, for example, when, when you say you're, uh, 21 and you're like, for example, super successful, you know, that person could be a short turn.
[SPEAKER_01] They could be super successful for like two years and then everyone could be just forget about that person.
[SPEAKER_01] So they have to also realize that it's, could be a super success and then the success could, you know, go away.
[SPEAKER_01] For example, you know, like with the Bitcoin stuff with all these cryptocurrencies, a lot of big names went out there.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when the Bitcoin started to go down and a lot of platforms collapsed, you know, a lot, a lot of different names just got disappeared as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So, and that's not only like with the Bitcoin, but with other examples as well, but people have to realize that, you know, if they're 50, 30, they could, you know, it could be one year where they could make a million dollars.
[SPEAKER_01] But if they have, if you don't have a vision, it's going to be, and mentality is going to be impossible.
[SPEAKER_01] If they know what they're doing, if they have a vision, if they have goals, if they're ready for it, then, you know, literally one year could change your life.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, man.
[SPEAKER_00] So how, how do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_00] You know, this day I've been, I've been doing some calculation and I, I put in my, in my calculator on the iPhone, um, 365 days in a year.
[SPEAKER_00] And when you, when you divide, uh, when you, when, when you know that 33% of your time, you are asleep and you have, you, you are sleeping for 121 days in a year.
[SPEAKER_00] It's crazy.
[SPEAKER_00] When you think about it that way.
[SPEAKER_00] And so how do you go about your day?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, if you know this and, uh, for me, what I try, what I try to do is I want to, uh, create a priorities out of my priorities.
[SPEAKER_00] I want to prioritize my priorities.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is the thing that, that you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00] And don't just disperse yourself in a lot of, uh, meaningful, uh, uh, little actions.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So how do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you prioritize?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you decide on what actions to take?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I mean, uh, you know, when you talk about priorities, you also, when you write.
[SPEAKER_01] down something like to-do list.
[SPEAKER_01] You also want to make sure that your to-do list is not so big because otherwise if you create a big to-do list, you're not gonna complete it.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to, you know, you it's, it's literally just how you're, uh, you have to understand yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I know that if I'm, uh, you know, gonna work, for example, in the evening, I'm not gonna be productive.
[SPEAKER_01] You just have to feel yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, you know, I think, I mean, it's literally.
[SPEAKER_01] It's, it's literally, you have to have some sort of a feeling.
[SPEAKER_01] You have to, you know, have to be afraid of taking risks.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have to just think about this.
[SPEAKER_01] Like every day you have to be progressing.
[SPEAKER_01] Doesn't matter if it's like less than 1%, but you have to be progressing.
[SPEAKER_01] At the same time, when you're building a business, 1% of every day, you have to try to outsource to your employers, to freelancers, you have to anyone.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's what I have in my mind that I know that, for example, some of the work, which I'm doing in the, I'm trying to find a way to also give it to employers.
[SPEAKER_01] So I can continue to expand, continue to, you know, go for others.
[SPEAKER_01] Because if you don't, if you're not going to be productive, you know, if you're not going to be, uh, you know, uh, I would say completing your to-do list, et cetera.
[SPEAKER_01] Then you're just going to be at one stage.
[SPEAKER_01] And then the year passes, you're in the same stage doing the same stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's what you have to be.
[SPEAKER_01] Always try to go back.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, for example, I can say that last year I had only like one, two team members.
[SPEAKER_01] Now we're over, uh, we have 12 team members.
[SPEAKER_01] We're building video production.
[SPEAKER_01] We have moved into the, we start with 10 meters, uh, 10 square meters office.
[SPEAKER_01] Now it's a 102 square meters.
[SPEAKER_01] So like, I, I see that, like, obviously when I'm doing it, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] I'm not realizing, but now when, when we're talking about this, like, I see the progress.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm like, wow, it's, it's incredible.
[SPEAKER_01] But for me, I'm still saying like, no, you have to keep going.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, don't stop.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, just, it's good that, you know, you have the progress, but still for yourself, you have to be always try to set higher barriers and, you know, always go.
[SPEAKER_01] So like, never stop and say, okay, that that's it.
[SPEAKER_00] I agree.
[SPEAKER_00] I think that you, you, you, you have to be proud of yourself for, for the things, for the things, for the things,
[SPEAKER_00] that you did so far.
[SPEAKER_00] And I know, and I know that, you know, that, that your potential is much, much bigger than, than you reached so far.
[SPEAKER_00] So can you tell me, okay, so when you wake up, maybe the day before the night, before you think to yourself, what you're going to do tomorrow, and you're going to focus, focus is really, really important.
[SPEAKER_00] So you're going to focus on these three big tasks and you're, you're going to delegate some, some tasks to, to your employees also.
[SPEAKER_00] And for you, you're going to try to focus on, on the things that will grow your organization.
[SPEAKER_00] You want, you want to be, uh, super effective and efficient.
[SPEAKER_00] So how, how do you go about, uh, the distractions during the day?
[SPEAKER_00] So, so you said a few times, you said that in the morning when everything is quiet, you try to do operational things.
[SPEAKER_00] Correct.
[SPEAKER_00] After it, maybe you, you, you leave some time to, uh, I don't know, communication, uh, with, with your employees, uh, doing some strategy work, uh, for meetings or things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I mean, that's, I mean, you said it exactly right.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, distractions, they come, but you know, if you can put the highest priority tasks at the very, because when you wake up in the, in the morning, like, especially.
[SPEAKER_01] Like now I woke up in Russia, like 6:30.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes I, I used to like last three, four days I was waking up much later, but that's what I had.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, usually my routine, I wake up early when I have this feeling, like I drive, uh, going in the car, you know, everything is, uh, still the city sleeping and I'm, you know, going out there.
[SPEAKER_01] There is some taxi drivers who are trying to make their hustle and, you know, working, uh, all night.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when I arrive to the office, everything is quiet.
[SPEAKER_01] No, one's going to tell me, uh, you know, to let's talk to sign problem or anything.
[SPEAKER_01] I just do highest priority tasks.
[SPEAKER_01] Like what I know that I need to do them.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when the day starts 10:00 AM, you know, the, the team is starting to come with the questions starting to arise and I have to just be prepared for that.
[SPEAKER_01] So I can't put the tasks, which only I have to do for the later time of the day, because then it's just going to be a mess.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I'll be distracted.
[SPEAKER_01] I can forget.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, you know, I think it's very important.
[SPEAKER_01] So just whatever you do, only you, you have to put, uh, in the morning as a first priority.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, then when, you know, you have all these team members coming and, you know, you need to discuss meetings, then you just, uh, have to be ready for that part.
[SPEAKER_01] So you can't really push your stuff till the, till the end of the day, because, uh, if, if you can do like, I cannot do it.
[SPEAKER_01] Like if I, if I try to do it, I'm not going to finish my task.
[SPEAKER_01] So if you can do it, it it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01] Do it.
[SPEAKER_01] But from my experience, I cannot do it.
[SPEAKER_01] So I found it much more effective to, to do stuff in the morning.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, man, you really, really inspired me.
[SPEAKER_00] So tomorrow, right now I'm going to go to, to the bed really early.
[SPEAKER_00] And tomorrow I'm going to wake up around five in the morning and I'm going to do, uh, I'm going to, uh, be working on my side hustle on, on my brand, on the company that I want to create.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, and I, I really, I really, really, really want to, to, to be, uh, starting a vlog also, just like you do.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, yeah, I, I think that you're going to be proud of me when you see, when you see really, really, uh, that I'm, that I started, started it really, really quickly.
[SPEAKER_01] You should.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, the thing is for me, for example, like it's obviously it's hard.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I'm still, I'm not, I'm not like a supernatural blogger who's going to go out there.
[SPEAKER_01] Like for me, it's, it's, it's hard, but I'm trying, but I'm trying to, I, because I, I like it.
[SPEAKER_01] Obviously if you don't enjoy it, like maybe it's not for you, but I still enjoy it, but I'm still shy.
[SPEAKER_01] I would say sometimes, so I'm trying to, you know, to have that more and more confidence every day.
[SPEAKER_01] So like, it's, I'm not perfect, but I know that when I do it and, uh, when I just, for me, it's that feeling, not like actual talking, but start talking, like actually, you know, start that first second.
[SPEAKER_01] So, uh, you know, if I can, if I can go through it, fight through it, then I'm just enjoying the process.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't care whoever like looking at me or anything.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's just, you know, getting through it.
[SPEAKER_01] And then when you're consistent, just continue to do it and doing the vlogs are it's, it's good.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, it's even though it's not going to convert into money yet or into the, you know, any results, you views, likes, it's still good practice for you.
[SPEAKER_01] Like you're going to be proud of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to practice the speech.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to be more, you know, you're going to be, uh, it's, it's just going to help you in the process.
[SPEAKER_01] You're just going to help you in the future anyways.
[SPEAKER_01] And if you can see other people, like, for example, if I going to see you doing that, uh, you can see other person, maybe you, you, which you had on, uh, on the podcast before you, you connect with them.
[SPEAKER_01] And if you're in, in that circle of people, you're going to feel much more confident as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And they, because that's a small percentage of people.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I wish there'll be more people in St. Petersburg or also driven, you know, vloggers, like ready to speak, but it's the community.
[SPEAKER_01] is not very big.
[SPEAKER_01] That's why I would go travel to other places, meet other people, host conferences.
[SPEAKER_01] So you can be in that environment because that environment is going to also push you further.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] And you are, you are the average of the five people that you spend most time with.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's good to surround yourself with, uh, with, uh, also successful people, people who you can learn from because then you're becoming also, uh, improving.
[SPEAKER_01] You're reaching another level and that's going to help you as well.
[SPEAKER_00] I agree.
[SPEAKER_00] So for the, for the end, I just want, I just want you to describe your typical day, you know, uh, there is a saying that, uh, goals are for loser.
[SPEAKER_00] And, and the system is for winners.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you want to be a winner, you got to have a system around it.
[SPEAKER_00] So what, what habits, uh, or what routines are you trying, trying to, to, to do every single day?
[SPEAKER_00] What's your typical day looks like?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, first thing I try to go to bed before I would say 11:30, uh, that's like the number one thing, because if I go later than that, it's just going to be miracle to wake up.
[SPEAKER_01] And then basically I'm going to collapse in the, in the middle of the week and just sleep until, I don't know, 10, 11, et cetera.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's, you have to obviously go to bed early.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's what for me is the first goal to go to bed early.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, then when I wake up, you know, I try first thing when I wake up, obviously alarm, I have like five of them set up just because that was my habit from university where I was literally working on the paper, on the exam, uh, you know, on the last minute.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I had to put like five, 10 alarms to make sure I can wake up in next, in two, three hours.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, I still have like three alarms wherever, but, uh, when I turn, uh, off the alarm, I try not to take the phone.
[SPEAKER_01] straight away.
[SPEAKER_01] So like I turned off and I tried to get from bed as soon as possible, because this is another thing.
[SPEAKER_01] You can stay there for 30 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01] If you're going to go on Instagram, if you're going to go on, uh, I don't know, WhatsApp or other, you're going to lose time.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] You're going to lose those 30, maybe an hour even.
[SPEAKER_01] And this is like, because if I'm going to open my phone, I'm going to go like on Fiverr.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm going to see a lot of messages, maybe some complaints, I don't know, emergencies to take or good things.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm going to spend like time.
[SPEAKER_01] So I try to turn off alarm, go to shower, you know, do all this necessary stuff, eat and then, you know, go to work.
[SPEAKER_01] And then at the work, I start and then open it.
[SPEAKER_01] If I'm working from home or let's say if I'm in travel, then once I get done with breakfast, all this stuff, I open my phone and then I'm in the working mood.
[SPEAKER_01] So once I'm working, then I try not go for like three hours.
[SPEAKER_01] I try to maybe, uh, set like a timer, like work for 90 minutes and then just take small break because obviously it's important to take those breaks sometimes as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So I try to put 90 minutes, small break, 90 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01] And then that's usually happens already, uh, closer to 11:00 AM.
[SPEAKER_01] That's where people already, the team is here.
[SPEAKER_01] So we're discussing or also enjoying or sometimes having fun, like for a few minutes, obviously not so much because of the work we have, but at the same time, we're communicating, talking.
[SPEAKER_01] And then after lunch, it's more about, uh, if we're recording a new video, if we're, you know, uh, working on something altogether.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's more about the teamwork, I would say happening.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, uh, once 6:00 PM, um, majority of, uh, the team leaves, we have someone who's still working on some stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] And usually I stay until, uh, I would say seven, eight.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, uh, once I'm at eight, my girlfriend, she gets, uh, obviously she's like, what are you doing?
[SPEAKER_01] So I know that at this stage at 8:00 PM, I have to, uh, you know, go with her and that's normal.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, obviously it's, it's very normal.
[SPEAKER_01] So we go together, just, you know, walk or eat dinner.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I, the rest, I just mostly spend time with her and then start my day again.
[SPEAKER_00] So when do you find time, uh, for, for working out?
[SPEAKER_01] Working out happens in the evening.
[SPEAKER_01] So it happens not always.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's where I finish my work.
[SPEAKER_01] So for example, six o'clock, uh, if I can, the best for me is to push six o'clock where majority of guys leave.
[SPEAKER_01] and then some of them go to the gym straight away.
[SPEAKER_01] So we go together.
[SPEAKER_01] And if I stay longer at work, which I try to, you know, eliminate because at that stage, I'm not very productive.
[SPEAKER_01] So I try to live with them.
[SPEAKER_01] And then by eight, we're eating together with my girlfriend and then spending time with her.
[SPEAKER_01] So I usually spend maximum an hour, an hour and a half working out.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, and, uh, if I can do it also consistently, like every day for one hour or at least like three times a week,
[SPEAKER_01] for one hour, you know, I, I feel very good.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm, I'm also proud of myself because I'm getting in better shape same time.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so you're lifting weights or what kind of.
[SPEAKER_01] I like running a lot because it helps me obviously like sweating, you know, you're just like getting that energy, bad energy out.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, you know, you're just, uh, good at the same time, listening to the podcast and then just doing, working out.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I can, for example, Monday I'm running for maybe 15, 20 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01] And then the rest time lifting weights and then, you know, just stretching for five to 10 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01] And then Wednesday, for example, if I'm going three times a week, Wednesday, I'll just do my like lower body legs, for example, and running as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So obviously, you know, it's not like, as I was training before professionally, but it's just to make sure I'm fit to make sure I can, you know, uh, break, uh, from the office atmosphere.
[SPEAKER_01] And just kind of like also have that feeling of fighting or kind of like, you know, pushing yourself a little bit more.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think it's important.
[SPEAKER_01] Great, man.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja.