[SPEAKER_01] So welcome my man! How are you? I'm doing pretty good Vinko. I'm honored to be in your podcast.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, thank you, thank you, thank you. I'm really grateful that you are here today.
[SPEAKER_00] So what do I want to know for in the beginning is I want you to tell me a little bit of your
[SPEAKER_00] background. So where did you grow up? Where are you born? Where do you live right now? And
[SPEAKER_00] some something like this, a little bit of info of the background story of yours.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay, yeah, for sure. First of all, my name is Abraham Cueto. I am from Mexico. I grew up over there.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm 20 years old. And well, when I was a kid, I was living like in a small, not small, like the capital
[SPEAKER_01] of a state in my country. But it wasn't that big. It wasn't that, yeah, I think it wasn't that big as
[SPEAKER_01] comparison of other cities. And the upbringing that I got from my parents wasn't that
[SPEAKER_01] that brilliant in terms of the world, knowledge about how lives goes. They just gave me whatever
[SPEAKER_01] they could, you know, their best. Of course. And I appreciate that. It's something that I value
[SPEAKER_01] very much. But I was thirsty of more. So since the beginning, that was kind of the kid. I am the oldest
[SPEAKER_01] of four kids. Oh, so I was always like exploring, you know, whenever my parents or my grandparents were
[SPEAKER_01] giving me a rule, I was like questioning it, you know, like, why do I have to follow that? Let me just do
[SPEAKER_01] what I want, you know. And so I that's pretty much what I did. I got into a lot of trouble.
[SPEAKER_01] I made a lot of mistakes, but I was following my heart, you know, and what I thought was right at the moment.
[SPEAKER_00] So what was the name of the city that you were born in and that you grew up in? So you said that
[SPEAKER_00] you are 20 or 28 years old? 28 years old. 28, okay. So you said that you are coming from Mexico
[SPEAKER_00] originally. So which city is that in Mexico? You said it is not a capital of Mexico, which is Mexico
[SPEAKER_01] city, is it? Right. So the city is Tepic. Tepic, okay. Tepic is T-E-P-I-C. Uh-huh. Okay. So was it,
[SPEAKER_00] so was it a, is it, is it a big city or a smaller city? So how, how many people are living there?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, actually, it's the capital of a state in my country, but the state is not that popular.
[SPEAKER_01] It's on the Pacific coast. We have like very good weather and stuff. And there's a lot of nature,
[SPEAKER_01] beach, weather, and vegetation type of thing. Cool. But it's not really big. I would say probably
[SPEAKER_01] right now, my city is maybe about half million people or a million people, maybe half million,
[SPEAKER_01] I would say half million. Yeah. It isn't that big. From our standards here in Croatia, this is a big city.
[SPEAKER_00] Really? Yeah. Because, man, Croatia is only four and a half million people. And right now I'm living
[SPEAKER_00] in capital and the capital is almost one million people. So a lot of people are living in the capital
[SPEAKER_00] city here in Zagreb. And yeah, this, this, this is a big city. Uh, when you think in our standards.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay. Gotcha. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay. So, uh, you were born there and, uh, how long did you stay there? When, when did you move to,
[SPEAKER_00] you are living in Los Angeles, Los Angeles right now, are you? Yeah, that's where I'm, I'm, I'm living
[SPEAKER_01] right now. And I moved here probably about four years and a half. December is going to be my, um,
[SPEAKER_01] it's going to be, um, five, five years, four years and a half. Okay. And, uh, my whole life I lived in
[SPEAKER_01] in my city, you know, uh, the thing is that with my family, we, we, we did travel around the country,
[SPEAKER_01] around Mexico, but it was like, you just go out to know the, what is, um, what life is in another
[SPEAKER_01] state, but you always come back to your home and, and you are okay there. You should not, wow, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] stuff like that. So I studied architecture in Mexico and I used to work with my dad who is an
[SPEAKER_01] architect as well. So I was really involved in, in that, uh, art and that type of job, but I was,
[SPEAKER_01] I wanted more, you know, I wanted something more. And then, um, one of my, my aunt, my dad's, uh,
[SPEAKER_01] sister brought me the first time to the U S when I was 15 years old,
[SPEAKER_01] completely changed my vision of the world, especially because there was another language.
[SPEAKER_01] I had the experience of being, uh, in a country that, uh, people don't speak my language or not most of
[SPEAKER_01] them because California, there are a lot of Hispanic speakers, but still, I had experienced English and I,
[SPEAKER_01] I felt the limitations, the, the language barrier, you know, so I was like, okay,
[SPEAKER_01] that's something that I would like to learn.
[SPEAKER_00] But man, your, your pronunciation right now and your, your language or your skill of, of speaking
[SPEAKER_00] English is really, really good right now. I don't know for how many, so for how much years do you speak
[SPEAKER_00] English, uh, on a regular basis, but it sounds perfect.
[SPEAKER_01] Oh, thank you. I appreciate that, man. I, I put the work, you know, I, I, I dedicated myself to
[SPEAKER_01] learn the language and I actually learned it when I moved here because when, when I was like, as I told
[SPEAKER_01] you, my aunt brought me to this country when I was 15, but I, I didn't like the language. I thought that
[SPEAKER_01] I would not need that language from in my life. I was coming like every year or so to the U S just
[SPEAKER_01] to work and have fun here, buy good stuff, you know, and Mexico. And also I was doing some business
[SPEAKER_01] like bringing cell phones and stuff, but I was not really caught on learning the language.
[SPEAKER_01] So when I decided to move here was to learn the language because I found that I, that I, that it
[SPEAKER_01] was required for my career. Well, again, I moved to the U S and learned the language. So when I moved to,
[SPEAKER_01] to LA, Los Angeles, uh, I dedicated probably two years and a half of my life to, to just learn the
[SPEAKER_01] language. And, um, cause I, I, I could not speak, man. I could not speak anything. So I decided to just
[SPEAKER_01] get involved and, and, um, submerge into the language and learn as much as I can practice as much as I can.
[SPEAKER_00] Something that helped me a lot was singing. You know, Arnold Schwarzenegger is living in,
[SPEAKER_00] in America for, I don't know, 40, 50 years, and there is still this accent there. But, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] when I hear you speak, I cannot hear any kind of accent, any kind of accent. You know, when,
[SPEAKER_00] when Arnold says, I'll be back in, in, in this German, German English language. Yeah, really,
[SPEAKER_00] really, really, really, really great. And this is, this is, uh, one of my goals. I don't have an
[SPEAKER_00] opportunity to speak English so much. I consume a lot of, a lot of content in English. I, I read a lot of
[SPEAKER_00] books in English. I, I watch a lot of videos. I, I listened to a lot of podcasts and, uh, this is,
[SPEAKER_00] this is my best, best, uh, opportunity and the best way to, to, to learn about in English language.
[SPEAKER_00] But I really, really need, uh, to practice it. I need to use it just like I'm using it,
[SPEAKER_00] using it right now. So this is something that I want to do in the future. So, so you said that, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] you moved to, to LA. So was it in 2014?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, about that. Actually, 2013, at the, almost the end of 2013.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. End of 2013. So you moved there all alone?
[SPEAKER_01] All by myself. Um, I moved by myself here, but I stayed with my aunt, the one that brought me
[SPEAKER_01] to this country the first time. I lived with her for a couple of months, probably eight.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh-huh. So she, she is living in, in LA?
[SPEAKER_00] Correct.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay. So she was, she was the, the connection there when you moved?
[SPEAKER_01] Exactly. And, and, you know, I appreciate all her effort and everything that she did
[SPEAKER_01] and still does for me, you know, um, cause it's, I think it's very shocking when you go to another
[SPEAKER_01] country and you don't, you have nothing but yourself. So she, she gave me that kind of like, uh, family vibe.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. Which can really, really help. Really, really help. So what, what, what was,
[SPEAKER_00] uh, can you describe a little bit to me and to the audience, what, what was, uh, the experience,
[SPEAKER_00] uh, of those first few days and the first few months when you moved to Los Angeles?
[SPEAKER_00] What, how, how did you feel? Um, and
[SPEAKER_00] just, just, can you describe a little bit the whole experience and the feelings?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, for sure. Um, even though this country like is so beautiful, man, and you have a lot of things to do
[SPEAKER_01] that, LA offers you a lot of stuff, but I had this, uh, battle within me about, uh,
[SPEAKER_01] where was my family? You know, I was so attached to them that I was missing them very much.
[SPEAKER_01] Yup. And I was scared. I was scared of doing something that wasn't what I've been doing here
[SPEAKER_01] for four years and it was just something so different. Um,
[SPEAKER_01] I was confused. I was scared. I was insecure.
[SPEAKER_01] I was afraid of going out because I didn't know the language. What if I get lost? What if something
[SPEAKER_01] happened to me? How could I communicate with them? You know, and I, I didn't feel protected, I think,
[SPEAKER_00] in my country. So you were 100% out of the comfort that you, that you were familiar with when you were
[SPEAKER_00] living in your, in your, uh, hometown. Yes. And this, the situations like this are always a great,
[SPEAKER_00] great, uh, learning opportunities and, and opportunities for growth. So whenever we are
[SPEAKER_00] our, out of our comfort and to do something like that, uh, something that you did four years ago,
[SPEAKER_00] it is a really, really bold, bold move. And I congratulate you on this. So, uh, did,
[SPEAKER_00] did you finish some kind of a university or college there in, uh, in Mexico?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes. I studied architecture and I finished my career over there. And then when, when I moved here,
[SPEAKER_01] my first intention was to just learn English, right? Okay. Uh, but then I liked the country. I liked the
[SPEAKER_01] lifestyle. I liked the opportunity. So I decided to stay. And then I started doing my working for a
[SPEAKER_01] construction company, even though I didn't know the system, you know, like architecture in the U.S.
[SPEAKER_01] is so different than the architecture in Mexico, especially the, the materials of we use the systems
[SPEAKER_01] that we used to, to build are totally different. So I had to kind of relearn a lot of stuff. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] And I had the fortune to, of meeting, um, great people. Um, my aunt introduced me to a, to a builder,
[SPEAKER_01] a contractor. And I remember that I told him like, Hey, I'll work for you for free. Just teach me how to,
[SPEAKER_01] how to, um, do the blueprints here. Cause I don't know the construction system.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, so he emailed that I worked for him probably, I offered 90 days about that, but I worked probably
[SPEAKER_01] about 60 days, like two months for free. I think he started paying me, you know, like Abraham,
[SPEAKER_01] I think you can cover one position. So I'll start paying you. Great.
[SPEAKER_01] I remember the, the first, um, plan that I charged for, I asked him like, Oh, just give me a hundred dollars,
[SPEAKER_01] you know, and he laughed and he told me, I'll give you 200, you know, and it made me feel so good.
[SPEAKER_01] I was like, Oh, I made more money, but because I wasn't expecting, um, uh, the right amount.
[SPEAKER_01] So he told, he already knew that that he was like, no, I'll give you more, you know, your, your job,
[SPEAKER_01] um, yeah, it's, it's worth more value than what you're asking for.
[SPEAKER_00] Um, so, uh, where did you hear about this kind of approach that you are, uh, you were willing to,
[SPEAKER_00] to give your service, your services, your knowledge for free, for free in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00] So that one day that you hoped that you, that you will get the opportunity to be a full-time employee there.
[SPEAKER_00] So where, where, where did you learn, uh, something like this?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, actually, yeah, no, no, no, just say it.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Actually when, uh, when I was visiting before moving to the U S when I was visiting,
[SPEAKER_01] Um, my aunt introduced me to this, uh, coach, life coach.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] That in the long, in, in, in, after a couple of years, we became friends and he's still my coach.
[SPEAKER_01] Until this day, uh, we meet each other probably once or twice a month.
[SPEAKER_01] But I remember that he started gave, giving me this new idea.
[SPEAKER_01] So ideas that I haven't heard before.
[SPEAKER_01] If you're service for free and just ask for, for, for the knowledge, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] because if you, no one is going to hire you just because you are pretty or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, he was like, you have to give them value so you can have an exchange.
[SPEAKER_01] He's going to give, you're going to give them work.
[SPEAKER_01] That's the approach that I learned from him.
[SPEAKER_00] Man, when I'm listening right now, I see that your aunt really,
[SPEAKER_00] really gave you a helping hand when, when, when you come, came there.
[SPEAKER_00] Great stuff. Great stuff.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you know, I've been fantasizing about California and Los Angeles for, for quite some time.
[SPEAKER_00] If I ever decide to, to, to move to another country, uh, it would really be California and it will be
[SPEAKER_00] uh, maybe Los Angeles or, or the, some smaller cities
[SPEAKER_00] that are around Los Angeles.
[SPEAKER_00] Because, uh, I think, and not only I, but the world knows already that, that the California
[SPEAKER_00] and, uh, and especially Los Angeles is, is maybe one of the centers of the, of the world,
[SPEAKER_00] of entrepreneurship world, of the entertaining, uh, entertainment world.
[SPEAKER_00] And a lot of other great things are happening there.
[SPEAKER_00] It is a great center for, you know, innovation, uh, of technology and a spot in the world that is
[SPEAKER_00] really, really moving humanity forward.
[SPEAKER_00] So I'm really, really inspired by that place.
[SPEAKER_00] So it is a great, great place to live.
[SPEAKER_00] And I hope that, that you are really, really aware of, uh, what kind of opportunities do you have there.
[SPEAKER_00] So could you, could you speak a little bit about Los Angeles?
[SPEAKER_00] Can you speak about the experience of, of living there?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, well, Los Angeles, the thing that caught me was the variety of people.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I can meet people from, of course, America,
[SPEAKER_01] South America, Asia, Europe, you know, um, from all over the world.
[SPEAKER_01] And all those people are living in just one city.
[SPEAKER_01] So, um, I have the fortune of meeting great people from different nationalities.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, one of my best friends, he is from Vietnam.
[SPEAKER_01] And I couldn't imagine meeting someone from Vietnam while living in my country.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, another thing here in, um, in Los Angeles is the weather.
[SPEAKER_01] It's not too cold.
[SPEAKER_01] It's not too hot.
[SPEAKER_01] You can have the beach like in a few minutes, like probably half an hour
[SPEAKER_01] away from, from almost any city around Los Angeles.
[SPEAKER_01] You can have the mountains, you can have the desert.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, you can have like the access to everything, man.
[SPEAKER_01] With, for example, the services like Amazon, we can have everything here.
[SPEAKER_01] You can have a lot of different communities.
[SPEAKER_01] If you like to do yoga, if you like to surf, if you like to do, uh, hiking, if you like to
[SPEAKER_01] do rock climbing, if you like to read books and even weird stuff, you know, like you can find
[SPEAKER_01] that type of people here.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's something that I like that you can connect with different people that like to do
[SPEAKER_01] similar activities or think this similar way as you do.
[SPEAKER_01] And, and also is, um, there are so many things to do in terms like work wise,
[SPEAKER_01] where you can give value that there's no excuse of not making money over here.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you can, you, you, you have too much or not too much, but a lot of industries
[SPEAKER_01] from where you can choose from and grow from there, you know, or you can start your own company.
[SPEAKER_01] It's not, and it's not that complicated.
[SPEAKER_00] It sounds like heaven to me.
[SPEAKER_00] It sounds like heaven.
[SPEAKER_00] The entrepreneurship opportunities, uh, uh, a lot of great people there.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm also a big, big, uh, lover of nature, just like you.
[SPEAKER_00] I've seen your photos on Instagram and the variety of nature there in California.
[SPEAKER_00] California is just absolutely beautiful, magnificent, magnificent.
[SPEAKER_00] But what, what about, uh, when we, when we watch, uh, Hollywood movies and things like that,
[SPEAKER_00] is, is there really this high level of, of crime there are, are, are there some kind
[SPEAKER_00] of a negative sides to it or is it everything nice and dandy?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I think there's, there must be some crime, but to be honest, man, I haven't seen anything.
[SPEAKER_01] Myself, I haven't, I haven't been around those, um, events.
[SPEAKER_01] I haven't seen, um, car crashes, you know, when they, there's an accident in the freeway
[SPEAKER_01] or on the streets, stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01] But not, not really like crime, not really.
[SPEAKER_01] I, actually, uh, no one has ever stolen anything from me.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think, um, of course, there is a factor of, like, uh, with whom you are surrounded with.
[SPEAKER_00] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] And also how, how well you protect yourself and your stuff, you know, you just have to be aware
[SPEAKER_01] where you are at and what are the measurements that you should, uh, the measures that you should take
[SPEAKER_01] to not get involved in any problem, you know, and, and I'm aware that stuff can happen to me
[SPEAKER_01] and to my stuff, but, but it hasn't happened.
[SPEAKER_01] And I hope that it stays like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Let it stay like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Great, man.
[SPEAKER_00] So I know that two of us don't have a lot of time today.
[SPEAKER_00] So I want to, I want to jump, uh, on another, another, uh, questions.
[SPEAKER_00] So you know that both of us are consuming a lot of content regarding the, the self or personal growth.
[SPEAKER_00] So as Tom Bilyeu says, you have, uh, you have people, uh, one, one, one type of, of people,
[SPEAKER_00] of person, they have a fixed mindset and some other people have growth mindset.
[SPEAKER_00] So what kind of a mindset do you have?
[SPEAKER_00] I suppose that you have a growth mindset and what do you do about it?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you grow?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, how do you learn?
[SPEAKER_00] Where do you learn from?
[SPEAKER_00] And all those other beautiful stuff.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you, can you, can you tell me a little bit about that?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, I think I don't have like a 100% defined, um, growth mindset.
[SPEAKER_01] Cause you know, sometimes, uh, uh, the fixed mindset appears, you know, it shows.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01] There's nothing to freak out about, but you just have to go back to the growth mindset.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, as soon as you can.
[SPEAKER_01] So the things that helped me stay there in the, um, growth mindset, be, first of all,
[SPEAKER_01] be surrounded of an environment that promotes, promotes that type of mindset.
[SPEAKER_01] What I mean is, you know, podcasts, videos, audios, books, conferences, friends.
[SPEAKER_01] I think friends are very important because, um, I think even Tom Bilo says that you're like
[SPEAKER_01] the average of the five people that you surround yourself with.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] A great Jim Rohn quote.
[SPEAKER_01] Correct.
[SPEAKER_01] So I try to be around the people that I want to, that I try to be around the people that is,
[SPEAKER_01] that is going to give me, um, one trade, one thing that is going to make me go forward and stay with that growth mindset.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's why I try to listen to, for example, this case like Tom Bilo, Jocko Willink, um, as much
[SPEAKER_01] as I can, so they can become one of my five people.
[SPEAKER_01] Yep.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is a great, great thing, uh, about internet.
[SPEAKER_00] So if we don't have five people around us and we cannot find, find them in person,
[SPEAKER_00] it is a great way that it is a great opportunity so that we can find them online and surround,
[SPEAKER_00] surround ourselves with them, uh, with, uh, through the things like, just like you mentioned,
[SPEAKER_00] YouTube videos, podcasts, books, and, uh, other, uh, other similar things.
[SPEAKER_00] Great, great way to, to learn.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Correct.
[SPEAKER_01] That's correct.
[SPEAKER_01] Binko.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, what, what is, what is your vision for, for, for your life?
[SPEAKER_00] What is the, the vision for your future?
[SPEAKER_00] You know, uh, the thing that I want to promote with, with this, uh, with this brand and the content
[SPEAKER_00] that I want to create is I want to help the, the people that, that, that, uh, consume this.
[SPEAKER_00] How can they really create the life of their dreams?
[SPEAKER_00] How can they find, uh, their, their passion and the, the purpose in life?
[SPEAKER_00] How can, how can they really, uh, live in their, in their element?
[SPEAKER_00] So, know what, what are their strengths?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, and really, really live in that element and try to grow that.
[SPEAKER_00] So, what is your vision?
[SPEAKER_00] What, what, what, what, what, what, what kind of a future do you, do you see for yourself?
[SPEAKER_00] And can you, can you speak a little bit about that?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, well, kind of, uh, the mission that I gave myself,
[SPEAKER_01] to people that is possible, you know, whatever you want to do is possible.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, probably you have seen, uh, my Instagram that I jumped from an airplane.
[SPEAKER_00] I didn't, I didn't, I, I didn't see that.
[SPEAKER_00] Oh, cool.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, there's a picture when, when I jumped from an airplane.
[SPEAKER_00] Cool, cool, cool.
[SPEAKER_01] And it was a really fun experience.
[SPEAKER_01] I recommend everybody to do it.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, but one of the main things of, of what I did was because I wasn't scared about it.
[SPEAKER_01] And also, a lot of people told me that, that I should not do it because I might die.
[SPEAKER_01] So, what, what I told that people, you know, is, it was like, um, I prefer to do something that I like to do and die than do not do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And always stay with that feeling of what could have happened.
[SPEAKER_01] What, how does it feel like to, to jump from an airplane and, and don't take action, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] And I remember my, my brother, he's, I'm 10 years older than him.
[SPEAKER_01] So, so he told me like, how did you do that?
[SPEAKER_01] Why did you do that?
[SPEAKER_01] And I was, I told him like, I do it because I, I could, you know, and I did it because I wanted to.
[SPEAKER_01] And you could do it as well.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you can, you just have to decide it.
[SPEAKER_01] So, that's my mission to, to, to, to, to show people that whatever you want to do, it's possible.
[SPEAKER_01] You can do it.
[SPEAKER_01] You just have to decide it and do something about it, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] So, what, what, what kind of future do you see for yourself regarding your, your, your work, your, your, your life?
[SPEAKER_00] Do, do you wanna, do you have a, maybe a girlfriend?
[SPEAKER_00] Do, do you, do you wanna have a family?
[SPEAKER_00] If, if you have a blank canvas in front of yourself, what, what kind of a painting would you really like to paint?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, um, I visualize myself, uh, in terms, like say, let's say then career-wise, I wanna become one of the best architects and, um, architecture, uh, servers in Los Angeles.
[SPEAKER_01] I wanna be able to help a lot of people with any project that they have, because I'm a creator.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I'm using architecture as a way to create.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I like to help other people have what they want.
[SPEAKER_01] So, architecture is one way of doing it.
[SPEAKER_01] Also, I wanna go to countries that are less fortunate than, than the U.S. or Mexico and, and help people that don't have the resources of how to, to have a decent home.
[SPEAKER_01] And compare, work with them, build, build with them their house, you know, and show them how, and, and it's gonna be for free.
[SPEAKER_01] I wanna do humanitarian projects as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So, that's gonna be a, one way of me giving back.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I see myself, uh, wife, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, and I see myself with kids.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, that's why I'm working a lot on myself right now.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I could become a better man, you know, the best version of myself.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I can give that to my kids.
[SPEAKER_01] I can, I can share that with my wife.
[SPEAKER_01] And also, I can become, I can become the man that the lady of my dreams wants, you know.
[SPEAKER_01] I could not be where I am right now, and wanting a, a woman that is in a higher position.
[SPEAKER_01] Not in terms of money, but in terms of being, you know, who she is.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I'm just going up, so I can align with her.
[SPEAKER_01] And then, when we align, we can, you know, live life together, improve ourselves, help ourselves to get better.
[SPEAKER_01] And just enjoy this adventure of life, you know.
[SPEAKER_01] We decide to have kids, bring them, and also teach them what we think is good, but also letting them decide what they think is good for them.
[SPEAKER_01] And I visualize myself traveling around the world, and I know that concept sounds redundant in terms of, like, everybody says that.
[SPEAKER_01] But my objective of traveling the world is because I want to know the culture.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, if, if I meet a French guy here, he's going to share, or she's going to share with me, to her or him, what France, what France is like.
[SPEAKER_01] But unless that I go and experience myself, I'm never going to have the right idea, because, you know, my perception is different than his or hers.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I would have a different image of France, you know, my own image of France.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I want to go to different countries and have the experience just to, to see what could I get from that country.
[SPEAKER_01] What is going to be my, my, my concept about the culture, the, the, the way they live, their food, their architecture.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, you want to, you want to, you want to taste it, you want to feel it.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, you know, uh, in, in the, in the Gary V's word, words, uh, this is the classic story of clouds and dirt.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is you, these are your clouds, your, your vision, your, your big picture.
[SPEAKER_00] It is something that you hold in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00] It is something that, that you visualize.
[SPEAKER_00] It is something that you imagine for yourself that you want to create in your life.
[SPEAKER_00] So, what, uh, how, how does your dirt looks like?
[SPEAKER_01] Um, it's pretty basic.
[SPEAKER_01] I think I, I have like three things, um, like cultivate good habits every day.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, be disciplined and look for optimization, you know, how to optimize everything.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, for example, what I do every day is, uh, is like when I wake up.
[SPEAKER_01] Right away, like I drink.
[SPEAKER_01] My water, so I have like, you know, I am hydrated.
[SPEAKER_01] I like to have a good amount of sleep.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably between four to eight hours.
[SPEAKER_01] It'd be less than that.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so when do you usually go to bed?
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I go around 11, 12 PM.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] About that.
[SPEAKER_01] And I woke up at 4, 4:30 AM.
[SPEAKER_00] Oh my God.
[SPEAKER_00] It's really, really early.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you, you, you don't, you don't feel, you don't feel that, uh, you're, you're not getting
[SPEAKER_00] enough of a sleep.
[SPEAKER_00] Are you feeling tired maybe?
[SPEAKER_01] To be honest, man, right now, I don't want to sleep
[SPEAKER_01] for a long time because I just have this drive to achieve my goals that I think is more important
[SPEAKER_01] for me to be working, working out, reading, doing meditation, serving other people than sleep.
[SPEAKER_01] I, I don't get me wrong, man.
[SPEAKER_01] I love to sleep.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I, I'm a big one on sleep, but, um, we're just right now.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, I've been, I've been just like trying to sleep as little as possible, but that, that gives me the rest
[SPEAKER_01] and to be able to, to, um, perform well during my day.
[SPEAKER_01] Something else that helped me is that around two to three PM, I take a, a powerful nap of like
[SPEAKER_01] 20 minutes, 30 minutes the most.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think that small sleep helps me to get throughout the rest of my day.
[SPEAKER_00] So you are, you are feeling after, after those of sleep, you are feeling, uh, energized
[SPEAKER_00] and you are feeling that you are performing on your optimal level.
[SPEAKER_00] You, you don't, you don't sense the, the, the need for more sleep.
[SPEAKER_00] So you have four hours at, by night and, uh, one power nap during the day.
[SPEAKER_00] This is enough for you.
[SPEAKER_00] Correct.
[SPEAKER_00] So you feel that this, this will, will be sustainable for you in the longer period of time also?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, I think, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] I think, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] Cause you know, I'm, I'm young, I'm 28.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think that right now, my mind, my brain and my body, they can,
[SPEAKER_01] they can work with that.
[SPEAKER_01] Cause you know, during the weekend I sleep like my eight hours,
[SPEAKER_01] sometimes a little bit more.
[SPEAKER_01] It depends on how I'm feeling.
[SPEAKER_01] I let my body rest as much as it wants during the weekend.
[SPEAKER_01] But during the week, it, it does what I tell it to do.
[SPEAKER_01] So if, if I just need to sleep four hours in order to do
[SPEAKER_01] all the activities that I want to achieve during my day,
[SPEAKER_01] that's the amount of sleep that I'm going to get.
[SPEAKER_01] And also one good thing is like, you know, I, I sleep those four hours,
[SPEAKER_01] drink my water with a little bit of, um, um, Himalayan pink salt and lemon juice.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I go right away.
[SPEAKER_01] I, I, I do my reading.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm reading, um, the book from, from, um,
[SPEAKER_01] joker willing, uh, discipline equals freedom.
[SPEAKER_01] And that gives me a fired up, you know, in the morning,
[SPEAKER_01] then I go straight to, to see my vision board of all, as you said, the clouds, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] like the motivation, what am I doing this for?
[SPEAKER_01] So it also gives me, you know, pumped up and then, um, I do a gratitude, uh, time.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, it could be, it can go from five minutes to probably 15 minutes in the morning.
[SPEAKER_01] So drink water, then, um, read visualization of my vision board and then gratitude.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, so, uh, when, when you meditate, I, I suppose that you use the technique of visualization.
[SPEAKER_01] is it, uh, actually like my meditation goes more towards, um,
[SPEAKER_00] end of the day, gratitude.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh-huh, gratitude.
[SPEAKER_01] Close my eyes.
[SPEAKER_01] And I started visualizing myself, as you said, like, you know, like with the things that I want,
[SPEAKER_01] the one, the things that I want to achieve today, the things that I want to achieve in their,
[SPEAKER_01] you know, in the upcoming months or years.
[SPEAKER_01] And I used to start to be grateful about it.
[SPEAKER_01] Like, oh, thank you for giving me these opportunities.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you for giving me these blessings.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you for giving me these, uh, resources.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you for giving me these challenges as well, you know.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, do you have enough of a discipline?
[SPEAKER_00] Have you built already a momentum that this is something that, that, that you do every single day?
[SPEAKER_00] Or do you do it, uh, on and off?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, to be honest with you, um, I don't do it, like, every day.
[SPEAKER_01] Because, you know, sometimes life happens and I, I have to prioritize sometimes.
[SPEAKER_01] And even though those are my priorities, if something comes up, I have to adapt and then,
[SPEAKER_01] you know, tackle down that thing that I have to do, you know.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, because there are some days that, um, that I have to be, for example, at work,
[SPEAKER_01] at building and safety to pull out some permits at 7:00 AM.
[SPEAKER_01] So sometimes it doesn't give me the chance.
[SPEAKER_01] Still, I have to, I just have to work on that and make a better, um, routine when those cases appear.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01] But I think most of the time I'm, I'm really doing my habits.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I'm doing the, the good habits.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes when I'm in a rush, what I do is I just dedicate less time to them, but I still do, do them.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, so what is, what is the most powerful, powerful habit that, that you, uh, really try to implement each and every day?
[SPEAKER_00] What, which one of all those things that you do, which one will you, uh, pick up as, as the most beneficial for yourself?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, because also after those four habits that I just mentioned, I, I work, I go to the gym and
[SPEAKER_01] work out probably for about two hours.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] Right. Uh, so working out, it's very powerful to me, to be honest.
[SPEAKER_01] But, um, if I could just pick up one of these habits, morning habits.
[SPEAKER_00] Interesting question, is it?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, probably I would choose.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably choose, uh, visualization.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, um, to be able to have the target, you know, my goals in my mind.
[SPEAKER_01] It's very important because, uh, I could have the bad day.
[SPEAKER_01] But if I remember for what I'm living and for what I'm doing, whatever I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01] And that even those bad days count as good days because they help you with something, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] You know, that gives you something else.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's, uh, a good time to taste, you know, to, yeah, to, to, to taste how good you have become.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, if you can handle those moments.
[SPEAKER_01] So if I have the vision of whatever I have to do during the day and my goals, I can go through anything.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Very interesting, uh, option, choice.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you know, have you ever heard about reticulate activating system?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, I have.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] With Tom Billy.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] So when, when you know how our mind is working, uh, I don't know, for example,
[SPEAKER_00] I knew that, uh, I will be getting a new car.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, since that moment when, when I knew what will be my next car, I started to, to see them on the streets.
[SPEAKER_00] Every single hour I can see, I don't know, a few of those car, or this car on the streets.
[SPEAKER_00] So when, when my mind knows where to shoot and what to, what to focus on, I can really, really,
[SPEAKER_00] see those things around me in my environment.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is why setting a goals, setting goals, and this is why visualization is so powerful.
[SPEAKER_00] And I really, really, uh, I'm glad that you picked visualization.
[SPEAKER_01] All right, man.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm glad that we, we, um, agree.
[SPEAKER_00] Something that is really, really interesting also, you know, I, I have a friend.
[SPEAKER_00] He's a, he's a ninjitsu, uh, practitioner.
[SPEAKER_00] Ninjitsu is an old, old Japanese traditional martial arts.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, there is a one part of this, uh, of this discipline called ninpo.
[SPEAKER_00] And ninpo is on Japanese, uh, some kind of a school for life.
[SPEAKER_00] And they emphasize on, on mental and emotional development of the, of the, of those, uh, practitioners
[SPEAKER_00] of the ninjas.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, he said to me that what is really, really important, uh, every day that when you wake up,
[SPEAKER_00] your brain starts recycling the history, the old stories, the old ideas and the memories inside of your hand.
[SPEAKER_00] And if, if you don't step this, this cycle, you will always be re, reliving your past.
[SPEAKER_00] So the thoughts will be about the past and your present will be about that past.
[SPEAKER_00] You, you will, you will just, uh, repeat the same actions that you, that you did yesterday.
[SPEAKER_00] So the only way to cut that cord and to, to cut this cycle, to break the cycle is by visualization.
[SPEAKER_00] So the first thing that you do when you wake up, just visualize how do you want to live from now into the future.
[SPEAKER_00] And what is really, really important is that you really, uh, you really emphasize
[SPEAKER_00] this picture inside of your mind and to really emphasize the emotion.
[SPEAKER_00] Because, you know, our minds work in pictures, we see images in our minds.
[SPEAKER_00] And when we see image, that image makes and creates emotion.
[SPEAKER_00] And only when the emotion is high enough or intense enough, then is the time that,
[SPEAKER_00] then is the time that, only time that we can make new action and change behavior.
[SPEAKER_00] So it is, it is a really, really interesting concept.
[SPEAKER_01] I agree with you, man, about all that too.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, when you said that, okay, so you, you, you, you have your routine for sleeping,
[SPEAKER_00] it is enough for you, you read.
[SPEAKER_00] So every day you're trying to, to learn something new to learn from, from the
[SPEAKER_00] people that you found, find inspiring and empowering.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, you visualize.
[SPEAKER_00] And can you tell me right now?
[SPEAKER_00] So we are talking about productivity right now.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you maybe tell me what is your main focus right now?
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, how do you set your priorities throughout the day?
[SPEAKER_00] So what is, what is your main focus right now in this period of time?
[SPEAKER_01] Well, in terms of how I prioritize, I, and really fast, I don't put too much thought on it.
[SPEAKER_01] But I analyze my situation, you know, my current situation.
[SPEAKER_01] And I analyze the action or the thing that I do that is going to give me the most.
[SPEAKER_01] That is going to influence even the other activities that I have to do.
[SPEAKER_01] So if I achieve this, if I do this, I could call, call it a good day.
[SPEAKER_01] This will benefit myself.
[SPEAKER_01] This will benefit my business.
[SPEAKER_01] They will, this will benefit my goals.
[SPEAKER_01] That's how I do it.
[SPEAKER_01] And sometimes, you know, you have to sacrifice some stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, and, and, and if you, let's say, also, I make a, uh, um,
[SPEAKER_01] Um, I'd say that, um, I go to my calendar and I put all the things that I, that I'm going to do at night.
[SPEAKER_01] So I create my day at night.
[SPEAKER_01] So I really, my brain already knows what's going to happen the next day.
[SPEAKER_01] So probably I have like 10 important activities.
[SPEAKER_01] But from those 10 important activities, I just select three.
[SPEAKER_01] And for those, from those three, I select one.
[SPEAKER_01] That is the one that I have to do no matter what.
[SPEAKER_01] So the next day, I just think, okay, I have this amount of time.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to go, go here and do this, this, and that.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I'm okay.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm just going to do my number one.
[SPEAKER_01] After I do my number one, whatever else I do is going to be extra.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's create mom, that creates momentum for me.
[SPEAKER_01] Because I already achieved the number one.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I can do number, number four, number five.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes I have done up to number 10.
[SPEAKER_01] And I feel like I gave my, my hundred percent, you know, during the day.
[SPEAKER_01] But there are some days that, uh, I'm not as productive as I would like to.
[SPEAKER_01] So sometimes I just achieve seven, sometimes five.
[SPEAKER_01] There weren't even days that I just achieved one or two things, you know.
[SPEAKER_01] But I don't let those days, um, define me and define what I, what I do.
[SPEAKER_01] And right now in terms of product.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know if I have to talk about this with you, but, uh, I started my own business, uh, 10 months ago.
[SPEAKER_01] December, last year.
[SPEAKER_01] And I created my job.
[SPEAKER_01] And I started my, my design studio for, for, you know, architecture, blueprints and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01] So at the beginning of the year, it was going pretty well.
[SPEAKER_01] And a couple of months ago, I just had a hard time about it.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, like hard time finding clients, uh, having hard time with current clients.
[SPEAKER_01] So what I started to do was like analyzing myself and asking those hard questions.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, like why, why, what am, why, what am I doing wrong?
[SPEAKER_01] Why I am not having more clients?
[SPEAKER_01] Why am, am I not product producing more money?
[SPEAKER_01] Why am I not selling more people?
[SPEAKER_01] Why my, my client list is not growing?
[SPEAKER_01] So I had a hundred reasons to blame something else.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, but at the end, I just recognized that it was all on me.
[SPEAKER_01] So what I started doing is, okay.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to fix this.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably I'm not good at following up with clients.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to get better at it.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably, uh, the way I produce blueprints are not good enough.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to, you know, like step up my game.
[SPEAKER_01] I started doing social media like Instagram to be able to reach more people.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I asked myself, am I doing the right thing?
[SPEAKER_01] So I asked a couple of my friends, um, and they guided me.
[SPEAKER_01] One of them is, um, my friend, my friend, one of my best friends, Keith and my other best friend,
[SPEAKER_01] Crystal, uh, my friend, Rafael.
[SPEAKER_01] I asked them a couple of questions about my business and about the experience that they
[SPEAKER_01] have had with their own businesses.
[SPEAKER_01] And they were able to guide me a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01] So I was like, okay, I was doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to do to have a different approach.
[SPEAKER_01] So I just been analyzing what the, all the process from where I get the client until I finished.
[SPEAKER_01] How has been my performing, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] So I just, just identify a lot of points that I have to get better at.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's not something crazy.
[SPEAKER_01] I just have to put in the work trial, you know, trial and error, see what works, what doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01] And, uh, adjust, then keep moving forward.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's my mentality right now, just to get better at it.
[SPEAKER_01] Ask for help to, to people, friends, even people that I don't know, you know, like
[SPEAKER_01] that I just know that they, they know what I don't.
[SPEAKER_01] So I asked them, uh, look in books, uh, you know, resources and try to, to, to even bring my,
[SPEAKER_01] my business to its best, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] So you are a, a fresh entrepreneur.
[SPEAKER_00] This, this is your first startup?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_00] So are you the only one, uh, employed right now in this startup?
[SPEAKER_00] Yes, I am.
[SPEAKER_00] It's not, it's, it's all, you are all by yourself right now.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay, correct.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] But then this, this is a very courageous of you.
[SPEAKER_00] It is really brave.
[SPEAKER_00] Congrats.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm, I want to congratulate you on, on opening your own business,
[SPEAKER_00] starting your own business.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is, this is, uh, maybe, uh, a great question for, for this point of, for this part
[SPEAKER_00] of the interview then.
[SPEAKER_00] And do you have maybe some kind of a mentors that, that is, that are mentoring you
[SPEAKER_00] about how to, how to start a business, how to grow a business?
[SPEAKER_00] Do you have maybe some coaches you, you, you said to me that you have, that you were using
[SPEAKER_00] the services of a life coach?
[SPEAKER_00] Is it?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, I do have a life coach.
[SPEAKER_01] We see each other probably once a month about that.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] He, he gives me advice in terms of business in general.
[SPEAKER_00] Also.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] But I've been looking for a mentor in terms of architecture, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] someone that is doing what I want to do.
[SPEAKER_01] I haven't succeeded on that.
[SPEAKER_01] I've been asking people.
[SPEAKER_01] I've been putting myself out there.
[SPEAKER_01] So I have faith that, that if I keep doing the work and keep asking,
[SPEAKER_01] one day I will find someone that wants to mentor me, you know, in terms of the business.
[SPEAKER_01] And, and be able to, to reach the next level, get better at it.
[SPEAKER_00] And what can, what, what can, what can you do for, for, for a mentor?
[SPEAKER_01] Oh, I can do work for free.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, that's something that I've been offering.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I can do work for free for you.
[SPEAKER_01] I can help you probably, if you already have your business established,
[SPEAKER_01] we'll see which parts are not been taken care of properly.
[SPEAKER_01] and probably I can, you know, feeling and, and, and bring value to those areas that,
[SPEAKER_01] that need some more attention.
[SPEAKER_01] Also, what I do is like, uh, most of the like to go to, uh, to visit the clients, you know,
[SPEAKER_01] they are more like, I want to work on my office so I could take care of that part.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, you know, like just the work that doesn't require them.
[SPEAKER_01] Do it.
[SPEAKER_01] That's pretty much what I'm offering for now.
[SPEAKER_01] And still I'm open to suggestions.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, people will sometimes come up to me and they are like,
[SPEAKER_01] Abraham, you should consider doing this for, for contractors, for builders, for architects,
[SPEAKER_01] for designers.
[SPEAKER_01] And, and I'm taking everything into account and then I'm reaching out.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I'm every time that I go to building and safety to submit plans.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, I, I talk with people up there because they are doing the same
[SPEAKER_01] thing or something similar that I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01] And I just ask them for their business card and I give them my business card and I now offer my
[SPEAKER_01] service like, Hey, I'll do this, this, and this.
[SPEAKER_01] I could use these programs and I could help you with something.
[SPEAKER_01] Probably we can create a relationship from where both benefit, you know, we both benefit from it.
[SPEAKER_01] So that's, I think it's been a good approach and people have been reacting to it.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I've been rich for, um, for, um, just so far two people have contacted me to,
[SPEAKER_01] in order to work with them.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think I'm already making progress.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, what I recommend people is you just have to keep doing the work until it works.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, and put yourself up there and try, just ask.
[SPEAKER_01] And people say, no, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01] You just go and ask for the next one.
[SPEAKER_01] Of course.
[SPEAKER_01] And no one is like, you know, taking care of, um, my business, but me.
[SPEAKER_01] So I have to, to do this, to, to, to give my all for my business.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, uh, one of my suggestions, maybe to do, this is something that I, that I do.
[SPEAKER_00] I also have a coach.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, I'm also visiting, I, I have meetings with this coach, uh, once a month, just like you.
[SPEAKER_00] And it is combination of business and life coaching also.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, once more thing I have, I don't have in-person mentor,
[SPEAKER_00] but I'm a part of, uh, one Facebook group and I paid 100 bucks.
[SPEAKER_00] And I, I've got a lifetime, uh, subscription to it.
[SPEAKER_00] And right now I think it's 40 or $50 a month.
[SPEAKER_00] So I don't know if you ever heard about Sean Thomas, Ask a Millionaire.
[SPEAKER_01] No, I haven't.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So, um, he's really popular on Instagram.
[SPEAKER_00] He has above 1 million followers, uh, on Ask a Millionaire.
[SPEAKER_00] It's, it's the name of the, of the Instagram page.
[SPEAKER_00] And there, there, there are right now around 10 mentors inside of this Facebook group that are doing regular live calls.
[SPEAKER_00] So live video, video, video Facebook calls inside of the Facebook group.
[SPEAKER_00] And the, some of those mentors are billionaires.
[SPEAKER_00] Not milk, not millionaires, but billionaires.
[SPEAKER_00] And we'd be, be, yes.
[SPEAKER_00] And we can, uh, so they, they schedule a live, uh, live call and we can ask questions there.
[SPEAKER_00] And they answer to our, to our questions.
[SPEAKER_00] So if you cannot find a mentor in person, maybe you can find something like that, that, that, that suits you.
[SPEAKER_00] And that, that, that can, that can help you until you, you find someone in person.
[SPEAKER_00] And the third thing that, that I also did, and that I have a great benefit with, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] till now is, is the mastermind group.
[SPEAKER_00] I, I formed a mastermind group here in Zagreb, in Croatia.
[SPEAKER_00] And we meet regularly.
[SPEAKER_00] We meet every Thursday at 7:00 PM.
[SPEAKER_00] And I have 20 members.
[SPEAKER_00] So 20 of us are in a Facebook group, but, uh, every, every week, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] around six or seven of us are meeting regularly.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, all of us are with, with different backgrounds, with different, uh, specialties, expertise,
[SPEAKER_00] and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] So we really, really help each other.
[SPEAKER_00] All of us have set, set our goals and presented those goals to the group.
[SPEAKER_00] And we all brainstorm, uh, about each other's goals and help each other, uh, give feedback back, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] create some plans, strategies, and really be, uh, an encouragement, empowerment.
[SPEAKER_00] And also what is really, really important on our accountability partners to each other,
[SPEAKER_00] so that we really, really do the actions that we need to do.
[SPEAKER_00] So this, this is my suggestion.
[SPEAKER_00] If you can form your own mastermind group there in Los Angeles, and it will be really easy for you.
[SPEAKER_00] So, I don't know, you, you can have one, one person who is, uh, I don't know,
[SPEAKER_00] he's working for a bank or the second person, he's, uh, his specialty is in digital marketing.
[SPEAKER_00] And the third person is, I don't know, in, in maybe some other industry.
[SPEAKER_00] And so if five or six or seven of you are meeting regularly, then each of you can benefit from each other.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, it's really, really a powerful idea.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is my suggestion to you.
[SPEAKER_00] And you can, you can really, you can think about it.
[SPEAKER_00] And if you need any, any help in the future, just, just send me a text and I will, I will be, I will gladly help you.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I appreciate the, the support, the idea and, uh, your offer, man.
[SPEAKER_01] I'll, I'm, I'm gonna definitely, definitely take the, take your word and, and ask for help about it.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, I'm gonna look for those masterminds, you know, in terms of architecture.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, but it's curious, like, um, it's, um, very, um, it's a coincidence, I think, or not a coincidence because we're, you know, in the same, um, path looking for, um, get better.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, so also my, my best friend, Kit and I, we have a mastermind.
[SPEAKER_01] It's just the two of us for now.
[SPEAKER_01] And we have, uh, a Google hangout, like a, a live, a video call.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay.
[SPEAKER_01] Every, every Tuesday of the week, every week, every Tuesday.
[SPEAKER_01] And we talk about everything, you know, uh, about, uh, business, about life, about problems,
[SPEAKER_01] about the good things, about, uh, anything.
[SPEAKER_01] And, and we're pretty transparent and we, we put ourselves in a vulnerable place, you know, like,
[SPEAKER_01] Hey, this is me.
[SPEAKER_01] These are my weaknesses.
[SPEAKER_01] These are my strengths.
[SPEAKER_01] And we help each other, you know, we motivate each other and we support each other.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think that helps a lot, you know, personally.
[SPEAKER_01] Uh, I don't know if my friend knows, I think he does.
[SPEAKER_01] But, uh, whenever he, he makes time to talk to me and share what he wants to share with me
[SPEAKER_01] and listen to me, give me advice and guide me or give me just his, his own opinion.
[SPEAKER_01] It means the world to me because I could, I could, I could keep going.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, it's like, oh, my friend is here to, to help me keep moving forward.
[SPEAKER_01] And I appreciate that very much.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think very soon we're going to start growing that, um, mastermind group.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm going to take, uh, into account what you said to me today and, um, really
[SPEAKER_01] bring that to the next level.
[SPEAKER_01] Hopefully you can give us some advice of how to get better.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, of course, of course, I'm doing it for six months right now.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, it's just getting better and better.
[SPEAKER_00] So we, we meet regularly every Thursday for six months and it's just getting better and better.
[SPEAKER_00] So this was a learning process for me also.
[SPEAKER_00] So we have, uh, the first part of the meeting right now is called rep rapid fire.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] So each member have around three to five minutes to give, give an update to the group of, uh,
[SPEAKER_00] what, what is he doing about his goals and what are his next actions actions.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is a rapid fire.
[SPEAKER_00] Each member does it.
[SPEAKER_00] And the second part of the, of the meeting is hot seat.
[SPEAKER_00] So we pick one person from the mastermind group and we focus only on him.
[SPEAKER_00] So he will get half an hour.
[SPEAKER_00] He will say to us, where is he right now?
[SPEAKER_00] What problems or challenges does he have?
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know, to, to make the next step to his, uh, goal.
[SPEAKER_00] And we are giving him feedback and we, we, we can do a workshop together.
[SPEAKER_00] We can make a big discussion.
[SPEAKER_00] We can brainstorm about something and really, really try to help him.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, just, just, just have the, this attitude of service to him for this half an hour.
[SPEAKER_00] And the last part of the meeting for, for the last half an hour, we just pick a subject.
[SPEAKER_00] We pick, we pick a topic and we just discuss it.
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know today.
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe we are going to talk about productivity.
[SPEAKER_00] And we spend half an hour talking about productivity.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is an interesting concept.
[SPEAKER_00] You said that you and your friend are talking about those things.
[SPEAKER_00] And you know, when two minds come together, you got a, a new mind, a better mind called mastermind.
[SPEAKER_00] So just imagine what, what will happen when you have five, six, seven, eight of the minds that are really, really have this attitude of, of this, this kind of a growth mindset.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's really, really beneficial.
[SPEAKER_00] It's really beneficial.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] All right.
[SPEAKER_01] So I'm going to take action on that.
[SPEAKER_00] Just, just text me if you, if you consider it and if you want to grow your mastermind, I'm really here to help you.
[SPEAKER_00] No problem.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, one, one more thing that I want to ask you, uh, regarding, uh, the, the productivity.
[SPEAKER_00] Do you have any, maybe challenges because of the use of, of this modern technology like phones or computers?
[SPEAKER_00] Because what I, what I thought, uh, is that a lot of people have big problems, uh, with distraction that is coming from, uh, the phones,
[SPEAKER_00] the social media and things like this.
[SPEAKER_00] So, so do you find this challenging?
[SPEAKER_00] Do you feel that you, you are losing maybe time and that you are being distracted by, by this, uh, new obsession, by, by this new disease in, in society?
[SPEAKER_01] Um, I think that I, that I am distracted by them, you know, because I decide to, you know, I spend sometimes
[SPEAKER_01] um, a little more than what I should be spending on the apps, you know, Instagram, Facebook, WhatsApp, YouTube.
[SPEAKER_01] But the thing is that I've been trying to turn them into my favor, you know, like, okay, you want to watch some videos on YouTube?
[SPEAKER_01] Um, watch videos that are going to give you value that's like for my business or for my habits or something that I want to learn, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] So that benefits me.
[SPEAKER_01] So I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes with this Instagram, I use it to, to post like kind of my journey and to inspire other people, you know, as I mentioned earlier, like what I do is just to show people that is possible.
[SPEAKER_01] So I'm using Instagram as a tool, not as a distractor.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, there are a lot of things to be distracted by, but, uh, I choose not to spend a lot of time on, over there.
[SPEAKER_01] Just a little bit, I'm not saying that I don't get distracted.
[SPEAKER_01] Just a little bit, I take a look here and there.
[SPEAKER_01] But I try more to share my journey and inspire others.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, it's, it's, it's the matter, it's the matter of the thing who is using whom?
[SPEAKER_00] Is your phone using you or you are using your phone?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] You said, you said that perfectly, man.
[SPEAKER_01] I like that phrase.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, uh, on the iPhone, on the new iOS, uh, software operating system, you, you have a new app that is built in
[SPEAKER_00] and it is called screen time.
[SPEAKER_00] So it is really interesting because it gives you the analytics of the, uh, apps that you are using.
[SPEAKER_00] How much time are you spending in each app?
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, what is the number of notifications that you get during the day?
[SPEAKER_00] So when you look at the numbers, you, your jaw just drops and you cannot believe that this is the amount
[SPEAKER_00] of the time that, that you have spent, uh, on, on, on the, on, on this phone and in those apps.
[SPEAKER_00] And when you know that, just like you said, you try to be productive.
[SPEAKER_00] You try to, to do the, to do something of value in there, but you know, we are all humans.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, we, we lose a track of, of, of productivity and, and those things.
[SPEAKER_00] And we just got distracted.
[SPEAKER_00] And we go in, in the, in the, that autopilot mode and do something that is not really in our favor.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's really, really interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] This is the topic that I've been thinking, uh, about a lot lately, because I see, I see, of course,
[SPEAKER_00] you, Abraham, when, when you walk on the streets of Los Angeles, if you go with a public transport or you are
[SPEAKER_00] next to you, I don't know, when you are, when you are stopping on the road,
[SPEAKER_00] you can see how much people are looking on their phones.
[SPEAKER_00] We, we, we, we, we, we look just like a zombies to me in the, in the last few years.
[SPEAKER_00] It's a, it's a big problem that, that I think that, that it needs to be addressed very, very soon.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, I agree with you, man.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I agree with you.
[SPEAKER_01] Um, you know, um, I used to be one of those.
[SPEAKER_01] I think I used to spend a lot of time on the phone, but right now I'm using it more as a tool.
[SPEAKER_01] And you know, whenever I have a chance, I just put it away, you know, and, and, and create a new habit of not
[SPEAKER_01] depending, not, not be depending on, on my phone.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, even at nights, I just put it away.
[SPEAKER_01] I, I leave the, the phone away from me.
[SPEAKER_01] And so I don't have that, um, feeling of, oh, I, I want to check Instagram.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to check Facebook.
[SPEAKER_01] No, it's away.
[SPEAKER_01] It's done.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to do other stuff, reading at night a little bit
[SPEAKER_01] and do other activities that are going to give me value instead of taking it from me, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] Let me, let me take a, a, a big turn, right?
[SPEAKER_00] So, uh, can you tell me maybe if you know, why is it that you want to be successful?
[SPEAKER_00] What, what is, what is this drive inside of you and what, what do you think where this drive comes from?
[SPEAKER_00] Why do you want to achieve bigger things in life and live above the average?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, that's a pretty good question.
[SPEAKER_01] Well, I think that I want to be successful because I want to enjoy life.
[SPEAKER_01] And I know some people can be average and still enjoy, enjoy life.
[SPEAKER_01] But to me, um, I want to be able to impact positively a lot of people.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to be able, as I travel the world and, and have, you know, be able to experience those
[SPEAKER_01] experiences that, you know, some of them cost money.
[SPEAKER_01] So you have the resources to have those experiences and also give those experiences to others.
[SPEAKER_01] I have to, to take care of myself and my business and be able to bring value to the marketplace.
[SPEAKER_01] So I can make money, so I can share those, that, that, that money with, with other people
[SPEAKER_01] or that success with other people, because let's say that I do, I am not successful,
[SPEAKER_01] that I'm, I'm not doing the work and anything.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm just an average guy.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, people don't, don't take you seriously, you know, when you share something.
[SPEAKER_01] If you want to invite them to have, um, to do certain activity, uh, they are like,
[SPEAKER_01] but you don't do that type of thing.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, you, you haven't done it.
[SPEAKER_01] So I don't believe you.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't trust you because you don't have anything to bug you up.
[SPEAKER_01] But if you are successful, if you have done the things that you are preaching,
[SPEAKER_01] people are going to trust you.
[SPEAKER_01] They are going to believe you.
[SPEAKER_01] They're going to follow you.
[SPEAKER_01] And, you know, I want to change humanity in a positive way.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I don't like when I see people suffering because they cannot confront fear or insecurities,
[SPEAKER_01] you know?
[SPEAKER_01] So if I confront them and, and, and I'm at the end, I'm a winner.
[SPEAKER_01] People can believe me and be able like, okay, I'm going to confront them as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So they can take the leap.
[SPEAKER_01] They can take the next step.
[SPEAKER_01] And we, you know, by being successful, I think we, we, we can change humanity, you know, in a good way.
[SPEAKER_01] I don't know about what happens in Croatia, but here, here in the U.S. and in my country, Mexico,
[SPEAKER_01] there are a lot of psychological problems, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] There are a lot of trauma that we have parents, grandparents, and the people that we're surrounded
[SPEAKER_01] with.
[SPEAKER_01] And, and I believe that if you become successful, if you do the work, you can change those programs
[SPEAKER_01] in our brain and, and really change society.
[SPEAKER_01] How have you ever imagined like a successful society?
[SPEAKER_01] How would it be that everybody can achieve what they want?
[SPEAKER_01] You know, of course, there is going to be challenges.
[SPEAKER_01] There is going to be struggle, but the people, instead of cry about it and complain about it,
[SPEAKER_01] they embrace it.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay, I have this challenge.
[SPEAKER_01] You're welcome.
[SPEAKER_01] You're welcome in my life.
[SPEAKER_01] Let's do it.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, man.
[SPEAKER_00] I agree.
[SPEAKER_00] I agree with you.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is, this is also my mission in life.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is why I started this, I started this, this brand, Allude.
[SPEAKER_00] So life of our dreams for the people that don't know still what the acronym stands for.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, I'm, I was thinking a lot.
[SPEAKER_00] You see, when you think about it, our, our minds are just a mental software, is it?
[SPEAKER_00] And, you know, this mental software was created by few things.
[SPEAKER_00] So I'm thinking about few pillars there.
[SPEAKER_00] So the first one is, we can, we can say it's genetics.
[SPEAKER_00] So we, we, we got some things by our genetics.
[SPEAKER_00] The second, the second pillar is our parenting.
[SPEAKER_00] So what did you learn with and about from your parents during your childhood?
[SPEAKER_00] This is a very, very important part.
[SPEAKER_00] The third part is your formal education system.
[SPEAKER_00] So what, how was, how was, how was your formal education system?
[SPEAKER_00] What did they learn you, learned you, taught you?
[SPEAKER_00] The, the fourth one is media.
[SPEAKER_00] Media, it is really, really important.
[SPEAKER_00] And when you combine all of this together, you really got a product
[SPEAKER_00] like Abraham.
[SPEAKER_00] So you, you had, you have, you had some kind of a parenting.
[SPEAKER_00] You, you, you lived in some kind of an environment in this, in one city in Mexico.
[SPEAKER_00] So you went to school there.
[SPEAKER_00] And, and then you, you had some kind of a media and you consume those,
[SPEAKER_00] this content from this media and this government has some kind of a plan.
[SPEAKER_00] So why they're going to, to produce content like this and share and distribute content,
[SPEAKER_00] like, like content like this.
[SPEAKER_00] And so when you combine all of this, so this, this is a part of your condition, conditioning.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is why you are right now the way you are, because all those things combine together.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is something that I'm trying to build in a company.
[SPEAKER_00] So Lude will be a media company.
[SPEAKER_00] So we're, we're going to create a lot of content.
[SPEAKER_00] Lude is going to be an educational company.
[SPEAKER_00] So we're, we are going to create, uh, courses.
[SPEAKER_00] And we're going to organize events, conferences, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] And the target, uh, target audience for, for it will be young people who are planning,
[SPEAKER_00] planning to be parents soon or young parents.
[SPEAKER_00] So they, they will have a motivation.
[SPEAKER_00] their biggest motivation will be to learn and to grow themselves.
[SPEAKER_00] So they can transfer that knowledge to their kids.
[SPEAKER_00] So they, that they break this negative cycle and that they can nurture and create
[SPEAKER_00] more, uh, empowering, uh, stronger human beings.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is, this is my vision about, about it.
[SPEAKER_00] So what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01] That's fantastic, man.
[SPEAKER_01] I think, uh, this world needs more people like you.
[SPEAKER_01] that is really looking for, to create a, an, an education system to teach, um, young people,
[SPEAKER_01] especially, you know, kids and as you mentioned, young people, that, um,
[SPEAKER_01] that there is something more than what, uh, what the regular education system offers, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] because, because what if they teach you how to love yourself, man?
[SPEAKER_01] That's very important.
[SPEAKER_01] And in school, they don't teach you that.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] The first time that I heard about it was when I found it in a book by myself when I was 25 years old.
[SPEAKER_00] See?
[SPEAKER_00] And it's, it is, it is, it is too late.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, it is too late.
[SPEAKER_01] It's not too late.
[SPEAKER_00] It is, it is late, but it's not too late.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, it is late.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] It's, it's just like, you just wasted, bro.
[SPEAKER_01] Not wasted, but you had trouble during those 25 years before, you know, finding that piece
[SPEAKER_01] of knowledge that changed your life, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] So what if kids were taught those, that type of knowledge when they are young,
[SPEAKER_01] so they can create a different humanity, you know, where they love each other, they support each other,
[SPEAKER_01] they, they embrace fear, they embrace pain, they embrace challenges, and they don't think that
[SPEAKER_01] they are bad, but the catalyst to become better, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] Um, if they teach you how to discipline will, will help you, will free you from the chains of,
[SPEAKER_01] of, you know, doubt and insecurity, you know, what if they teach you how, how to create money,
[SPEAKER_01] you know, it's just, you have to give value to people, that's easy.
[SPEAKER_01] If you give value to people, they are going to give you money.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course.
[SPEAKER_01] There's a phrase I think that says, if you help people get what they want,
[SPEAKER_01] you will get what you want, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] They will give you the resources to get what you want, so.
[SPEAKER_00] It's, it sounds so simple.
[SPEAKER_00] It sounds so simple, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] It is.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, but, you know, if nobody tells us that, it's just, they just tell us,
[SPEAKER_01] oh, at least that's how I grew up.
[SPEAKER_01] You have to go to school, you know, per what, 23 years, so you can get a career,
[SPEAKER_01] then work for someone else, and then you produce money enough to have a house,
[SPEAKER_01] have a family, and live an average life until you become 50, 60 years old, then you retire,
[SPEAKER_01] then you're going to enjoy your golden years, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And, dude, I don't know about you, but I don't want to have the money and be able to enjoy life
[SPEAKER_01] when I'm 60.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to enjoy it now.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to have the money now, and I want to enjoy it, enjoy life now.
[SPEAKER_01] I know, it's a process, it will take time for me to get
[SPEAKER_01] at the economic level that I want to be, but I want to enjoy life now.
[SPEAKER_01] And I want other people to do it as well.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, this is, this is why I asked you the question,
[SPEAKER_00] where do you think that this drive of yours comes from?
[SPEAKER_00] Where does this ambition comes from?
[SPEAKER_00] And I think that maybe it comes from, from the, from the things like media,
[SPEAKER_00] from the, from things like Hollywood, the movies.
[SPEAKER_00] So they are, they are, for years, they are trying to impress our subconscious
[SPEAKER_00] that this is something that we need to strive for.
[SPEAKER_00] All of us need to strive to become better, to become more, to become richer, to become smarter,
[SPEAKER_00] more handsome, I don't know, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Which, what this creates inside of a human being, it can create a lot of frustration.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, especially if you have a, a big expectations for your life
[SPEAKER_00] and you cannot produce it in reality.
[SPEAKER_00] So in this moment, you can create a lot of headaches for yourself and a lot of frustrations.
[SPEAKER_00] And I think that a lot of people will really, really feel something like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Because on a, on a, on a big scale, a lot of us are trying to be special.
[SPEAKER_00] We are trying to be successful, whatever that means in our terms.
[SPEAKER_00] And not many of us will come to that, to that point.
[SPEAKER_00] So, do you have any opinion, maybe, on that?
[SPEAKER_00] How do you, how do you take care of that, your big expectations?
[SPEAKER_00] You know, Tony Robbins have a, a, a saying, he has, he says,
[SPEAKER_00] trade your expectations with appreciations.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, because if you have this expectation that, that you want to achieve something,
[SPEAKER_00] and you are not achieving it day by day, day by day, year by year is passing by,
[SPEAKER_00] and you are not achieving it, and you are having this vision inside of your head,
[SPEAKER_00] and you are not doing enough, or maybe you are not doing anything about it,
[SPEAKER_00] and you're just creating a frustration, a lot of people are doing that.
[SPEAKER_00] So, what is your opinion on that, how do you make sure that you have enough of a patience,
[SPEAKER_00] and when you know that life really is not 100% under your control.
[SPEAKER_00] So, something that I was taught in this ninjitsu school of nympho, this is something that I also went
[SPEAKER_00] through, is that we can control, this is how we were thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00] You control 51% and the environment controls 49%.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, so I will do my part, I will go into the direction that I want to go,
[SPEAKER_00] and those dominoes will fall how they want to fall outside.
[SPEAKER_00] So, there are some kind of outside forces that I cannot control, but I can steer in the direction that I want to steer,
[SPEAKER_00] and the things will fall how they want to fall, and I need to react, and I gotta have the attitude that will
[SPEAKER_00] bring me through this noise and bring me through those challenges.
[SPEAKER_00] So, what is your opinion on all of this that I just said?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, actually, I used to be like very anxious, you know, about achieving my goals now, you know, I had no patience,
[SPEAKER_01] and I was feeling bad about myself, you know, I was like, Abraham, you're not good enough.
[SPEAKER_01] I used to think that I was a good for nothing, because I was not achieving my goals, you know.
[SPEAKER_01] I was like, well, I decided to have this goal, and then I've been working for so long, and it hasn't happened.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, but I was not analyzing myself, like, why it hasn't happened.
[SPEAKER_01] Is it because you are not doing the right thing? Is it because your strategy is lacking something?
[SPEAKER_01] Is it because you're not surrounded with the right people? Is it because of your thought process,
[SPEAKER_01] your beliefs? You know, a lot of facts. So, then I started analyzing those parts in my life,
[SPEAKER_01] and then I was like, okay, then all these facts are involved in the results that I have.
[SPEAKER_01] So, what I started to do is, okay, I have this big goal, but I'm going to enjoy the small ones
[SPEAKER_01] that are going to lead me to that goal, you know, that are going to help me get there.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I just appreciate everything, man. Like, even that I'm having, like, for example, right now,
[SPEAKER_01] that I'm having this moment with you, I appreciate that. How many people have the chance to do this?
[SPEAKER_01] You know, with a friend from another continent, and we're able to do this when
[SPEAKER_01] in my place is 2:00 p.m. and in your place is what, 11:00 p.m., you know?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, almost 12:00, man. And we're doing it, you know? And I'm grateful about it.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm grateful that I have a place where to live, you know? And because that place is leading me to the
[SPEAKER_01] next place that I want. You know, I have to have this. I have to experience this in order to value
[SPEAKER_01] the next thing. So, what I believe is that people are so fixated, you know, and focus on the end up
[SPEAKER_01] result that they are not enjoying the process. They are not enjoying the now, what they have now.
[SPEAKER_01] Even though it might not be what you want, but it's what you have. So, be grateful about it.
[SPEAKER_01] Because, you know, sometimes I compare myself, like there are people that they don't have the
[SPEAKER_01] opportunity that I have. You know, there are people that they they haven't even have a phone in their
[SPEAKER_01] hands. You know? So, I'm like, okay, I have a phone, I have a computer, I have friends, I have a car,
[SPEAKER_01] I have an education, I have a business, I have all these things. I have my arms, I am 20 years old,
[SPEAKER_01] and my brain works well, I can eat, I can drink water, I can think, I can, all my senses are working
[SPEAKER_01] well. So, I'm thankful about that, you know? So, I think that helps me go through my days and don't
[SPEAKER_01] feel that I'm not progressing. Because, you know, every day it's helping me a little bit, a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00] And you are the only one who is going to decide what is fast and what is slow.
[SPEAKER_01] Correct. You know, like one of my friends, he always remind me, you know, like your time will come.
[SPEAKER_01] Your time will come. Because, you know, sometimes your time is already here.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah? It is. Oh yeah. But, you know, sometimes we compare ourselves with someone that is more
[SPEAKER_00] successful than us. Because we have opportunity to do that today. Because 100 years ago, we cannot,
[SPEAKER_00] we could not compare ourselves to someone living on another continent. Because we didn't have a way to do it.
[SPEAKER_00] You have Hollywood in your place. So, you are living in Los Angeles. And Hollywood is making a propaganda for
[SPEAKER_00] for half of the planet. So, we in Croatia here, we also watch the Hollywood movies.
[SPEAKER_00] And they are the ones setting the ideals for something. They are the ones creating the value systems also.
[SPEAKER_00] This is very, very important.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes. And, you know, I think one of the scenes in several movies that I have seen, you know, the time lapse, you know, that they put where this guy or this girl is, is having a goal. And then you can see like everything passing fast. Like, oh, you can see a scene where he's studying, but he is working out, where he is not spending money.
[SPEAKER_01] And then all the sudden, after five years, he's successful, you know, but gives you that type of scene gives you the idea that it's gonna pass fast, you know, and that after five years, whatever you're doing is gonna bring you to that place that you desire.
[SPEAKER_01] And it's not true. During those five days, you have to put in the work, you have to make mistakes, and you have to learn and optimize your habits, your the way you think, the way you believe, the way you act, the way you speak, the way you communicate, you know, all those aspects, you have to take care of them during that period of time.
[SPEAKER_01] And then you might achieve that success in five years or it might take you 10 years, then it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. And what is really interesting also is that all those celebrities or successful people that are presented to us, we see them only right now when they're already on the top.
[SPEAKER_00] And nobody nobody showed to us what what they look like 15 or 20 years ago when they're just starting when they're feeling their struggles inside of them, and really trying to find clarity in their lives, and really trying to find faith in themselves and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00] Nobody showed us this. They showed us the end product, you know. And this is why I just wanna, you know, when two of us are speaking right now, I don't know for how many people would be this interesting because when they see our names, they don't know who we are.
[SPEAKER_00] They're not going to be, we're not going to be, we're not going to be a great click bait on internet, are we? You know, and we are, we are two, two of guys that are on the base of the mountain.
[SPEAKER_00] And I don't know, Connor McGregor, he's on the top of the mountain, you know, he's on the top of the mountain. So a lot of us are looking to them and trying to learn from them. And sometimes they are too far away that we cannot even relate to them.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, maybe, maybe the people that are starting right now can learn more from us than from them. You know?
[SPEAKER_01] Correct. I remember that.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. Have you watched maybe, I think that I saw on your Instagram that you are part of the MMA community, that you are watching maybe UFC or something like this?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, I used to watch those fights because I think a couple of years ago, I used to practice mixed martial arts. I practiced it for a little bit, a couple of months and have fun with it, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] Have you watched the last match between McGregor and Nurmagomedov?
[SPEAKER_01] And Khabib?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, it was a really good fight, I think.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah?
[SPEAKER_01] You know, it's just superior than Conor McGregor, in my opinion.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, he's been working harder than McGregor, even though McGregor works hard, but he just found someone that has done more work.
[SPEAKER_01] than him.
[SPEAKER_00] You're right. You're right. You're right. You know, it is funny. This year, so Croatia, our national team in soccer or in football, like it is said here in Europe, have you heard about the World Cup in football?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, I have.
[SPEAKER_00] So this year, Croatia was playing in the finals with France, and Croatia won the second place.
[UNKNOWN] Correct.
[SPEAKER_00] And I was in the finals, I was in Russia, in Moscow, and there I met Khabib.
[SPEAKER_00] Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, I met Khabib there, and I took a picture with him. And fast forward a few months ahead, and he and Conor are competing for a lightweight championship.
[SPEAKER_00] And he won.
[UNKNOWN] And he won.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, but I was rooting for Conor, despite of his big mouth and all those things, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] But interesting. This is something that I really enjoyed to watch, because I think that a lot of things that we are talking about right now, you can find in martial arts.
[SPEAKER_00] So, yeah. So, man, a couple of questions more. Can you tell me maybe what brings a smile on your face?
[SPEAKER_01] That brings a smile on my face.
[SPEAKER_01] There are a lot of things, but I'm going to share what happened a couple of days ago.
[SPEAKER_01] Actually, last Thursday.
[SPEAKER_01] Man, I was just driving back home. And I was just looking at the sky. And I know it's going to sound silly, but you know, I just found that the sky was so beautiful, man.
[SPEAKER_01] Different tones of blue, white, and gray. All the clouds were bright and different tones as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And it was just a beautiful scene. And I was so grateful that I was able to spot it and be able to appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I was just driving, like, slow and enjoying it. And I asked myself, you know, like, how many times I have missed this beautiful scene, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] And I was just smiling, smiling, smiling, smiling, smiling, smiling, smiling, smiling.
[SPEAKER_01] So, that was one of the best moments that I have had.
[SPEAKER_01] In a couple of months, you know, and as I said, it sounds silly. It's something so simple. It's something so simple, man, that we take sometimes for granted, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] We take a lot of things for granted, a lot of things, things every day, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I think the simple things, the simple things are the ones that bring me big smiles.
[SPEAKER_01] Cool.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes I could just receive a text from someone and then I smile.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes I could just be aware of the moment and then smile.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, a lot of people, if you stop them on the street and you ask them, what do you want to accomplish in life?
[SPEAKER_00] A lot of them will say, I want to be happy. Aren't they? And I was thinking about it and I really came to the conclusion that we really don't want to be happy, but we are always searching for moments of feeling fully alive.
[SPEAKER_00] Correct.
[SPEAKER_00] You know, when moments like this present themselves, we feel fully alive, then we are happy.
[SPEAKER_00] And the moment that you just mentioned earlier, so you were looking at the sky and you felt alive, you felt present in this moment.
[SPEAKER_00] And this is why you felt happy.
[SPEAKER_00] Yep.
[SPEAKER_00] Definitely.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] And, can you tell me maybe for the end, what is the importance of humor in your life?
[SPEAKER_00] And how do you not take life so seriously?
[SPEAKER_00] Because I can see in you and I can see in myself that we are too ambitious and driven persons.
[SPEAKER_00] And that we can sometimes take life so seriously that we forgot maybe to laugh, to smile and to really keep it more simple.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[UNKNOWN] Well, humor.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, how I use humor is whenever I have, I made a mistake or something bad happens to me, something weird happens to me.
[SPEAKER_01] I just laugh about it.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, even when people get mad sometimes, you know, I'm just laughing.
[SPEAKER_01] Sometimes even on the freeway, you know, here traffic is crazy.
[SPEAKER_01] So there are some crazy drivers as well.
[SPEAKER_01] And they hear and tell you the F word and everything, you know, like, and I just laugh.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I just laugh.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm like, Oh, that was cool.
[SPEAKER_01] I haven't heard that word or I haven't seen that action in a long time.
[SPEAKER_01] So thank you, man.
[SPEAKER_01] Cool.
[SPEAKER_01] And I just laugh about it.
[SPEAKER_01] And sometimes I've been involved in the embarrassing moments.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, that if I were the Abraham of the past, I would feel ashamed and hide myself bad about it.
[SPEAKER_01] I know.
[SPEAKER_01] No, I have like embarrassing moments and I just laugh, you know, and I'm like, Okay, that's happened to me.
[SPEAKER_01] That's okay.
[SPEAKER_01] And I laugh about it.
[SPEAKER_01] And the curious thing that happens is sometimes the people that are seeing you while that happens,
[SPEAKER_01] just because of your reaction wasn't negative in certain way.
[SPEAKER_00] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] They laugh with you, you know, and they don't bother you because you're not affected by that action, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] So I like to laugh about that and about my mistakes, about bad decisions.
[SPEAKER_01] Or sometimes when I'm very frustrated about something that I think that it's going to happen and at the end doesn't happen.
[SPEAKER_01] Or it's just different than I thought.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'm like, Oh, Abraham, you were so worried about this and it didn't happen, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] And I laugh about it.
[SPEAKER_00] So a lot of opportunities to laugh, man.
[SPEAKER_00] This is great, of course.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you recommend one book to the listeners?
[SPEAKER_01] One book?
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] I would say...
[SPEAKER_01] From all the books.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] I would say discipline equals freedom, man.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] You can read two pages every day.
[SPEAKER_00] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] And it gives you this sense of not bullshit, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] Because sometimes we just make a lot of excuses and lies about our life.
[SPEAKER_01] And about why we're not doing or we're not where we want to be.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] So it takes out the bullshit.
[SPEAKER_01] All the lies, all the excuses, and you execute.
[UNKNOWN] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] So I think that book has very good insights.
[SPEAKER_01] And yeah, I think the book I would recommend right now.
[SPEAKER_00] Thanks for the recommend.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, well, can you maybe tell the audience, uh, who do you follow and who do you recommend them to follow on the internet?
[SPEAKER_00] What kind of a shows do you watch on YouTube?
[SPEAKER_00] What kind of a podcast do you listen to?
[SPEAKER_00] So who is the person that influenced you the most right now on the internet?
[SPEAKER_01] We're right now following a lot Joko Willink, which is the author of the book "Discipline Equals Freedom".
[SPEAKER_01] He has another couple of books, "Extreme Ownership", that is, uh, another book that I would recommend.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] And he has another book, the new one is "The Dichotomy of Leadership".
[SPEAKER_01] I haven't read that one.
[SPEAKER_01] I already have it, but I'm rereading "Extreme Ownership" so I can get on the other one.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm following him a lot because I needed discipline in my life.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think, I believe that that guy is the, the incarnation or, yeah, incarnation of discipline, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] He is so disciplined that his discipline is shared, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] You absorb a piece of it.
[SPEAKER_00] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] And then you decide to, to, to, to be disciplined because of everything that he shares.
[SPEAKER_01] You know? And it makes sense if you study what he says, what he promotes.
[SPEAKER_01] It makes sense, man.
[SPEAKER_01] Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Just that phrase, discipline equals freedom.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it is right on point, you know?
[SPEAKER_01] Right on point, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I love, I love, I love his photos on Instagram.
[SPEAKER_00] The first, the first photo is, so it is around four o'clock in the morning and the second photo is always, uh, the, the floor after the workout.
[SPEAKER_00] So, yeah, I just, I just, I love his, his photos on Instagram. Yeah. And he, he says a lot of, with those two pictures. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. So, I think that's the biggest one that I'm following right now. And of course, Tom Bellew from Impact Theory. I follow him on social media and I watch his YouTube channel every time that I have a chance.
[SPEAKER_01] And I guide that for me is very strong as well as, um, Aubrey Marcus. Yeah. And, um, I would recommend also Jordan B. Peterson as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. I'm reading his book right now. That's well. That's well.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah. And, um, I would recommend also Jordan B. Peterson as well.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. I'm reading his book right now. The 12 rules, rules for life. And it is magnificent so far. Yeah. Magnificent.
[SPEAKER_01] So, you're going to become a lobster, huh?
[SPEAKER_00] So, you know it. Yeah. I'm going, I'm going to be the, the, the one, the lobster that, that, that has his, uh, back.
[SPEAKER_00] His chest. Shoulders back. Shoulders back and, uh, chest, uh, yeah. Up.
[SPEAKER_01] Chest up. Yup. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] And what, who else? I would recommend also Ed Milet, uh, Bedros, Kulian, and Andy Frisela. I think those guys are the ones that have been influencing me a lot, you know, because I'm looking for, become the best version of myself.
[SPEAKER_01] And be disciplined, you know, a bit discipline right now, discipline. So, these guys have been giving me tools and just their stories motivate me, you know?
[SPEAKER_00] Mm. You know what is interesting? If you cannot find the five people around yourself that, that you are going to be average of, you can find them on the internet right now.
[SPEAKER_00] You can find them on the internet these days because, you know, uh, are the people before us, uh, maybe 15, 20 or 30 years, uh, in, in the past, they, they really didn't have this kind of opportunity.
[SPEAKER_00] So this is, this is something that is really, really interesting. And we gotta be grateful for that also.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes, definitely, man.
[SPEAKER_00] Yep. Uh, let us, I could go with you for 100 hours. Believe me.
[SPEAKER_00] And, uh, but I want to have some kind of a format of the show. Uh, can you tell me for the end, one or two questions more? So your top three life values, your top three core life values?
[SPEAKER_01] Life, three top core values. Okay. Hmm. Hmm. The first one is believe in yourself, man. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Second one, be open to change. Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] The third one, always be learning, man. Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] So I believe that's what I think. If you believe in you, you know, it doesn't matter where you are in life. It doesn't matter who you think you are right now. Believe in you, believe in you, love you, believe in you, that you could do the change, you know? And so then it comes the second one that you're open to change.
[SPEAKER_01] Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] I believe in myself and I'm willing to change. Mm-hmm. And then you're going to learn, you know? The learning, learning, learning, learning, learning from everybody that you think will bring value to your life. Learn from that person. Mm-hmm. Great, man. Great. The final question. If you watched, uh, Lewis House's.
[SPEAKER_00] Lewis House's, uh, School of Greatness, he has a similar question for, uh, in the end of the show. So, it is your last day on Earth, and the loved ones gathered around you, the last moments, and you want to share with them the, the pure knowledge and the pure wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00] Uh, of, of, of your life experience. And you need to condense it in just one point. What did you learn from life and what, what would you tell them? What is one point? What is the most important thing that you learned about life that you want to give them like a clue?
[SPEAKER_00] What is the truth? What is the truth? What is the truth? What is, what is your truth in life?
[SPEAKER_01] Let me think, let me think, let me put some thought on it. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it would be, do what makes you happy, regardless of someone else's opinion. Mm-hmm. And even the negative thoughts that you might have. Mm-hmm. Do what makes you happy. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I know it's pretty, probably simple, and a lot of people have said that. But I think, yeah, you have to be happier, or be really alive, you know? Do what makes you feel alive, makes you happy, regardless of your negative thoughts, regardless of what other people say. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_01] Mm-hmm. And regardless of the limitations, you know, because we sometimes stop because of the limitations, but they are not limited for a human being, I believe. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] Again, great choice. Great choice, man. You know what? I just want to congratulate you, and I want to thank you for, for being with me, and for helping me create this podcast episode.
[SPEAKER_00] I want to thank you for your patience, because only two of us know how much time we have lost trying to figure it out how this Anchor app works.
[SPEAKER_00] So, super grateful, and super thankful for this. And I just want to congratulate you also for being so, so positive, and for being so ambitious and driven, and for having this, this need and this thirst inside of yourself to succeed, and to also inspire others around you,
[SPEAKER_00] with your actions to do the same things. And if you know, there are only two needs of the Spirit, of our Spirit in life. And those two needs are growth and service. And you are my man working on both of them.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you are constantly growing, and you are always finding ways to serve others. So, I just want to congratulate you on that.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you very much, Vinko. It's an honor to be part of LUT podcast. And I enjoyed very much being interviewed by you. I think your, your questions were right on point, man.
[SPEAKER_01] Thank you very much, thank you very much, Vinko. They moved a lot of my thoughts and feelings. And I hope that what I share with you can benefit the audience, even just a little bit, you know.
[SPEAKER_01] Make, help them make a small change in their lives. And you know that you can count on me, man. If I can help you with anything else, just hit me up, and I'll be there. All right? So,