Ivona_NaMjesnik is in front of me. Thank you for accepting my call. Thank you for calling me. How are you, Ivona? I am very good. I will not lie, I'm a bit nervous, but I'm always nervous. Really? Yeah, just a little bit though. So how do you deal a bit nervousness?
I acknowledge it. I admit that the nervousness is there and I always try to ask what type of message does this feeling have? And in this situation, it just means that it's something that I care about. So it's a good feeling.
So you know, I was, as we were talking just earlier, I was a part of Toastmasters International. It's a public speaking and leadership organization that develops leaders and public speakers.
And I was going there for three years and I learned a lot. I went to do some challenges, competitions. And I was having one talk in front of 400 people. That was my biggest presentation.
And aside of all the knowledge, tips, tricks and everything that I got from Toastmasters, one of the best tips that I got was when you go out on the stage, you just go strongly from your body.
You let your voice, you let your voice, you move on the stage, just that you feel your body. And then if, because when you are afraid, then you shrink, your voice becomes small. And if you do it just at the beginning, then it helps.
It's such a good point. One of the things that I learned when I was doing train the trainers conferences, and I know that we mentioned that a couple of minutes ago.
It's actually when you go in front of the people, you go there to be fully present, and it's okay to be fully present and it's okay. And it's actually something that it's supposed to be that your body reflects that you stand up straight, you are in the moment.
You're not shying away from being there with them and transferring any type of knowledge or message that you do have.
So, I also prepared some questions for you.
Awesome.
So, we have some things to talk about. And the questions that I prepared, and we exchanged some questions between us, it's a very, what is the word, funny, or it's a coincidence that it happens that we had some similar ideas. And one of the most important
and the most interesting question for me, I think that I never really answered it to myself, I tried to Google it, I tried to ask other people, but I still think that I'm not satisfied with the answer.
And the question is, I'm not going to ask myself, I'm not going to ask you, who are you, but I'm asking for a human being, for everybody. And the question is, who am I? Who am I? So it's a question about identity. Who am I without my job, without my career?
Who am I without my partner, without my friends' interests, school, college, whatever, that is attached to you? Who am I?
Well, do you want me to answer first, who am I, without all of those roles? Or do you want me to discuss?
No, I will just give you one of your quotes before you start. And I want you to answer in general terms, generically, not who are you as Ivona, but who am I, who are we as a human being. So you said, what is between us and our results are actually steps towards immersing ourselves in that new person, in that new role.
Between us and results are steps of immersing ourselves into that new person. Let's start to unpack this, who am I?
I think that sometimes we underestimate the power that lies in becoming this new person. We always expect that there is this finished product that we are moving to reach. And that, you know, there is almost this, this force of, at that moment, when I reach that situation, or when I reach that goal, I will be able to acknowledge so fully.
That I became XYZ. But in reality, what really makes the difference are those steps that you take when you are becoming that new person, when you are becoming whoever you envision to be.
Because it is that type of bravery, it is that type of movement, literally movement, and there is so much power in moving gently, in moving compassionately, in moving presently while experiencing all of it and not shying away from it, kind of gives us the power to become whoever we want to be. Does that make sense?
It makes sense. It makes sense. Maybe we can make more sense.
Yeah.
Who am I?
Can I tell you something? And I'm sorry to interrupt, but one of the things I feel strongly about, I have been working on myself for the past, in one way or the other, I think, seven or eight years, maybe a little bit more, you know, like, programs, education, psychotherapy, coaching, all of this stuff, you name it.
I've probably tried it. And one of the things that I learned is, people think they know themselves, because they have a lot of experience with themselves.
And that's simply not true.
You spent a lot of time with yourself.
Oh, yeah.
But that doesn't mean that you know yourself.
Exactly.
Is it?
I think, one of the ways to get better at knowing ourselves is to keep asking ourselves better and better questions.
One of the things that I'm working on with my clients is, they tell me, oh, I already know this stuff, or I already heard this.
I'm like, okay, yes, but are you living the result that you want to be living?
They're like, well, no.
Mmm.
But then you actually don't know it.
You heard about it, but you haven't implemented it.
It's not a real change.
Yeah.
Exactly.
So, we will stay with this question, who am I?
Mm-hmm.
So, my daughter is nine months old right now.
And I'm thinking about this, who is she genetically?
Mm-hmm.
What will she become because of my parenting style?
Because of the parenting style of my wife?
What is she becoming, will become, because of the surroundings?
Mm-hmm.
And her reaction to everything.
Uh, what is the temperament?
Mm-hmm.
What is the character?
What are all those things in identity?
How the person is formed?
Mm-hmm.
Well, we can think about identity in several different ways.
And I remember when I came to my mentor at one point when I was submitting for my graduate thesis,
and I was like, I want to do a thesis that's about identity and entrepreneurship.
And I want to connect the two.
And she's like, okay, what is identity?
How you're going to define it?
How you're going to measure it?
What is going to be in the questionnaire?
I was like, oh, okay.
Now we have a lot of loaded questions.
And then I started looking into things and I noticed that there's so many different ways that we can actually define identity.
We can say, and that's one of the theories.
It says, hey, identity is a set of characteristics and behaviors and expressions that a person or a group has.
Awesome.
And then there is this other theory that says, well, yeah, but it's also about social belonging and which groups do you kind of go with or get along with.
So it's about interchange between those groups.
Oh, awesome.
Then there is the third theory, which says, well, it can be about your past and the way that your past shaped you.
And it can be about the present, which is who am I and how do I experience myself at this moment.
But then there is also about the future.
So who exactly am I becoming?
And then it can be about the place and the physical, literal moment that we are now.
So am I different if I'm in New York or if I'm in a desert or if I'm from a small village in Croatia?
And then you kind of start to understand it's complicated and it's complex.
And that's where the beauty is.
I remembered one of your writings.
You said that you are curious about curiosity.
And I can see right now why I'm very similar.
Very similar.
So if we talk about who am I, about identity, as I'm a really hobbyist, also philosopher, but also psychologist.
I do it as a hobby.
I like it.
I have the interest in it.
So when we are talking about this, who am I?
And people tend to tell me, authors or people around me, that self-awareness is one of the most important things in life.
Because if you are more self-aware, you will have better quality of life, you can get along better with yourself and the people around you.
You will know your faults, you will know your strengths and things like that.
So when we are talking about those things, about identity and who am I, how are we going to connect it with self-awareness?
So how, do you have some techniques, tools that you use to become more self-aware than you were 10 years ago?
For sure.
How to be more self-aware when this is a peeling the onion type of question, who am I?
I will tell you an anecdote first.
So I was back home maybe two or three years ago or something like that.
And I was with my mom shopping for, I don't know, detergents or something.
And at one point we met my professor from high school.
And she looked at me and she was like up and down.
She's like, you're different.
And it was in that moment, like that surprise that got me really thinking, yes, I am different, but I'm not working on myself to stay the same.
And this is where I believe self-awareness comes in.
It's about, first of all, in my experience and in the experience of my clients, it's about slowing down.
We cannot change something that we are not able to recognize or something that we feel extreme resistance towards.
We need to allow for change to happen.
I feel that when we are becoming somebody other than who we are, so we are making different choices and we want to create those different experiences.
It's not about becoming more of something.
We want to be more beautiful, more smart, more educated, more worthy.
It's usually about becoming less, about losing the expectations of other people, about losing some societal norms or losing whatever we thought we were supposed to be doing at a given moment.
Or losing our ideal perfection or our ideal version or how we are supposed to be.
I think that is where self-awareness comes in.
I already am enough.
I already am beautiful, smart, educated.
All of those things.
We will come to that question later.
I have one question in my mind right now, but we will postpone it.
Can you give to the audience some of the techniques or tools that you can use to improve your self-awareness?
I know this is going to sound like such a cliche, but slowing down or even better stopping for a moment.
I love the technique of boxed breathing.
I don't know, have you ever heard about it?
Yes.
Maybe somebody from the audience hasn't, so I will kind of summarize it very quickly.
It is essentially when we breathe in for four seconds and then we stop for four seconds and then we breathe out for four seconds and then stop for four seconds and we repeat the process.
And what happens in that process is that we are able to isolate or even ignore some of our thoughts and we realize that we are more than the thoughts that are running in our mind.
That slowness really brings clarity.
People can also try with meditation.
Sometimes we can go with guided meditation.
It's a great start.
But I would also advise that or say that meditation doesn't have to be this cumbersome process that we are trying to get better at every day.
We can literally just be sitting on the floor or standing or sitting on a chair with our feet on the floor, focusing on our breathing and that's it.
Because even sometimes the guided meditation can become the distraction, you know.
I am also a huge fan of journaling.
Whenever I have a lot of confusion in my mind, I will just sit down.
I will write it out.
And in some cases, and this is the experience of people that I have been working with.
The block comes from thinking, well, how do I phrase this in a specific or certain way so that the other person or whoever is, quote unquote, supposed to read it better understands it.
But it's not about writing it for another human being.
It's about writing it for yourself.
So what would you write if you were writing to gain clarity, to allow yourself that everything that's currently filling you with anger or confusion or sadness or I mean, I literally sometimes cried over a piece of paper.
And that release coming from it's everything stays on the paper.
And that's beautiful.
So, yes, there are other techniques and we can find resolution or peace in them.
I'm always saying that meditation can be going for groceries and, you know, kind of shopping for cucumbers.
It doesn't have to be super complicated.
It can be running at 6pm when there are no mosquitoes and it can be swimming.
It can be, you know, whatever it is, but it is the mindfulness that we bring to the process that makes the experience cleansing for us.
Very good ideas.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
So, you said box printing, you said meditation, whether guided or unguided.
You said running, you said a lot of other interesting things, journaling also.
I journal for a long time.
I think that I started 2011.
So, it's 11 years at the moment.
But what I also included in my journaling is the habit of continually rereading what I wrote.
So, I learned about it, I'm not sure from who, but very, very long ago.
And what I do, I must confess, I don't do it that regularly anymore.
But whenever I have the need to do, I do it.
I reread my journals every week, every Sunday.
Whatever I wrote, if I wrote a few sentences, I reread them.
And I make a conclusion on Sunday.
Then, on the end of the month, I reread those Sundays and make another conclusion.
And when the end of the year comes, then I read everything as a book.
That is such a great idea.
And then, I say, okay, Winko, what are we going to do next year?
And, but this is a good technique because usually we do this only once a year.
It's a New Year's, and we have our resolutions.
But if you do it regularly, then you can change or tweak some things on time, not to postpone them.
But a good thing is when you read your journal from the last year in one bite in one week, for example, then some things tend to pop up on the surface.
And you say, hmm, this is repeating.
Let's see.
That is such a good idea.
When we are regularly tracking our thoughts and emotions associated with specific thoughts and situations, then we are able to identify, oh, look, it's interesting.
Whenever I'm living through a specific situation or whenever I am with a specific person or whenever X, Y, Z is happening, I get the same reaction.
I am repeating something.
The behavior is the same.
The feeling is the same.
And this is the self-awareness that you have been talking about and you keep asking me about.
This is the moment where, look, sometimes when we look at our year in reverse, we as humans beings, we tend to forget what caused specific feelings.
And we were like, well, it was fine.
And that's why people stay in unhappy relationships.
And that's why they don't change jobs.
Because at the end of the year, nothing is that bad.
We just have three glasses of champagne and we party it out.
But when you're tracking things, I sometimes feel that people don't want to do different things because they are more scared of succeeding than a failure.
Definitely.
Because failure is familiar to them or being average or fitting in.
So this is why.
Okay.
Let's go a little bit further.
Who am I?
We are still going around this question with a sub question of self-awareness.
So character, genetics.
I learned that nevertheless, so I work on myself for a very long time consciously.
I think that there are, there is a lot of people who work on themselves unconsciously.
Mm-hmm.
They become better.
Unconsciously.
They're maybe not going to psychotherapy.
They're maybe not doing coaching.
Mm-hmm.
They're going, having a coach.
They're not, I don't know, meditating, whatever.
But they are improving themselves.
And when we talk all about those things, I learned still that there is one part of me that
is still the same as a child I was when I was five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten years old.
Mm-hmm.
How are you going to explain that?
You know, we are changing.
Mm-hmm.
Our environment is changing.
Our locations are changing.
Mm-hmm.
Whatever.
Uh, we are growing, definitely.
Mm-hmm.
We are learning.
But somehow, I think, I see it in my daughter.
She's nine months old.
Mm-hmm.
But I see who she is already.
It doesn't matter what she will learn in life.
I know who she is right now.
And I feel about myself the same.
Mm-hmm.
I knew who I was when I was five, ten.
I'm still the same.
Mm-hmm.
I just changed on the, some tools, techniques, reactions.
But on the, in the core, I'm the same.
Do you think this is true?
Absolutely.
Um, this is part of, I would say, more of a philosophy rather than psychology.
But I feel that core is actually who we are.
I believe it was Eckhart Tolle who said that you are not your thoughts.
You are the observer of your thoughts.
And the irony lies in the fact, as soon as you recognize that, it kind of escapes you.
You know?
Like, you cannot say, oh, now I see this person underneath.
I can see my core.
No.
Like, whatever it is inside, and we can call it light, and we can call it soul, and we can call it purpose.
And, you know, like there are bold things and names out there.
But in the end, that's what drives you.
That's what kind of propels you forward.
And you can accept it, and you can allow it.
And the more that you accept and allow it, the more, and I will use this word that keeps on floating up in every conversation that I have, it's being more authentic.
What does that even mean?
Yes.
What does it mean?
I suppose that it means, when we talk about ego, my definition is, how I interpret it to myself is, all of those things that we put on ourselves to get along with the society.
Mm-hmm.
This is the ego.
And our authentic self is, is, is Ivana from five years old, or 10 years old.
Mm-hmm.
This, this means, so that you don't, that you are not afraid of what others will think.
That you don't try to fit in.
Mm-hmm.
That you don't want to hurt anybody, but you're not trying to fit in.
You just want to express yourself.
Mm-hmm.
Who you are.
In a way, I feel there is so much conditioning going on for every single human being on the planet, whether that's, be a good girl, or be a boy who doesn't cry, or be smart, or be a valuable member of the society, or whatever it is.
And parents, or caretakers, they don't say that because they want to F us up, to be very clear.
It's just that sometimes their best intentions are not necessarily how we want our life to play out.
You know, I think one of the best phases in life of a kid is, they're usually around two or three years old, they learn how to speak, I say something and the world responds, but they still don't have the filter of what's appropriate.
You know, like, oh, happy birthday, mom, you're one year older, are you going to get ugly now, or whatever it is, you know.
And I remember kids saying things like that, where they're not thinking about what they say, this is their truth.
And I'm not saying that we should be going through life offending people, but I'm saying that we should allow ourselves to, for that part within, to speak through us.
You know, like through all of the conditioning to, like, do you know how kids sometimes get very curious about, well, why does this work like this?
When are we going to get there? How much time is there left for XYZ? They keep asking questions, and they don't stop until they actually get the answer.
Daddy, why is the sky blue? Well, because blah, blah, blah. Okay, so when does, but daddy, the sky is not blue all the time.
And then another set of questions. And then eventually, most of the dads are going to get very upset and say, the sky is blue, because the sky is blue.
Because I say so. Because I say so. But what would happen if we allowed ourselves to be as curious as we were when we were kids?
I'm that curious, but I don't want to bother people with my questions. This is why I have a podcast.
Yes. So I can ask questions.
It's a channeled curiosity.
Yes, yes, yes. I have an alibi to ask questions.
So we were talking about who am I, identity, self-awareness. Maybe we will go a little bit further. And I will ask you, what is a mindset?
Is mindset somehow attached to identity? What is a mindset? Everybody is speaking about the mindset.
Yeah.
You need to have mindset like this, like that. You need to be strong. You need to be productive. You need to believe in yourself. You need that.
What is mindset?
Well.
And what is a growth mindset? If you're familiar with the term.
Yeah. Yes, I am. It was one of the first things that we learned when I was in ISEC, the global organization for student exchange.
One of the first things they told us, people who want to grow, they need to have a growth mindset. And I remember having these little blop, blop, blop, blop, blop above my head thinking, well, what in the world is that?
And then I learned, okay, growth mindset is when you allow for change and when you are curious about how things can be different.
When you believe that you can change.
Yes. Yes.
You believe.
100%.
And one of the things that I strongly believe is that our perception of who we are is the filter that shapes our mindset.
So if we believe that, let's say, I'm a person who can only work nine to five for the rest of my life, and I am the best team player, and this is how my life will play out, then that's it for you.
Because you don't believe another possibility is out there.
So identity is driving mindset.
In a way.
Yeah.
I would say so.
I think that those filters and filters are very closely connected to identity.
Because if I say, I am a woman, I am 30 years old, I am creation.
I am a lesbian.
I am in a partnership.
I am earning XYZ.
I am a coach.
I am whatever it is, whatever label we put on ourselves.
We look for other things that will be the recognition of that.
What is possible for people that have those labels?
And our identity, and those different labels that we put on there, actually will shape that filter.
Oh, okay, I see what's happening there.
So a woman of my age, of my status, of my appearance, of my expression, of my education, these are the things that are possible for her.
So our mindset, yes, it definitely becomes shaped by who we are.
And then again, it can change if we are curious about other things outside of those labels.
I sometimes say to my clients, and I definitely said it to myself, you don't need 17 different proofs that different is possible.
You need only one.
So if I find one person who is, let's say, not working nine to five, but works three hours per week and earns, I don't know, bajillion of monies, then I'm going to believe that is possible because I have proof.
And let us not get confused, people love proof.
We can say, oh, I believe this is possible for me.
I know that I can do it.
And this is what startup founders do, you know, but it's so much easier when that person can say, you know what, I'm dropping from Harvard because Steve Jobs or whoever it was already did that.
So I know this is possible for me as well.
You know, like, it's a connection thing.
Oh, yeah.
You're absolutely right.
It's the famous four mile rule when the first person hit the four mile.
Yes.
No, one mile under the four minutes.
Sorry.
Yes.
Then suddenly, dozens, hundreds and thousands and millions of people did it after him.
Yeah.
So this is very interesting.
Uh, so it's a pity that I had a friend, unfortunately.
Uh, he passed away.
Uh, I was, uh, having a lot of talks with him about his mindset.
Uh, he was, uh, a person that you can see on him that he had a fixed mindset.
Mm-hmm.
He thought that he is as he is and then he cannot change.
And he didn't want to do it.
He didn't want to fight for it.
Mm-hmm.
This is who I am.
Accept me.
Mm-hmm.
He's, he was trying to accept himself, but he, he really thought that he was stuck.
Uh, with, with, uh, everything that he had.
Mm-hmm.
That he cannot change and, or improve.
But, uh, when we are talking about it.
Can I just add something?
Mm-hmm.
Um, one of the things that I hear people say so often, or better yet, make it two.
Is, the first one is, I am the way that I am.
You know, it's kind of take it or leave it situation.
And they don't believe that they can change.
And, at that point, I always love asking them, oh, okay.
But if a tree can change, does that make you less than a tree?
Everything is able to change in nature.
So are you.
And then, there's this other thing that people love saying, and it's extremely popular.
And that other thing is, you know what?
When X changes, then I will.
So, if I have more money, then I will invest in education.
Or, if, or when I have a partner, then I will be going to, I don't know, museums, or countryside,
or whatever it is.
We believe that something outside of us has greater power than something inside of us.
And we look for that safety somewhere else.
And that is the problem.
The safety always comes from within.
And yes, sometimes other people will not be able to reciprocate that.
But that doesn't mean that your desires, or your goals, or your dreams, or your expression is less worthy.
It just means that those people have a different outlook on life.
And this is an extremely important phrase.
Because we love thinking that, well, if somebody doesn't agree with me, then they are to blame.
We love looking for a guilty party.
And sometimes, it's just that the experience is different.
The magical part is, when you are who you are, you don't have to think about who likes it.
And what did you say to that person?
On which occasion?
And which role are you playing right now?
You just get to be yourself.
And then, in that magic, you invite the right people, and the right jobs, and the right opportunities, and whatever is "right for you".
Lately, I was saying often, relationships are one of the hottest things to do.
I'm not thinking only about relationships with a loved one, with your partner, but relationships in work environment, with friends.
And then, I know that what I think, what I say, will finally be presented in my behavior, and in my results.
And then, I bite my tongue, and I said, "Why am I saying this out loud? I need to stop saying this, that relationships are hard."
And then, relationships will be hard for me, if I say it.
So, with this question, how to improve yourself right now, or how can you improve yourself right now, let's try to talk a little bit about this process.
First, it comes the thought in our mind, then we say it, then it starts to become our behavior, and it is a cycle, we get emotion, we reaffirm this emotion, and we have, again, thought, behavior, and this never-ending cycle.
So, why is it important to track what you think and what you say?
I love saying, why would you choose that thought?
But I was not aware of this thought, I was not aware. I was saying it, relationships are hard.
I didn't even think how this would affect my relationships, if I say relationships are hard.
Okay, I was thinking that you are aware of that.
I was being aware that, because I see it around myself, that people get into conflicts a lot, you know.
Yeah.
When I say something, I can hurt you. When you say something, you can hurt me.
Then you have group dynamics, you have all kinds of flavors of relationship.
And I was believing this so, this is so, that relationships are hard, because I see it around myself.
But then I said, this is not going to be a truth for me.
I will stop saying it, I will stop thinking it, I will stop believing it.
Okay.
Well, I think the answer is twofold.
First, we go back to what we were already talking about, becoming aware of a thought that we are having.
And we can do that in a number of ways.
But then the other part of the puzzle comes in, where we, in that moment of stopping or slowing down at least,
where we do have to think and discuss with ourselves first, why am I choosing to think this?
People sometimes act like, it's almost like we are mad at a certain part of ourselves.
It's almost like, why am I doing this to myself?
But whatever we are thinking, it is serving us in one way or the other.
We learn to have a specific behavior, a mechanism, or at some points, it's almost automatic.
Because it helped us, it did something for us.
You know?
So attacking that part of ourselves is counterproductive.
That part of ourselves is going to have a tantrum every time when we try to shut it down or kill it or do something to it.
I was with a client yesterday and she has what we call an inner critic that wants her to be perfect.
I was like, okay, what does perfect mean?
What is that inner critic like?
And then she described the inner critic.
Okay.
Interesting.
How does the inner critic sound?
Does he have a voice of another person or your voice or maybe a person from a TV or what phrases is that inner critic using?
And then she slowed down.
Okay.
Then she answered.
Oh, interesting.
Well, what is the inner critic requesting?
What would that little person inside of you like you to do?
And then she said, "He just wants to be heard."
Oh, okay.
What is happening to the shape, the color, the texture of that inner critic?
It is so fascinating for me to see how we can literally visualize the resistance that is within us.
And it's not going to look the same for you or for me or for a third party.
It's going to be different for everyone.
Sometimes it will have a face.
Sometimes it will have a voice of your grandmother who was very strict or your teacher from third grade who never wanted you to erase anything on your paper.
Sometimes it will be very pointy or sharp and the texture will be like a little cactus inside of you.
Are you talking about the focusing technique?
I'm not sure actually how to call that.
I'm not sure is that the right phrase.
Are you familiar with the focusing technique?
No.
This is a technique that I learned when I was going through…
What you're describing is focusing technique.
Oh, awesome.
This is the exercise that I learned when I was doing an NLP practitioner education.
It is super helpful in so many situations.
When we are mad at someone.
When we are mad at ourselves.
When we are sad or disappointed.
Imagine or visualize the feeling.
And then how can I actually change the shape, the color, the texture, the voice, whatever it is that you can envision.
Because for that client, for example, she said, "Oh, when I listen to it, when I'm with it, it becomes smaller.
And the little pointy things, they soften.
They're very fluffy now.
And it just wants to be in a box in my stomach.
And it wants me to hear him out when he's whispering."
So, yes, she had an inner critic and obviously he's still there.
But he doesn't have the purpose that she originally thought he has.
Like the original thought was, "He's just trying to destroy my life.
That's why he's there."
No.
He wants to warn you.
He wants you to listen to a specific signal that he has.
And when we understand that whatever automatic that we have or a process that we have in place is there to serve some sort of purpose, then we can change it.
We cannot go against the grain in this situation.
If you are the ruler of all kindergartens in the world, what would you teach children?
I would love to say enoughness, but I'm not sure how to teach that.
You know, I would love every kid to know that they are enough in the way that they are.
You still don't know how to teach that.
I would love to think that I would know how to teach that to a grown-up.
But with a kid, maybe it is the same like with grown-ups, you know, letting them be.
In their fullest expression, whatever that means in a given moment.
But when the boy tells the girl, "Haha, you're fat," how is she going to be now?
I know that you had a wonderful guest, Gloria Peranich, who was talking about what is the phrase, I would say, conscious parenting or something of that sort in English.
I'm not sure how to translate that.
And I actually have a friend who is amazing at doing that.
And her kid at some point had a tantrum.
And you will probably see that with your own kid.
They tend to do that.
She likes to scream even now, especially in public.
It's going to be a fun couple of years for you.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But I remember that my friend told her kid, "It's okay, you can scream, but it doesn't mean that it will change mom's decision.
I'm going to be here to hear you out."
I was like, what?
What are you doing?
Like, I've never heard a parent say that.
And this is the part of, yes, it's okay.
You can do that.
It just doesn't change the circumstance.
But if it's painful for you or it makes you upset, then that's okay.
Let it out.
Yeah.
So when we are talking about improving ourselves.
I don't like that phrase.
What is better, personal growth, growing?
What do you like?
I love ability or willingness to explore ourselves.
To explore ourselves.
Yeah.
Because here's the thing.
Maybe that's not the best phrase either.
And I fully acknowledge that.
But when we are talking about improving ourselves, we are, again, putting ourselves on some sort of scale.
There's like a, it's almost like we're grading ourselves.
You know, like there is a comparison point.
Well, how do I know am I better if I don't have something outside to say that I am better?
You know, because that scale is not within us.
So it has to be willingness to first explore.
Maybe it's, maybe the phrase is, I love this English phrase that says, human being versus human doing.
You know?
So, no, it doesn't really sums up what you wanted to say.
I know where you were going at.
But I almost have a resistance towards humans thinking that they should be better in some sort of way.
So, in Croatian language, you were mentioning the term that can be translated into personal growth.
Osobni razvi, personal growth.
Is this the term also that you don't like?
Is it personal growth or personal development?
Personal growth.
Is it?
Is it development?
How do you translate it?
I don't know.
I love development.
The growth?
No.
The, the terminology that I...
What resonates with you?
I will not say hate, but I don't like is self-help.
Oh, yes.
This genre of self-help.
I don't know who invented this term.
And it's becoming the...
Both of those words are super worrying to me.
Which ones?
Self-help.
Self-help?
Yes.
Because in the 21st century, we constantly keep thinking that everything should be about self,
including the way that we grow.
Relational wounds cannot disappear in a self setting.
So, we need some sort of mirror or a connection point.
Like, it would be almost like saying, "Well, I'm a great girlfriend, but I'm not in a relationship."
How do you know?
There is no such thing.
You know?
So, saying that self-help is like, "Yes, I can get to a certain point, but after that point, I need to know how will I react when I am triggered."
And it is so easy to be Zen at the top of the mountain.
Or surrounded by other monks.
Yes.
But what happens when you are in a business setting, when you are in a meeting surrounded by 12 people who do not understand you?
What happens when your girlfriend or wife or best friend get angry over a silly thing that you cannot put into words, but you know it's important to you?
You don't know what's triggering, but something is triggering you.
What happens when something changes within the dynamic of your primary family?
Like, let's say, I can use my personal example.
My parents got divorced a year and a half ago.
I'm 30 years old.
They're like 54 and 55.
They got divorced now.
Yes, I am my own person, but it still changes the dynamic.
So, how do you react in those situations?
Can I know what is the trigger without actually being in that situation?
Absolutely not.
Okay.
Yeah, you're right.
Definitely.
You're right.
What term can I use?
Use whatever term you want.
I just wanted to kind of pinpoint.
What one?
What is the one that you like?
I love personal development.
Personal development?
Yeah.
Okay.
Self-exploration.
So, are you familiar with a guy called Sadhguru?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
So, he says, he was explaining to one guy what is yoga.
Mm-hmm.
And he said, yoga is not twisting and turning like leftover noodle.
Yoga means union, he says.
Mm-hmm.
But not union that you need to create a union.
It's a realization of everything is one thing.
Mm-hmm.
It's already there.
You just need to notice it.
Mm-hmm.
Yes.
That is it.
Yeah.
So, when you're talking about self-exploration, maybe we can connect it with this realization
that everything is a union.
Mm-hmm.
That everything is connected.
Maybe we just need to see something that we don't see.
Yes.
At the moment.
Yeah.
Maybe we just need to use something that we don't use at the moment.
Mm-hmm.
Maybe we have everything.
But we just need to notice it.
Mm-hmm.
I like to philosophize about, for example, this phone or this laptop.
everything was here 5,000 years ago.
Mm-hmm.
In the universe, on our planet, with those two hands and this mind, this brain.
everything was here that we can make this, but we didn't make it 5,000 years ago.
Mm-hmm.
We did it only recently.
Yeah.
So, maybe there is more, but we don't see it and we don't understand it.
We don't know how to use it.
Mm-hmm.
Absolutely.
One of the awesome things that I learned through self-exploration is that our brain
didn't change that much from prehistoric times.
It changed or evolved maybe 5%, like when we are talking about biology.
I was, like, amazed by that fact.
Because we humans love to believe, well, we have cars now and we have airplanes and we have
internet, which we use to look at funny memes of cats and things like that.
But in reality, our brains, which are the driving force of our reactions and the primary "place"
where our thoughts happen, it's practically the same.
Hardware is the same.
Maybe we need to improve or update the software.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, how are we going to do it?
Let's try to give, I always try to give practical tips and examples to the audience.
So, you were talking about techniques when we are talking about exploring ourselves,
becoming more self-aware.
We're talking about meditation.
We were talking about various types of meditation that we can do, about journaling,
breathing techniques like box breathing, and let's expand this list with more techniques
or tools of how we can explore ourselves and work on our personal development.
What still do you see?
Or that you use in your life or maybe you suggest to your clients?
I would say that one of the most underestimated things is being mindful of the content that
we consume with, especially with social media.
And you can look up your own Instagram statistics and see how many hours per day you spend scrolling
or, I don't know, what is the word on TikTok?
I guess the same, TikToking or whatever.
What type of content are you consuming there?
Sometimes people will say, "Well, I don't want to unfollow this person that I've known since I was 14 years old
because I am scared of hurting their feelings."
But in reality, how much do you have in common right now?
You can at least hide them.
You don't have to unfollow them, you know?
I think that first step or one of the steps can be extremely valuable because when we consciously decide what are we going to expose ourselves to,
then we can see what changes will occur, you know?
So, for example, I don't watch TV.
And people always tell me I live in a happy bubble.
Like, I am not unaware of how the world works,
but why would I consciously expose myself to XYZ media that is going to fill my mind with things that are out of my control?
So I have this rule.
If something bothers me, I will either stop worrying about it or I will do something about it.
And like 95% of the things, it just doesn't bother me that much, you know?
So, yeah, maybe it's about I'm not I'm not sure what is the correct answer for every single person that is listening.
But I can say that you can start by seeing, hey, am I following the accounts on social media that are fueling my sense of self and my values or they are fueling my insecurities?
If you're looking at pictures of, I don't know, Kim Kardashian and thinking, my body is so bad or I should be richer or I should be in a happier relationship.
Like, my brother is 26 years now.
And he's like, I thought I was going to be married by now.
Like, oh, OK, but you're not actually going out meeting people.
So I think that one of the things that people very often underestimate are the people that I actually they are surrounded with.
So who are the five people that you spend your time with?
How do you spend that time with them?
Are you arguing?
Are you negotiating?
Are you compromising yourself?
Are those people inviting you into something that is possible for you?
Are they inviting you to reconsider specific things?
Are they inviting you to explore yourself and life?
I love that phrase being invited into fullness, giving yourself grace.
Are those people.
What does it mean?
Being invited in the fullness.
Into your fullness.
Yeah.
Fullness.
How would you describe it?
What does it mean?
Can you give us a second example?
For me, yeah.
For me, it means not apologizing for the way that you behave, operate and feel in life.
You don't have to compromise parts of yourself.
You don't have to dim your light.
You know, like if you have an opinion about something, you're going to share it freely.
You are going to speak your truth, even if it's a little bit inconvenient.
You're not trying to manage other people emotions by suppressing your thoughts.
You are clear about voicing your boundaries.
Those people respect them.
It's a beautiful dynamic where you're not protecting people from the consequences of their actions.
You're responsible for yourself and the other person is too.
You know what I want to ask you right now is to work on yourself.
It's a long process.
It's a lifelong process.
It's hard to measure it.
The only person that can measure it are with ourselves.
So it's a subjective measure.
But if we feel better, if we feel that the quality of our life is better, then we are right.
That's why it's important to have a good measuring stick.
Yes, yes.
And we can use several techniques.
We can really work on ourselves diligently, continuously for years, for decades.
And sometimes I have this feeling sometimes that somehow it seems to me that I didn't change, that it's going, that it's too hard.
Mm-hmm.
That I think about it, write about it, try to implement it in my life.
And sometimes I see I just didn't do it.
I didn't transfer it into my behavior.
Yes.
So the question is, how can we truly, truly, truly transform ourselves?
How can we truly change our behavior?
Mm-hmm.
For example, I want to be more confident or I want to be more clear communicator.
I want to, but I still find myself to catch myself that I still don't communicate clearly.
I still don't.
And I'm working on it for several years.
Mm-hmm.
How to truly transform?
Well, in that question, I actually hear a little bit of perfectionism.
Truly.
Here.
Yes, I'm perfectionist 101.
I know it's because I was doing self-exploration.
Yeah.
And I know when I got, when I get over, when the perfection gets all over me, gets all
over me, so I can sense it and I can say, okay, stop.
Mm-hmm.
So how to truly transform?
There is no D answer.
It's a pity.
Yeah, it is.
It's not so good.
Mm-hmm.
Because that means that there is no secret recipe that anyone is hiding from you.
Because nobody has the recipe.
Exactly.
Mm-hmm.
You just go at it.
What would you do if you just wanted to make this path fun for you?
Can I say then that self-improvement or personal development, self-exploration, they are somehow
ruining our life, ruining our peace?
It's a bold, bold phrase that you just used.
Is it?
Yeah.
Can it ruin our life?
Yes, if we look.
Can it make it harder to live?
Yes, if we look at it like another thing on our to-do list, absolutely.
Like, I think that people can OD on pretty much anything.
It's not just the drugs or the alcohol or whatever.
It can be on PlayStation or it can be on personal growth.
There can be too much of everything.
And I feel that the point of personal growth or self-exploration is not to reach at a certain
destination.
It's about learning how to enjoy that path.
I feel that some of the most important questions that we have in life, they don't unfold in
a shape of an answer.
They unfold in a shape of a path.
Can you give us an example?
Absolutely.
Let's say, I don't want to use romantic relationships because that's, you know, like everybody uses
that.
So let's go with family and family dynamic.
So I will use my personal example again and say, when I was growing up, I used to describe
the relationship with my mom like, we're practically best friends.
Like we get along so well.
It was awesome.
And then when I grew up, I was like, maybe something's wrong with that.
Like my mom is supposed to be my mom.
She's not supposed to be my best friend.
And then we changed the dynamic because of my therapy books, coaching, et cetera, et cetera.
It was so hard.
It was one of the hardest things that I've ever, ever done.
The relationship we had before.
It doesn't mean that it was bad.
It just means that when I got to this level where I'm at now, and when I became a specific
thing that doesn't work for me, I decided to change it and invite her into that change.
But that doesn't mean that we still don't have the moments where I need to be very clear
about my boundaries, about my responses.
Like the other day she came, she doesn't live in Zagreb.
She lives in Yapaga where I grew up.
It's a very small village in Slavonia.
And she brought me an early birthday present.
She brought me red wallet, like red leather wallet.
And I looked at it and she told me why she bought it.
But my first thought was like, it's red.
It's like very, very, very red, red wallet.
And personally, I would never buy something like that for myself ever.
It's just not my style.
But she told me, you know what?
I was reading this book about how red invites money.
And I was like, you know what?
Like if there's anything that I want my daughter to have to invite money, then it's a red wallet.
I was like, this is so sweet.
This is awesome.
Thank you.
So yeah, it's not my personal preference, but that story matters more than my personal preference.
Do you still have it?
Yes, absolutely.
I wear it everywhere.
Okay.
So you were mentioning boundaries.
And I heard, I hear this word often lately.
And this is a thing that I didn't install in my life so far, or I didn't think about it consciously.
Why do we need boundaries?
I suppose that I have boundaries in my life, that I put them to other people also.
Everybody has boundaries.
The first one, the one that we underestimate and kind of take for granted is our skin.
It's a literal physical boundary.
This is how I like my skin is not your skin.
We know that we are different from each other.
But where it gets tricky is how do we communicate boundaries that are not so obvious?
And what is a healthy boundary?
How do we know that we have a healthy boundary?
We are talking about mental emotional boundaries.
Okay.
How do we know that?
For example, someone is teasing you.
Someone is making fun of you.
But in a masculine environment, that could be normal.
And you can tease back.
And that person can tease you back again.
It can go back and forth.
And at the moment, at one moment, one person will say, you'll lose it and start yelling or screaming or arguing with the other person.
And this is not a good way, I suppose, to set boundaries by yelling and fighting.
Maybe we can tell to the other person with words, with clear words, that this is just too far for us.
But what can happen in a male environment is that they start to tease you even more when you show your weakness.
Don't be a sissy.
Yes.
When you show your weakness.
Well, in the specific example that you use, I would love to say, well, does this go against your personal values?
You know, because boundaries are very, like, boundary should be coming from a sense of self.
Like, what is important to me?
What I'm trying to protect?
What is my peace?
What is that center that really makes it worthy to kind of have - I'm not sure what would be the English word for that - but almost like a filter.
How do you say those things that you have in the kitchen that you use to drain spaghetti or pasta in general?
I have no idea what is the word, but you know what I'm referring to.
Yes, it's the part of the word.
Imagine it in your mind.
Yes, please.
So it's that type of filter that, you know, some things will go through, but some things won't.
An unhealthy boundary would be having either no visible distinction between where you are and where the other person is.
So it's almost like, imagine it like a line in the sand that any wave that comes, like, it will just disappear.
And the other version of that, but it has the same sources if you have walls build up too high so that nothing can come in.
So that kind of middle road is where we can be connected both to ourselves and the other person at the same time.
That's how we know the boundary is healthy.
One more way to know if a boundary is healthy is when exactly am I setting it.
In your example, if the other person is already so upset and starts yelling and gets very angry and that means that the boundary should have been set way before.
Yes, but if the person expressed the boundary, expressed himself, yeah, maybe the teasing will start to become even more aggressive.
And then this will finish.
I understand what you're trying to say, but here's the thing, us constantly being nice people, it's also an attempt in manipulating others.
Okay.
You know, like, if we are trying to be in a way that we expect a certain reaction, it doesn't matter if we're good or bad, it's still manipulation.
How so?
We're trying to get something out of another person.
We are trying to get them to like us.
We are trying to get accepted.
We are trying to be XYZ, whatever it is.
And that's one of the hardest things to accept that us constantly being nice and good and polite and never saying anything about what we need and what we want and what we love.
Yes, that is a form of manipulation.
How to balance this dance?
So it's really a dance.
You're trying not to stand on some other person's feet.
The other person is also trying that.
And sometimes we did it.
We do it.
How to find that balance?
We need to, I suppose, that the only answer is that we need to try and we need to experiment.
Sometimes we will step on that foot.
And sometimes we will see that communication and the relationship is good.
And we just learn.
It's about practicing.
What do you say to someone who is maybe a little bit too timid in relationships, very careful not to insult other person, even holding himself or herself back in relationships?
Where does it come from?
That's the first thing I would say.
Where did you pick up on that?
Maybe that person was trying to not insult someone else in her life.
But look, it's very normal that when we are meeting new people, there is almost like this testing it out phase, you know, like almost like testing the water when we are getting into the sea.
And we are trying to figure out, well, does it make sense to actually hang out with this person or even become something more or whatever it is.
And we don't, we shouldn't be underestimating that part of the process.
It's sometimes it's our gut feeling telling us, yes, this is safe for us.
This is okay for us.
Sometimes it will be not really.
But then if after figuring out that it is safe, we still hold back and we still try to navigate the experience through completely suppressing ourselves because of a fear of another human's reaction, then we need to ask ourselves, where did I pick up on this?
Where did I learn this?
What exactly am I afraid of?
What exactly am I afraid to lose or to gain or what type of impression I don't want to make?
Like, sometimes, very often, actually 99% of the cases, people actually don't want to do something, not because of the action, but because of what they think it will mean about them.
You know, like, oh, if I set a boundary, then I will be clingy or I will be I will be someone who asks for too much or I will show that I am weak or I will be too vulnerable.
And if I'm vulnerable, then I am not worthy or I'm complicated and nobody can deal with me and blah, blah, blah.
You know, like, there's like a blank line and you can fill in what feels right.
But we attribute specific meanings to things.
And that's why we don't do those things.
And then in the exploration of where we are setting the boundary, the only center that we should going back to is ourselves.
Like, how do I actually feel about this?
And if we don't say it, then yes, we are trying to manage what other people think about us and we are not allowing ourselves to be fully accepted, but we are actually denying the opportunity to be fully accepted because we are not sharing it.
You know, yes, there is vulnerability in fully saying who we are.
Absolutely.
But without that vulnerability, we can't actually be accepted.
Do you think that it comes more naturally to the extroverts than to the introverts?
I don't think it has anything to do with that.
No.
Okay.
I think being one way or the other is just about how you quote unquote charge your batteries.
Well, I don't really like the phrase charging batteries.
As you can see, I have a lot of aversion towards specific phrases.
But let's say if we are using that phrase, charging our batteries.
Introverts, they charge their batteries alone.
Like, it doesn't have anything to do with their communication style.
You know?
Yes, they are usually quieter and calmer and don't tend to communicate a lot with people, etc., etc.
And this is just me being like generalist about it.
But the main difference is that extroverts, they need other people to charge their batteries.
You know?
So you can be extremely good communicator and still be introvert.
And still express yourself fully.
Absolutely.
And be vulnerable.
Yes.
While expressing yourself.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's say a few words about you.
I think usually it's at the beginning, but I purposely leave it for the later part of the conversation.
So, who is Ivona?
But really right now who is Ivona?
Not with those philosophical things that we started with.
Okay.
Let's do facts first and then see where we go next.
I am a coach for overachievers.
Coach for overachievers.
Okay.
For women who love to describe themselves as overachievers.
And they kind of tend to be good girls and then good wives and then good mothers.
And they are also usually in a very high position.
So they're managers or directors or super successful entrepreneurs.
And they kind of identify themselves through that.
And we work together on uncovering where does that come from?
And what would happen if I wasn't achieving all of the time?
Wow.
That's a great idea.
What would person be if he or she stops achieving so much?
Yeah.
What happens?
Who are you when you are not quote unquote rewards?
And reward can be anything.
It can be a title.
It can be a salary.
It can be a compliment that you constantly keep getting.
Like one of my clients actually told me that she loves hearing how are you managing it all?
You know?
Like it's…
You're a super woman.
Yeah.
Are you?
You know?
What happens when we take that away?
And what usually…
You're not enough.
Mm-hmm.
Usually there is this huge fear of abandonment or other people expectations or self-put pressure
to be a specific way.
You know?
But what happens if you allow yourself to be, to actually be a human being, not human doing?
But this is a regular story of all the high performers in all fields of life.
Mm-hmm.
Whether it's business, sports, art, whatever.
Usually what happens, people try to feed themselves with the material possessions,
with the success, with the validation of others.
Mm-hmm.
And at one moment they see that it's not enough.
And that how much they accomplish, no matter how much they accomplish in life,
that they will never be enough or that it will never be enough to get as love, as respect,
as validation, whatever it is.
Mm-hmm.
So what is the bypass or what is the shortcut?
Is it the gratitude?
Mm-hmm.
Is it something else?
What can, what can a person do to, to find that, I suppose that the gratitude would bring
you back to the center, to the peace, to this moment, that you will not need validation from
outside of yourself?
Is it enoughness?
Honestly, I don't know, I don't know a better bypass than the program that I created because,
and I'm not saying this because, oh, this is the best for every single person out there.
I honestly believe it's the best thing that I created, but it's not necessarily a match for
everyone.
However, in the program, we go through so many things that you just mentioned.
We go, the first, we have three topics that we are covering.
The first one is self-sabotage and getting to know yourself, kind of rediscovering your
fullness and your wholeness and what would that mean?
And then we go into being open to accepting everything, like every good thing that can happen
when you lose those expectations of others and the pressure that you keep putting on yourself.
And then we go into, oh, the easy part, the plan, forgetting something, you know, because
in reality, the change happens throughout the process.
Like, think of this as learning a new language.
You know, when you start speaking it, you are, you know, it's a little bit sucky and I need
time to figure out which word to use and I'm not sure about the grammar, but you keep drilling
and you keep learning and you keep communicating even if you don't get the right phrase every
single time, you know, but it's a process.
So you'll give yourself grace through it.
And one of the things that I love saying is your iPhone needs time to be updated.
So do you.
Like, you have been operating on the same software for like, what, 25, 30, 35, 40 years.
And then you expect that the change is going to happen overnight.
Oh, I had an amazing coaching session.
I read this book.
It was a blast.
Now I know everything.
Elon Musk, please help us.
Because I was, I fantasize about this, that one day we will go to the internet and I want
to learn to fly a plane, $1,000.
Okay.
Oh, I know how to fly a plane.
That would be very good.
Maybe, maybe it will not be good.
I want to learn karate.
Okay.
Pinko knows karate.
Or some other skills or some other updates.
So something is happening in our body, in our mind with time day by day, iteration by iteration.
And somehow when I, when I go, I don't know, to Brazilian Jiu Jitsu practice for 10 years,
somehow I know it after 10 years.
But how to speed up this process?
And would it be even a good thing to speed?
I was about to ask the same thing.
Like, yes, there are some ways to kind of shorten the process from, let's say, 10 years to
five months.
Or three years to two months.
Ayahuasca.
Yes.
But in some cases, the reward is in the process.
You know, because that's how we learn to be gentle and patient with ourselves.
And those are two very underestimated skills.
Yes.
Who loves to be patient?
Yeah.
I'm still learning.
What is coaching?
Giving yourself a tool in your toolbox for better managing the experiences that you have.
Giving yourself.
Mm-hmm.
So if you're a coach and I'm a coachee.
Then it's giving, then it's giving it to another person.
You know?
Mm-hmm.
Like, it's giving another human being a tool in their toolbox for when they want to
manage certain experience, certain actions, certain feeling.
So how does one coaching session looks like, for example?
Mm-hmm.
Can you describe it to people?
Well, yes I can.
But the answer is very simple.
I work with clients on two things.
One is catching their thoughts.
And the other one is redirecting them if they're not serving them.
Mm-hmm.
And I know that sounds very straightforward, but here's the thing.
A lot of people don't know what they're thinking.
And as a consequence, they have no idea what they're saying.
Yeah.
They don't know what they're thinking because they didn't say it out loud.
And somebody didn't pinpoint to them.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
So we all put up a dialogue.
Mm-hmm.
It's almost like, I sometimes have, when a client is getting into the emotion of things,
and then I literally stop her like, "Oh, did we catch that?
Did you hear what you just said?"
It's like, "Oh, I had no clue.
What did I say?"
Mm-hmm.
It's my job to notice that.
I was like, "Well, this is an interesting thought."
And then I love saying, "How is this thought serving you?
Mm-hmm.
Why are you choosing it?
Can you tell me five or 10 or 30 better thoughts that would serve you better?"
You know?
And sometimes, when we identify a thought, it's not about changing the thought, but it's also
about changing the way that we connect it to our body.
So let's say that a client came to me and said, and this actually happened, said, "I'm
not sure how to accept my body.
I'm not sure."
In Croatian, we say, "Pri grliti."
How can I, quote unquote, hug myself into something?
Mm-hmm.
And I'm like, "Okay, what does that mean for you?
How would that feel?
How would it feel?
How would you know that you fully accepted yourself?"
And sometimes we expect that this is going to be this great big moment where I know that
I fully accepted myself.
I kind of hugged myself out.
Then I ask her, "If I ask you right now to sit on the floor and hug yourself, what would
happen?"
Tears.
Because it is that type of physical reaction.
Mm-hmm.
Like, can you do that physically?
There are other exercises that sound equally simple but are so loaded with emotion.
When we have, let's say, a situation when we know that something that's hurting us has
been extremely painful because it's loaded with an emotion that we are carrying since we
were a child but we keep pushing it out.
Like, "I don't want to feel this.
I don't want to do this."
And then we keep screaming at ourselves.
Let's say, "Well, imagine yourself as a three-year-old or five-year-old," or better
yet, if they have a picture of themselves when they were a kid, can you scream at this
person?
So you were living in London until recently.
Yeah.
And coaching is somewhat a new term.
Mm-hmm.
A new thing.
And usually people were going to psychotherapists before.
Mm-hmm.
They go even right now, but coaching is a new field.
I'm not sure how old is it, but especially if we are talking about the terms, let me ask
you, how do you like the term of life coaching?
Mm-hmm.
Because in my experience, this term has a stigma.
When people heard about it, hear it, they have some kind of pushback, something like that.
where does life coaching go?
Where does psychotherapy go?
Mm-hmm.
Or maybe some other things like mentoring or what is the difference, you know, between all
of those things?
Mm-hmm.
Well, I would say both are equally valuable, but are for different types of situations, problems,
and maybe even people depending on their inner state.
I had people who applied to work with me, and I told them very honestly, "I don't think
I'm a match for you.
I think that you need to see a therapist first."
Because therapy is more oriented towards understanding the now, being in the process, putting the past
in their rightful boxes, and then that will inspire action that will make the change.
And that is a beautiful process, and I have been in it for four and a half years now.
I still have things that I'm working on in therapy.
But coaching is very heavily oriented towards action.
Mm-hmm.
It's like coaches here to coach you on the coachable emotions, and not every emotion is coachable.
Not every situation is coachable if you don't allow it.
And if you haven't, if you're not self-aware enough, and that in this specific sentence means
if you're not open enough, then the change will not happen.
You will have extreme resentment towards that.
You will not be able to implement something.
So coaching is not for everyone.
I don't use labels.
I've never said I'm a life coach or a business coach, or I don't...
Just say coach.
I just say coach.
If Michael Jordan had a coach, who am I not to have one?
Yes.
And I want to add something.
People ask, "Well, I can do this alone."
I'm like, "Yes, absolutely."
Like 90% of the people who have a coach...
Well, this is a made up percentage, but in my experience working with my clients, they would
probably make the same or similar change if they have been at it on their own.
But you know what changes?
It's the timeline that would take them to make that change.
So, in every life situation, we have this decision that we are making.
Am I paying for something with my time, with my energy, or with my money?
Money is the best choice.
Yes.
Just paid.
Yes, exactly.
I have one last question for you.
Based on your perception, is it a good word, or perspective?
What is the ultimate goal in life for you?
Peace.
Acceptance.
Fullness.
That fullness that we have been talking about earlier.
Yeah.
I would say that too.
Enoughness?
Enoughness.
Yeah.
Unity?
Mm-hmm.
What is the ultimate goal in life for humans as a species?
Ooh.
Not just as an individual.
Mm-hmm.
What is the ultimate goal?
I think about those crazy things, you know?
Because I like anthropology, also as a hobby.
Mm-hmm.
And I see our civilization and like a colony of ants.
I watched some documentary.
It says that each individual ant doesn't know its purpose or the bigger purpose of the colony,
but he knows his task.
Mm-hmm.
But this intelligence of the colony knows its purpose.
So what is the purpose of the human race?
What are we trying to accomplish?
Mm-hmm.
Why are we building Facebook?
Why are we, I don't know, trying to get to Mars?
Mm-hmm.
What are we doing?
I'm not sure why, but I think that maybe the driving force is curiosity, which gets manifested
in so many different ways for so many different people.
What would you say, what are we trying to accomplish?
Do you think that we have a goal that we are striving towards that we are not aware of it?
As a species?
Yes.
Like one goal?
I don't think so.
Or not, I don't, not that I'm aware of.
I have a deep feeling that we have.
Yeah?
Yeah.
What do you think it is?
We are, I think that we are trying to become one.
Really?
Yeah.
With each other or with nature or?
Because we are, everything that we are doing regarding the development of the technology,
we are trying to communicate better.
Mm-hmm.
We are trying to travel faster to the other part of the world to connect, to cooperate, to become one.
It's an interesting thought.
I would love to believe it's true.
We want this better bandwidth.
Mm-hmm.
I don't want to communicate with you.
I want to know what you're feeling and what you're thinking at the moment.
Why do I need to say a word?
Mm-hmm.
No.
I think that we want to connect.
I think.
Become one.
For some reason, this reminded me of a quote.
I love quotes, by the way.
That says, you go out there to find yourself, only to come back and find you waiting.
Find your waiting?
Find you waiting.
Like, you have already been there.
Wow.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
So, patience.
Yeah.
Patience, little one.
Patience, we wait.
Ivona, thank you so much.
Thank you, Vinco.
For being my guest.
I know that people will learn a lot from you and from our conversation.
I wish you all the best in your future work and life.
Thank you.
And maybe we will repeat one day again.
Yes.
Guys and girls, that's all for today from a new studio with some technical problems that
you will not see.
Let's see each other again in two weeks.
Bye.