Kyriljo,So,How much of your network do you have in crypto?
So now it's 99.9% but it was not always like that so I'll give you my personal story so basically when the war started in Ukraine back in the early 2022 I had real estate and something in the bank and obviously crypto but then we need to we needed to go with my family like what we were having just
grabbing the documents and the kids jumping in the car and leaving the country the whole situation was crazy obviously banks were not working ATMs were not working gas stations was not working because the people were fleeing out of the country and through the customs you cannot bring more than 10 000 euros always with you so that's where the crypto demonstrated the new use case not just a charity when you can send any money to everyone
immediately without any borders document commissions etc but you are you are free to move your capital
you can protect against inflation so basically invest in this capital and get the profits out of it
and also be able to send your transactions anywhere at any time without any complex procedures so it's actually
my personal experience that moved me to the 100 percent in crypto so unbelievable so 99.9 percent yeah okay
so before we proceed my name is vinco mihaljević and this is lud so we explore human development on both
an individual and societal level so today we have uh kirillio kumjakov uh who is a regional head for
central and eastern europe and central asia as what i know maybe it's not official but you told me uh
even even africa right now so it's it's unbelievable congratulations uh for binance so yeah thanks for
having me yeah so what we'll do today we'll explore why cryptocurrencies are compared to digital gold
uh the rise of central bank digital currencies and crypto's role in financial innovation let me say it
like that okay so uh so can you explain why cryptocurrencies are sometimes compared to
digital gold and how does this affect their perception uh as an investment asset yeah so basically uh bitcoin
is the best ever asset class created by the humanity in terms of the growth of the price of it
since first created uh back in like 13 years ago it's now more than 10 million percent
growth in terms of the bitcoin price versus it was what it was before
however uh it's uh has some risks too because the crypto in general and bitcoin in particular is
quite a new assets class it's not that big and liquidity is not that high as the traditional
financial markets like forex like stocks like bonds like gold that's why it's quite volatile so that's why
you can get a high profits but you can also have a higher risks when the
prices are going down so this young industry uh is not that big in terms of the liquidity and that's why
any industry news enforcement actions regulatory changes can significantly influence the price
so the advice for the ones who are just starting in crypto is not to go all in but just invest a little
bit the amount that you are okay to lose easily and then as you go along and get more experience knowledge
and uh being on the both positive and negative sides of things continue investing more so of course
the the the big uh opportunities but also the risks are high so yeah that's the situation so let us go
back to the to the beginning uh so you were previously you had roles in uh traditional uh financial system
ecosystems like like banks like commercial banks uh not the government governmental or central banks so
commercial banks yeah then was it for 10 years or even longer yeah it was a big chunk of time i suppose
from my research and uh you moved after that in in fintech yeah so you have you have the the experience of both
traditional uh financial systems and uh right now someone in between and the new one uh that that we are
looking uh towards uh in the future so can you maybe maybe you're one of the best people to talk about that
then uh can you do a simple breakdown i know it's very hard to do so but see simple breakdown of what do you
think that money is it's a very philosophical question basically but uh let them to put it simple money
is the result of the value that person is created so the value you create for the society the value you
create for the humankind is basically translated into the money that is given back to you for the value you
deliver but that's uh that's very tricky question so that uh to put it short way that how i would answer
okay okay so what do you think that crypto or blockchain is is bringing to the to the scene
where where is the innovation here so if we are thinking about the money i suppose that in 1971
nixon removed uh us dollar from the gold standard this was one of the most disruptive uh points in in
history for the money well was it not that much not that much we do not feel it yet right you think
that we don't feel it yet well dollar still remains like a more the most stable most reliable currency in
in the world isn't it well still definitely but all other currencies so let let us call them fiat yeah
currencies uh they're all attached even right now to to the dollar so let me explain to the to the
people watching you can correct correct me if i'm wrong so for every third party interactions for example
if ukraine is selling something to to turkey the dollar is used okay so they are not using the the local
currencies the national currencies but the dollar is uh is is is the currency that is that was using this
was being used in those in those transactions not necessarily right so that's the subject of the
agreement between the countries but provided that every country wants to trade in their own currency
and would never agree to something else that's why dollar became the like a global um global currency
for the operating operations and the transactions between the countries and that's where the the power
of the dollar is coming from yeah of course we have uh big political powers and the military powers at
the moment like china uh like russia talking about moving away from the dollar or countries in the
middle east as well so there are a lot of geopolitical instabilities at the moment uh but let me proceed
on on this thought of of of money uh and uh what crypto then uh innovates here so if we have
fiat currencies and before they were uh tied to to the gold so us dollar was tied to the gold
uh after 1971 so you had this possibility to to print money so whatever you think of when i
say the term print money so it's not really printing but it's typing like yeah two of us were typing just
before it's much easier to then than to actually print it yes that's right so uh
what what what is really that for example crypto or especially uh bitcoin innovating here when
you're comparing comparing it uh to the traditional fiat currencies or us dollar for example yeah
i thought you will you will ask uh that the dollar was backed by gold what is bitcoin backed by so
so this is a good question as well so bitcoin is backed by massimatics right and this is something
you cannot uh adopt so basically all the uh all the fiat currency traditional currency they are deflationary
right so the governments are printing more and more money every day inflationary inflationary yeah oh sorry i said
deflationary inflationary yeah but the but the bitcoin supply is finite so there is basically just 21
million bitcoins and this is never going to be more and how many satoshis yeah so you can then
multiply by 100 000 and that's going to be the number of the satoshi so basically that that's that's the power of the bitcoin is just a finite supply of the first
and the most reliable crypto assets and it's fully transparent there is a lot of the visibility and
there is a lot of the use cases for the bitcoin so basically that's the currency that cannot be
manipulated by any government and that's how it gets its power and that's why it's growing so
so fast so it basically gives the people and to other governments the freedom the freedom of money they
do not need to be politically economically or in any other way connected to the other bigger countries or
their own government to transact and be free and that's actually what the main mission of binance is
to achieve and give the people the freedom of money and that's in everything that we do this mission
yeah so from what i understood when i was learning for the first time about blockchain and crypto so
there was a promise that everything was decentralized that there is no middleman so for example i want to
send some cryptocurrency to you there is no middleman but at one moment for example the company that you
work for binance uh was started five years ago was it seven seven right yeah 2017 2017 uh so it it was
an idea from the beginning but you have binance you have other companies as well that are in the role of
intermediary between people and organizations uh so how do you think uh what do you think uh uh was was was this
uh what is the english word uh promise uh still on or or is it is it is it off no it's it's still
on in order to achieve the mass adoption you need to give to the millions of people easy way to do it
and there is no easier way to do it than rather than this through the centralized platforms right
there is of course a slight percentage of the bitcoin maximalists or crypto anarchists or whatever you
call them that do not trust and do not do not trust to any centralized exchange and don't want to pass
the kyc etc so they want to have full anonymity and full control of their assets and it's actually
and a normal sync right there is a saying in crypto that not your keys not your crypto so if
there is something you can do there is bunch of options to do it we are the non-custodial wallets or
even through the like separate separate devices to hold your crypto without transaction through the
centralized exchanges it's just much more easier much more comfortable much more user friendly for the
the majority 99 percent of the users but it's just uh making it easier without
trying to monopolize the industry
so uh when i asked you what what is uh a thing that crypto innovates on uh so from what i understood
you you told me that it innovates uh in the way that is it is uh stopping inflation if i can express
myself like that so bitcoin so let us talk about bitcoin then we can talk about other cryptocurrencies as
well so bitcoin is is a blockchain as well not not just a cryptocurrency uh so you use you mentioned
the the the characteristic of uh being finite of of of having only 21 million bitcoins we are still not
there yet so they we need to mine i'm not sure how much uh more bitcoin a couple of million couple of
million so far uh i suppose it will last for probably 100 years around like that something something like that
uh but uh what other character characteristics can you can you mention that bitcoin innovates on
so basically that's the that cannot be controlled right by any government so it cannot be political or
economically influenced this is fully transparent so you can track down every bitcoin from the time it was
first mind to whatever it is right now so it gives like much more clarity and transparency to the industry
and the most important thing that it goes through the very complicated banking and central banking and
commercial banking mechanics that's now getting super complicated these days you need to have a bunch of the
documents you need to have a proof of proof of your earnings you need to have all these millions of the
documents it's long it's complicated it's expensive and basically that's the movement we see globally that
the people are migrating from the traditional finance to the bitcoin and other altcoins which is the new
finance finance to zero which is faster cheaper easier transparent and uh cannot be influenced by the
governments so when you say that you have uh almost 100 of your asset of your network in in uh in
cryptocurrency which group cryptocurrency is it so how how do you divide it and how do you use it in
your everyday life i suppose that you have uh needs to to spend uh yeah so buy things so so day-to-day basis
so what i'm saying is not a financial advice right let me let me do a quick disclaimer here so
basically most is is in bitcoin there is some other uh potential uh interesting new uh crypto projects
that are also there but that's like uh minority uh yeah and um in at binance uh we can we cannot trade
there is a very strict rules um about the trading for the binance employees so basically we do not
allow to be a day traders because the day trading is a it's a full-time profession right and cz was
very strict about that so he said that if you want to be a trader we are welcoming you to our platform
please come and trade but if you want to to work at binance you cannot trade so basically we are
we are having the rules that if you buy some assets for the 30 days you cannot sell it
and that's very serious the fall for the violations people can get fired for violating these rules so
basically myself as all the other binance team we are just buying some crypto assets and holding it so
that's that's that's how we operate so i suppose then then you you divide it between
some stable coin and probably a bitcoin or ethereum maybe no stable coin i don't have because it's
you don't have it's a bull market so we need to maximize the portfolio potential okay so how do you go
about your everyday uh uh spendings so do you use some maybe some binance card oh it's very easy it's
uh what what do you spend do you spend the ethereum do you spend bitcoin or do you spend stable coin
no i spend euro i spent hungarian foreign there is a lot of the there is a lot of the methods now for the
binance users both fiat and p2p so if you want to sell any crypto there is a bunch of options you
have you can directly send it to your card you can send it via sepa to your banking account you can
use our p2p platform when the users are trading between themselves not through the fiat providers so
there is uh all these very cheap and very quick options how you can convert crypto to fiat and fiat to
crypto that's not a problem nowadays you can also use the cards schemes unfortunately currently we have
suspended uh binance card program in europe uh however we have a lot of the third party uh providers
the card issuers that are connected we are the api to your binance account and you can issue their
digital or physical cards and connect them to their wallets and if you don't want to keep the fiat
even one euro in your account you can use these cards and it's auto converted at the time of the
payment so everyone selects the the option they like so i'm not sure if you answer this part of the
question so do you use your uh crypto uh do you deposit it on exchange like binance or do you deposit in
deposit it on on the wallets no 100 what i got is on binance everything is on binance yeah
it's just to to prove your loyalty to the company or do you uh do you propose uh for the people to do
do similar or why is everybody why is everybody going to uh to the wallets uh solutions no it's not
everybody it's actually very very small number of the of the population are using quality solutions
so basically it's not to prove the the the loyalties because it's more useful and more reliable
and more secure okay it's more secure that that's yeah that's the most important thing
because i have a big family right and it's not about the loyalty it's about like protecting my family
first of all so that's why i'm doing this basically um there is a lot of scams and there is a lot of
scammers in the crypto industry and methods these scammers are using are amazing right now so the they
can use the ai to fake the id and then register with the fake id they can do the social engineering
methods to get to your device they can do whatever all these so sophisticated scammers are becoming right
now so it's getting more and more complicated to protect your data and protect your devices especially
with the level of the usage we are having and interactions with our devices right the number of
the applications transactions everything we are using social networks etc so it's like super complicated
to protect yourself even for advanced users that i treat myself as an advanced user so basically um
centralized exchanges uh and have their own risks right and and this risk is that the centralized
exchanges may go crazy and can start misusing your funds that that's what we saw with for example
ftx situation when they were misusing your funds but i know what's happening on binance and
for the users we put together a proof of reserves method when you basically can go online and see
the hot wallets of binance and how much assets of what kind these hot wallets are holding and you can
ever check if your zero zero one of bitcoin is a part of this wallet so you can check your hash id or
transaction id and confirm whether or not it is a part of this hot wallet just to make sure
the users can be sure that their funds are not misused as well as we are having a very
strong security that's being protected by so-called binance ledger that's the security stack that
protects us but we operate on the basic on the basis that any security can be breached and that's how we
build not just our security controls but also our teams so we have a 70 70 crypto investigators
that partner with the law enforcement authorities around the globe i don't know if you heard but
but there was a recent scam with zk casino the people that were doing the online gambling platform and
they basically was uh offering this uh gambling and they scammed people for 30 million so binance
together with the law enforcement helped to freeze these funds and basically these guys were arrested so we
have a big team working with the law enforcement we have hundreds of people of compliance that are
working on the iml kyc transactional monitoring sinks to protect our users and we have a huge
customer support desk that are using ai etc so these all pillars are focused on
protecting users from the technology perspective but also help you know prevent any other external
risk factors so that's why i trust binance so what do you think who are the key differences between
commercial banks and centralized exchanges for the crypto like like binance you mentioned some of the
differences right now in the in your last answer but maybe if you can tell us not much right but
that's the same thing but that's the in intermediaries for the people's transactions from the past
and from the future is basically the same idea of the intermediary right to make people easily and freely
transact to support their everyday needs of spending and receiving money
it's just the new technology right the new way of thinking and more importantly the new way of
operating and the different vision and mission but the the idea and the concept is the same
so basically when we are talking about the crypto uh firstly what we need to talk about is
the technology that it was built on uh its blockchain so what blockchain brings
innovatively that we have not seen before it brings transparency it brings uh decentralization in in
in which way transparency uh so i i i'm sure that you heard or there is so many uh scammers in crypto
there is so many illicit funds bribes etc but the funny thing is that if you compare the percent of
the scam or illicit fund in crypto and percent of the scam or illicit fund in the traditional financial system
or percent of the illicit funds in cash that is going to be much more way more bigger than in crypto
because the crypto is transparent if you do one transaction this transaction or this asset that
you are holding can be tracked down to the very beginning once this asset was created it's all there
even the basic skill using chain analysis or some or crystal the the these these methods and these
tools you can easily track all the wallets all the transactions that's why i don't know if you notice
but recently when the scammers scamming something they have these assets but they cannot spend it
so that's why very often for a very small bounty of like five ten percent they are returning
everything that they were able to scam from the victim because there is no use for them it's better
for them to keep five or ten percent rather than not be able to use all this money because this crypto can
be marked as illicit fund and that's it you cannot do anything with crypto so it bill it brings transparency
it brings the new technology it brings decentralized operations of the network which is basically a lot of
the validator rather than the one computer or one server where everything can be the same information
is distributed to all the computers on the network exactly because you cannot delete any information or
any uh you know you cannot change block in in the in the blockchain that's already happened and that's
why there is zero potential for the manipulation you know uh in in today's world where in from information
goes like this it's uh when you cannot hide anything it's very mysterious or i can use some other other
adjectives uh that we do not know who is behind technology like bitcoin because bitcoin was the first
blockchain ever developed uh what what are your your opinions on that like who is satoshi asking yes
how is how is this possible that today's ain't an age we don't do not know who is behind one of the
most important technology technological innovations usually people when they invent something
everybody wants to say i was the one who who did this yeah nobody
comes and say this there are people there are people who are saying that they are satoshi but
yeah so that's that's the beauty of it isn't it it's uh it's so cool uh that it's truly decentralized
and even if the creator which is obviously one of the brightest minds
living uh living uh in our in the previous century uh even without this creator and without uh his
knowledge his expertise technology not just live but also develops and become really great so that's
the beauty of the blockchain isn't it it is the beauty but in some people i suppose that it brings
emotions of untrustworthiness for example in the in the in the end of course technology
works it works it's it's it's unbelievable but uh some people uh that are a little bit harder to trust
uh maybe they are thinking that some governments are behind it maybe some intergovernment uh
organizations uh are behind it you don't think about it you just and for these people etf was
created yeah so that's exactly why the etf come into the play to open the crypto markets to the trade
traditional finance and the traditional thinking so the people who was afraid was not ready was not
not trusting to open account to go through the kyc or to have their own crypto and have their own keys
now they can easily buy uh this bitcoin index through the etfs offered by the big financial organizations
like black rock etc and it's just the beginning of the trend basically u.s market is the biggest for the
liquidity globally but uh we can see other markets are following so hong kong started this south korea
starting this soon and i'm sure that others will follow and that's a big big thing for crypto because
it opens the doors not just for people who distrust but also for traditional financial institutions for
funds for pension funds for these people that are sitting on the bags of money and will start investing
into crypto too what do you think that it is a better move to to invent something like blockchain
and crypto and disappear uh we what what is the bigger bigger gangster move to disappear like for
for example satoshi if he's a only one person or maybe team of people or to
to say that you are the the one behind it maybe this is this is even the bigger gangster move to
to disappear and not not be there well i think he disappeared because something happened to him
you think so yeah that's why that's the only reason i see satoshi still
remains one of the most uh the richest people in the world right for the number of the bitcoin he's
holding in his wallet but i think uh how much does he hold i think he's in the top 20 global it's around
like 60 or 70 billion dollars is his uh the the the current price of his wallet but it's not been moving
since basically his last tweet yeah so but but but i don't think that he like
made the move right so the the the industry is working the the technology is working for every one
of us of ours benefit uh are you aware of a person called michael sailor sure uh what do you think about
him and his philosophy and thoughts about bitcoin oh i love it i love him i think he's a great guy so
his favorite saying is like um when are you going to be selling your bitcoin so there is one rule in
bitcoin you never sell your bitcoin that's what he says and i think he has a brilliant idea right so he's
just uh buying bitcoin and he's going to the traditional markets and he's issuing more debt
he's issue issuing more shares and he's getting more traditional financial money and move it to the
bitcoin again so that's a great combination between person that really trusts and move the crypto industry
forward and benefits from the traditional financial money via this uh corporatization mechanism so i i think
he is one of the great guys in the industry uh so i was a a part of the conference today that that you
were speaking on uh and i was uh listening uh what what you were speaking about uh
can you tell me about safety in uh in this world in cryptocurrency blockchain uh so what is
binance doing right now uh uh i suppose that this is your biggest role this is your primary
role in in the in the company uh not just safety but uh compliance to the governments and uh relationship
with the governments and uh uh making sure that everything fits correctly on on the regulation side
so you said security and then compliance that are two different things let's let's let's let's start
with with compliance then yeah so compliance is a big thing basically the biggest thing for the
crypto industry right now so initially back into 2017 2019 there was no compliance there was no
regulation that was nothing because everyone thought it is just a joke and then uh it it will not move
on and it will like a new hype it will go away after a couple of years but when the governments
understood that this is not this will not go away despite the fact all the negative things they were
doing for the crypto and they understood that this is big and it is getting bigger quite fast
they started to think how to regulate it which is basically a good thing to do right because
government needs to to to protect their people their users and that's where uh the compliance thing
started and when the compliance became really really important for the industry so basically
uh all the stakeholders which is government organizations businesses like ours and the users we want
all one thing we want to have crystal clear framework the set of rules where we all agree to follow
this will remove all the misunderstandings and we all will go together ahead
so that's what the governments are trying to achieve but provided that's that's a new industry
it's not goes without mistakes without delays without disagreement between the stakeholders
but eventually i'm sure we will get there and the crypto will be regulated as a traditional finance
Uvijem sviđanje u njegovljenju.
Uvijem sviđanju u njegovljenju u njegovljenju u njegovljenju.
U njegovljenju u njegovljenju u njegovljenju u njegovljenju u njegovljenju.
U njegovljenju u njegovljenju u njegovljenju.
Hvala što pratite.
što pratite.
kripto.
Hvala što pratite.
Hvala što pratite kanal.