[SPEAKER_00] I am supposed to be speaking to you on the heart of an intercessor.
[SPEAKER_01] And as I present to you the heart of an intercessor,
[SPEAKER_00] I think I will present a model before you.
[SPEAKER_00] And that model is St. John Mary Vianney.
[SPEAKER_01] I taj primer slijedi Svet Ivan Marija Vianney.
[SPEAKER_01] Everything that an intercessor needs is in him.
[SPEAKER_01] If you look at the life of St. John Mary Vianney,
[SPEAKER_01] He was born and brought up in a very, very rural setting.
[SPEAKER_01] He used to be working in the fields and tending the flock.
[SPEAKER_00] So, till he joined the seminary,
[SPEAKER_00] He had not much formal education.
[SPEAKER_01] So, when he joined the priesthood,
[SPEAKER_00] He did not know Latin.
[SPEAKER_01] It was a big challenge for him to cope up with his studies.
[SPEAKER_00] Because he did not know Latin,
[SPEAKER_00] He had to study things in French,
[SPEAKER_00] Which is unusual.
[SPEAKER_01] That time.
[SPEAKER_01] He failed on many subjects.
[SPEAKER_01] So, his ordination was very difficult.
[SPEAKER_00] Finally, with a lot of difficulty,
[SPEAKER_01] His ordination was cleared.
[SPEAKER_01] But after he was ordained,
[SPEAKER_00] The bishop had the problem.
[SPEAKER_01] The problem was where to post this man.
[SPEAKER_00] Because he did not know theology.
[SPEAKER_00] He did not know how to preach a homily.
[SPEAKER_00] He was not even given the faculty to listen to confessions.
[SPEAKER_01] So, for a year,
[SPEAKER_00] He was sitting in the bishop's house.
[SPEAKER_00] Because they could not find a place to send him.
[SPEAKER_01] After a year,
[SPEAKER_00] To get rid of him,
[SPEAKER_00] He was posted in a parish
[SPEAKER_00] Where there were no people.
[SPEAKER_01] There were only 230 people in that parish.
[SPEAKER_00] But these people did not used to come to the church.
[SPEAKER_01] So, the parish was closed.
[SPEAKER_01] And that is the place to which
[SPEAKER_00] Father John Mary Vianney was posted.
[SPEAKER_00] He reached that place on a bullock cart.
[SPEAKER_00] On?
[SPEAKER_00] On a bullock cart.
[SPEAKER_00] Bullock.
[SPEAKER_00] Not on the car.
[SPEAKER_00] There was no car.
[SPEAKER_00] But a car that was driven by the bullock.
[SPEAKER_01] And then,
[SPEAKER_00] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] He had no people
[SPEAKER_00] To attend the Mass on the first Sunday.
[SPEAKER_01] One day.
[SPEAKER_01] It was good for Father John Mary Vianney
[SPEAKER_00] Because he did not have to preach the homily.
[SPEAKER_01] And when He began the Mass
[SPEAKER_00] And people started coming.
[SPEAKER_00] Then,
[SPEAKER_00] He had to preach the homily.
[SPEAKER_01] They said that the first time
[SPEAKER_00] He preached the homily.
[SPEAKER_01] He was not an intelligent man.
[SPEAKER_01] He could not remember things.
[SPEAKER_01] So, He started saying like this.
[SPEAKER_01] My dear people.
[SPEAKER_01] God loves you.
[SPEAKER_00] Then, He did not know what to say again.
[SPEAKER_00] So, He repeated.
[SPEAKER_01] My dear people.
[SPEAKER_00] God loves you.
[SPEAKER_01] And,
[SPEAKER_00] He said that a third time.
[SPEAKER_01] But,
[SPEAKER_00] They said,
[SPEAKER_00] Those who were present
[SPEAKER_01] Were touched by that.
[SPEAKER_01] But,
[SPEAKER_00] They said,
[SPEAKER_00] Those who were present
[SPEAKER_00] Were touched by that.
[SPEAKER_01] Tears started flowing down their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01] His first biographer says,
[SPEAKER_00] That he made the church his home.
[SPEAKER_00] He used to spend the whole day in the church all alone.
[SPEAKER_01] And,
[SPEAKER_00] That is how he began his ministry.
[SPEAKER_01] For forty years,
[SPEAKER_00] He lived on boiled potatoes and dried bread.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] His ministry begins in this way.
[SPEAKER_00] Slowly the people who were away from the parish started coming back one by one.
[SPEAKER_01] After that,
[SPEAKER_00] People from the neighboring parishes started coming.
[SPEAKER_01] People from the neighboring dioceses started coming.
[SPEAKER_01] People started coming from abroad.
[SPEAKER_00] And,
[SPEAKER_00] It is said that he used to get something like hundred thousand people a year.
[SPEAKER_00] Satan himself told him that you snatched away eighty thousand people from my clutches.
[SPEAKER_01] So, he was a true intercessor.
[SPEAKER_00] He is a perfect model for intercessors.
[SPEAKER_01] Because,
[SPEAKER_00] Through his prayer,
[SPEAKER_00] He revived the whole parish.
[SPEAKER_01] Through his prayers,
[SPEAKER_00] He revived a lot of parishes around.
[SPEAKER_01] He won over so many souls for Jesus.
[SPEAKER_00] So,
[SPEAKER_00] If we look at the life of Father John Mary Vianney,
[SPEAKER_01] We find,
[SPEAKER_00] We find many qualities of an intercessor.
[SPEAKER_00] That we find,
[SPEAKER_00] In the life of John Mary Vianney,
[SPEAKER_00] Is his holiness.
[SPEAKER_01] I want to insist on this.
[SPEAKER_01] Because,
[SPEAKER_00] As intercessors,
[SPEAKER_00] We need to be people who are holy.
[SPEAKER_00] During my teachings on spiritual warfare,
[SPEAKER_01] I did quote Ephesians chapter 6,
[SPEAKER_01] Where I said that,
[SPEAKER_00] Our righteousness,
[SPEAKER_00] Becomes,
[SPEAKER_00] A spiritual armor for us.
[SPEAKER_00] Sveti Pavel also says,
[SPEAKER_00] That we need to wear,
[SPEAKER_00] The belt of truth.
[SPEAKER_01] Sveti Pavel also says,
[SPEAKER_00] That we need to wear,
[SPEAKER_00] The belt of truth.
[SPEAKER_00] Sveti Pavel also says,
[SPEAKER_00] That we need to wear,
[SPEAKER_00] The belt of truth.
[SPEAKER_01] Sveti Pavel also says,
[SPEAKER_01] That we need to wear,
[SPEAKER_01] The belt of truth.
[SPEAKER_01] Sveti Pavel also says,
[UNKNOWN] That we need to wear,
[SPEAKER_00] The belt of truth.
[SPEAKER_00] So,
[SPEAKER_00] As intercessors,
[SPEAKER_00] We are expected to be people,
[SPEAKER_01] Who are holy.
[SPEAKER_01] Now,
[UNKNOWN] Speaking about holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] Many of us think,
[SPEAKER_00] That to be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] Is something,
[SPEAKER_00] So difficult.
[SPEAKER_01] To make it simple,
[SPEAKER_01] Pope Francis has brought out,
[SPEAKER_00] An apostolic exhortation.
[SPEAKER_01] And,
[SPEAKER_00] That is called,
[SPEAKER_00] Gaudate et exultate.
[SPEAKER_00] And,
[SPEAKER_00] In this,
[SPEAKER_00] It is,
[SPEAKER_00] A call to holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] In today's world.
[SPEAKER_01] I just want to quote this,
[SPEAKER_01] Because,
[SPEAKER_00] When I say,
[SPEAKER_00] That we are called to be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] You must be thinking,
[SPEAKER_00] That then it is going to be difficult,
[SPEAKER_00] For us to be intercessors.
[SPEAKER_01] These are very simple things,
[SPEAKER_00] That Pope Francis speaks,
[SPEAKER_00] About holiness.
[SPEAKER_01] In paragraph 14,
[SPEAKER_00] Pope Francis says,
[SPEAKER_00] To be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] Does not require,
[SPEAKER_00] Being a bishop.
[SPEAKER_00] To be holy,
[SPEAKER_01] Does not require,
[SPEAKER_01] Being a bishop.
[SPEAKER_01] Or a priest,
[SPEAKER_00] Or a religious.
[SPEAKER_00] We are frequently tempted,
[SPEAKER_00] To think,
[SPEAKER_00] That holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] Is only,
[SPEAKER_00] For those who can withdraw,
[SPEAKER_00] From ordinary affairs,
[SPEAKER_00] To spend,
[SPEAKER_00] Much time in prayer.
[SPEAKER_01] This is not the case.
[SPEAKER_00] We are called to be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] By living,
[SPEAKER_00] Our lives,
[SPEAKER_00] With love,
[SPEAKER_00] And by bearing,
[SPEAKER_00] Witness,
[SPEAKER_00] In everything,
[SPEAKER_00] We do.
[SPEAKER_00] We are called,
[SPEAKER_00] To be holy.
[SPEAKER_01] Wherever we find,
[SPEAKER_00] Ourselves,
[SPEAKER_00] Are you called,
[SPEAKER_00] To the consecrated life?
[SPEAKER_00] Be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] By living out,
[SPEAKER_00] Your commitment,
[SPEAKER_00] With joy.
[SPEAKER_01] Are you married?
[SPEAKER_01] Be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] By loving,
[SPEAKER_00] And caring,
[SPEAKER_00] For your husband,
[SPEAKER_00] Or wife.
[SPEAKER_01] Do you work,
[SPEAKER_00] For a living?
[SPEAKER_01] For a living?
[SPEAKER_01] Be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] By laboring,
[SPEAKER_00] With integrity,
[SPEAKER_00] And skill,
[SPEAKER_00] In the service,
[SPEAKER_00] Of your brothers,
[SPEAKER_00] And sisters.
[SPEAKER_01] Are you a parent,
[SPEAKER_00] Or grandparent?
[SPEAKER_00] And parent,
[SPEAKER_01] Be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] By patiently teaching the little ones,
[SPEAKER_00] How to follow Jesus.
[SPEAKER_01] Are you in a position of authority?
[SPEAKER_01] Be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] By working,
[SPEAKER_00] For the common good,
[SPEAKER_00] And renouncing,
[SPEAKER_00] Personal gain.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] Pope Francis teaches us,
[SPEAKER_01] That to be holy,
[SPEAKER_01] Is something,
[SPEAKER_01] Very,
[SPEAKER_01] Very simple.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] Pope Francis teaches us,
[SPEAKER_00] That to be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] Is something,
[SPEAKER_00] Very,
[SPEAKER_00] Simple.
[SPEAKER_01] He does not say,
[SPEAKER_00] It is easy,
[SPEAKER_01] But he says,
[SPEAKER_00] It's not complicated.
[SPEAKER_01] It is not something,
[SPEAKER_00] That we need to be scared of.
[SPEAKER_00] I think,
[SPEAKER_00] It's good for me,
[SPEAKER_00] To speak to you,
[SPEAKER_00] About a saint,
[SPEAKER_00] From Germany.
[SPEAKER_01] His name is,
[SPEAKER_00] Sveti Konrad,
[SPEAKER_00] Of Parham.
[SPEAKER_01] Sveti Konrad,
[SPEAKER_00] That is enough.
[SPEAKER_01] He was,
[SPEAKER_00] He was,
[SPEAKER_00] Doing the work of a porter,
[SPEAKER_00] At the shrine of Our Lady,
[SPEAKER_00] Of Alto Ting.
[SPEAKER_01] And he was,
[SPEAKER_00] There for 40 years.
[SPEAKER_01] The only thing,
[SPEAKER_00] That he used to do,
[SPEAKER_00] Was to attend to the doorbell,
[SPEAKER_01] And give them bread and wine.
[SPEAKER_00] He did nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] After his death,
[SPEAKER_00] His case for,
[SPEAKER_00] Beatification,
[SPEAKER_00] And canonization,
[SPEAKER_00] Was taken up.
[SPEAKER_00] When this case came up for,
[SPEAKER_00] Canonization,
[SPEAKER_01] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] There is always,
[SPEAKER_00] A devil's advocate,
[SPEAKER_01] Who argues,
[SPEAKER_00] Against,
[SPEAKER_00] Canonization.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] There is somebody,
[SPEAKER_00] Who presents the case,
[SPEAKER_00] For,
[SPEAKER_00] Canonization,
[SPEAKER_00] And there is somebody,
[SPEAKER_00] Who argues,
[UNKNOWN] Against,
[SPEAKER_00] Canonization.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] The devil's advocate said,
[SPEAKER_01] That,
[SPEAKER_01] This man,
[SPEAKER_01] Has,
[SPEAKER_01] Not,
[SPEAKER_01] Contributed,
[SPEAKER_01] Anything,
[SPEAKER_01] To the life,
[SPEAKER_01] Of the church,
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] The devil's advocate said,
[SPEAKER_00] That,
[SPEAKER_00] This man,
[SPEAKER_00] Has,
[SPEAKER_00] Not,
[SPEAKER_00] Contributed,
[SPEAKER_00] Anything,
[SPEAKER_00] To the life,
[SPEAKER_01] Of the church,
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] He cannot,
[SPEAKER_01] Be canonized.
[SPEAKER_01] And,
[SPEAKER_01] Finally,
[SPEAKER_01] You know,
[SPEAKER_01] The pope,
[SPEAKER_01] Had to come in.
[SPEAKER_00] And,
[SPEAKER_00] The pope came,
[SPEAKER_01] And then,
[SPEAKER_01] You know,
[SPEAKER_01] The devil's advocate,
[SPEAKER_00] Again said,
[SPEAKER_00] Your holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] This man,
[SPEAKER_00] Has not,
[SPEAKER_01] Done anything,
[SPEAKER_01] For the life,
[SPEAKER_01] Of the church,
[SPEAKER_00] And the pope came,
[SPEAKER_00] And then,
[SPEAKER_00] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] The devil's advocate,
[SPEAKER_00] Again said,
[SPEAKER_00] Your holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] Has not,
[SPEAKER_00] Done anything,
[SPEAKER_00] For the life,
[SPEAKER_00] Of the church,
[SPEAKER_00] That he cannot,
[SPEAKER_01] Be canonized.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] That time,
[SPEAKER_00] The pope,
[SPEAKER_00] I forget,
[SPEAKER_00] The name of the pope,
[SPEAKER_00] I think,
[SPEAKER_00] It was Pope Pius,
[SPEAKER_00] Five,
[SPEAKER_00] He said,
[SPEAKER_00] If,
[SPEAKER_00] You,
[SPEAKER_00] Work as a potter,
[SPEAKER_00] For 40 years,
[SPEAKER_00] Without complaining,
[SPEAKER_00] I will canonize,
[SPEAKER_00] You too.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] Holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] Is made,
[SPEAKER_01] So simple.
[SPEAKER_00] The pope,
[SPEAKER_00] Pope Benedict XVI said,
[SPEAKER_01] Pope Benedict XVI said,
[SPEAKER_00] Holiness does not consist,
[SPEAKER_00] In never having sinned,
[SPEAKER_00] But holiness increases the capacity for conversion,
[SPEAKER_01] For repentance,
[SPEAKER_00] For repentance,
[SPEAKER_00] For willingness to start again,
[SPEAKER_00] And specially for reconciliation and forgiveness.
[SPEAKER_00] For forgiveness.
[SPEAKER_01] This is what I want to insist on.
[SPEAKER_01] Because,
[SPEAKER_01] Once,
[SPEAKER_00] A young man came to me,
[SPEAKER_00] And said,
[SPEAKER_01] He said,
[UNKNOWN] He said,
[SPEAKER_00] I suffer from,
[SPEAKER_00] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] This habit,
[SPEAKER_00] Of self abuse.
[SPEAKER_01] But,
[SPEAKER_01] I try to be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] I fall again.
[SPEAKER_01] Can I be an intercessor?
[SPEAKER_01] Can he be an intercessor?
[SPEAKER_00] So,
[SPEAKER_01] There are,
[SPEAKER_01] I think,
[SPEAKER_00] two opinions.
[SPEAKER_00] But,
[SPEAKER_01] we,
[SPEAKER_01] all of us,
[UNKNOWN] fall.
[SPEAKER_00] We are humans.
[SPEAKER_00] Despite our best efforts,
[SPEAKER_01] we fall into sin,
[SPEAKER_00] We are humans.
[SPEAKER_01] Despite our best efforts,
[SPEAKER_00] we fall into sin,
[SPEAKER_00] but what the Lord expects from us is,
[SPEAKER_01] Despite our best efforts,
[SPEAKER_00] when we fall,
[SPEAKER_00] We repent for our sins.
[SPEAKER_00] That is why Pope Benedict XVI says,
[SPEAKER_00] Holiness does not consist in never having sinned.
[SPEAKER_01] But holiness increases the capacity for conversion.
[SPEAKER_01] Pope Francis was asked in an interview,
[SPEAKER_00] Who is George Mario Bergoglio?
[SPEAKER_00] That was his name.
[SPEAKER_01] And he said,
[SPEAKER_00] I am a sinner,
[SPEAKER_00] whom the Lord has forgiven.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] the Holy Father himself says,
[SPEAKER_00] I was a sinner,
[SPEAKER_00] whom the Lord has forgiven.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] I want to insist on this,
[SPEAKER_01] that we,
[SPEAKER_00] that we,
[SPEAKER_00] strive towards holiness,
[SPEAKER_01] and,
[SPEAKER_00] as we strive towards holiness,
[SPEAKER_00] and,
[SPEAKER_01] and,
[SPEAKER_00] there are times we fall,
[SPEAKER_01] there are times we fall,
[SPEAKER_00] but,
[SPEAKER_01] we get up again.
[SPEAKER_00] We repent for our sins.
[SPEAKER_00] We make a good confession,
[SPEAKER_00] and,
[SPEAKER_01] we go forward.
[SPEAKER_00] And,
[SPEAKER_00] that way we can still be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] and,
[SPEAKER_00] be good in the sacers.
[SPEAKER_01] and,
[SPEAKER_01] we are good in the sacers.
[SPEAKER_00] Archbishop Fulton Jeisín said,
[SPEAKER_00] A saint is a recovering sinner.
[SPEAKER_00] So,
[SPEAKER_00] a saint was a sinner.
[SPEAKER_00] The saint is recovering from sin.
[SPEAKER_01] So, we all need to be holy.
[SPEAKER_01] And,
[SPEAKER_00] that is the heart of an intercessor.
[SPEAKER_00] The second one is humility.
[SPEAKER_01] again,
[SPEAKER_00] I am presenting you,
[SPEAKER_00] before you,
[SPEAKER_01] Father John Mary Vianney.
[SPEAKER_00] It is said about,
[SPEAKER_00] Father John Mary Vianney,
[SPEAKER_00] that,
[SPEAKER_00] when he used to go to his room,
[SPEAKER_00] he used to be laughing aloud.
[SPEAKER_00] The sacristian used to hear this.
[SPEAKER_01] The sacristian used to hear this.
[SPEAKER_00] So, the sacristian started thinking,
[SPEAKER_01] that,
[SPEAKER_00] something must be wrong with John Mary Vianney.
[UNKNOWN] that,
[SPEAKER_00] when you are in your room,
[SPEAKER_01] if you start laughing aloud,
[SPEAKER_00] it's not a healthy sign.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] he reported this matter,
[SPEAKER_00] to the priest,
[SPEAKER_00] who is in charge of the dinary.
[SPEAKER_01] So, the priest in charge of the dinary came,
[SPEAKER_00] one day,
[UNKNOWN] after,
[SPEAKER_01] Father John Mary Vianney went to the room,
[SPEAKER_00] he too was listening from outside,
[SPEAKER_01] that,
[UNKNOWN] that,
[SPEAKER_00] father is laughing.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] he knocked at the door.
[SPEAKER_00] So,
[SPEAKER_00] he sat with Father John Mary Vianney.
[SPEAKER_01] He asked him,
[SPEAKER_00] Father,
[SPEAKER_00] everything is okay?
[SPEAKER_00] So,
[SPEAKER_00] he said,
[SPEAKER_01] yeah,
[SPEAKER_01] everything is fine.
[SPEAKER_01] But,
[SPEAKER_00] I am told that,
[SPEAKER_00] when you go to your room,
[SPEAKER_00] late in the night,
[SPEAKER_00] you start laughing.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] Father John Mary Vianney said,
[SPEAKER_00] when I come to the room,
[SPEAKER_01] when I start realizing,
[SPEAKER_00] how the Lord is making use of me,
[SPEAKER_01] who is really a fool,
[SPEAKER_01] I cannot but laugh.
[SPEAKER_01] See his humility.
[SPEAKER_00] He was so humble.
[SPEAKER_01] And,
[SPEAKER_00] as intercessors,
[SPEAKER_00] we need to be humble.
[SPEAKER_01] I spoke about this,
[SPEAKER_00] during my talks,
[SPEAKER_00] during the training program.
[SPEAKER_01] But,
[SPEAKER_00] when we speak about the heart,
[SPEAKER_00] of an intercessor,
[SPEAKER_00] we need to really speak about humility.
[SPEAKER_00] because,
[SPEAKER_00] I know that,
[SPEAKER_00] you are already powerful intercessors.
[SPEAKER_01] One of the things,
[SPEAKER_00] that can happen with us,
[SPEAKER_00] in our ministry,
[SPEAKER_00] is,
[SPEAKER_00] that we can become proud.
[SPEAKER_00] you know,
[SPEAKER_00] very often,
[SPEAKER_00] the charismatics,
[SPEAKER_00] are not liked by the parish priests.
[SPEAKER_01] You know the main reason?
[SPEAKER_01] Because,
[SPEAKER_00] after some time,
[SPEAKER_00] we start saying,
[SPEAKER_00] the parish priests,
[SPEAKER_00] does not have the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_00] because,
[SPEAKER_00] when we start growing in our ministry,
[SPEAKER_00] when things start happening,
[SPEAKER_01] we tend to think that,
[SPEAKER_00] the priests,
[SPEAKER_00] and the bishops,
[SPEAKER_00] do not have the Holy Spirit,
[SPEAKER_00] but,
[SPEAKER_00] only we have the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_01] It makes us proud,
[SPEAKER_01] haughty,
[SPEAKER_01] and arrogant.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] as intercessors,
[SPEAKER_01] we need to,
[SPEAKER_00] stay humble.
[SPEAKER_00] To send,
[SPEAKER_00] a question,
[SPEAKER_00] somebody asked,
[SPEAKER_01] what are the qualities,
[SPEAKER_01] of a saint?
[SPEAKER_00] He said,
[SPEAKER_00] the first quality,
[SPEAKER_00] is humility.
[SPEAKER_00] The second quality,
[SPEAKER_01] is humility.
[SPEAKER_01] The second quality,
[SPEAKER_00] The second quality,
[SPEAKER_00] is humility.
[SPEAKER_01] is humility.
[SPEAKER_01] The second quality,
[SPEAKER_00] is humility.
[SPEAKER_00] and the third,
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] if you want to be a saint,
[SPEAKER_00] if you want to be holy,
[SPEAKER_00] we need to be humble.
[SPEAKER_01] Why I am saying this is,
[SPEAKER_00] definitely,
[SPEAKER_00] you are going to do mighty things,
[SPEAKER_01] in the area of intercession.
[SPEAKER_00] What I am saying this is,
[SPEAKER_00] definitely,
[SPEAKER_00] you are going to do mighty things,
[SPEAKER_01] in the area of intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] Why I am saying this is,
[SPEAKER_01] definitely,
[SPEAKER_01] you are going to do mighty things,
[SPEAKER_01] in the area of intercession.
[SPEAKER_00] Why I am saying this is,
[SPEAKER_00] definitely,
[SPEAKER_00] you are going to do mighty things,
[SPEAKER_00] in the area of intercession.
[SPEAKER_00] Why I am saying this is,
[SPEAKER_01] definitely,
[SPEAKER_01] you are going to do mighty things,
[SPEAKER_01] in the area of intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] you will witness,
[SPEAKER_00] miracles happening,
[SPEAKER_00] through your prayer.
[SPEAKER_01] And that is the time,
[SPEAKER_00] when,
[SPEAKER_00] we tend to,
[SPEAKER_00] become proud.
[SPEAKER_01] This is something,
[SPEAKER_00] very subtle.
[SPEAKER_01] We don't realize,
[SPEAKER_00] when we go proud.
[SPEAKER_01] but we need to,
[SPEAKER_01] really,
[SPEAKER_01] keep a check,
[SPEAKER_01] on ourselves.
[SPEAKER_00] Am I proud?
[SPEAKER_00] When great,
[SPEAKER_00] and mighty things happen,
[SPEAKER_01] when people appreciate you,
[SPEAKER_01] you,
[SPEAKER_01] we are to become sign boards.
[SPEAKER_00] Sign,
[SPEAKER_01] sign,
[SPEAKER_00] sign,
[SPEAKER_00] signages.
[SPEAKER_00] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] the boards,
[SPEAKER_00] which indicate something,
[SPEAKER_00] you know,
[SPEAKER_00] the road,
[SPEAKER_01] signages.
[SPEAKER_01] towards God,
[SPEAKER_01] that all glory belongs to Him,
[SPEAKER_01] and not to us.
[SPEAKER_01] As,
[SPEAKER_00] Father Cantalamesa says,
[SPEAKER_01] the power passes through us,
[SPEAKER_00] but we are not the generators.
[SPEAKER_00] we don't generate the power,
[SPEAKER_01] but it passes through us.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] we do not have the right,
[SPEAKER_00] to take the credit for that.
[SPEAKER_01] We should become humble instruments,
[SPEAKER_00] in the Lord's hands.
[SPEAKER_01] the next quality,
[SPEAKER_00] of the heart of an intercessor,
[SPEAKER_01] is this.
[SPEAKER_01] We need to be people of prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] Now the question comes,
[SPEAKER_00] I am spending a lot of time,
[SPEAKER_00] for intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] So, should I have my personal prayer?
[SPEAKER_00] If you are already praying,
[SPEAKER_01] as an intercessor,
[SPEAKER_01] you are doing Jericho prayer,
[SPEAKER_00] you are going to the intercessory groups,
[SPEAKER_01] and praying,
[SPEAKER_00] then should you have personal prayer?
[SPEAKER_00] Yes or no?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] Because,
[SPEAKER_00] in the intercession ministry,
[SPEAKER_01] we are serving the Lord.
[SPEAKER_00] In the intercession ministry,
[SPEAKER_00] we are going out,
[SPEAKER_01] and ministering,
[SPEAKER_00] for doing that ministry,
[SPEAKER_01] we need empowerment.
[SPEAKER_01] We need to be recharged.
[SPEAKER_00] We need to be equipped.
[SPEAKER_01] For that, we need personal prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] Again,
[SPEAKER_00] I am referring to
[SPEAKER_00] St. John Mary Vianney.
[SPEAKER_00] As the biographer says,
[SPEAKER_01] he made the church his home.
[SPEAKER_00] He used to be spending time in prayer,
[SPEAKER_00] right from 4 am in the morning,
[SPEAKER_01] till very late in the night.
[SPEAKER_00] So, he was all the time in prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] as a person of prayer,
[SPEAKER_00] as a man of prayer,
[SPEAKER_01] he could do mighty things.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you and I,
[SPEAKER_00] as intercessors,
[SPEAKER_01] can do mighty things,
[SPEAKER_00] if we are men and women of prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] The personal prayer for an intercessor is like,
[SPEAKER_00] I don't know if you can translate that,
[SPEAKER_00] what we call the umbilical cord,
[SPEAKER_00] which is,
[SPEAKER_00] you know,
[SPEAKER_00] the cord that connects the baby with the mother.
[SPEAKER_01] You know,
[SPEAKER_00] when the mother is,
[SPEAKER_01] the baby is in the womb of the mother,
[SPEAKER_00] for nine months the baby lives,
[SPEAKER_01] but we know that the baby doesn't eat or drink anything,
[SPEAKER_00] but the baby is being supplied food,
[SPEAKER_00] through the umbilical cord.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] our personal prayer is something like this,
[SPEAKER_01] that we are nourished and sustained and strengthened
[SPEAKER_00] through our personal prayer.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] if you and I want to be effective,
[SPEAKER_00] prophetic intercessors,
[SPEAKER_01] we need to be people of prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] John 15,
[SPEAKER_00] can somebody read that?
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] Because Maria,
[SPEAKER_00] you will be able to read?
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] John 15, 4-5.
[SPEAKER_01] 4-5.
[SPEAKER_01] Ostanite u meni i ja u vama.
[UNKNOWN] Kao što loza ne može roditi roda sama od sebe,
[UNKNOWN] ako ne ostane na čokotu,
[UNKNOWN] tako i vi ako ne ostanete u meni.
[UNKNOWN] Ja sam čokot, vi loza.
[UNKNOWN] Tko ostaje u meni i ja u njemu,
[SPEAKER_01] on rodi mnogi rod, jer bez mene ne možete ništa učiniti.
[SPEAKER_01] Ja sam čokot, vi loza.
[SPEAKER_01] Tko ostaje u meni i ja u njemu, on rodi mnogi rod, jer bez mene ne možete ništa učiniti.
[SPEAKER_01] tko ostaje u meni i ja u njemu.
[SPEAKER_00] Kao što loza ne može roditi roda sama od sebe,
[SPEAKER_01] ako ne ostane na čokotu ili trsu u drugom prijevodu,
[SPEAKER_00] tako i vi ako ne ostanete u meni.
[SPEAKER_01] Tako i vi ako ne ostanete u meni.
[SPEAKER_00] Tako i vi ako ne ostane u meni.
[SPEAKER_01] Tako i vi ako ne ostane u meni.
[SPEAKER_01] Kada zagovarate događa se određeni duhovni boj.
[SPEAKER_00] To je duhovna borba.
[SPEAKER_00] I za to trebamo duhovnu energiju.
[SPEAKER_00] Tako i vi ako ne ostane u meni.
[SPEAKER_01] A nju možemo imati jedino ako smo ljudi molitve.
[SPEAKER_01] U Izaija 40:31 imamo jedan dobar citat koji govori o tome.
[SPEAKER_00] Izaija 40:31.
[SPEAKER_00] 40:40.
[SPEAKER_00] Ja, you can read that.
[SPEAKER_01] Ima nešto vrlo posliječno o olovima.
[SPEAKER_00] Ima nešto vrlo posliječno o olovima.
[SPEAKER_00] susrešćete se s mnogim zaprekama.
[SPEAKER_00] Mnogim izazovima.
[SPEAKER_00] Tako da u tim vremenima
[SPEAKER_00] jedino što će vas spasiti je vaša osobna molitva.
[SPEAKER_01] Zato svetopismo kaže,
[SPEAKER_00] krila im rastu kao o olovima.
[SPEAKER_00] koji se uzdaju gospodina.
[SPEAKER_01] Tako da, ako nismo ljudi koji se uzdaju gospodina,
[SPEAKER_00] mi ćemo pobjeći.
[SPEAKER_00] Tako da, ako nismo ljudi koji se uzdaju gospodina,
[SPEAKER_01] mi ćemo pobjeći.
[SPEAKER_01] Tako da, ako nismo ljudi koji se uzdaju gospodina,
[SPEAKER_00] mi ćemo pobjeći.
[SPEAKER_00] Tako da, ako nismo ljudi koji se uzdaju gospodina,
[SPEAKER_00] Također Izaija kaže da oni koji se uzdaju gospodina,
[SPEAKER_01] trče i ne umaraju se.
[SPEAKER_01] Također Izaija kaže da oni koji se uzdaju gospodina,
[SPEAKER_00] Hode i ne malakšu.
[SPEAKER_01] Tako da, ako smo mi ljudi molitve,
[SPEAKER_00] mi se ne uznemirujemo i ne brinamo zbog malih problema i izazova.
[SPEAKER_00] Tako da, ako smo mi ljudi molitve,
[SPEAKER_00] tako da, ako smo mi ljudi molitve,
[SPEAKER_01] mi se ne uznemirujemo i ne brinamo zbog malih problema i izazova.
[SPEAKER_01] Tako da, ako smo mi ljudi molitve,
[SPEAKER_00] mi se ne uznemirujemo i ne brinamo zbog malih problema i izazova.
[SPEAKER_00] moramo se ojačati u osobnoj molitvi.
[SPEAKER_01] Moramo se ojačati u osobnoj molitvi.
[SPEAKER_01] nekada prije zagovarao sam.
[SPEAKER_01] U isto vrijeme imao sam vrlo mnogo odgovornosti.
[SPEAKER_00] Bio sam obiteljski čovjek s djecem i ženom.
[SPEAKER_01] imao sam puno radno vrijeme u parlamentu Indije.
[SPEAKER_00] Imao sam puno radno vrijeme u parlamentu Indije.
[SPEAKER_00] I za sve to imao sam i voditeljsku odgovornost.
[SPEAKER_01] Bio sam nacionalni koordinator obnove u Indiji.
[SPEAKER_01] Imao sam na međunarodnoj razini također neke odgovornosti.
[SPEAKER_00] odgovornosti.
[SPEAKER_00] Dakle, izazov pred kojim sam se našao,
[SPEAKER_01] bilo je kako ću naći vremena za osobnu molitu.
[SPEAKER_00] U sve stvarima koje vam gospodin stavi na leđa, ne dodaje vam više vremena.
[SPEAKER_01] dan i dalje ostane 24 sata.
[SPEAKER_01] U vrijeme kada sam imao najviše obveza,
[SPEAKER_01] to je bilo pri otprilike osam godina,
[SPEAKER_01] stvarno sam mučio tražeći vrijeme da sjednem i imam osobnu molitu.
[SPEAKER_01] Zato što sam svakog dana ustajao ujutro i odmah imao sto stvari koje sam trebao obaviti.
[SPEAKER_00] i onda sam pomislio: "Oke, ostavit ću osobnu molitvu za na večer."
[SPEAKER_00] sve stvari u učinu i odmah imao na učinu razne učinu,
[SPEAKER_00] učinu učinu na učinu,
[SPEAKER_00] da sam učinu učinu učinu za obnovu.
[SPEAKER_01] U tada tako kasno,
[SPEAKER_00] kad bi došao učinu učinu,
[SPEAKER_00] da sjednem i molim.
[SPEAKER_01] i ubrzo sam shvatio da ne pronalazim vremena za osobnu molitvu.
[SPEAKER_01] Ubrzo sam shvatio da ne pronalazim vremena za osobnu molitvu.
[SPEAKER_00] Nastavio sam dalje sa svojim ostalim obavezama.
[SPEAKER_00] Bio sam voditelj,
[SPEAKER_00] činio sam mnoge stvari,
[SPEAKER_00] i nastavio sam raditi u uredu,
[SPEAKER_00] jedan dan pročitao sam jedan kratki citat Svetog Ivana Krizosoma.
[SPEAKER_00] Znate,
[SPEAKER_00] sada je učinje učinu
[SPEAKER_00] učinu od svetog Ivana Krizosoma.
[SPEAKER_01] neke situacije koje ima neki citat iz Svetog pisma,
[SPEAKER_01] ili neka rečenica Sveca stvarno dotaknu.
[SPEAKER_00] I ovaj citat koji ću vam sada reći,
[SPEAKER_00] je u meni u mom srcu eksplodirao kao bomba.
[SPEAKER_01] A ovo je bio taj citat:
[SPEAKER_00] A ovo je bio taj citat:
[SPEAKER_00] A fish taken out of water
[SPEAKER_00] does not live,
[SPEAKER_00] it dies.
[SPEAKER_00] So will the man
[SPEAKER_00] who does not have personal prayer
[SPEAKER_00] he cannot live long,
[SPEAKER_01] he will die.
[SPEAKER_00] So a fish cannot live without water,
[SPEAKER_00] the same way
[SPEAKER_00] a man without personal prayer
[SPEAKER_00] cannot live
[SPEAKER_01] but will die.
[SPEAKER_00] so it sounded like a,
[SPEAKER_00] you know,
[SPEAKER_00] sounded like a bomb
[SPEAKER_00] exploding within me.
[SPEAKER_01] That's the time
[SPEAKER_00] the Lord really spoke to me
[SPEAKER_01] telling that
[SPEAKER_00] you are not going to live for long.
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe physically I would live
[SPEAKER_00] but spiritually I cannot sustain
[SPEAKER_00] that I am not doing the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00] The Lord convicted me
[SPEAKER_01] but the problem before me was
[SPEAKER_01] where do I find time.
[SPEAKER_01] I felt very guilty
[SPEAKER_00] that I was
[SPEAKER_00] neglecting my personal prayer.
[SPEAKER_01] So I went before the Lord,
[SPEAKER_00] I sat and cried before the Lord.
[SPEAKER_01] I told the Lord,
[SPEAKER_00] Lord what shall I do?
[SPEAKER_00] I want to spend time in personal prayer
[SPEAKER_00] but there is so much of demand on my time
[SPEAKER_01] that I am really not able to find the time.
[SPEAKER_00] And that's the day the Lord spoke to me something.
[SPEAKER_01] The Lord said,
[SPEAKER_01] in all your life
[SPEAKER_00] was there a day
[SPEAKER_01] was there a day
[SPEAKER_00] when you did not eat food for your body
[SPEAKER_00] because you did not have time.
[SPEAKER_00] and that was very true in my life.
[SPEAKER_01] Unless I decided to fast,
[SPEAKER_01] I would definitely eat my food.
[SPEAKER_00] I will definitely eat my food.
[SPEAKER_00] I will repeat that.
[SPEAKER_01] In all your life
[SPEAKER_01] was there any day
[SPEAKER_00] when you did not eat food for your body
[SPEAKER_01] because you did not have time.
[SPEAKER_00] And that was very true in my life.
[SPEAKER_01] and that was very true in my life.
[SPEAKER_00] Unless I decided to fast,
[SPEAKER_00] I would definitely eat my food.
[SPEAKER_00] Because I realized that I cannot live
[SPEAKER_00] without food for my body.
[SPEAKER_01] And maybe it may be late by one or two hours,
[SPEAKER_01] but if I am hungry,
[SPEAKER_00] I will definitely eat my food.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] I realized that what is lacking in me
[SPEAKER_00] is this conviction
[SPEAKER_01] that I cannot live spiritually
[SPEAKER_00] unless I have food for my spirit,
[SPEAKER_00] for my soul.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] that day,
[SPEAKER_01] I decided that whatever I may do,
[SPEAKER_00] I will definitely try to find time
[SPEAKER_01] for personal prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] Because I need food for my soul.
[SPEAKER_00] Now,
[SPEAKER_00] when we used to travel to Rome
[SPEAKER_01] for meetings,
[SPEAKER_00] we used to stay mostly in some hotels.
[SPEAKER_00] so,
[SPEAKER_00] in Rome,
[SPEAKER_00] when you have the lunch,
[SPEAKER_00] when you have lunch or dinner,
[SPEAKER_00] they serve you four courses.
[SPEAKER_00] the first,
[SPEAKER_00] maybe salad,
[SPEAKER_01] then they serve,
[SPEAKER_00] the first is soup,
[SPEAKER_00] then they serve you salad,
[SPEAKER_00] then they serve you the meat,
[SPEAKER_00] then they serve you the sweet dish,
[SPEAKER_01] so,
[SPEAKER_00] every time they change your plate.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] it takes something like,
[SPEAKER_00] one hour, fifteen minutes for you to have your lunch.
[SPEAKER_01] since I am not accustomed to spending so much time for eating,
[SPEAKER_00] once I suggested to the council,
[SPEAKER_00] why not we ask the hotel people to keep everything here,
[SPEAKER_01] so that we can take and eat and save our time.
[SPEAKER_00] but the hotel people refused,
[UNKNOWN] they said,
[SPEAKER_00] no,
[SPEAKER_01] we want to serve you hot.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] that day,
[SPEAKER_00] I calculated when I am in Rome,
[SPEAKER_00] how much time do I spend
[SPEAKER_00] for eating food for my body?
[SPEAKER_01] I realized I am spending more than three hours a day.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I am saying that I don't have one hour to spend with the Lord.
[SPEAKER_01] that was a matter of my own personal conviction.
[SPEAKER_00] For me to realize that how important it is for me to spend time with the Lord
[SPEAKER_00] if I have to serve the Lord.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] as intercessors,
[SPEAKER_00] we really need to spend time with the Lord.
[SPEAKER_00] And only that will sustain us and strengthen us for intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] Along with that is also reading God's word.
[SPEAKER_01] In Ezekiel chapter 3 we see,
[SPEAKER_01] the Lord puts God's word
[SPEAKER_00] in the mouth of Ezekiel.
[SPEAKER_01] and it says that it tasted sweet.
[SPEAKER_01] But,
[SPEAKER_00] that is what strengthened Ezekiel
[SPEAKER_00] when he had to prophesy
[SPEAKER_00] in the valley of dry wounds.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] we need to be people who read God's word
[SPEAKER_00] and study God's word.
[SPEAKER_01] should be people who read and read God's word.
[SPEAKER_00] That,
[SPEAKER_00] again,
[SPEAKER_00] strengthens us for the battle.
[SPEAKER_01] That,
[SPEAKER_00] again,
[SPEAKER_00] gives us that power
[SPEAKER_00] to prophesy as Ezekiel did
[SPEAKER_00] in chapter 37.
[SPEAKER_00] 37.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_01] when Ezekiel prophesied to the dry wounds,
[SPEAKER_00] we see that the dry wounds
[SPEAKER_00] really stood up as humans.
[SPEAKER_01] and humans.
[SPEAKER_01] So,
[SPEAKER_00] let us be people
[SPEAKER_00] who spend time before the Lord
[SPEAKER_00] in prayer
[SPEAKER_00] and also read God's word
[SPEAKER_00] to be effective in the sacers.
[SPEAKER_01] the next quality of an intercessor
[SPEAKER_00] is to be a lover of the cross.
[SPEAKER_01] I gave you a detailed teaching on this
[SPEAKER_00] during the training.
[SPEAKER_00] If you look at the life of Saint John Mary Vianney,
[SPEAKER_00] he really led a life of abstinence
[SPEAKER_00] and sacrifices.
[SPEAKER_01] I would say,
[SPEAKER_00] almost all his life was a fast,
[SPEAKER_00] fast.
[SPEAKER_00] He did not even eat the essentials
[SPEAKER_00] for his body.
[SPEAKER_01] As intercessors,
[SPEAKER_00] we participate
[SPEAKER_00] in the salvation of Jesus.
[SPEAKER_00] we continue the work of salvation
[SPEAKER_00] that Jesus does.
[SPEAKER_01] In that process,
[SPEAKER_00] we do suffer with Jesus.
[SPEAKER_01] Since you are a grown-up group,
[SPEAKER_00] I also like to mention to you
[SPEAKER_00] that sometimes
[SPEAKER_00] we need to,
[SPEAKER_00] that Jesus calls us to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01] That is,
[SPEAKER_00] we become the victim soul.
[SPEAKER_00] in the lives of mystics.
[SPEAKER_00] It is done,
[SPEAKER_01] normally,
[SPEAKER_01] in the lives of mystics.
[SPEAKER_00] Mystics are the ones
[SPEAKER_00] who suffer
[SPEAKER_00] for the salvation of souls.
[SPEAKER_00] we can find examples of saints.
[SPEAKER_01] We have examples of Saint Margaret Mary Alacoc.
[SPEAKER_01] of Saint Gemma Galgani,
[SPEAKER_00] who lived only 25 years,
[SPEAKER_00] but she suffered so much.
[SPEAKER_00] that.
[SPEAKER_00] But this is a special calling.
[SPEAKER_00] Not all of you will be called to do this.
[SPEAKER_00] So you don't know how to be scared of this.
[SPEAKER_00] But why I am mentioning is,
[SPEAKER_01] we find some people
[SPEAKER_00] who have this special calling to suffer
[SPEAKER_00] and through their suffering
[SPEAKER_00] to save souls.
[SPEAKER_01] There is something beautiful
[SPEAKER_00] that Saint Catherine of Siena said.
[SPEAKER_01] She said,
[SPEAKER_00] "In the midst of my sufferings,
[SPEAKER_00] I smell the fragrance of the rose,
[SPEAKER_00] which is blossoming."
[SPEAKER_00] So, as she was suffering,
[SPEAKER_01] she says,
[SPEAKER_00] "In that suffering,
[SPEAKER_00] I can smell the fragrance of the rose
[SPEAKER_00] that is blossoming."
[SPEAKER_00] especially the saints
[SPEAKER_00] have realized that
[SPEAKER_00] through their sufferings,
[SPEAKER_01] they are able to win over
[SPEAKER_00] many souls.
[SPEAKER_01] So there may be times
[SPEAKER_00] when we too have to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01] And I will,
[SPEAKER_00] in my second talk,
[SPEAKER_00] I will also be speaking to you
[SPEAKER_00] a little more about spiritual warfare.
[SPEAKER_01] Even the spiritual battle
[SPEAKER_00] is not very easy.
[SPEAKER_01] A number of saints
[SPEAKER_00] in their battle
[SPEAKER_00] had to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01] And it was through their sufferings
[SPEAKER_00] that they were winning over souls
[SPEAKER_00] for Jesus.
[SPEAKER_00] this happened
[SPEAKER_00] in the life of Padre Pio,
[SPEAKER_01] this happened
[SPEAKER_00] in the life of Saint Teresa of Avila,
[SPEAKER_00] in the life of Saint John of the Cross,
[SPEAKER_00] and many other saints.
[SPEAKER_00] So they all had to undergo
[SPEAKER_00] some suffering
[SPEAKER_00] or the other.
[SPEAKER_00] and there are times
[SPEAKER_00] when they had
[SPEAKER_00] even faced
[SPEAKER_00] physical battles
[SPEAKER_00] with Satan.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, these are not meant
[SPEAKER_00] for ordinary people.
[SPEAKER_01] These are circumstances
[SPEAKER_00] when you grow holy
[SPEAKER_01] and when the Lord
[SPEAKER_00] uses you
[SPEAKER_00] for much greater things,
[SPEAKER_01] to win over many souls
[SPEAKER_00] for Jesus,
[SPEAKER_01] that's the time
[SPEAKER_00] when the Lord
[SPEAKER_00] specially calls us
[SPEAKER_00] for this.
[SPEAKER_01] that.
[SPEAKER_01] But it is good for us
[SPEAKER_00] to know this
[SPEAKER_01] because sometimes
[SPEAKER_00] this question mark
[SPEAKER_00] comes in our mind
[SPEAKER_01] when we face hardships
[SPEAKER_00] and challenges
[SPEAKER_01] as we grow
[SPEAKER_00] in the intercession ministry.
[SPEAKER_01] I am saying this also
[SPEAKER_00] because
[SPEAKER_00] some people
[SPEAKER_00] asked me this question
[SPEAKER_01] why these sufferings
[SPEAKER_00] come
[SPEAKER_00] when we intercede.
[SPEAKER_01] We become
[SPEAKER_00] the victim souls
[SPEAKER_00] for the salvation
[SPEAKER_00] of others.
[SPEAKER_00] and it is through this
[SPEAKER_00] that we are able
[SPEAKER_00] to win many souls
[SPEAKER_00] for Jesus.
[SPEAKER_01] Another speciality
[SPEAKER_00] that we find
[SPEAKER_00] in St. John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_00] is this
[SPEAKER_01] that he was
[SPEAKER_00] very gifted.
[SPEAKER_00] he had the gifts
[SPEAKER_00] and charisms
[SPEAKER_00] of the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_01] When people
[SPEAKER_00] used to go
[SPEAKER_00] for confession
[SPEAKER_00] to St. John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_01] and they would not
[SPEAKER_00] disclose their sins
[SPEAKER_01] to him
[SPEAKER_01] maybe deliberately
[SPEAKER_01] or because
[SPEAKER_00] they have forgotten this
[SPEAKER_01] Father John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_00] would point out
[SPEAKER_00] their sins
[SPEAKER_00] to them.
[SPEAKER_01] Because
[SPEAKER_00] he was using
[SPEAKER_00] the gift
[SPEAKER_00] of word of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01] Once
[SPEAKER_00] there was a lady
[SPEAKER_00] who was
[SPEAKER_00] sitting
[SPEAKER_00] in a pew
[SPEAKER_00] in the church
[SPEAKER_00] and crying.
[SPEAKER_01] St. John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_00] was hearing
[SPEAKER_00] confessions
[SPEAKER_00] in the confessional
[SPEAKER_01] in the church
[SPEAKER_01] so
[SPEAKER_01] sitting there
[SPEAKER_00] he had
[UNKNOWN] the word
[SPEAKER_00] of knowledge
[UNKNOWN] about this
[SPEAKER_00] lady.
[SPEAKER_01] So
[SPEAKER_00] he got off
[SPEAKER_00] from the confessional
[SPEAKER_00] and came
[SPEAKER_01] and sat near her.
[SPEAKER_01] He asked her
[SPEAKER_01] "Why are you crying?"
[SPEAKER_01] She said
[SPEAKER_00] "I am crying
[SPEAKER_00] because
[SPEAKER_00] all my life
[SPEAKER_00] I have been praying
[SPEAKER_00] for the conversion
[SPEAKER_00] of my husband."
[SPEAKER_01] "Plače"
[SPEAKER_01] "But
[SPEAKER_00] a week ago
[SPEAKER_00] he jumped
[SPEAKER_00] from the bridge
[SPEAKER_00] into the river
[SPEAKER_00] and committed suicide."
[SPEAKER_00] "I am crying
[SPEAKER_01] because
[SPEAKER_01] all my prayers
[SPEAKER_01] have gone waste."
[SPEAKER_00] "I am crying
[SPEAKER_00] because
[SPEAKER_00] all my prayers
[SPEAKER_01] have gone waste."
[SPEAKER_00] But
[SPEAKER_00] John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_01] told her
[SPEAKER_01] "Your prayers
[SPEAKER_01] are not
[SPEAKER_00] wasted."
[SPEAKER_01] from the time
[SPEAKER_00] he jumped
[SPEAKER_00] from the bridge
[SPEAKER_01] and
[SPEAKER_00] before
[SPEAKER_00] he touched
[SPEAKER_00] the water
[SPEAKER_01] he had
[SPEAKER_00] his conversion
[SPEAKER_00] experience.
[SPEAKER_01] Conversion
[SPEAKER_00] does not need
[SPEAKER_00] a day
[SPEAKER_01] or a month.
[SPEAKER_01] It takes
[SPEAKER_00] a moment.
[SPEAKER_01] So
[SPEAKER_00] St. John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_00] had
[SPEAKER_00] these gifts
[SPEAKER_00] that he used
[SPEAKER_00] for his ministry.
[SPEAKER_01] in five minutes.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, so
[SPEAKER_00] one of the gifts
[SPEAKER_00] that
[SPEAKER_00] I mean
[SPEAKER_00] there are
[SPEAKER_00] a number of gifts
[SPEAKER_00] that
[SPEAKER_00] John Mariviani
[SPEAKER_00] used.
[SPEAKER_01] So
[SPEAKER_00] when we look
[SPEAKER_00] at the heart
[SPEAKER_01] of an intercessor
[SPEAKER_01] we too
[SPEAKER_00] need
[SPEAKER_00] these
[SPEAKER_01] charisms
[SPEAKER_00] especially
[SPEAKER_00] for
[SPEAKER_01] prophetic
[SPEAKER_01] intercession.
[UNKNOWN] So
[SPEAKER_00] when I was speaking
[SPEAKER_00] to you
[UNKNOWN] about
[SPEAKER_00] prophetic
[SPEAKER_00] intercession
[SPEAKER_01] and
[SPEAKER_00] when we had
[SPEAKER_00] the workshops
[UNKNOWN] on
[SPEAKER_00] prophetic
[SPEAKER_00] intercession
[SPEAKER_01] and
[SPEAKER_01] the Holy Spirit
[SPEAKER_00] we were using
[SPEAKER_00] these gifts
[SPEAKER_00] and charisms
[SPEAKER_00] of the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_01] That really helps us
[SPEAKER_00] to intercede
[SPEAKER_00] according to
[SPEAKER_01] God's will.
[SPEAKER_00] it helps us
[SPEAKER_00] to discern
[SPEAKER_00] what is moving
[SPEAKER_00] in the heart
[SPEAKER_00] of Jesus.
[SPEAKER_01] It helps us
[SPEAKER_00] to intercede
[SPEAKER_00] prophetically.
[SPEAKER_01] And when we
[UNKNOWN] intercede
[SPEAKER_00] prophetically
[SPEAKER_01] we see that
[SPEAKER_00] there are
[SPEAKER_00] very very
[SPEAKER_00] very fast
[SPEAKER_00] effects
[SPEAKER_00] to our
[SPEAKER_01] intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] Our
[SPEAKER_00] prayers are
[SPEAKER_01] answered.
[SPEAKER_00] We see
[SPEAKER_00] a lot of miracles
[SPEAKER_01] happening.
[SPEAKER_00] So for this
[SPEAKER_00] we need to use
[SPEAKER_00] the gifts and charisms
[SPEAKER_00] of the Holy Spirit.
[SPEAKER_01] So as people
[SPEAKER_00] with
[SPEAKER_00] the heart
[SPEAKER_00] of an intercessor
[SPEAKER_01] we need to pray
[SPEAKER_00] for
[SPEAKER_00] the reception
[SPEAKER_01] of these charisms.
[SPEAKER_01] And if
[SPEAKER_00] we have these charisms
[SPEAKER_00] we need to grow
[SPEAKER_01] in these charisms.
[SPEAKER_00] And if you do not
[SPEAKER_00] have these charisms
[SPEAKER_00] then we need to pray
[SPEAKER_00] that we receive
[SPEAKER_00] these gifts.
[SPEAKER_01] Especially
[SPEAKER_00] the gifts
[SPEAKER_00] of
[SPEAKER_00] tongues.
[SPEAKER_01] The gift of
[SPEAKER_00] prophecy.
[SPEAKER_00] word of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00] The gift of
[SPEAKER_00] word of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01] These are
[SPEAKER_00] some of the gifts
[SPEAKER_00] that really
[SPEAKER_00] helps us
[SPEAKER_00] in our intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] the gift of
[SPEAKER_01] prayer.
[SPEAKER_00] So let us
[SPEAKER_00] stand.
[SPEAKER_00] It's time for
[SPEAKER_00] rosary.
[SPEAKER_00] And we
[SPEAKER_00] want to just pray
[SPEAKER_00] before we
[SPEAKER_00] conclude this talk.
[SPEAKER_00] it was a short
[SPEAKER_00] session
[SPEAKER_00] to see the heart
[SPEAKER_00] of the intercessor.
[SPEAKER_01] And we took
[SPEAKER_00] St. John
[SPEAKER_00] Mary Vianney
[SPEAKER_00] as the model
[SPEAKER_00] for intercessors.
[SPEAKER_00] St. John
[SPEAKER_00] Mary Vianney
[SPEAKER_00] achieved very good results
[SPEAKER_01] through his intercession.
[SPEAKER_01] Because
[SPEAKER_00] he was a man of love and compassion.
[SPEAKER_00] Because
[SPEAKER_01] he was humble.
[SPEAKER_00] because he led a very holy life.
[SPEAKER_01] Because
[SPEAKER_00] he endured a lot of sufferings.
[SPEAKER_00] he used the charisms.
[SPEAKER_00] Let us also ask the Lord to give us these qualities of the intercessor.
[SPEAKER_00] we need to have an intercessor's heart.
[SPEAKER_01] We also saw
[SPEAKER_00] during our teachings
[SPEAKER_00] during the training
[SPEAKER_00] that we need to be compassionate and loving.
[SPEAKER_00] we need to be people of faith.
[SPEAKER_01] We need to be people
[SPEAKER_00] who reach out to others.
[SPEAKER_00] Let us ask the Lord for these qualities of the intercessor.
[SPEAKER_01] Let us ask Jesus to give us his own heart.
[SPEAKER_01] Let us ask Jesus to share with us the burdens of his heart.
[SPEAKER_01] We just want to recite the Hail Mary together.
[SPEAKER_00] Asking also for the intercession of our Blessed Mother.
[SPEAKER_01] Who had an intercessor's heart.
[SPEAKER_00] Who is the most powerful intercessor among the human beings.
[SPEAKER_00] that each one of us may receive an intercessor's heart.
[SPEAKER_01] We recite the Hail Mary together.
[SPEAKER_00] We will recite the Hail Mary together.
[SPEAKER_01] We will recite the Hail Mary together.