[SPEAKER_01] One of the companies that we're working with is in the travel space, which is about a $2 trillion market.
[SPEAKER_01] Now, that's an opportunity to understand what you're going to build this company into, and you can start to build the roadmap to get there.
[SPEAKER_01] Clientele and customers that want to continually recommend your service or your product to other people, you're reducing your customer acquisition costs dramatically.
[SPEAKER_01] What do you actually want to do with this company? Because a lot of founders, they're in build mode.
[SPEAKER_01] They haven't had the chance to think, what do I actually want to build this into?
[SPEAKER_01] Do I want to exit with $5 million, go do it again? Do I want to exit with $20 million, be able to go retire, chill on a beach in Montenegro?
[SPEAKER_01] How much equity you have will ultimately reduce how much you're going to get at exit.
[SPEAKER_01] So, the entrepreneurship journey and the founder journey is full of peaks and valleys.
[SPEAKER_00] Bitcoin. Why is Bitcoin overrated?
[SPEAKER_00] Hello, everyone. Welcome to a new episode of podcast Horizons of Leadership.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm your host, Filip Djurovic, and today we're recording from Web Summit in Vancouver, one of the most exciting gatherings of innovation and tech.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm honored to be joined by Brandon Spitt, VP of growth at Get Fresh Ventures.
[SPEAKER_00] Brandon has helped over 60 early stage startups close more than $25 million in funding and generate $150 million in revenue.
[SPEAKER_00] Today, we're driving into startup growth, fundraising, and what really makes the difference between early traction and long-term success.
[SPEAKER_00] Brandon, welcome to the show.
[SPEAKER_00] Awesome. Thank you for having me, Phil. Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you for joining.
[SPEAKER_00] Brandon, in one of the articles I read about you is that you went from moving loans at 11 years old to helping startup raise the insane numbers that we mentioned.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you briefly walk us through that journey and introduce yourself a bit more to the audience?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely. Yeah. So, very uncommon. I get this question a lot.
[SPEAKER_01] How did you end up in VC? And I don't have a traditional answer.
[SPEAKER_01] I went into finance and then I got into VC or I went into big consulting and got into VC.
[SPEAKER_01] For me, I didn't have much business exposure growing up.
[SPEAKER_01] Both my parents were blue collar.
[SPEAKER_01] My dad's a firefighter and my mom was a sheriff.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I really didn't get much exposure from business growing up.
[SPEAKER_01] But I always had that work ethic in me.
[SPEAKER_01] So, starting by cutting lawns at 11 years old, it started with family members.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I started going door to door, selling those services and getting my feet wet with entrepreneurship that way.
[SPEAKER_01] So, that took me through high school and graduated, ended up in hospitality.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I was running restaurants.
[SPEAKER_01] I was a sommelier at one point as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I got my business exposure that way.
[SPEAKER_01] That took me back to university where I was able to secure a degree in business administration and commerce.
[SPEAKER_01] So, that was a global supply chain on logistics management.
[SPEAKER_01] And through that, I started as an intern at GetFresh Ventures.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's where my journey kind of started from there.
[SPEAKER_01] And we can, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you started bringing, like, your career from interposition to all the way to VP position.
[SPEAKER_00] Yes.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] Maybe one interesting thing to mention as well is that in the high school, you were playing sports.
[SPEAKER_00] So, probably from there, you as well catch that discipline and to be consistent, to work hard.
[SPEAKER_00] Definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] Growing up, playing basketball and getting into martial arts, which got to teach me that motivation and sticking with something until the end.
[SPEAKER_00] Perfect.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, if we are going now to touch a bit on the startup scene.
[SPEAKER_00] So, you work with thousands of startups.
[SPEAKER_00] Probably, just today, you talked more than 50 startups.
[SPEAKER_00] When a founder first pitched you, like, startup idea, what's the something that you're looking for there?
[SPEAKER_00] What are you listening to?
[SPEAKER_00] Are there any details, like, you want to catch in order to see if the idea is going to be successful or not?
[SPEAKER_01] That's a great question.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] There's two main things that I'm looking for.
[SPEAKER_01] And I actually just gave this feedback earlier today, which was, what is the actual business impact?
[SPEAKER_01] What's the economic impact based on what you want to do in the market?
[SPEAKER_01] How are we going to make money?
[SPEAKER_01] Or how is the investor going to get their investment back, ideally with a high return?
[SPEAKER_01] Additionally, on the other side, I'm looking at, do you have a market that is captivated?
[SPEAKER_01] Do they care enough to buy your product and not even just buy it once, but buy it en masse?
[SPEAKER_01] Are they going to stay retained and continue to buy your product?
[SPEAKER_01] Or is it just going to be the one time?
[SPEAKER_01] How are we going to continually expand that market?
[SPEAKER_00] So, most important thing, in your opinion, would be kind of markets.
[SPEAKER_00] In which market they are operating and how big opportunity is there in the markets?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] At times, it depends on the business that they want to build.
[SPEAKER_01] I like to start my conversations with founders being, hey, what do you actually want to do with this company?
[SPEAKER_01] Because a lot of founders are, they're in build mode.
[SPEAKER_01] They haven't had the chance to think, what do I actually want to build this into?
[SPEAKER_01] Do I want to exit with $5 million, go do it again?
[SPEAKER_01] Do I want to exit with $20 million, be able to go retire, chill on a beach in Montenegro?
[SPEAKER_01] Or do they want to swing for the fences and go for the, be the next Uber, be the next WeWork and such?
[SPEAKER_01] Which may be a bad example on that one.
[SPEAKER_01] But based on that, we can start to determine, well, what is the market size that we need to be able to get that exit that they want to have, right?
[SPEAKER_01] If you tell me you want to exit with $20 million, but the market size is not going to be able to allow that, perhaps we need to identify a different market segment that will allow them to achieve that exit that they want to get to.
[SPEAKER_01] But what is more important is less of the market size, but understanding the specific persona within that market that is going to buy that on a repeatable way.
[SPEAKER_00] So basically understanding the customer, understanding your customer and his wants.
[SPEAKER_00] Definitely.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Understanding their wants and being able to speak their language as well.
[SPEAKER_01] That's why I love talking to founders that have specific domain experience or they have done an extreme amount of research onto the market that they're targeting.
[SPEAKER_01] Instead of just building in a bubble and assuming that these are the things that their persona are going to want, they are actively in conversations with these customers that they want to sell to.
[SPEAKER_00] What do you think about passion?
[SPEAKER_00] Like in the way, do founders need to be very passionate about it?
[SPEAKER_00] And if they're a passion that success rates is higher or you have a different opinion on it?
[SPEAKER_01] It's a great question.
[SPEAKER_01] I think passion is something that is extremely important as long as it can sustain throughout the journey as well.
[SPEAKER_01] Passion at the beginning may help to start you off, but the entrepreneurship journey and the founder journey is full of peaks and valleys.
[SPEAKER_01] And having that motivation and that need to want to have that is definitely a key piece.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, very interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] What about, let's say, we have a good idea.
[SPEAKER_00] We have good market.
[SPEAKER_00] Market is open for us.
[SPEAKER_00] We understand our customer.
[SPEAKER_00] What are some, like, next steps?
[SPEAKER_00] Do we think in a way, okay, this is working.
[SPEAKER_00] I need one million to, or two million or 10 million to increase my business to get it rolling even more, or I need to bootstrap and go in the direction that, okay, we're going slowly, but we are alone, let's say.
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] I think it's very important to go back to that question of what do we want to do with this company, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Because that's going to feed the decision making on whether you raise and when you raise and how much you raise as well.
[SPEAKER_01] If you can verify your market and be able to start generating your early revenue by only getting around, you know, $50,000 to $100,000 to be able to get to that stage where you're generating your first revenue versus having to raise $1 million, diluting yourself to get to that first stage of revenue.
[SPEAKER_01] But reducing how much equity you have will ultimately reduce how much you're going to get at exit.
[SPEAKER_01] So maybe you're not going to be on a beach in the Caribbean and you might have to settle for a beach, a sandy beach in Vancouver.
[SPEAKER_01] So not bad, though.
[SPEAKER_00] Let's check on the other side.
[SPEAKER_00] What does, in your opinion, like a venture-ready startup look like?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] Venture-ready startup.
[SPEAKER_01] So the venture scene from what I've seen over the past four and a half years is they're looking for companies that have that massive market that we're talking about where usually it's at least a billion plus, ideally even larger.
[SPEAKER_01] I know one of the companies that we're working with is in the travel space, which is about a $2 trillion market.
[SPEAKER_01] Now that's an opportunity where if you're coming in and generating any kind of revenue, let's say $100,000 or even a couple million, there is still room to expand because that market size is just so massive that even a sliver of that is going to be enough to generate the returns that they want to achieve.
[SPEAKER_01] And then additionally, so that's just on the market size.
[SPEAKER_01] And then additionally from there is they're going to care about those customers that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01] Do they, they'll want to have interviews with the customers that are actually buying the product that you're selling, product or service that you're selling.
[SPEAKER_01] And they'll want to understand, are they buying, what reasons are they buying this for?
[SPEAKER_01] And are they going to continue to buy that?
[SPEAKER_01] So in determining that, they're going to start to see all the metrics that you're tracking.
[SPEAKER_01] So in addition to just top line revenue, they're also going to be looking at, okay, what is our retention rate, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Is that, is it high enough that we can verify that they're not just buying it once and then churning?
[SPEAKER_01] Or are they continuing to buy this to the point where we're never going to lose them as a customer and their lifetime value is just massive?
[SPEAKER_00] That's increasing.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, so definitely going to get very metrics driven at the seed to series A level.
[SPEAKER_01] Pre-seed, you can definitely get away with some earlier traction.
[SPEAKER_01] But yeah, definitely at that seed to series A is where you start to know your numbers.
[SPEAKER_00] What are some common mistakes that you have seen in your journey working with startups when they want to scale?
[SPEAKER_00] Is it exactly this that they get funding and that they don't even think what are they going to do with it?
[SPEAKER_00] Or there are some different kind of paths that they're taking and that they're doing wrong in a way?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Depending, definitely I'll start, I'll move to the scale side, but I'll go back to kind of even the early stage is something I was touching on earlier,
[SPEAKER_01] which is building in a bubble, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Making sure that they're actively in conversations with their customers.
[SPEAKER_01] Not even just at that early stage, but also when you get to that scale stage.
[SPEAKER_01] At that scale stage, we start to understand and want to build almost a customer advisory board
[SPEAKER_01] is usually a very tactical way of implementing a lot of the feedback that you're getting from your customers
[SPEAKER_01] and making sure that you're pivoting and building your product roadmap based on the exact things that your customers,
[SPEAKER_01] who are the ones buying your product en masse, that they want and want to continue to see.
[SPEAKER_01] So I keep coming back to knowing your market and having that deep conversation with them,
[SPEAKER_01] but I think that's a very key component when it comes to scaling that startup and understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01] But also on the human side, making sure that you have the right people in the right seats, right?
[SPEAKER_01] If you have a thing that I was chatting with a founder with last week that I think could be beneficial
[SPEAKER_01] is build your first pitch deck, not for an investor.
[SPEAKER_01] Build that first pitch deck for yourself and your founding team.
[SPEAKER_01] If you can't convince yourself to invest in your time and your energy into that company,
[SPEAKER_01] then you may need to pivot or you may need to re-evaluate why you're doing this.
[SPEAKER_01] Because if you can't convince yourself or the rest of your team to invest in this, why would an investor?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Time is kind of the most valuable asset, right?
[SPEAKER_00] And it's not something that we can get back.
[SPEAKER_00] But money, money comes back.
[SPEAKER_01] If you find a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] If you find a way to get that.
[SPEAKER_01] If I find a way, I'll call you.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00] In your articles and in general in the articles I mentioned you, I read that you kind of like that word repeatable revenue.
[SPEAKER_00] And you kind of use it a lot.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you tell us how can startups shift that early traction that they get, if they get early traction, into actually repeatable revenue?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, it will definitely depend on what they're offering in the markets, whether it's something that can be repeatable.
[SPEAKER_01] But especially in the technology space, I would say about 60 to 70% of the companies we work with are B2B SaaS.
[SPEAKER_01] And a lot of the companies with that, they may not have a strategy yet on how they're going to build a recurring model associated with it.
[SPEAKER_01] And maybe it's a SaaS or a platform, whatever that may be, but building out that repeatable engine through a subscription service.
[SPEAKER_01] And even if you have to maybe sacrifice a little bit to get them on board for that, maybe it's giving the first three months free or maybe it is utilizing some interesting pricing models.
[SPEAKER_00] Giving some amount of credits, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] You know all about that.
[SPEAKER_01] So there's a lot of strategies that you can do to secure them as a user, not just for that initial few months.
[SPEAKER_01] Because, yeah, you could have a customer and have them pay monthly for the first three months, but they may churn.
[SPEAKER_01] Versus, okay, we're going to sign them up for one year and we're going to give them three months free, but you've got them for a year and you've got opportunity to retain them.
[SPEAKER_01] But that's where, you know, the departments really come in and customer success becomes a very key component because if you're giving something away for free, you have to make sure that they recognize the value.
[SPEAKER_01] Otherwise, the brain just doesn't connect the two, right?
[SPEAKER_01] They need a motivation to get on there and utilize that platform or service.
[SPEAKER_00] Definitely, very good advice.
[SPEAKER_00] I mean, to touch upon what you said, even if 9 of 20, 80 of them churns, those two can become big customers and actually bring everything back from all other losses, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, yeah, and that's where, you know, the NPS score can start to come in where they become your sales team, right?
[SPEAKER_01] If you can create clientele and customers that want to continually recommend your service or your product to other people, you're reducing your customer acquisition cost dramatically.
[SPEAKER_01] And I don't know about you, but I buy, anytime one of my friends suggests something, I take it much more serious than I would when I'm getting Instagram ads on it.
[SPEAKER_00] Of course, word of mouth.
[SPEAKER_01] Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01] That's the way we run, so.
[SPEAKER_00] Brandon, you're VP of growth at Get Fresh Ventures.
[SPEAKER_00] I would like you to tell us how do you at Get Fresh Ventures help actually startups and how do you provide them that kind of support and help them scale?
[SPEAKER_00] On the other side, before this recording, you mentioned that you operate quite different than other VCs.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you touch upon that a bit?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] We coined the term venture catalyst, and I like that term because a lot of the companies that we do chat to and explain what we do,
[SPEAKER_01] it's hard for them to pinpoint.
[SPEAKER_01] When they say, okay, it sounds like an accelerator, it also sounds like you are a VC, it's a fun terminology to use.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you repeat the term?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, venture catalyst.
[SPEAKER_00] Venture catalyst.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Is that something you invented or?
[SPEAKER_01] My CEO came up with it and, yeah, supported it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Came at it together.
[SPEAKER_01] So that is the terminology we've been using because our main goal is to catalyze growth, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And the issue, I don't know if there are certain companies that maybe aren't the right fit for venture capital, right?
[SPEAKER_01] We were chatting about that earlier on the massive market size.
[SPEAKER_01] There is an opportunity for a lot of different businesses to grow depending on what that founder's goals are.
[SPEAKER_01] Perhaps instead of becoming a venture-backed company, you want to just build a company that's going to generate you $100,000 in annual recurring revenue
[SPEAKER_01] that you're able to now do whatever else it is that you want to do.
[SPEAKER_01] And that might be your goal, but that's not going to be a good fit for venture capital.
[SPEAKER_01] So what we do is we partner with those founders and understand what those goals are and help them achieve that.
[SPEAKER_01] So, again, if they want to become a venture-backable company, we'll do the math.
[SPEAKER_01] We'll figure out whether that is possible and build them the roadmap to get there and guide them along the way.
[SPEAKER_01] So it's a lot of growth coaching, executive coaching, and growth advisory.
[SPEAKER_01] We got to that stage when I first started with the company.
[SPEAKER_01] We were doing fractional growth officer services.
[SPEAKER_01] We were an extension of the C-suite and really integrated within all the different departments within a company.
[SPEAKER_01] But we wanted to impact more companies, which is why we shifted to that advisory model.
[SPEAKER_01] But we didn't want to do it en masse.
[SPEAKER_01] We wanted to make sure that every single company we were working with, we were putting in 110% effort
[SPEAKER_01] because there is the power law that does happen in venture capital where probably 10% of the companies are going to return the investment
[SPEAKER_01] and then maybe one or two might be a unicorn while the other 90% may not make it.
[SPEAKER_01] We want to see them all succeed, right?
[SPEAKER_01] You're building a business.
[SPEAKER_01] You likely are putting in, we were chatting about that, you're never going to get time back.
[SPEAKER_01] You're putting in that time.
[SPEAKER_01] You're putting in that effort.
[SPEAKER_01] We want to make sure every founder is successful and that they are exiting with what they want to achieve with that company.
[SPEAKER_00] Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] When we talk about like you have startups that join you and want to get funding.
[SPEAKER_00] You have startups that join you and they're maybe just bootstrapping and want to help you scale.
[SPEAKER_00] You help them scale.
[SPEAKER_00] In the way, how picky are you in your portfolio?
[SPEAKER_00] In the way, do you do more like the companies that are looking for funding?
[SPEAKER_00] Or do you more go for companies that are bootstrapping?
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Both are okay and we're happy to work with both types of companies depending on what their goals are as a founding team.
[SPEAKER_01] We typically want to work with companies before they go to a fundraise because if they're coming to us and actively fundraising, we can definitely help.
[SPEAKER_01] But the real work that gets done is getting that business to the stage where we understand the business well enough to position it in the market rather than you're coming to us already positioned in the market.
[SPEAKER_01] And we now have to make some major pivots that we could have figured out three, four months prior by starting early.
[SPEAKER_00] Interesting.
[SPEAKER_00] What is maybe some advice that you would like to give to young founders that are just starting the company and that are just bringing that idea to life?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] Just do it.
[SPEAKER_01] It's a big one, of course, but understand why you want to do that as well, right?
[SPEAKER_01] I keep coming back to that of entrepreneurs are builders.
[SPEAKER_01] They're builders first, typically visionaries as well.
[SPEAKER_01] They see the eventual goal of what they want to build that company into, but that company that you're building is also your path to your net worth, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And what you want to do with that company, you need to understand what that is from the beginning because you're going to have to communicate it to investors along the way.
[SPEAKER_01] And if you don't have an exit, start planning your exit immediately.
[SPEAKER_01] Understand what you're going to build this company into and you can start to build the roadmap to get there.
[SPEAKER_01] And it might be an acquisition and for $5 million, $10 million and great, that's a great first business and great first exit.
[SPEAKER_01] Or maybe it's something different.
[SPEAKER_01] You build a lifestyle business that is going to generate you $50,000, $60,000 a year, which is not anything to knock on.
[SPEAKER_01] And that may free you up to focus on other things.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I think build, but understand why you're building so that you can stay motivated throughout that journey.
[SPEAKER_00] So, have that passion, know the market size, know the market fit, find the right market and just go for it.
[SPEAKER_00] Even if you lose, you learned a lot.
[SPEAKER_00] So, on the next stage, you probably know what mistakes not to make, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] It helps to fall down a couple times to get back up.
[SPEAKER_01] I know I've fallen down many times and I've always learned from it, right?
[SPEAKER_01] And staying open to that learning definitely makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01] But don't always just, I do want to say, don't always just push through and continue to push through.
[SPEAKER_01] Be aware.
[SPEAKER_01] Always have a mentor that you're working with that is going to guide you when it's time to truly pivot.
[SPEAKER_01] Because you can continue to be pushing down a path and I think that's great for muscle memory to learn how to roll with the punches.
[SPEAKER_01] But also, it's good to have somebody with a separate point of view that's able to say, hey, it is time for you to pivot.
[SPEAKER_01] You've done very well, but it's time for you to either pivot what you're doing right now or drop it.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's okay.
[SPEAKER_00] How important is the mentorship in the whole journey?
[SPEAKER_01] Massive.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I mean, mentorship has really driven me to where I am today.
[SPEAKER_01] If I didn't have mentors throughout my career journey, I'm not too, too sure what I'd be doing.
[SPEAKER_01] But I definitely wouldn't be at the current stage that I am in my career.
[SPEAKER_00] Can you give us some examples, maybe?
[SPEAKER_00] Definitely.
[SPEAKER_00] Where from were you taking those mentors, let's say?
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01] So, one of my key mentors, who is now a very good friend of mine, he met me while I was in hospitality.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I was bartending at the time and took a shine to me and realized that there was a skill set that I had been developing and wanted to encourage me to explore it more.
[SPEAKER_01] And that was business.
[SPEAKER_01] And I'd never considered that in the past whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01] Like I say, no exposure except like a long-distance second cousin.
[SPEAKER_01] So, for me, I'm like, this is interesting.
[SPEAKER_01] So, but through my conversations with them, they really helped open my mind up to what that really could be and what the future might be if I decided to pursue that.
[SPEAKER_01] So, in addition to opening my eyes, it was also that support system that I needed and supported me in writing my application and ultimately getting into one of the top business schools in Canada.
[SPEAKER_01] And that's mentorship definitely drove that result.
[SPEAKER_01] And throughout my journey, that's been the same way.
[SPEAKER_01] I mean, you know, we mentioned that I'm a vice president of growth, that I get fresh.
[SPEAKER_01] But when I started as an intern, right, and continually looking for opportunities to grow within the company, right, I took four or five promotions, something like that, because I just identify areas that the business needed support and I would just own that area.
[SPEAKER_01] And I continued to do that because that gave me that exposure and I would likely not have done that had I not had the mentorship and the leadership from my team as well as my mentors externally.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, usually when we say and mention mentors, people always associate it with lots of money, you need to pay lots of money to them.
[SPEAKER_00] And it's like time consuming and money consuming.
[SPEAKER_00] But actually, it's not something that you have to always pay.
[SPEAKER_00] Like, you can find mentors from lots of people around you in the way.
[SPEAKER_00] Like, I don't know, for me, for example, I'm a student, I find the mentors in my professors that are successful, that work good, and they're always there to give advice, to talk, you know, you can ask them always something.
[SPEAKER_00] Same in the company, like you find people that are on the bigger position than you that know what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_00] So you kind of mimic them, try to do it your way, you know, catch that.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's not always about money and mentorship, like paying for it.
[SPEAKER_00] You can always find it like around.
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely. I think giving back is the biggest thing, because that's what I've learned.
[SPEAKER_01] Being a mentee has driven me to become a mentor myself.
[SPEAKER_01] So any opportunity I get to mentor people that are at the earlier stages of their career or even, you know, in a certain area that I have expertise, I'm always happy to have time for them.
[SPEAKER_01] And a lot of the times it's chatting with startups.
[SPEAKER_01] Yes, we do run a service where we do, we are paid for our advisory services, but the mentorship that I'm able to give to startups is something that's honestly rewarding for myself to do and seems to help a lot of the startups as well.
[SPEAKER_01] So mentorship is a key component of that.
[SPEAKER_01] And I think every founder and honestly, every person should probably have a mentor.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] A good example of your, let's say, mentorship and everything is accepting this podcast and being so thank you very much for it.
[SPEAKER_00] 100%.
[SPEAKER_00] I would like to ask you if you have any quotes or a book or principle you live by and that you would like to share with young founders or young entrepreneurs.
[SPEAKER_01] You know, I'll probably paraphrase a couple quotes when I say just be open to a lot of different experiences.
[SPEAKER_01] I learned this when I originally graduated from high school.
[SPEAKER_01] I wanted to be a doctor and that was my main focus and I would just, I had tunnel vision for that.
[SPEAKER_01] And I didn't take the opportunities as they were presenting themselves and I really focused too, too much on that, that path that ultimately was not the right fit for me.
[SPEAKER_01] So always staying open to new opportunities while also making sure that you're doing good.
[SPEAKER_01] Be, you never know how you can affect somebody's day by just being a nicer person than other people around you, right?
[SPEAKER_01] Just do good, be good, and work hard.
[SPEAKER_00] It will come back.
[SPEAKER_01] It will.
[SPEAKER_00] What about books do you read?
[SPEAKER_01] Definitely, definitely.
[SPEAKER_01] So, you know, there's a few different ones.
[SPEAKER_01] Give me one moment to just think of a few.
[SPEAKER_01] Okay, so I think The Alchemist is a good one for learning about your journey.
[SPEAKER_01] That's definitely a classic that a lot of people will pick up for guidance in that piece.
[SPEAKER_01] and then 50 Laws of Power is actually one of my favorite ones because I listened to it on audiobook and that's, I think it's Robert Green is the author, but it was through 50 Cents.
[SPEAKER_01] Cents, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, and I listened to it on audiobook and it was pretty awesome to listen to, I will say.
[SPEAKER_00] Honestly, 50 Laws of Power is right now one of my favorite books that I've read, maybe even favorite one.
[SPEAKER_00] I love it.
[SPEAKER_01] I love it.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah, it's, you know.
[SPEAKER_00] It talks exactly what you said, don't be scared, go for it.
[SPEAKER_01] And the experience that that man faced throughout his trials and tribulations is something else and very much not business related, but the DMX autobiography is also really good.
[SPEAKER_01] Especially if you like 50 Cents and how he presents information because DMX had also faced a lot of those same adverse situations and I think those are the books that speak out to me, is people that have had difficult times and faced those difficult times and overcame them.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, at the end of this podcast, I have one game for you, but before we start this game, is there anything that we missed to cover that you would like to share?
[SPEAKER_00] That's a great question, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] It can be related to startups or personal growth or whatever you think we missed.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm sure we didn't have time to cover everything that you did.
[SPEAKER_01] We could talk for the next five days, I'm sure we could, and I'm sure we will over time.
[SPEAKER_01] So, as I think of more things, I'll add them into the comment section.
[SPEAKER_00] Perfect.
[SPEAKER_00] And keep open to it.
[SPEAKER_00] So, let's go up to the game.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm excited.
[SPEAKER_00] I will give you a word and you will tell me if that is currently overrated or underrated.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] AI.
[SPEAKER_01] Overrated.
[SPEAKER_01] Bitcoin.
[SPEAKER_01] Books.
[SPEAKER_01] Underrated.
[SPEAKER_00] Podcast.
[SPEAKER_01] Underrated, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01] Especially yours.
[SPEAKER_00] Bootcamps.
[SPEAKER_01] Bootcamps.
[SPEAKER_01] Ah.
[SPEAKER_01] You know what?
[SPEAKER_01] I saw that online the other day of those people paying like $20,000 to basically get beaten up.
[SPEAKER_01] So, I would say overrated in that sense, but underrated if we're talking about like a mentorship
[SPEAKER_01] or a coaching opportunity where you're actually investing in things that aren't like the one
[SPEAKER_01] that I mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01] Sass.
[SPEAKER_01] Underrated.
[SPEAKER_00] This is going to be subjective right now.
[SPEAKER_00] Vancouver.
[SPEAKER_01] Overrated for how expensive it is.
[SPEAKER_00] Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_01] So expensive.
[SPEAKER_00] And you're from Vancouver.
[SPEAKER_01] I'm from Victoria, which is about just the island to the west of here.
[SPEAKER_01] But yeah, Vancouver is a little bit overrated, I will say, based on the price point associated.
[SPEAKER_01] But it is an absolute beautiful place during the summer.
[SPEAKER_01] And then outside of the summer, it's time to go travel to Europe.
[SPEAKER_00] To Montenegro.
[SPEAKER_01] Montenegro.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm not going to question any of these except one.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] Bitcoin.
[SPEAKER_00] Why is Bitcoin overrated, in your opinion?
[SPEAKER_01] I got into it in like 2017 and really got into it.
[SPEAKER_01] And then I got burned a couple of times and rug pulled.
[SPEAKER_01] And now I'm just a bitter old man about it.
[SPEAKER_01] That's basically what it is.
[SPEAKER_01] But the underlying technology is underrated, though, I will say.
[SPEAKER_01] So Bitcoin itself, as if we're just talking about one specific cryptocurrency, then yeah,
[SPEAKER_01] got a little bit overrated, but the overall functionality of the technology is underrated.
[SPEAKER_01] Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Brandon, thank you very much for joining me on this podcast.
[SPEAKER_00] It was a pleasure to talk with you, to learn so much.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you for sharing all your insights about startups.
[SPEAKER_00] I'm looking forward to how your career will progress.
[SPEAKER_00] And thank you very much for joining us.
[SPEAKER_01] Likewise to you.
[SPEAKER_00] Thank you so much for having me.
[SPEAKER_00] Awesome.